<?xml version="1.0"?><metadata><idinfo><citation><citeinfo><origin>Itasca County</origin><title>Public Land Survey System (PLSS) Townships, Itasca County, Minnesota</title><pubinfo><publish>Itasca County</publish></pubinfo><pubdate>20151215</pubdate><onlink>https://gisdata.mn.gov/dataset/us-mn-co-itasca-plan-townships</onlink></citeinfo></citation><descript><abstract>This dataset represents the PLSS Townships for Itasca County.
The Itasca County PLSS data is based on the best and most current survey records available.
This data is used to create the parcel dataset.
Data users should be aware that Itasca County is continually updating this dataset.  Updates to this dataset are expected as horizontal control positions from GPS are added.</abstract><purpose>This data is a key component of the PLSS framework upon which parcel boundary information is assembled.</purpose><supplinf>Itasca County</supplinf></descript><timeperd><current>The data set is complete, but is being continually updated as better positional accuracy becomes available.</current><timeinfo><sngdate><caldate>20160310</caldate></sngdate></timeinfo></timeperd><status><progress>In work</progress><update>Monthly</update></status><keywords><theme><themekey>PLSS, Township, Public Land Survey System, PLS</themekey></theme><place><placekey>Itasca County, Minnesota</placekey></place></keywords><spdom><bounding><westbc>-94.419272199455</westbc><eastbc>-93.0555277417487</eastbc><northbc>47.8989785603538</northbc><southbc>47.0251605088806</southbc></bounding></spdom><accconst>None</accconst><useconst>See Distribution Liability</useconst><ptcontac><cntinfo><cntperp><cntorg>Itasca County Department of Surveying and Mapping</cntorg><cntper>David Bily</cntper></cntperp><cntpos>GIS Coordinator</cntpos><cntaddr><addrtype>Mailling and Physical</addrtype><address>123 NE 4th St</address><city>Grand Rapids</city><state>MN</state><postal>55744</postal></cntaddr><cntvoice>218-327-7380</cntvoice><cntemail>Dave.Bily@co.itasca.mn.us</cntemail></cntinfo></ptcontac></idinfo><spref><vertdef><altsys><altdatum>not applicable</altdatum></altsys><depthsys><depthdn>not applicable</depthdn></depthsys></vertdef><horizsys><planar><gridsys><gridsysn>Universal Transverse Mercator</gridsysn><utm><utmzone>15</utmzone></utm></gridsys><planci><plandu>meters</plandu></planci></planar><geodetic><horizdn>NAD83</horizdn><ellips>GRS80</ellips></geodetic></horizsys></spref><distinfo><distliab>THE COUNTY FURNISHES THIS DATABASE "AS IS", WITHOUT ANY SUPPORT WHATSOEVER, AND WITHOUT REPRESENTATION OR WARRANTY, INCLUDING BUT NOT IN ANY MANNER LIMITED TO, FITNESS, MERCHANTABILITY OR THE ACCURACY AND COMPETENESS OF THE DATABASE. The database is neither a legally recorded map nor a survey and is not intended to be used as one. The database is a compilation of records, information and data from various sources with varying accuracies and should be used for reference only. Verification of the data by qualified field survey or any other process is the sole responsibility of the user. No representation is made that data and features presented, accurately reflect true location. Itasca County or any other entity from whom data was obtained assume no liability for any errors or omissions herein. If discrepancies are found, please contact the Itasca County Department of Surveying and Mapping. Because the database is inherently complex and may not be completely free of errors, user is hereby advised to verify its work. In no event will the County be liable for direct, indirect, special, incidental or consequential damages arising out of the use of or inability to use the Database even if advised of the possibility of such damages. Specifically, the county is not responsible for any costs including, but not limited to, those incurred as a result of lost profits or revenue, loss of use of data, the costs of recovering such programs or data, the cost of any substitute program, claims by third parties, or for other similar costs.  User agrees to indemnify and hold harmless the County from any and all claims, actions, suits, or damages including but not limited to, the cost of attorney's fees in the defense of any claims, arising from users use or dissemination of the Database herein.</distliab><distrib><cntinfo><cntperp><cntorg>Itasca County Department of Surveying and Mapping</cntorg><cntper>David Bily</cntper></cntperp><cntpos>GIS Coordinator</cntpos><cntaddr><addrtype>mailing and physical</addrtype><address>123 NE 4th St</address><city>Grand Rapids</city><state>MN</state><postal>55744</postal></cntaddr><cntvoice>218-327-7380</cntvoice><cntemail>Dave.Bily@co.itasca.mn.us</cntemail></cntinfo></distrib></distinfo><metainfo><metd>20151215</metd><metstdn>Minnesota Geographic Metadata Guidelines</metstdn><metstdv>1.2</metstdv><metextns><onlink>http://www.mngeo.state.mn.us/committee/standards/mgmg/metadata.htm</onlink></metextns><metc><cntinfo><cntperp><cntorg>Itasca County Department of Surveying and Mapping</cntorg><cntper>David Bily</cntper></cntperp><cntpos>GIS Coordinator</cntpos><cntaddr><addrtype>mailing and physical</addrtype><address>123 NE 4th St</address><city>Grand Rapids</city><state>MN</state><postal>55744</postal></cntaddr><cntvoice>218-327-7380</cntvoice><cntemail>Dave.Bily@co.itasca.mn.us</cntemail></cntinfo></metc></metainfo><dataqual><posacc><vertacc><vertaccr>Not Applicable</vertaccr></vertacc><horizpa><horizpar>+- 5 feet, with a 98% confidence level.</horizpar></horizpa></posacc><complete>The PLSS Townships are complete, with the exception of: T14728W, T14628W</complete><attracc><attraccr>All attribute values have been verified by the Department of Surveying and Mapping.</attraccr></attracc><lineage><procstep><procdesc>The PLSS positions, as shown, were determined using Global Position Systems and traditional survey measurements in a least squares adjustment. Interior corner positions and unrecovered PLSS corner positions were established using acceptable survey methods.</procdesc></procstep></lineage><logic>GIS software checks are performed for topological consistency. 
This ensures there are no duplicate lines, gaps, overlaps, undershoots, or overshoots. </logic></dataqual><eainfo><detailed><enttyp><enttypl>PLSS_Townships</enttypl></enttyp><attr><attrlabl>TWP</attrlabl><attrdef>Township Number</attrdef></attr><attr><attrlabl>RNG</attrlabl><attrdef>Range Number</attrdef></attr><attr><attrlabl>TOWNSHIP</attrlabl><attrdef>Concatenation of township and range numbers</attrdef></attr><attr><attrlabl>TWP_NAME</attrlabl><attrdef>Name of the township</attrdef></attr></detailed></eainfo></metadata>