<?xml version="1.0"?><metadata><idinfo><citation><citeinfo><origin>Minnesota Valley Transit Authority</origin><pubdate>periodically revised</pubdate><title>Minnesota Valley Transit Authority - General Transit Feed Specification (GTFS)</title><mgmg1cid>N/A</mgmg1cid><pubinfo><publish>Minnesota Valley Transit Authority</publish></pubinfo><onlink>https://gisdata.mn.gov/dataset/com-mvta-trans-transit-schedule-google-fd</onlink></citeinfo></citation><descript><abstract>The Minnesota Valley Transit Authority (MVTA) schedule data includes bus schedules for the seven suburbs located approximately 15 miles south of Minneapolis and St. Paul: Apple Valley, Burnsville, Eagan, and Rosemount in Dakota County, Savage, Prior Lake and Shakopee in Scott County. The data is provided as comma-delimited text files that use the General Transit Feed Specification found at https://developers.google.com/transit/gtfs/reference?csw=1

This data resource on the Geospatial Commons links to an external resource. To see regular updates, please browse to http://wiki.mvta.com/</abstract><purpose>To provide schedule data for public transit services in the Minnesota Valley Transit Authority (MVTA) service area. Allows developers to write applications that consume MVTA transit data in an interoperable way.</purpose><supplinf>Suburbs south of Minneapolis and St. Paul, Minnesota</supplinf></descript><timeperd><current>Updated 3-4 times per year based on MVTA transit schedule updates. The data files may be updated more often around holidays to accommodate special schedules.</current></timeperd><status><progress>Complete</progress><update>As needed</update></status><spdom><bounding><westbc>-93.554915</westbc><eastbc>-93.084810</eastbc><northbc>44.988425</northbc><southbc>44.690287</southbc></bounding></spdom><keywords><theme><themekt>ISO 19115 Topic Category</themekt><themekey>transportation, transit, buses, nodes, transportation, schedules</themekey></theme><place><placekey>Minnesota, MN, Minneapolis, St. Paul, Twin Cities, Dakota County, Scott County, Apple Valley, Burnsville, Eagan, Rosemount,  Savage, Prior Lake, Shakopee, Hennepin County, Ramsey County</placekey></place></keywords><accconst>None</accconst><useconst>By acceptance of this data, the user agrees to include a copy of this metadata record, including the liability disclaimer, whenever the user transmits or provides this data to another user.</useconst><browse><browsen>None available</browsen></browse><native>General Transit Feed Specification</native><crossref><citeinfo><title>bus routes, bus segments, bus service, bus shelters, park and rides, bus stops</title></citeinfo></crossref><ptcontac><cntinfo><cntperp><cntorg>Minnesota Valley Transit Authority (MVTA)</cntorg><cntper>Jen Lehmann</cntper></cntperp><cntpos>Planning Manager</cntpos><cntaddr><addrtype>mailing</addrtype><address>100 E. Highway 13</address><city>Burnsville</city><state>MN</state><postal>55337</postal></cntaddr><cntvoice>952-230-1234    </cntvoice><cntemail>jlehmann@mvta.com</cntemail></cntinfo></ptcontac></idinfo><dataqual><attracc><attraccr>Attributes are assumed to be accurate on the effective date</attraccr></attracc><complete>Entire service area is covered.</complete><posacc><horizpa><horizpar>Positional accuracy is unknown.</horizpar></horizpa></posacc><logic>Not applicable</logic><lineage><procstep><procdesc>Not available.</procdesc></procstep></lineage></dataqual><spdoinfo><indspref>None</indspref><direct></direct><mgmg3obj></mgmg3obj><mgmg3til></mgmg3til></spdoinfo><eainfo><overview><eaover>The following text files are included in the download:
agency.txt
calendar.txt
calendar_dates.txt
feed_info.txt
routes.txt
shapes.txt
stop_times.txt
stops.txt
trips.txt

The text file attributes are described here:  https://developers.google.com/transit/gtfs/reference?csw=1</eaover></overview></eainfo><distinfo><distliab>NOTICE:  The Geographic Information System (GIS) Data to which this notice is attached are made available pursuant to the Minnesota Government Data Practices Act (Minnesota Statutes Chapter 13).  THE GIS DATA ARE PROVIDED TO YOU AS IS AND WITHOUT ANY WARRANTY AS TO THEIR PERFORMANCE, MERCHANTABILITY, OR FITNESS FOR ANY PARTICULAR PURPOSE.  The GIS Data were developed by the MVTA for its own internal business purposes.  The MVTA does not represent or warrant that the GIS Data or the data documentation are error-free, complete, current, or accurate.  You are responsible for any consequences resulting from your use of the GIS Data or your reliance on the GIS Data.  You should consult the data documentation for this particular GIS Data to determine the limitations of the GIS Data and the precision with which the GIS Data may depict distance, direction, location, or other geographic features.  If you transmit or provide the GIS Data (or any portion of it) to another user, it is recommended that the GIS Data include a copy of this disclaimer and this metadata.</distliab><stdorder><digform><digtinfo><formname>General Transit Feed Specification</formname><formvern></formvern><transize>12 MB</transize></digtinfo></digform><ordering>See Online Linkage below or navigate to http://wiki.mvta.com/files/Home/google_transit.zip. </ordering></stdorder><distrib><cntinfo><cntperp><cntorg>Minnesota Valley Transit Authority (MVTA)</cntorg><cntper>Jen Lehmann</cntper></cntperp><cntpos>Planning Manager</cntpos><cntaddr><addrtype>mailing and physical</addrtype><address>100 E. Highway 13</address><city>Burnsville</city><state>MN</state><postal>55337</postal></cntaddr><cntvoice>952-230-1234    </cntvoice><cntemail>jlehmann@mvta.com</cntemail></cntinfo></distrib></distinfo><metainfo><metd>20151211</metd><metstdn>Minnesota Geographic Metadata Guidelines</metstdn><metstdv>1.2</metstdv><metextns><onlink>http://www.mngeo.state.mn.us/committee/standards/mgmg/metadata.htm</onlink></metextns><metc><cntinfo><cntperp><cntorg>MN Geospatial Information Office</cntorg><cntper>Mike Dolbow</cntper></cntperp><cntpos>GIS Supervisor</cntpos><cntaddr><addrtype>mailing and physical</addrtype><address>658 Cedar Street</address><city>St. Paul</city><state>MN</state><postal>55155</postal></cntaddr><cntvoice>651-201-3944</cntvoice><cntemail>gisinfo.mngeo@state.mn.us</cntemail></cntinfo></metc></metainfo><Esri><ModDate>20120913</ModDate><ModTime>13341100</ModTime></Esri><mdDateSt Sync="TRUE">20110825</mdDateSt><spref><horizsys><planar><gridsys><gridsysn>Universal Transverse Mercator</gridsysn><utm><utmzone>15</utmzone></utm></gridsys><planci><plandu>meters</plandu></planci></planar><geodetic><horizdn>NAD83</horizdn><ellips>GRS80</ellips></geodetic></horizsys></spref></metadata>