<?xml version="1.0"?><metadata><idinfo><citation><citeinfo><origin>Metropolitan Council</origin><pubdate>20120406</pubdate><title>Transit Rights-of-Way Segments (Transit Advantages)</title><mgmg1cid>N/A</mgmg1cid><pubinfo><publish>Metropolitan Council - Metro Transit</publish></pubinfo><onlink>https://gisdata.mn.gov/dataset/us-mn-state-metc-trans-transit-row-segments</onlink></citeinfo></citation><descript><abstract>This dataset includes transportation network segments where transit vehicles are permitted to operate and mixed-traffic is prohibitied or has limited access to operate on.  The advantages have been categorized by type and include bus lanes, busways, commuter rail, HOT lanes, light rail, meter bypasses, online stations and shoulder lanes.  The line work for the dataset was derived from NCompass Technologies' Street Centerline dataset. A number of street segments were added to depict all transit advantages.

Information in this layer is subject to changes and may not be fully accurate.  Refer to street signage and field conditions for the most accurate information. </abstract><purpose>To identify transit advantages in the Twin Cities metropolitan area.</purpose><supplinf>Twin Cities 7 County Metropolitan Area.  This includes the counties of Anoka, Carver, Dakota, Hennepin, Ramsey, Scott and Washington in Minnesota.</supplinf></descript><timeperd><timeinfo><sngdate><caldate>20110406</caldate></sngdate></timeinfo><current>Includes all transit advantages as of the time period of content date.</current></timeperd><status><progress>Complete</progress><update>Annually</update></status><spdom><bounding><westbc>-94.012</westbc><eastbc>-92.732</eastbc><northbc>45.415</northbc><southbc>44.471</southbc></bounding></spdom><keywords><theme><themekt>None</themekt><themekey>transit, buses, segments, transit advantage, roads, transportation, right of way, ROW, right-of-way, light rail, dedicated,</themekey></theme><place><placekey>Twin Cities, Anoka County, Carver County, Dakota County, Hennepin County, Ramsey County, Scott County, Washington County</placekey></place></keywords><accconst>None</accconst><useconst>None</useconst><native>ArcView version 3.x</native><crossref><citeinfo><title>NCompass Technologies Street Centerline and Address Ranges </title></citeinfo></crossref><ptcontac><cntinfo><cntperp><cntorg>Metropolitan Council - Metro Transit</cntorg><cntper>Steve Baisden</cntper></cntperp><cntpos>Associate Planner</cntpos><cntaddr><addrtype>mailing and physical</addrtype><address>560 6th Ave N</address><city>Minneapolis</city><state>MN</state><postal>55411</postal></cntaddr><cntvoice>612.349.7361</cntvoice><cntemail>stephen.baisden@metrotransit.org</cntemail></cntinfo></ptcontac></idinfo><dataqual><attracc><attraccr>The database is maintained by Metro Transit's Service Development Division.  Attributes of non-fixed guideway segments may not be complete.  Attributes are updated annually by Metro Transit staff.</attraccr></attracc><complete>Data consists of known transit right-of-ways.  Segments may not be completely accurate and complete.</complete><posacc><horizpa><horizpar>Positional accuracy varies throughout the dataset. Most line work in most counties falls within the road right of way, often near the center. 
</horizpar></horizpa></posacc><lineage><srcinfo><srcscale></srcscale></srcinfo><procstep><procdesc>To create this dataset, the NCompass Technologies Street Cemterline and Address Ranges dataset along with other street centerlines were used to map the ROW segments.  Checks were performed to insure that the selected street centerlines were contiguous for each segment. </procdesc></procstep></lineage></dataqual><spdoinfo><indspref>None</indspref><direct>Vector</direct><mgmg3obj>arcs, nodes</mgmg3obj><mgmg3til>One layer for entire seven county region.</mgmg3til></spdoinfo><eainfo><overview><eaover>Line Attributes:

SEGID:  A unique identification number for each transit advantagey segment.

LINE_ID:    A unique identification string for each transit advantage segment.

TYPE:       The physical construction of the transit advantage segment.

MJR_RDWY:   The main road where the transit advantage exists.

DESC_:       A description of the transit advantage segment.

MILES:      The approximate length in miles.

MODE:  A system for carrying transit passengers described by specific right-of-way, technology and operational facilities.  MB = bus, LRT = light rail transit, CRT = commuter rail transit.

NTD:  This binary classification provides inventory of the transit advantages found in the Fixed Guideway Segments (S-20) form of the National Transit Database (NTD) annual report.

NTD_MILES:  The length in miles of a fixed guideway segment as reported in the National Transit Database S-20 report.</eaover><eadetcit>None</eadetcit></overview></eainfo><distinfo><resdesc>TransitAdvantages</resdesc><distliab>NOTICE:  The Geographic Information System (GIS) Data to which this notice is attached are made available pursuant to the Minnesota Government Data Practices Act (Minnesota Statutes Chapter 13).  THE GIS DATA ARE PROVIDED TO YOU AS IS AND WITHOUT ANY WARRANTY AS TO THEIR PERFORMANCE, MERCHANTABILITY, OR FITNESS FOR ANY PARTICULAR PURPOSE.  The GIS Data were developed by the Metropolitan Council for its own internal business purposes.  The Metropolitan Council does not represent or warrant that the GIS Data or the data documentation are error-free, complete, current, or accurate.  You are responsible for any consequences resulting from your use of the GIS Data or your reliance on the GIS Data.  You should consult the data documentation for this particular GIS Data to determine the limitations of the GIS Data and the precision with which the GIS Data may depict distance, direction, location, or other geographic features.  If you transmit or provide the GIS Data (or any portion of it) to another user, it is recommended that the GIS Data include a copy of this disclaimer and this metadata.</distliab><stdorder><digform><digtinfo><formname>ArcView Shape files</formname><formvern>ArcGIS 9x</formvern><transize>Less than 1 MB for zip file.</transize></digtinfo></digform><ordering>See Online Linkage Below</ordering></stdorder><distrib><cntinfo><cntperp><cntorg>Metropolitan Council</cntorg><cntper>Jon Hoekenga</cntper></cntperp><cntpos>GIS System Administrator</cntpos><cntaddr><addrtype>mailing and physical</addrtype><address>390 Robert Street North</address><city>St. Paul</city><state>MN</state><postal>55101-1805</postal></cntaddr><cntvoice>651.602.1561</cntvoice><cntemail>jonathan.hoekenga@metc.state.mn.us</cntemail></cntinfo></distrib></distinfo><metainfo><metd>20150106</metd><metstdn>Minnesota Geographic Metadata Guidelines</metstdn><metstdv>1.2</metstdv><metextns><onlink>http://www.gis.state.mn.us/stds/metadata.htm</onlink></metextns><metc><cntinfo><cntperp><cntorg>Metropolitan Council - Metro Transit</cntorg><cntper>Steve Baisden</cntper></cntperp><cntpos>Associate Planner</cntpos><cntaddr><addrtype>mailing and physical</addrtype><address>560 6th Ave N</address><city>Minneapolis</city><state>MN</state><postal>55411</postal></cntaddr><cntvoice>612.349.7361</cntvoice><cntemail>stephen.baisden@metrotransit.org</cntemail></cntinfo></metc></metainfo><Esri><ModDate>20100615</ModDate><ModTime>12170100</ModTime></Esri><mdDateSt Sync="TRUE">20100615</mdDateSt><spref><horizsys><planar><gridsys><gridsysn>Universal Transverse Mercator</gridsysn><utm><utmzone>15</utmzone></utm></gridsys><planci><plandu>meters</plandu></planci></planar><geodetic><horizdn>NAD83</horizdn><ellips>GRS80</ellips></geodetic></horizsys></spref></metadata>