<metadata>
  <idinfo>
    <citation>
      <citeinfo>
        <origin>Metropolitan Council</origin>
        <pubdate>2003</pubdate>
        <title>Metropolitan Council Districts 2003</title>
        <mgmg1cid>N/A</mgmg1cid>
        <pubinfo>
          <publish>Metropolitan Council</publish>
        </pubinfo>
        <onlink>https://gisdata.mn.gov/dataset/us-mn-state-metc-bdry-mcdistricts2003</onlink>
      </citeinfo>
    </citation>
    <descript>
      <abstract>This layer defines the district boundaries for the Metropolitan Council members.

NOTES:
-  The current Metropolitan Council Districts were enacted in 2003.
-  Council member names and spellings are taken directly from the Metropolitan Council web site and press releases.
-  Hanover, New Prague, Northfield, and Rockford have been removed from the district boundaries.
-  Only the cities of Minneapolis, St. Paul and Eagan have significant populations split into more than one Council District.  Chanhassen, Hastings and Spring Lake Park have small areas accross county boundaries in another Council district.
- The actual descriptions of Metropolitan Council District boundaries were taken from Minnesota Statutes 2003, 473.123  http://www.revisor.leg.state.mn.us/stats/473/123.html
- The 2003 plan files, details and components passed by the 2003 MN Legislature are available here: http://www.gis.leg.mn/html/mc03/mc03.html </abstract>
      <purpose>This layer was developed as a general reference for Metropolitan Council districts.</purpose>
      <supplinf>Twin Cities 7 county metropolitan area.  This includes the counties of Anoka, Carver, Dakota, Hennepin, Ramsey, Scott and Washington.</supplinf>
    </descript>
    <timeperd>
      <timeinfo>
        <sngdate>
          <caldate>20110426</caldate>
        </sngdate>
      </timeinfo>
      <current>The attributes and municipal boundaries within this layer are up to date as of the Time Period of Content date. </current>
    </timeperd>
    <status>
      <progress>Complete</progress>
      <update>None Planned</update>
    </status>
    <spdom>
      <bounding>
        <westbc>-94.012</westbc>
        <eastbc>-92.732</eastbc>
        <northbc>45.415</northbc>
        <southbc>44.471</southbc>
      </bounding>
    </spdom>
    <keywords>
      <theme>
        <themekt>None</themekt>
        <themekey>Metropolitan Council Districts, Council Districts, Metropolitan Council, administrative boundaries</themekey>
      </theme>
      <place>
        <placekey>Twin Cities, Anoka County, Carver County, Dakota County, Hennepin County, Ramsey County, Scott County, Washington County</placekey>
      </place>
    </keywords>
    <accconst>None</accconst>
    <useconst>None</useconst>
    <browse>
      <browsen>ftp://ftp.gisdata.mn.gov/pub/gdrs/data/pub/us_mn_state_metc/bdry_mcdistricts_2003/metadata/preview.jpg</browsen>
      <browsed>Sample map showing the Metropolitan Council Districts 2003 layer.</browsed>
    </browse>
    <native>ArcGIS 10x</native>
    <crossref>
      <citeinfo>
        <title>Counties and Cities &amp; Townships, Twin Cities Metropolitan Area</title>
      </citeinfo>
    </crossref>
    <ptcontac>
      <cntinfo>
        <cntperp>
          <cntorg>Metropolitan Council</cntorg>
          <cntper>Craig Skone</cntper>
        </cntperp>
        <cntpos>GIS Specialist</cntpos>
        <cntaddr>
          <addrtype>mailing and physical</addrtype>
          <address>390 Robert Street North</address>
          <city>St. Paul</city>
          <state>MN</state>
          <postal>55101-1805</postal>
        </cntaddr>
        <cntvoice>651.602.1328</cntvoice>
        <cntemail>craig.skone@metc.state.mn.us</cntemail>
      </cntinfo>
    </ptcontac>
  </idinfo>
  <dataqual>
    <attracc>
      <attraccr>Attributes for all 16 council districts have been checked and are accurate as of the Time Period of Content date.</attraccr>
    </attracc>
    <logic>The dataset is topologically 'clean'.</logic>
    <complete>Entire seven county geographic area is covered.</complete>
    <posacc>
      <horizpa>
        <horizpar>The positional accuracy of the dataset has not been tested under the National Standards for Spatial Data Accuracy.</horizpar>
      </horizpa>
    </posacc>
    <lineage>
      <srcinfo>
        <srcscale/>
      </srcinfo>
      <procstep>
        <procdesc>Line work for the mc_districts layer is derived primarily from the city and townships boundary layer assembled by the Metropolitan Council.  Some additional lines were derived from heads up digitizing of the TLG street centerline data, Minneapolis neighborhood boundaries, 2004 USGS High Resolution Orthoimagery, and the 1997 Metropolitan Council digital orthophotos.  Where divided highways serve as the boundary between districts, the district border was digitized between the representative TLG centerlines.  Where divided by city or township boundary, the district border is based on the most current quarterly update of the city and township boundary layer.

The actual descriptions of Metropolitan Council District boundaries were taken from Minnesota Statutes 2003, 473.123  http://www.revisor.leg.state.mn.us/stats/473/123.html 

Council Member names and spellings were taken directly from the Metropolitan Council web site and press releases.

The 2003 plan files, details and components passed by the 2003 MN Legislature are available here: http://www.gis.leg.mn/html/mc03/mc03.html 
Hanover, New Prague, Northfield, and Rockford have been removed from the district boundaries.</procdesc>
      </procstep>
    </lineage>
  </dataqual>
  <spdoinfo>
    <indspref>None</indspref>
    <direct>Vector</direct>
    <mgmg3obj>polygon shapes</mgmg3obj>
    <mgmg3til>One layer for entire seven county region.</mgmg3til>
  </spdoinfo>
  <eainfo>
    <overview>
      <eaover>Polygon Attributes (SDE alias names in parentheses):
 
MCDIST (District Number): Metropolitan Council district numbers 1-16
 
MEMBER (Council Member):  The council member representing that district. 

FIVE_COLOR: Numbers 1 through 5 for shading polygons so adjacent polygons have different colors. 
</eaover>
    </overview>
  </eainfo>
  <distinfo>
    <resdesc>MetCouncilDistricts2003</resdesc>
    <distliab>NOTICE  The Geographic Information System (GIS) Data to which this notice is attached are made available pursuant to the Minnesota Government Data Practices Act (Minnesota Statutes Chapter 13).  THE GIS DATA ARE PROVIDED TO YOU AS IS AND WITHOUT ANY WARRANTY AS TO THEIR PERFORMANCE, MERCHANTABILITY, OR FITNESS FOR ANY PARTICULAR PURPOSE.  The GIS Data were developed by the Metropolitan Council for its own internal business purposes.  The Metropolitan Council does not represent or warrant that the GIS Data or the data documentation are error-free, complete, current, or accurate.  You are responsible for any consequences resulting from your use of the GIS Data or your reliance on the GIS Data.  You should consult the data documentation for this particular GIS Data to determine the limitations of the GIS Data and the precision with which the GIS Data may depict distance, direction, location, or other geographic features.  If you transmit or provide the GIS Data (or any portion of it) to another user, it is recommended that the GIS Data include a copy of this disclaimer and this metadata.</distliab>
    <stdorder>
      <digform>
        <digtinfo>
          <formname>ArcView Shape file</formname>
          <formvern>ArcGIS 10x</formvern>
          <transize>1 MB for zip file.</transize>
        </digtinfo>
      </digform>
      <ordering>See Online Linkage Below</ordering>
    </stdorder>
    <distrib>
      <cntinfo>
        <cntperp>
          <cntorg>Metropolitan Council</cntorg>
          <cntper>Jon Hoekenga</cntper>
        </cntperp>
        <cntpos>GIS Specialist</cntpos>
        <cntaddr>
          <addrtype>mailing and physical</addrtype>
          <address>390 Robert Street North</address>
          <city>St. Paul</city>
          <state>MN</state>
          <postal>55101-1805</postal>
        </cntaddr>
        <cntvoice>651.602.1561</cntvoice>
        <cntemail>jonathan.hoekenga@metc.state.mn.us</cntemail>
      </cntinfo>
    </distrib>
  </distinfo>
  <metainfo>
    <metd>20130528</metd>
    <metstdn>Minnesota Geographic Metadata Guidelines</metstdn>
    <metstdv>1.2</metstdv>
    <metextns>
      <onlink>http://www.gis.state.mn.us/stds/metadata.htm</onlink>
    </metextns>
    <metc>
      <cntinfo>
        <cntperp>
          <cntorg>Metropolitan Council</cntorg>
          <cntper>Jon Hoekenga</cntper>
        </cntperp>
        <cntpos>GIS Specialist</cntpos>
        <cntaddr>
          <addrtype>mailing and physical</addrtype>
          <address>390 Robert Street North</address>
          <city>St. Paul</city>
          <state>MN</state>
          <postal>55101-1805</postal>
        </cntaddr>
        <cntvoice>651.602.1561</cntvoice>
        <cntemail>jonathan.hoekenga@metc.state.mn.us</cntemail>
      </cntinfo>
    </metc>
  </metainfo>
  <Esri>
    <ModDate>20110426</ModDate>
    <ModTime>15455500</ModTime>
  </Esri>
  <mdDateSt Sync="TRUE">20110426</mdDateSt>
  <spref>
    <horizsys>
      <planar>
        <gridsys>
          <gridsysn>Universal Transverse Mercator</gridsysn>
          <utm>
            <utmzone>15</utmzone>
          </utm>
        </gridsys>
        <planci>
          <plandu>meters</plandu>
        </planci>
      </planar>
      <geodetic>
        <horizdn>NAD83</horizdn>
        <ellips>GRS80</ellips>
      </geodetic>
    </horizsys>
  </spref>
</metadata>
