<metadata>
  <idinfo>
    <citation>
      <citeinfo>
        <origin>Metropolitan Council</origin>
        <title>Transit Market Areas</title>
        <pubinfo>
          <publish>Metropolitan Council - Metro Transit</publish>
        </pubinfo>
        <pubdate>20130624</pubdate>
        <onlink>https://gisdata.mn.gov/dataset/us-mn-state-metc-trans-transit-market-areas</onlink>
      </citeinfo>
    </citation>
    <spdom>
      <bounding>
        <westbc>-94.012</westbc>
        <eastbc>-92.732</eastbc>
        <northbc>45.415</northbc>
        <southbc>44.471</southbc>
      </bounding>
    </spdom>
    <timeperd>
      <timeinfo>
        <sngdate>
          <caldate>20150114</caldate>
        </sngdate>
      </timeinfo>
      <current>This dataset will be reviewed with updated to the TPP and updated as necessary.</current>
    </timeperd>
    <descript>
      <abstract>At the regional level, transit market areas approximate the level of transit service an area can support. The concept was initially developed in 1996 Transit Redesign to provide general guidelines on the mix of transit services that may be appropriate for a given area. This guidance is provided for broad regional context; appropriate transit services are defined through professional transit service planning processes. 

The existing market area definitions identify five market areas, with Area I supporting the most intensive transit service and area 5 supporting the least intensive transit service. Transit Market Areas were first introduced in the 1996 Transit Redesign report produced by the Metropolitan Council. They have been updated periodically since then to better reflect census geography and demographic shifts and to refine the appropriate measures of transit supportiveness.

The current Transit Market Areas, developed for the 2040 TPP update, are based on an index of population density, employment density, automobile availability (population over 16 less available automobiles), and intersection density (an indicator of urban form measured as a weighted count of intersections by block group).

</abstract>
      <supplinf>Twin Cities 7 county metropolitan area which included Anoka, Carver, Dakota, Hennepin, Ramsey, Scott and Washington Counties. It also includes portions of Wright and Sherburne Counties.</supplinf>
      <purpose>To identify service levels and area can support</purpose>
    </descript>
    <status>
      <progress>Complete</progress>
      <update>As needed</update>
    </status>
    <accconst>None</accconst>
    <useconst>None</useconst>
    <keywords>
      <place>
        <placekey>metro</placekey>
      </place>
      <theme>
        <themekey>transit, transit market areas</themekey>
      </theme>
    </keywords>
    <browse>
      <browsen>None Available</browsen>
    </browse>
    <ptcontac>
      <cntinfo>
        <cntperp>
          <cntorg>Metropolitan Council - Metro Transit</cntorg>
          <cntper>Kyle Burrows</cntper>
        </cntperp>
        <cntpos>Associate Planner</cntpos>
        <cntaddr>
          <addrtype>mailing and physical</addrtype>
          <address>560 6th Ave N</address>
          <city>Minneapolis</city>
          <state>MN</state>
          <postal>55411</postal>
        </cntaddr>
        <cntvoice>612.349.7749</cntvoice>
        <cntemail>kyle.burrows@metrotransit.org</cntemail>
      </cntinfo>
    </ptcontac>
  </idinfo>
  <distinfo>
    <distliab>NOTICE:  The Geographic Information System (GIS) Data to which this notice is attached are made available pursuant to the Minnesota Government Data Practices Act (Minnesota Statutes Chapter 13).  THE GIS DATA ARE PROVIDED TO YOU AS IS AND WITHOUT ANY WARRANTY AS TO THEIR PERFORMANCE, MERCHANTABILITY, OR FITNESS FOR ANY PARTICULAR PURPOSE.  The GIS Data were developed by the Metropolitan Council for its own internal business purposes.  The Metropolitan Council does not represent or warrant that the GIS Data or the data documentation are error-free, complete, current, or accurate.  You are responsible for any consequences resulting from your use of the GIS Data or your reliance on the GIS Data.  You should consult the data documentation for this particular GIS Data to determine the limitations of the GIS Data and the precision with which the GIS Data may depict distance, direction, location, or other geographic features.  If you transmit or provide the GIS Data (or any portion of it) to another user, it is recommended that the GIS Data include a copy of this disclaimer and this metadata.</distliab>
    <stdorder>
      <ordering>See Online Linkage Below</ordering>
    </stdorder>
    <distrib>
      <cntinfo>
        <cntperp>
          <cntorg>Metropolitan Council</cntorg>
          <cntper>Jon Hoekenga</cntper>
        </cntperp>
        <cntpos>GIS System Administrator</cntpos>
        <cntaddr>
          <addrtype>mailing and physical</addrtype>
          <address>390 Robert Street North</address>
          <city>St. Paul</city>
          <state>MN</state>
          <postal>55101-1805</postal>
        </cntaddr>
        <cntvoice>651.602.1561</cntvoice>
        <cntemail>jonathan.hoekenga@metc.state.mn.us</cntemail>
      </cntinfo>
    </distrib>
  </distinfo>
  <metainfo>
    <metd>20130624</metd>
    <metstdn>Minnesota Geographic Metadata Guidelines</metstdn>
    <metstdv>1.2</metstdv>
    <metextns>
      <onlink>http://www.mngeo.state.mn.us/committee/standards/mgmg/metadata.htm</onlink>
    </metextns>
    <metc>
      <cntinfo>
        <cntperp>
          <cntorg>Metropolitan Council - Metro Transit</cntorg>
          <cntper>Kyle Burrows</cntper>
        </cntperp>
        <cntpos>Associate Planner</cntpos>
        <cntaddr>
          <addrtype>mailing and physical</addrtype>
          <address>560 6th Ave N</address>
          <city>Minneapolis</city>
          <state>MN</state>
          <postal>55411</postal>
        </cntaddr>
        <cntvoice>612.349.7749</cntvoice>
        <cntemail>kyle.burrows@metrotransit.org</cntemail>
      </cntinfo>
    </metc>
  </metainfo>
  <eainfo>
    <overview>
      <eaover>Market Areas:  Numerical market area designation</eaover>
    </overview>
  </eainfo>
  <dataqual>
    <lineage>
      <procstep>
        <procdesc>The base geography used to develop transit market areas is the 
census block group. Aggregation and smoothing applied to the geographies and may not match other data set boundaries. </procdesc>
      </procstep>
    </lineage>
  </dataqual>
  <spref>
    <horizsys>
      <planar>
        <gridsys>
          <gridsysn>Universal Transverse Mercator</gridsysn>
          <utm>
            <utmzone>15</utmzone>
          </utm>
        </gridsys>
        <planci>
          <plandu>meters</plandu>
        </planci>
      </planar>
      <geodetic>
        <horizdn>NAD83</horizdn>
        <ellips>GRS80</ellips>
      </geodetic>
    </horizsys>
  </spref>
</metadata>
