<?xml version="1.0"?><metadata><idinfo><citation><citeinfo><origin>Minnesota Department of Natural Resources (DNR), Ecological and Water Resources Division, County Geologic Atlas Program</origin><title>Pollution Sensitivity of the Bedrock Surface, Minnesota Hydrogeology Atlas series HG-01</title><pubinfo><publish>Minnesota Department of Natural Resources (DNR)</publish></pubinfo><pubdate>20160212</pubdate><onlink>https://gisdata.mn.gov/dataset/geos-hydrogeology-atlas-hg01</onlink></citeinfo></citation><descript><abstract>Pollution Sensitivity of the Bedrock Surface characterizes the relative rate of vertical travel time of a contaminant that moves conservatively with or within water from the land surface to the buried bedrock surface. Legacy maps from the County Geologic Atlas program were used and modified to reflect the bedrock surface since some legacy maps were created for specific units or aquifers. These data will be updated with every new atlas.</abstract><purpose>Minnesota Hydrogeology Atlas was created to help manage and protect groundwater resources by providing accessible, statewide, hydrogeologic data. The Pollution Sensitivity of the Bedrock Surface was created in order to compile legacy data of bedrock pollution sensitivity. These legacy data were modified to reflect the bedrock surface in mapped areas across the state.</purpose><supplinf>Minnesota</supplinf></descript><status><progress>Complete</progress><update>As needed</update></status><spdom><bounding><westbc>-97.23</westbc><eastbc>-89.53</eastbc><northbc>49.37</northbc><southbc>43.5</southbc></bounding></spdom><keywords><theme><themekey>pollution, sensitivity, pollution sensitivity, bedrock, bedrock surface, vertical travel time, groundwater, resources, geologic, hydrogeology</themekey></theme><place><placekey>Anoka, Blue Earth, Carlton, Carver, Chisago, Dakota, Fillmore, Goodhue, McLeod, Mower, Nicollet, Olmsted, Pine, Ramsey, Renville, Rice, Scott, Sibley, Wabasha, Minnesota</placekey></place></keywords><timeperd><current>Data were obtained from County Geologic Atlases completed between 1988 and Time Period of Content.</current><timeinfo><sngdate><caldate>20160211</caldate></sngdate></timeinfo></timeperd><accconst>None</accconst><useconst>Users may wish to verify critical information; sources include both the references here and information on file in the offices of the Minnesota Geological Survey and the Department of Natural Resources. Every effort has been made to ensure the interpretation shown conforms to sound hydrogeologic and cartographic principles. This map should not be used to establish legal title, boundaries, or locations of improvements. The user is responsible for the results of any application of data other than its intended purposes.</useconst><crossref><citeinfo><title>County Geologic Atlas, available at http://www.dnr.state.mn.us/waters/groundwater_section/mapping/status.html</title></citeinfo></crossref><browse><browsen>http://www.dnr.state.mn.us/waters/programs/gw_section/mapping/platesum/mha_ps-bs.html</browsen></browse><ptcontac><cntinfo><cntperp><cntorg>Minnesota Department of Natural Resources</cntorg><cntper>Holly Johnson</cntper></cntperp><cntpos>GIS Specialist</cntpos><cntaddr><addrtype>mailing and physical</addrtype><address>500 Lafayette Rd</address><city>St. Paul</city><state>MN</state><postal>55155-4025</postal></cntaddr><cntvoice>651-259-5693</cntvoice><cntemail>holly.je.johnson@state.mn.us</cntemail></cntinfo></ptcontac></idinfo><distinfo><distliab>These data were compiled and generated in a geographic information system (GIS) from publicly available information only. Every reasonable effort has been made to ensure the accuracy of the factual data on which the individual interpretations were based. However, the DNR does not warrant the accuracy, completeness, or any implied uses of these data. Users may wish to verify critical information; sources include both the references here and the information on file in the offices of the Minnesota Geological Survey and the Minnesota Department of Natural Resources.

The Minnesota Department of Natural Resources General Geographic Data License Agreement is online: http://www.dnr.state.mn.us/sitetools/data_software_license.html</distliab><resdesc>geos_hydrogeology_atlas_hg01</resdesc><stdorder><ordering>All reports, maps, GIS data, and metadata are available on the Pollution Sensitivity of the Bedrock Surface page: http://www.dnr.state.mn.us/waters/programs/gw_section/mapping/platesum/mha_ps-bs.html

Please visit the download page for this dataset on the Minnesota Geospatial Commons website using the web link below (Online Linkage).</ordering></stdorder><distrib><cntinfo><cntperp><cntorg>Minnesota Department of Natural Resources</cntorg><cntper>Holly Johnson</cntper></cntperp><cntpos>GIS Specialist</cntpos><cntaddr><addrtype>mailing and physical</addrtype><address>500 Lafayette Rd</address><city>St. Paul</city><state>MN</state><postal>55155-4025</postal></cntaddr><cntvoice>651-259-5693</cntvoice><cntemail>holly.je.johnson@state.mn.us</cntemail></cntinfo></distrib></distinfo><metainfo><metd>20160212</metd><metstdn>Minnesota Geographic Metadata Guidelines</metstdn><metstdv>1.2</metstdv><metextns><onlink>http://www.mngeo.state.mn.us/committee/standards/mgmg/metadata.htm</onlink></metextns><metc><cntinfo><cntperp><cntorg>Minnesota Department of Natural Resources</cntorg><cntper>Holly Johnson</cntper></cntperp><cntpos>GIS Specialist</cntpos><cntaddr><addrtype>mailing and physical</addrtype><address>500 Lafayette Rd</address><city>St. Paul</city><state>MN</state><postal>55155-4025</postal></cntaddr><cntvoice>651-259-5693</cntvoice><cntemail>holly.je.johnson@state.mn.us</cntemail></cntinfo></metc></metainfo><eainfo><detailed><enttyp><enttypl>bedrocksurface_pollutionsensitivity</enttypl></enttyp><attr><attrlabl>ATLAS</attrlabl><attrdef>County Geologic Atlas Series Identifier</attrdef></attr><attr><attrlabl>COUN</attrlabl><attrdef>County number</attrdef></attr><attr><attrlabl>CTY_NAME</attrlabl><attrdef>County name</attrdef></attr><attr><attrlabl>ORG_RATING</attrlabl><attrdef>Rating given in the original map and spatial data</attrdef></attr><attr><attrlabl>RATING</attrlabl><attrdef>Sensitivity rating created to unify the compilation</attrdef></attr></detailed><overview><eaover>This data is a compilation of previously published CGA plates that represent the pollution sensitivity of the bedrock surface. The data were not spatial altered. Tabular data were added to reflect a common sensitivity rating system.</eaover></overview></eainfo><dataqual><complete>The bedrock surface pollution sensitivity is available for counties that previously contained this map layer, either if it was digitally available in the original County Geologic Atlases (CGAs), or it had been converted to digital format after publication. This product is updated when new atlases are completed; those data are integrated into this product. Areas that are not rated have either not been completed, not been digitized, are currently being updated, or their pollution sensitivity maps depict particular bedrock units or bedrock aquifers that do not form the top of bedrock surface.</complete><lineage><procstep><procdesc>CGAs with bedrock surface pollution sensitivity in spatial format were collected for those applicable counties. Updated travel time and rating terminology was applied to the original terminology in order to have consistency across the map layer. Individual maps were then unioned together into one spatial file.</procdesc></procstep></lineage><attracc><attraccr>1:100,000</attraccr></attracc></dataqual><spref><horizsys><planar><gridsys><gridsysn>Universal Transverse Mercator</gridsysn><utm><utmzone>15</utmzone></utm></gridsys><planci><plandu>meters</plandu></planci></planar><geodetic><horizdn>NAD83</horizdn><ellips>GRS80</ellips></geodetic></horizsys></spref></metadata>