<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!--  <!DOCTYPE metadata SYSTEM "metadata.dtd">-->
<metadata>
    <idinfo>
        <citation>
            <citeinfo>
                <origin>Minnesota Geological Survey (MGS) and Minnesota Department of Natural Resources (DNR)</origin>
                <pubdate>1993</pubdate>
                <title>Regional Hydrogeologic Assessment - Anoka Sand Plain, Minnesota</title>
                <mgmg1cid/>
                <pubinfo>
                    <publish>Minnesota Geological Survey</publish>
                </pubinfo>
                <onlink>http://conservancy.umn.edu/handle/11299/59762</onlink>
            </citeinfo>
        </citation>
        <descript>
            <abstract>A County Geologic Atlas is a systematic study of a county's geologic and ground water resources. Geologic studies include both near-surface deposits and bedrock.  Ground water studies include flow systems, aquifer capacity, and ground water chemistry.  In some areas sand and gravel deposits, sinkholes, or other features are studied.  Interpretation of sensitivity to pollution is also part of an atlas.  The information is organized, analyzed, and displayed using geographic information technology.

A Regional Hydrogeologic Assessment (RHA) is similar to a County Geologic Atlas in that both geology and ground water are studied.  However, a Regional Hydrogeologic Assessment covers a larger area, typically four to nine counties, in less detail.  The  RHA emphasizes near-surface geologic, ground water, and pollution sensitivity mapping.</abstract>
            <purpose>County Geologic Atlas and Regional Hydrogeologic Assessment information is used in planning and environmental protection efforts at all levels of government.  Wellhead protection and well-sealing programs are examples of local programs that need geologic and ground water information. The information is also used by businesses and the general public.</purpose>
            <supplinf>Anoka Sand Plain Area of Minnesota, comprising all or portions of the counties of Anoka, Chisago, Isanti, and Sherburne.</supplinf>
        </descript>
        <timeperd>
            <timeinfo>
                <sngdate>
                    <caldate>1993</caldate>
                </sngdate>
            </timeinfo>
            <current>Geologic Maps were derived based on information available during the period 1991-1993.</current>
        </timeperd>
        <status>
            <progress>Complete</progress>
            <update>None Planned</update>
        </status>
        <spdom>
            <bounding>
                <westbc>-94.17</westbc>
                <eastbc>-92.5</eastbc>
                <northbc>45.75</northbc>
                <southbc>45.00</southbc>
            </bounding>
        </spdom>
        <keywords>
            <theme>
                <themekt>ISO 19115 Topic Category</themekt>
                <themekey>geoscientificInformation, Geology, Hydrogeology, Surficial Geology, Pollution Sensitivity, Regional Hydrogeologic Assessment</themekey>
            </theme>
            <place>
                <placekey>Minnesota, MN, Anoka Sand Plain, Anoka County, Chisago County, Isanti County, Sherburne County</placekey>
            </place>
        </keywords>
        <accconst>None</accconst>
        <browse>
            <browsed>.pdf file representing one of the map plates for the RHA</browsed>
        </browse>
        <native>Arc/INFO</native>
        <crossref>
            <citeinfo>
                <title>Map Series and Report:  Anoka Sand Plain Regional Hydrogeologic Assessment, Report RHA-1, Meyer, G.N., Patterson, C.J., Hobbs, H.C., Lehr, J.d., (Minnesota Geological Survey, 1993). Report is out of print. 

There is no &quot;Part B&quot; for this Atlas.  Both geology and hydrogeology are included in this map product. 

For a listing of Maps and Data published by the Minnesota Geological Survey, see U of M Library Digital Conservancy: http://conservancy.umn.edu/handle/11299/708

For additional information on the DNR Ground Water Mapping Program, visit: 
http://www.dnr.state.mn.us/waters/groundwater_section/mapping/index.html</title>
            </citeinfo>
        </crossref>
        <useconst>Credit should be given to the Minnesota Geological Survey and the Minnesota Department of Natural Resources for any use of the given digital data in any publication.</useconst>
        <ptcontac>
            <cntinfo>
                <cntperp>
                    <cntorg>Minnesota Geological Survey</cntorg>
                    <cntper>Gary N. Meyer</cntper>
                </cntperp>
                <cntpos>Quaternary Geology</cntpos>
                <cntaddr>
                    <addrtype>Mailing and Physical</addrtype>
                    <address>2609 Territorial Road</address>
                    <city>St. Paul</city>
                    <state>MN</state>
                    <postal>55114</postal>
                </cntaddr>
                <cntvoice>612-626-1741</cntvoice>
                <cntemail>meyer015@umn.edu</cntemail>
            </cntinfo>
        </ptcontac>
    </idinfo>
    <dataqual>
        <lineage>
            <srcinfo>
                <srcscale>200000</srcscale>
            </srcinfo>
            <procstep>
                <procdesc>Investigations begin with a review of existing information, such as earlier geologic maps, soil maps, and hydrologic reports. Drillers send water well logs to the Minnesota Geological Survey, where they are reviewed, interpreted, and entered into the County Well Index (CWI), an interactive data base of water-well information.  Building on the previous data, field studies are conducted to improve the understanding of local geologic and hydrologic conditions.

Data was originally digitized in UTM Coordinates, Zone 15, NAD27, with a y-shift of 4,700,000. In 1999 the data was converted to UTM, Zone 15, NAD83, unshifted.

There is no layer-specific metadata for this data set. </procdesc>
            </procstep>
        </lineage>
        <logic>Not available</logic>
        <complete>Not available</complete>
        <posacc>
            <horizpa>
                <horizpar>Not available</horizpar>
            </horizpa>
        </posacc>
        <attracc>
            <attraccr>Not available</attraccr>
        </attracc>
    </dataqual>
    <spdoinfo>
        <indspref/>
        <direct>Vector</direct>
        <mgmg3obj>Point, Vector</mgmg3obj>
        <mgmg3til>Anoka Sand Plain Study Area; some overlay files are in county tiles.</mgmg3til>
    </spdoinfo>
    <eainfo>
        <overview>
            <eaover>The Anoka Sand Plain Regional Hydrogeologic Assessment consists of 23 separate GIS data layers. Five were created by the Minnesota Geological Survey especially for this assessment; the others are background layers from various sources used as reference and for cartography.  Much of the background information is from the Bureau of the Census TIGER Line files. 

The geology work was based on creating a map series at 1:200,000. Some of the background layers consist of larger-scale data. (TIGER data is scaled at 1:100,000).  An overall scale of 1:200,000 is assigned to the dataset. 

The data is accompanied by two text files, describing Pollution Sensitivity and Surficial Geology.</eaover>
            <eadetcit>ANOKA SAND PLAIN REGIONAL ASSESSMENT DATA:

Covers created by the Minnesota Geological Survey:

 aspmw.e00 Anoka Sand Plain Monitoring Wells
 aspps.e00 Anoka Sand Plain Pollution Sensitivity
 aspsg.e00 Anoka Sand Plain Surficial Geology
 aspwt.e00 Anoka Sand Plain Water Table
 aspww.e00 Anoka Sand Plain Water Wells 

Covers from other sources representing background cartographic information. (These are largely derived from Census TIGER-Line data):
 
 asphydro.e00 Anoka Sand Plain Area Surface Hydrology 
 asproads.e00 Anoka Sand Plain Area Roads 
 c02bord.e00 Anoka County Border
 c02quad.e00 Anoka County Quad Borders
 c02sec.e00 Anoka County Section Lines
 c02tr.e00 Anoka County Township Lines
 c13bord.e00 Chisago County Border
 c13quad.e00 Chisago CountyQuad Borders
 c13sec.e00 Chisago County Section Lines
 c13tr.e00 Chisago County Township Lines
 c30bord.e00 Isanti County Border
 c30quad.e00 Isanti County Quad Borders 
 c30sec.e00 Isanti County Section Lines
 c30tr.e00 Isanti County Township Lines
 c71bord.e00 Sherburne County Border
 c71quad.e00 Sherburne County Quad Borders
 c71sec.e00 Sherburne County Section Lines
 c71tr.e00 Sherburne County Township Lines

 Text Files:

 aspps.txt Text for Pollution Sensitivity Cover
 aspsg.txt Text for Surficial Geology Cover


ASPPS.TXT . . CODE FILE FOR ANOKA SAND PLAIN POLLUTION SENSITIVITY COVER (ASPPS)

MGSCODE ** DEFINITION OF CODE ** TRAVEL TIME

(Travel time represents the estimated time of travel for contamination to reach the uppermost aquifer).

421** water
440051** low ** Decades to a century
440052**moderate** Years to a decade
440053** high** Weeks to years
440054** very high** Hours to minutes


ASPSG.TXT . . CODE FILE FOR ANOKA SAND PLAIN SURFICIAL GEOLOGY COVER (ASPSG)
 
Postglacial Deposits
 
 MGSCODE** DEFINITION
 
 421** water
 443001** organic deposits
 443002** alluvium
 443003** eolian sand
 443004** terrace deposits
 443005** lake silt and clay
 
Grantsburg Sublobe Deposits

 MGSCODE** DEFINITION
 
 443101**  lake sand
 443107**  lake silt and clay
 443102**  outwash deposits
 443103**  ice-contact deposits
 443106**  till
 443104**  till - yellow-brown (oxidized)
 443105**  till of mixed composition

Superior Lobe Deposits

 MGSCODE** DEFINITION

 443205**  lake silt and clay
 443202**  outwash deposits
 443203**  ice-contact deposits
 443204**  till- red brown

Bedrock

 MGSCODE** DEFINITION
 
 442001**  ordovician, cambrian, or precambrian</eadetcit>
        </overview>
    </eainfo>
    <distinfo>
        <resdesc>rha-1 (asp) (http://conservancy.umn.edu/handle/11299/59762)</resdesc>
        <stdorder>
            <digform>
                <digtinfo>
                    <formname>Arc Export</formname>
                    <formvern>Arc 7.2.1</formvern>
                    <transize>5.9 MB in self-extracting zipfile (.exe) format</transize>
                </digtinfo>
            </digform>
            <ordering>Digital data and PDF files representing map plates are available for download from the University of Minnesota Libraries Digital Conservancy.  The direct Digital Conservancy Link to this product is http://conservancy.umn.edu/handle/11299/59762

</ordering>
        </stdorder>
        <distrib>
            <cntinfo>
                <cntperp>
                    <cntorg>Minnesota Geological Survey</cntorg>
                    <cntper>Timothy E. Wahl</cntper>
                </cntperp>
                <cntpos>Geologic Information Systems</cntpos>
                <cntaddr>
                    <addrtype>mailing and physical</addrtype>
                    <address>2609 Territorial Road</address>
                    <city>St. Paul</city>
                    <state>MN</state>
                    <postal>55114</postal>
                </cntaddr>
                <cntvoice>612-626-0992</cntvoice>
                <cntemail>tewahl@umn.edu</cntemail>
            </cntinfo>
        </distrib>
    </distinfo>
    <metainfo>
        <metd>20150418</metd>
        <metstdn>Minnesota Geographic Metadata Guidelines</metstdn>
        <metstdv>1.2</metstdv>
        <metextns>
            <onlink>http://www.mngeo.state.mn.us/committee/standards/mgmg/metadata.htm
</onlink>
        </metextns>
        <metc>
            <cntinfo>
                <cntperp>
                    <cntorg>Minnesota Geospatial Information Office (MnGeo)</cntorg>
                    <cntper>Nancy Rader</cntper>
                </cntperp>
                <cntpos>GIS Data Coordinator</cntpos>
                <cntaddr>
                    <addrtype>mailing and physical</addrtype>
                    <address>658 Cedar Street</address>
                    <city>St. Paul</city>
                    <state>MN</state>
                    <postal>55155</postal>
                </cntaddr>
                <cntvoice>651-201-2489</cntvoice>
                <cntemail>gisinfo.mngeo@state.mn.us</cntemail>
            </cntinfo>
        </metc>
    </metainfo>
    <spref>
        <horizsys>
            <planar>
                <gridsys>
                    <gridsysn>Universal Transverse Mercator</gridsysn>
                    <utm>
                        <utmzone>15E</utmzone>
                    </utm>
                </gridsys>
                <planci>
                    <plandu>meters</plandu>
                </planci>
            </planar>
            <geodetic>
                <horizdn>NAD83</horizdn>
                <ellips>GRS80</ellips>
            </geodetic>
        </horizsys>
    </spref>
</metadata>