<?xml version="1.0"?><!--  <!DOCTYPE metadata SYSTEM "metadata.dtd">  --><metadata><idinfo><citation><citeinfo><origin>Minnesota Geological Survey</origin><pubdate>2001</pubdate><title>Geologic Atlas of Wabasha County, Minnesota  (Part A)</title><mgmg1cid></mgmg1cid><pubinfo><publish>Minnesota Geological Survey</publish></pubinfo><onlink>http://conservancy.umn.edu/handle/11299/58557</onlink></citeinfo></citation><descript><abstract>A County Geologic Atlas is a systematic study of a county's geologic and ground water resources. Geologic studies include both near-surface deposits and bedrock. Ground water studies include flow systems, aquifer capacity, and ground water chemistry. In some areas sand and gravel deposits, sinkholes, or other features are studied. Interpretation of sensitivity to pollution is also part of an atlas. The information is organized, analyzed, and displayed using geographic information technology.

Most Geologic Atlas and Regional Hydrogeologic Assessment projects are done in two parts. The Minnesota Geological Survey covers basic geology and creates databases of information such as wells and soil borings in part A. The Minnesota Department of Natural Resources handles hydrogeology and ground water sensitivity layers in Part B. Completion of a project's two parts is staggered: Part A is completed about two years before Part B, compiling information used to create part B. Parts A and B are published and distributed as two separate products.</abstract><purpose>County Geologic Atlas and Regional Hydrogeologic Assessment information is used in planning and environmental protection efforts at all levels of government. Wellhead protection and well-sealing programs are examples of local programs that need geologic and ground water information. The information is also used by businesses and the general public.</purpose><supplinf>Wabasha County, Minnesota</supplinf></descript><timeperd><timeinfo><sngdate><caldate>2001</caldate></sngdate></timeinfo><current>The GIS files were generated in support of the Wabasha County Geologic Atlas, 1998-2001.  Geologic maps were derived based on information available to MGS during the period 1998-2001.</current></timeperd><status><progress>Complete</progress><update>None Planned</update></status><spdom><bounding><westbc>-92.55</westbc><eastbc>-91.85</eastbc><northbc>44.45</northbc><southbc>44.12</southbc></bounding></spdom><keywords><theme><themekt>ISO 19115 Topic Category</themekt><themekey>geoscientificInformation, Bedrock Geology, Surficial Geology, Quaternary Stratigraphy, Bedrock Topography, Drift Thickness, Bedrock/Aggregate Resources, Quarry, Sand/Gravel, Karst Features, Sinkholes, Springs, Seeps,Wells, Geologic Resources</themekey></theme><place><placekey>Wabasha County, Minnesota, Southeastern Minnesota</placekey></place></keywords><accconst>None</accconst><useconst>Credit should be given to the Minnesota Geological Survey for any use of the given digital data in any publication.</useconst><browse><browsen>None available</browsen></browse><native>Arc/INFO 7.0.4</native><crossref><citeinfo><title>C-14, Part A. Geologic atlas of Wabasha County, Minnesota. Anthony C. Runkel, Project Manager. 2001. Color.  Scale 1:100,000. Paper map and report available from MGS Map Sales Office (2609 Territorial Road, St. Paul, Minnesota, 55114, 612-626-2969.)

For a listing of other geologic maps go to the Minnesota Geological Survey website at http://www.mngs.umn.edu/mgsdocs.html

For a complete listing of MGS State Map Series Maps, Reports, and GIS Data, see http://conservancy.umn.edu/handle/11299/708 

For other County Atlas and Regional Hydrogeologic Assessment data see: http://www.mngs.umn.edu/county_atlas/countyatlas.htm 

For a listing of the status of the DNR Ground Water Mapping Program, go to: http://www.dnr.state.mn.us/waters/groundwater_section/mapping/index.html</title></citeinfo></crossref><ptcontac><cntinfo><cntperp><cntorg>Minnesota Geological Survey</cntorg><cntper>Anthony C. Runkel</cntper></cntperp><cntpos>Chief Geologist</cntpos><cntaddr><addrtype>Mailing and Physical</addrtype><address>2609 Territorial Road</address><city>St. Paul</city><state>MN</state><postal>55114</postal></cntaddr><cntvoice>612-626-1822</cntvoice><cntemail>runke001@umn.edu</cntemail></cntinfo></ptcontac></idinfo><dataqual><attracc><attraccr>See individual layer metadata file.</attraccr></attracc><logic>See individual layer metadata file.</logic><complete>See individual layer metadata file.</complete><posacc><horizpa><horizpar>See individual layer metadata file.</horizpar></horizpa></posacc><lineage><srcinfo><srcscale>100000</srcscale></srcinfo><procstep><procdesc>Investigations begin with a review of existing information, such as earlier geologic maps, soil maps, and hydrologic reports. Drillers send water well logs to the Minnesota Geological Survey, where they are reviewed, interpreted, and entered into the County Well Index (CWI), an interactive data base of water-well information. Building on the previous data, field studies are conducted to improve the understanding of local geologic and hydrologic conditions. Linework is created based upon the field studies and base data, and digitized. Background GIS data layers such as roads, surface hydrography, township grids, etc., are obtained from various sources. See also lineage field on individual layer metadata file.</procdesc></procstep></lineage></dataqual><spdoinfo><indspref></indspref><direct>Vector</direct><mgmg3obj>Point, Vector, Polygon</mgmg3obj><mgmg3til>Wabasha County</mgmg3til></spdoinfo><eainfo><overview><eaover>The following is a list of the digital files used in compiling the Wabasha County Geologic Atlas, 1998-2001.

Data Base plate:
CWIPT = point cover of county well index well locations
SBPT = point cover of MNDOT soil boring locations
GPPT = point cover of seismic line locations
GRPT = point cover of gravity station locations
OCPG    = poly cover of outcrop areas
QSPT = point cover of Quaternary stratigraphy includes:
          Giddings hole &amp; hand sample locations

Bedrock Geology: 
BGNT  = net cover of bedrock and structural geology
STLN  = line/point cover of structural features
STLNCJDN = line cover of top of Jordan bedrock
XSLN  = line cover of cross section traces

Surficial Geology:
SGNT    = net cover of surficial geology
SGPGE    = poly cover of sand dune and loess extent
GMLN   = line/point cover of geomorphic features
TPLN  = line cover of surface topography (20 meter intervals) 

Drift thickness:
DTNT = net cover of drift thickness isopachs
OCPG = polygon cover of outcrop areas

Bedrock topography:
BTNT  = net cover of bedrock topography

Bedrock/Aggregate resources:
RSNTBG = net cover of bedrock geological resources
RSPT = point cover of bedrock quarry and sand/gravel pit locations
RSNTSG   = net cover of surficial resources

Karst Features:
SKPT  = point cover of sink holes; locations verified
SKPTU  = point cover of sink holes; locations unverified
SPPT    = point cover of springs
SEPT  = point cover of seeps
SWPT  = point cover of swallow holes
FLPT  = point cover of flow measurement locations
HYLNLS  = line cover of losing streams
HYLNIN  = line cover of intermittent streams
HYLNPR  = line cover of perennial streams
MSLNXSEC = line cover of cross section line
MSLNFLTS = line cover of fault lines
MSPGKRST = poly cover of karst units
MSPGNKRS = poly cover of non-karst units
OCPGOPDC = poly cover of Prairie du Chien outcrops
MSPGLAKE = poly cover of lakes

GEOGRAPHIC BASE (located in subdirectory wababase):
bsan     = annotation cover for lake, city, etc. names(MGS)
ctybdne2 = project area polygon (DNR)
dlgstln2 = line cover of streams (DNR)
dlglkmd  = poly cover of lakes (DNR)
plsln    = line cover of public land survey, modified from plsscne3 (DNR/MGS)
plsscne3 = net cover of public land survey, T-R-S (DNR)
dotrdln3 = line cover of major highways, roads (MNDOT)
rdpt     = point cover of highway road symbols(MGS)

A text file named MNDOT.txt contains a disclaimer from the Minnesota  Department of Transportation.  This text is required when any of the geographic data from their BaseMap digital set is used by any outside party.</eaover><eadetcit>See individual layer metadata file.</eadetcit></overview></eainfo><distinfo><resdesc>c14 (http://conservancy.umn.edu/handle/11299/58557)</resdesc><stdorder><digform><digtinfo><formname>Arc/Info Export</formname><formvern></formvern><transize>11.7 MB as zipfile</transize></digtinfo></digform><ordering>Data download is from the U of M Libraries Digital Conservancy. All GIS data and metadata for the Wabasha County Geologic Atlas is provided in the zip file C14 Part A Extras.zip. (Supplementary Files).  GIS distribution format for most data in this dataset is Esri .e00 (arc interchange format).

If you would prefer to have the digital data on DVD, contact MGS Map Sales office at (612) 626-2969. 

The direct Digital Conservancy link to PDF map products and GIS data projects (Supplementary Files) for this data set is: http://conservancy.umn.edu/handle/11299/58557

If you would like paper copies of the geologic plates; contact the MGS Map Sales office at 612-626-2969 and specify publication County Atlas Series C-14, part A, or County Geologic Atlas of Wabasha County.</ordering></stdorder><distrib><cntinfo><cntperp><cntorg>Minnesota Geological Survey</cntorg><cntper>Timothy E. Wahl</cntper></cntperp><cntpos>Geologic Information Systems</cntpos><cntaddr><addrtype>mailing and physical</addrtype><address>2609 Territorial Road</address><city>St. Paul</city><state>MN</state><postal>55114</postal></cntaddr><cntvoice>612-626-0992</cntvoice><cntemail>tewahl@umn.edu</cntemail></cntinfo></distrib></distinfo><metainfo><metd>20150416</metd><metstdn>Minnesota Geographic Metadata Guidelines</metstdn><metstdv>1.2</metstdv><metextns><onlink>http://www.lmic.state.mn.us/gc/stds/metadata.htm</onlink></metextns><metc><cntinfo><cntperp><cntorg>Minnesota Geospatial Information Office (MnGeo)</cntorg><cntper>Nancy Rader</cntper></cntperp><cntpos>GIS Data Coordinator</cntpos><cntaddr><addrtype>mailing and physical</addrtype><address>658 Cedar Street, Room 300</address><city>St. Paul</city><state>MN</state><postal>55155</postal></cntaddr><cntvoice>651-201-2489</cntvoice><cntemail>gisinfo.mngeo@state.mn.us</cntemail></cntinfo></metc></metainfo><spref><horizsys><planar><gridsys><gridsysn>Universal Transverse Mercator</gridsysn><utm><utmzone>15E</utmzone></utm></gridsys><planci><plandu>meters</plandu></planci></planar><geodetic><horizdn>NAD83</horizdn><ellips>GRS80</ellips></geodetic></horizsys></spref></metadata>