<?xml version="1.0"?><metadata><idinfo><citation><citeinfo><title>MetroGIS Address Points Dataset</title><origin>Contains data originating from cities and counties in the Twin Cities metropolitan area.</origin><pubinfo><publish>Metropolitan Council</publish></pubinfo><pubdate>periodically revised</pubdate><onlink>https://gisdata.mn.gov/dataset/us-mn-state-metrogis-loc-address-points</onlink></citeinfo></citation><descript><abstract>This dataset is a compilation of address point data from metro area address authorities, which are predominantly cities. The dataset is intended to contain a point location and the official address (as defined by the address authority) for all occupiable units and any other official addresses within the jurisdictional boundary of each address authority. A number of other attributes are available in the dataset, but may not be populated by some address authorities. 

Metro area counties are playing a coordinative role to work with cities to create, maintain and aggregate address points.  Currently this dataset contains points for Carver, Dakota  and Ramsey counties. It will grow over time as more counties contribute  data. </abstract><purpose>To view, query and analyze address point data anywhere it is available in the seven county metro area, and to have a single, authoritative source of the official address for any location</purpose><supplinf>Contributing counties in Minnesota</supplinf></descript><timeperd><timeinfo><sngdate><caldate>20150115</caldate></sngdate></timeinfo><current>Currently this dataset is updated on a quarterly basis (January, April, July, October), though more frequent updates are planned in the future and additional updates between quarters are possible now. It is up to each address authority to work with their county to send updates to the data distributor, Metropolitan Council. This dataset contains all updates received by the Metropolitan Council as of the Time Period of Content date shown above.</current></timeperd><status><progress>In work</progress><update>Irregular</update></status><spdom><bounding><westbc>-94.012</westbc><eastbc>-92.732</eastbc><northbc>45.415</northbc><southbc>44.471</southbc></bounding></spdom><keywords><place><placekey>Twin Cities, Anoka County, Carver County, Dakota County, Hennepin County, Ramsey County, Scott County, Washington County</placekey></place><theme><themekey>addresses, address points, mailing</themekey><themekt>None</themekt></theme></keywords><accconst>None</accconst><useconst>None</useconst><crossref><citeinfo><title>MetroGIS Regional Parcel Dataset</title></citeinfo></crossref><native>Native environment varies by address authority.</native><ptcontac><cntinfo><cntperp><cntorg>Metropolitan Council</cntorg><cntper>Jon Hoekenga</cntper></cntperp><cntpos>GIS System Administrator</cntpos><cntaddr><addrtype>mailing and physical</addrtype><address>390 Robert Street North</address><city>St. Paul</city><state>MN</state><postal>55101-1805</postal></cntaddr><cntvoice>651.602.1561</cntvoice><cntemail>jonathan.hoekenga@metc.state.mn.us</cntemail></cntinfo></ptcontac></idinfo><dataqual><attracc><attraccr>This regional dataset requires that all contributing datasets be submitted with a standard set of attributes.  However, many attributes are optional. Full databases specificaions can be found at &lt;a href="MetroGIS_Address_Points_Database_Specifications.pdf" target=_blank&gt;MetroGIS Address Points Database Specifications&lt;/a&gt; .  No attempt has been made by MetroGIS to assess the accuracy of the attribute data.  Please report any perceived discrepancies or errors in the data to the designated data provider. A list can be found in the &lt;a href="MetroGIS_Address_Points_Data_Provider_Registry.pdf" target=_blank&gt;MetroGIS Address Points Data Provider Registry&lt;/a&gt;</attraccr></attracc><logic>The dataset is topologically 'clean'.</logic><complete>No attempt has been made by MetroGIS to assess the completeness of addresses or attributes provided by address authorities.  The datasets tested to ensure that all required attributes are populated.</complete><posacc><horizpa><horizpar>No attempt has been made by MetroGIS to assess the horizontal positional accuracy of points in this dataset. See the Positional Accuracy Indicator attribute for feature level information about positional accuracy.

It has been observed for multi-address parcels that in some instances all address points are provided and in other instances only a single point is provided, even when multiple official addresses exist within that parcel.  In other cases, some but not all address points are provided for such parcels.  Data users should use some discretion in making assumptions about the completeness of the dataset.  It is expected that this dataset will become more complete over time.</horizpar></horizpa></posacc><lineage><procstep><procdesc>Each county participating in the MetroGIS GIS Address Points Dataset works with the city address authorities within their jurisdiction to create and maintain the address points data.  Counties then contribute a file geodatabases  to the Metropolitan Council where they are aggregated using geoprocessing methods and made available for redistribution. No attempt is made to further process the data at the regional level. For information about lineage at the data development level, contact each address authority. </procdesc></procstep><srcinfo><srcscale></srcscale></srcinfo></lineage></dataqual><spdoinfo><indspref>Address</indspref><direct>Point</direct><mgmg3obj>Point</mgmg3obj><mgmg3til>One layer for entire area covered</mgmg3til></spdoinfo><eainfo><overview><eaover>A list of the attribute names and field types is shown below.  Detailed information
about the attributes within the &lt;a href="MetroGIS_Address_Points_Database_Specifications.pdf" target=_blank&gt;MetroGIS Address Points Database Specifications&lt;/a&gt; 

Field Name  Description
------------------------------------------------------------------------------------
ADD_ID_NAT:  National Address Unique ID (Text 60)

ADD_ID_LOC:  Local Address Unique ID (Text 50)

ANUMBERPRE:  Address Number Prefix (Text 6)

ANUMBER:     Address Number (Integer10)

ANUMBERSUF:  Address Number Suffix (Text 6)

ANUMBERSEP:  Address Number Separator Element (Text 1)

ST_PRE_MOD:  Street Name Pre Modifier (Text 10)

ST_PRE_DIR:  Street Name Pre Directional (Text 9)

ST_PRE_TYP:  Street Name Pre Type (Text 24)

ST_NAME:     Street Name (Text 42)

ST_POS_TYP:  Street Name Post Type (Text 12)

ST_POS_DIR:  Street Name Post Directiona (Text 9)

ST_POS_MOD:  Street Name Post Modifier (Text 12)

SUB_TYPE1:   Subaddress Type 1 (Text 12)

SUB_ID1:     Subaddress Identifier 1 (Text 12)

SUB_TYPE2:   Subaddress Type 2 (Text 12)

SUB_ID2:     Subaddress Identifier 2 (Text 12)

MUNI_NAME:   Municipal Jurisdiction Name (Text 30)

MUNI_CODE:   Munipal Jurisdiction Code (Text 8)

USPS_PLACE:  USPS Place Name (Text 30)

CO_CODE:    County Code (Text 3)

CO_NAME:     County Name (Text 20)

STATE_CODE:  State Code (Text 2)

ZIP:    Zip Code  (Text 5)

ZIP4:        Zip Plus 4 (Text 4)

LOC_DESC:    Location Description (Text 40)

LANDMARK:    Landmark Name (Text 40)

RESIDENCE:   Residence (Text 10)

MAILABLE :   Mailable Address (Text 10)

STATUS:      Lifecycle Status (Text 10)

PIN:         Parcel Unique Identifier (Text 17)

LONGITUDE:   Longitude (Double)

LATITUDE:    Latitude (Double)

POSI_ACCU:   Positional Accuracy Indicator (Integer2)

ADIRSOURCE:  Address Direct Source (Text 40)

AAUTHORITY:  Address Authority (Text 40)

EDIT_ORG:    Editing Organization (Text 40)

UPDATEDATE:  Update Date (Date)

COMMENTS:    Comments (Text 254)</eaover><eadetcit>A detailed description of the attributes available in this dataset can be found within the &lt;a href="MetroGIS_Address_Points_Database_Specifications.pdf" target=_blank&gt;MetroGIS Address Points Database Specifications&lt;/a&gt; </eadetcit></overview></eainfo><distinfo><resdesc>AddressPoints</resdesc><distliab>NOTICE:

By accessing these geographic information system (GIS) data, you agree to be bound by the terms and conditions provided below.  These GIS data are made available as a public service. The data have been compiled using information received from Data Contributors including cities and counties. Data Contributors are not obligated to provide updates to data when newer versions become available. Although reasonable efforts have been made to ensure the accuracy of these data, no guarantee is given or implied.

Maps and data are to be used for reference purposes only. All users are strongly urged to independently verify these data before relying on such data. The use of these data is at the sole risk of the party using such data. Data Contributors may make changes or corrections to the data and to these conditions at any time without notice.

Data Contributors, and their officials, employees and agents, supplying these data cannot be held liable for any improper or incorrect use of the information. They assume no responsibility for any use of the information. They will not be liable for any direct, indirect, incidental, special, exemplary, or consequential damages however caused and on any theory of liability arising in any way out of the use of these data. All information is provided "as-is" without any warranty of any kind. All warranties of any kind, express or implied, such as merchantability and fitness for a particular purpose, are specifically disclaimed.

User agrees to defend, indemnify, and hold harmless, the Data Contributors, and their officials, employees and agents from and against all claims and expenses, including attorneys' fees, arising out of the use of these data.

This agreement is governed by the law of Minnesota, and any lawsuits involving this agreement or these data must take place in Minnesota. This agreement is the exclusive statement of the agreement between the parties and may be modified only by a written agreement.

By using these data, the user acknowledges that the above conditions have been read and that the user is bound by them.</distliab><stdorder><digform><digtinfo><formname>Shapefile</formname><formvern>ArcGIS 9x</formvern><transize></transize></digtinfo></digform><ordering>See Online Linkage Below</ordering></stdorder><distrib><cntinfo><cntperp><cntorg>Metropolitan Council</cntorg><cntper>Jon Hoekenga</cntper></cntperp><cntpos>GIS System Administrator</cntpos><cntaddr><addrtype>mailing and physical</addrtype><address>390 Robert Street North</address><city>St. Paul</city><state>MN</state><postal>55101-1805</postal></cntaddr><cntvoice>651.602.1561</cntvoice><cntemail>jonathan.hoekenga@metc.state.mn.us</cntemail></cntinfo></distrib></distinfo><metainfo><metd>20150115</metd><metstdn>Minnesota Geographic Metadata Guidelines</metstdn><metstdv>1.2</metstdv><metextns><onlink>http://www.gis.state.mn.us/stds/metadata.htm</onlink></metextns><metc><cntinfo><cntperp><cntorg>Metropolitan Council</cntorg><cntper>Jon Hoekenga</cntper></cntperp><cntpos>GIS System Administrator</cntpos><cntaddr><addrtype>mailing and physical</addrtype><address>390 Robert Street North</address><city>St. Paul</city><state>MN</state><postal>55101-1805</postal></cntaddr><cntvoice>651.602.1561</cntvoice><cntemail>jonathan.hoekenga@metc.state.mn.us</cntemail></cntinfo></metc></metainfo><Esri><ModDate>20110721</ModDate><ModTime>14080800</ModTime></Esri><mdDateSt Sync="TRUE">20110721</mdDateSt><spref><horizsys><planar><gridsys><gridsysn>Universal Transverse Mercator</gridsysn><utm><utmzone>15</utmzone></utm></gridsys><planci><plandu>meters</plandu></planci></planar><geodetic><horizdn>NAD83</horizdn><ellips>GRS80</ellips></geodetic></horizsys></spref></metadata>