<!--  <!DOCTYPE metadata SYSTEM "metadata.dtd">  -->
<metadata>
  <idinfo>
    <citation>
      <citeinfo>
        <origin>Minnesota Geospatial Information Office</origin>
        <pubdate>201102</pubdate>
        <title>Composite Image Service WMS, Minnesota</title>
        <mgmg1cid/>
        <pubinfo>
          <publish>Minnesota Geospatial Information Office</publish>
        </pubinfo>
        <onlink>http://www.mngeo.state.mn.us/chouse/wms/composite_image.html</onlink>
      </citeinfo>
    </citation>
    <descript>
      <abstract>The goal of the Composite Image Service is to provide a single layer image service with the 'best' air photo or satellite image available for a certain extent.  The images are provided as a WMS (web map service).  The primary focus is the Twin Cities Metropolitan Area and the State of Minnesota.  The secondary interest is the areas bordering Minnesota, especially Wisconsin counties close to the metro area.

Imagery is evaluated based on criteria of color, currency, resolution, coverage, season, leaf cover and image quality in order to determine which imagery to include at which scale.  See the Lineage field for a list of imagery layers that are visible at different scales.

More information about this map service and the imagery resources displayed at various scales is available on the MnGeo Composite Image Service webpage:  http://www.mngeo.state.mn.us/chouse/wms/composite_image.html</abstract>
      <purpose>This image service is intended only to be a backdrop or reference layer and is not intended for any specific image analysis purposes.</purpose>
      <supplinf>1. Small-scale: Landsat extends 100-200 miles into adjoining states and Canada. 2. Medium-scale: Minnesota and the western Wisconsin counties listed in the Lineage field. 3. Large-scale: Areas in the Twin Cities described in the Lineage field.</supplinf>
    </descript>
    <timeperd>
      <timeinfo>
        <sngdate>
          <caldate>2010</caldate>
        </sngdate>
      </timeinfo>
      <current>The dates of each imagery layer are listed in the Lineage field.

This service will be updated annually as new or improved image datasets become available.  These new image layers will wholly or partially replace image layers in the service.</current>
    </timeperd>
    <status>
      <progress>Complete</progress>
      <update>Annually</update>
    </status>
    <spdom>
      <bounding>
        <westbc>-101.2</westbc>
        <eastbc>-86.8</eastbc>
        <northbc>51.3</northbc>
        <southbc>40.8</southbc>
      </bounding>
    </spdom>
    <keywords>
      <theme>
        <themekt>ISO 19115 Topic Category</themekt>
        <themekey>imageryBaseMapsEarthCover, Digital Orthorectified Image, Digital Orthophoto Quad, Ortho, Orthophoto, DOQ, NAIP, Compliance, Air Photo, Air Photography, Aerial Photo, Aerial Photography</themekey>
      </theme>
      <place>
        <placekey>Minnesota</placekey>
      </place>
    </keywords>
    <accconst>None.</accconst>
    <useconst>In obtaining this service from MnGeo, it is understood that you and/or your organization have the right to use it for any purpose. If you use the service to transmit or provide data to another user, it is your responsibility to provide appropriate content, limitation, warranty and liability information as you see fit.</useconst>
    <browse>
      <browsen>None available</browsen>
    </browse>
    <native/>
    <crossref>
      <citeinfo>
        <title>For information on other air photos available for Minnesota, see http://www.mngeo.state.mn.us/chouse/airphoto/index.html</title>
      </citeinfo>
    </crossref>
    <ptcontac>
      <cntinfo>
        <cntperp>
          <cntorg>Minnesota Geospatial Information Office</cntorg>
          <cntper>Pete Olson</cntper>
        </cntperp>
        <cntpos>Systems Programmer</cntpos>
        <cntaddr>
          <addrtype> Mailing and Physical</addrtype>
          <address>658 Cedar Street, Room 300</address>
          <city>St. Paul</city>
          <state>MN</state>
          <postal>55155</postal>
        </cntaddr>
        <cntvoice>651-201-2467</cntvoice>
        <cntfax>651-296-3698</cntfax>
        <cntemail>clearing.house@state.mn.us</cntemail>
      </cntinfo>
    </ptcontac>
  </idinfo>
  <dataqual>
    <attracc>
      <attraccr>See documentation for each image layer. Links to the documentation are provided in the Lineage field.</attraccr>
    </attracc>
    <complete>All of Minnesota is covered by at least two different layers at different scales.  Some layers cover smaller geographic extents.</complete>
    <posacc>
      <horizpa>
        <horizpar>See documentation for each image layer. Links to the documentation are provided in the Lineage field.</horizpar>
      </horizpa>
    </posacc>
    <lineage>
      <srcinfo>
        <srcscale/>
      </srcinfo>
      <procstep>
        <procdesc>Criteria for Selecting the Imagery to Include in the Service

The Composite Image Service Workgroup evaluated candidate imagery on a number of factors including color, currency, resolution, coverage, season, leaf cover and image quality in order to determine which imagery to include at which scale. No quality is definitively more important than another, and different qualities may have different priorities at different scales.

The workgroup selected true-color Landsat scenes for small scales (state- and region-wide) and the most recent Farm Service Agency NAIP imagery for medium scales. The NAIP imagery also serves as the 'default' large-scale background in areas that do not have higher resolution imagery available. Beyond that, the workgroup discussed a long list of imagery concerns and agreed that decisions about large scale, high-resolution imagery choices would primarily come down to balancing three: currentness, resolution, and accuracy.

Some additional guidelines used:

- True color imagery is preferred.
- Recent imagery is preferred to older imagery.
- Imagery acquired during the winter months is not preferred.
- Leaf-off is acceptable at large scales.
- Lower resolution is preferred at smaller scales.
- Higher resolution is preferred at larger scales.
- Datasets with larger coverage areas are preferred to patchy coverages.
- Image quality is subjective; images may meet or exceed technical specifications of other imagery but still be rejected based on image quality.


Layers that are Displayed at Different Scales and Links to Source Imagery Documentation:

For each of these, the layers higher in the list will show through in areas not covered by layers further down. For example, Landsat will continue to be displayed across bordering states where the FSA 2010 data does not exist.

1:250,000-scale and above
- 1999-2002 Landsat: http://landsat.usgs.gov

1:250,000 - 1:10,000 scale
- 2010 Farm Service Agency NAIP for Minnesota: http://www.mngeo.state.mn.us/chouse/airphoto/naip10.html
- 2008 FSA NAIP for the following western Wisconsin counties: Douglas, Washburn, Polk, Barron, Dunn, St. Croix, Eau Claire, Pierce, Pepin, Jackson, Trempealeau, Buffalo, Monroe, La Crosse, Vernon, Richland, Crawford and Grant.

1:10,000 - 1:3,000 scale
- 2010 natural color leaf-off imagery for 11 counties in the Twin Cities metro area ( Anoka, Carver, Chisago, Dakota, Hennepin, Isanti, Ramsey, Scott, Sherburne, Washington and Wright): http://www.mngeo.state.mn.us/chouse/airphoto/ecmn10.html

&lt;1:3,000-scale
- 2006 NGA (National Geospatial-Intelligence Agency) over downtown St. Paul; this was used since there was excessive building lean in the 2010 leaf-off imagery:   http://extract.cr.usgs.gov/distmeta/servlet/gov.usgs.edc.MetaBuilder?TYPE=HTML&amp;DATASET=UA_292_03</procdesc>
      </procstep>
    </lineage>
  </dataqual>
  <spdoinfo>
    <indspref/>
    <direct>Raster</direct>
    <mgmg3obj>Cell</mgmg3obj>
    <mgmg3til/>
  </spdoinfo>
  <spref>
    <vertdef>
      <altsys>
        <altdatum>not applicable</altdatum>
      </altsys>
      <depthsys>
        <depthdn>not applicable</depthdn>
      </depthsys>
    </vertdef>
    <horizsys>
      <planar>
        <gridsys>
          <gridsysn>Universal Transverse Mercator</gridsysn>
          <utm>
            <utmzone>15</utmzone>
          </utm>
        </gridsys>
        <planci>
          <plandu>meters</plandu>
        </planci>
      </planar>
      <geodetic>
        <horizdn>NAD83</horizdn>
        <ellips>GRS80</ellips>
      </geodetic>
    </horizsys>
  </spref>
  <eainfo>
    <overview>
      <eaover>N/A</eaover>
    </overview>
  </eainfo>
  <distinfo>
    <distliab>DISTRIBUTION LIABILITY STATEMENT
For data or maps delivered online or by physical media by
the Minnesota Geospatial Information Office

Limitations: Although extensive effort has been made to produce error-free and complete data, all geographic information has limitations due to the scale, resolution, date and interpretation of the original source materials. Users should consult available data documentation (metadata) for this particular data to determine limitations and the precision to which the data depict distance, direction, location or other geographic characteristics. Data may be subject to change without prior notification.

No warranty: Data is provided as is, without any warranty whatsoever, including but not limited to any warranty as to performance, merchantability or fitness for any particular purpose.

Liability: The entire risk as to the results of the use of this data is assumed by the user. MnGeo is not responsible for any interpretation or conclusions made by those who acquire or use it. MnGeo shall not be liable for any direct, indirect, special, incidental, compensatory or consequential damages or third-party claims resulting from the use of this data, even if MnGeo has been advised of the possibility of such potential loss or damage. In states that do not allow the exclusion or limitation of incidental or consequential damages, this data may not be used.

Redistribution conditions: In obtaining this service from MnGeo, it is understood that you and/or your organization have the right to use it for any purpose. If you use the service to transmit or provide data to another user, it is your responsibility to provide appropriate content, limitation, warranty and liability information as you see fit.

Data delivered on electronic media: If data has been requested from MnGeo on magnetic media, CD or any other physical media, MnGeo will deliver it in the computer-readable format agreed upon with the requestor. MnGeo will reissue data if it is unreadable by correctly adjusted computer input devices or when the media is delivered in a damaged condition. Requests for reissue of this digital data product must be made within 30 days of the date shipped from MnGeo.</distliab>
    <stdorder>
      <digform>
        <digtinfo>
          <formname/>
          <formvern/>
          <transize/>
        </digtinfo>
      </digform>
      <ordering>You can use a WMS with free software such as Google Earth and ArcGIS Explorer, and with many different GIS software packages.

The url for users to paste into their software, or for developers to access the WMS service is: 

http://geoint.lmic.state.mn.us/cgi-bin/mncomp?

[Note:  You cannot just click on the url to see the imagery.  For help with using WMS services, see: http://www.mngeo.state.mn.us/chouse/wms/how_to_use_wms.html ]</ordering>
    </stdorder>
    <distrib>
      <cntinfo>
        <cntperp>
          <cntorg>Minnesota Geospatial Information Office</cntorg>
          <cntper>Nancy Rader</cntper>
        </cntperp>
        <cntpos>GIS Data Coordinator</cntpos>
        <cntaddr>
          <addrtype>mailing and physical</addrtype>
          <address>658 Cedar Street, Room 300</address>
          <city>St. Paul</city>
          <state>MN</state>
          <postal>55155</postal>
        </cntaddr>
        <cntvoice>651-201-2489</cntvoice>
        <cntfax>651-296-3698</cntfax>
        <cntemail>clearing.house@state.mn.us</cntemail>
      </cntinfo>
    </distrib>
  </distinfo>
  <metainfo>
    <metd>20140917</metd>
    <metstdn>Minnesota Geographic Metadata Guidelines</metstdn>
    <metstdv>1.2</metstdv>
    <metextns>
      <onlink>http://www.gis.state.mn.us/stds/metadata.htm</onlink>
    </metextns>
    <metc>
      <cntinfo>
        <cntperp>
          <cntorg>Minnesota Geospatial Information Office</cntorg>
          <cntper>Nancy Rader</cntper>
        </cntperp>
        <cntpos>GIS Data Coordinator</cntpos>
        <cntaddr>
          <addrtype>mailing and physical</addrtype>
          <address>658 Cedar Street, Room 300</address>
          <city>St. Paul</city>
          <state>MN</state>
          <postal>55155</postal>
        </cntaddr>
        <cntvoice>651-201-2489</cntvoice>
        <cntfax>651-296-3698</cntfax>
        <cntemail>clearing.house@state.mn.us</cntemail>
      </cntinfo>
    </metc>
  </metainfo>
</metadata>
