<metadata>
  <idinfo>
    <citation>
      <citeinfo>
        <origin>Metropolitan Council</origin>
        <pubdate>20151002</pubdate>
        <title>Regional Trail Search Corridors</title>
        <mgmg1cid>N/A</mgmg1cid>
        <pubinfo>
          <publish>Metropolitan Council</publish>
        </pubinfo>
        <onlink>https://gisdata.mn.gov/dataset/us-mn-state-metc-trans-regional-trails-search-cor</onlink>
      </citeinfo>
    </citation>
    <descript>
      <abstract>This dataset includes two categories of regional trail search corridors defined as follows:

2040 System Additions:
These are general search corridors for new regional trails or extensions of existing regional trails and were designated to connect regional parks and trails to one another. The specific alignment of the regional trails will be determined through a planning process led by the regional park implementing agency.  These regional trail search corridors were approved by the Metropolitan Council in 2015 as part of the 2040 Regional Parks Policy Plan.

Regional Trail Search Corridors:
These are general search corridors for new regional trails and were designated to connect regional parks and trails to one another. The specific alignment of the regional trails will be determined through a planning process led by the regional park implementing agency.  &#8220;Proposed&#8221; trails from past datasets are also now classified as regional trail search corridors.  These regional trail search corridors were approved by the Metropolitan Council as part of various Regional Parks Policy Plans over the years and also affirmed in 2015 as part of the 2040 Regional Parks Policy Plan.
</abstract>
      <purpose>This layer was created to show potential additions to the existing Regional Park and Trail System for regional analysis and planning.</purpose>
      <supplinf>Twin Cities 7 County Metropolitan Area.  This includes the counties of Anoka, Carver, Dakota, Hennepin, Ramsey, Scott and Washington in Minnesota.</supplinf>
    </descript>
    <timeperd>
      <timeinfo>
        <sngdate>
          <caldate>20151002</caldate>
        </sngdate>
      </timeinfo>
      <current>Data current as of the Time Period of Content Date above.  Updated as new/corrected information becomes available.</current>
    </timeperd>
    <status>
      <progress>Complete</progress>
      <update>As needed</update>
    </status>
    <spdom>
      <bounding>
        <westbc>-94.012</westbc>
        <eastbc>-92.732</eastbc>
        <northbc>45.415</northbc>
        <southbc>44.471</southbc>
      </bounding>
    </spdom>
    <keywords>
      <theme>
        <themekt>None</themekt>
        <themekey>Regional Parks, Parks, Open Space, Recreation, Regional Trails, Regional Trail Search Corridors</themekey>
      </theme>
      <place>
        <placekey>Twin Cities, Anoka County, Carver County, Dakota County, Hennepin County, Ramsey County, Scott County, Washington County</placekey>
      </place>
    </keywords>
    <accconst>None</accconst>
    <useconst>None</useconst>
    <native>ArcGIS 9x</native>
    <crossref>
      <citeinfo>
        <title>Regional Trails; Regional Parks; Regional Park Search Areas; Regional Trail Corridor Land.  https://gisdata.mn.gov/dataset/us-mn-state-metc-trans-regional-trails-exst-plan</title>
      </citeinfo>
    </crossref>
    <ptcontac>
      <cntinfo>
        <cntperp>
          <cntorg>Metropolitan Council</cntorg>
          <cntper>Craig Skone</cntper>
        </cntperp>
        <cntpos>Senior GIS Technician</cntpos>
        <cntaddr>
          <addrtype> mailing and physical address </addrtype>
          <address>390 Robert Street North</address>
          <city>St. Paul</city>
          <state>Minnesota</state>
          <postal>55101-1805</postal>
        </cntaddr>
        <cntvoice>651-602-1328</cntvoice>
        <cntfax>651-602-1674</cntfax>
        <cntemail>craig.skone@metc.state.mn.us</cntemail>
      </cntinfo>
    </ptcontac>
  </idinfo>
  <dataqual>
    <logic>The dataset is topologically 'clean'.</logic>
    <complete>Entire seven county geographic area is covered.</complete>
    <posacc>
      <horizpa>
        <horizpar>The positional accuracy of the dataset has not been tested under the National Standards for Spatial Data Accuracy.  The positional accuracy of the dataset is UNKNOWN</horizpar>
      </horizpa>
    </posacc>
    <lineage>
      <srcinfo>
        <srcscale/>
      </srcinfo>
      <procstep>
        <procdesc>Data Sources: Regional Park Operating Agencies and the Metropolitan Council.

Accuracy: Data represent potential additions to the regional trail system and are cartographic in nature.  The data are not intended to portray precise locations and/or alignments.</procdesc>
      </procstep>
    </lineage>
  </dataqual>
  <spdoinfo>
    <indspref>None</indspref>
    <direct>Vector</direct>
    <mgmg3obj>polygon shapes</mgmg3obj>
    <mgmg3til>One layer for entire seven county region.</mgmg3til>
  </spdoinfo>
  <spref>
    <vertdef>
      <altsys>
        <altdatum>not applicable</altdatum>
      </altsys>
      <depthsys>
        <depthdn>not applicable</depthdn>
      </depthsys>
    </vertdef>
    <horizsys>
      <planar>
        <gridsys>
          <gridsysn>Universal Transverse Mercator</gridsysn>
          <utm>
            <utmzone>15</utmzone>
          </utm>
        </gridsys>
        <planci>
          <plandu>meters</plandu>
        </planci>
      </planar>
      <geodetic>
        <horizdn>NAD83</horizdn>
        <ellips>GRS80</ellips>
      </geodetic>
    </horizsys>
  </spref>
  <eainfo>
    <overview>
      <eaover>Attributes for regional_trail_search_corridors:
 
AGENCY: Responsible Regional Park Operating Agency Name

TYPE: "Trail"

STATUS:  "Search Corridor" or "Addition"

NAME:   Trail search corridor identifier (also used for map labeling)

METERS:  Trail search corridor segment length in meters

FEET: Trail search corridor segment length in feet

MILES: Trail search corridor segment length in miles

OLD_CAT:    Legacy categorization from previous Regional Park Policy Plans


</eaover>
      <eadetcit>None</eadetcit>
    </overview>
  </eainfo>
  <distinfo>
    <resdesc>Regional_Trail_Search_Corridors</resdesc>
    <distliab>NOTICE:  The Geographic Information System (GIS) Data to which this notice is attached are made available pursuant to the Minnesota Government Data Practices Act (Minnesota Statutes Chapter 13).  THE GIS DATA ARE PROVIDED TO YOU AS IS AND WITHOUT ANY WARRANTY AS TO THEIR PERFORMANCE, MERCHANTABILITY, OR FITNESS FOR ANY PARTICULAR PURPOSE.  The GIS Data were developed by the Metropolitan Council for its own internal business purposes.  The Metropolitan Council does not represent or warrant that the GIS Data or the data documentation are error-free, complete, current, or accurate.  You are responsible for any consequences resulting from your use of the GIS Data or your reliance on the GIS Data.  You should consult the data documentation for this particular GIS Data to determine the limitations of the GIS Data and the precision with which the GIS Data may depict distance, direction, location, or other geographic features.  If you transmit or provide the GIS Data (or any portion of it) to another user, it is recommended that the GIS Data include a copy of this disclaimer and this metadata.</distliab>
    <stdorder>
      <digform>
        <digtinfo>
          <formname>ArcView Shape file</formname>
          <formvern>ArcGIS 9x</formvern>
          <transize>1.0 Mb for zip file.</transize>
        </digtinfo>
      </digform>
      <ordering>See Online Linkage Below</ordering>
    </stdorder>
    <distrib>
      <cntinfo>
        <cntperp>
          <cntorg>Metropolitan Council</cntorg>
          <cntper>Jon Hoekenga</cntper>
        </cntperp>
        <cntpos>GIS System Administrator</cntpos>
        <cntaddr>
          <addrtype>mailing and physical</addrtype>
          <address>390 Robert Street North</address>
          <city>St. Paul</city>
          <state>MN</state>
          <postal>55101-1805</postal>
        </cntaddr>
        <cntvoice>651.602.1561</cntvoice>
        <cntemail>jonathan.hoekenga@metc.state.mn.us</cntemail>
      </cntinfo>
    </distrib>
  </distinfo>
  <metainfo>
    <metd>20151002</metd>
    <metstdn>Minnesota Geographic Metadata Guidelines</metstdn>
    <metstdv>1.2</metstdv>
    <metextns>
      <onlink>http://www.mngeo.state.mn.us/committee/standards/mgmg/metadata.htm</onlink>
    </metextns>
    <metc>
      <cntinfo>
        <cntperp>
          <cntorg>Metropolitan Council</cntorg>
          <cntper>Jon Hoekenga</cntper>
        </cntperp>
        <cntpos>GIS System Administrator</cntpos>
        <cntaddr>
          <addrtype>mailing and physical</addrtype>
          <address>390 Robert Street North</address>
          <city>St. Paul</city>
          <state>MN</state>
          <postal>55101-1805</postal>
        </cntaddr>
        <cntvoice>651.602.1561</cntvoice>
        <cntemail>jonathan.hoekenga@metc.state.mn.us</cntemail>
      </cntinfo>
    </metc>
  </metainfo>
  <Esri>
    <ModDate>20110729</ModDate>
    <ModTime>15004800</ModTime>
  </Esri>
  <mdDateSt Sync="TRUE">20110729</mdDateSt>
</metadata>
