<?xml version="1.0"?><metadata><eainfo><overview><eaover>Attributes 

TAZ: Transportation Analysis Zone (TAZ) number based on Metropolitan Council 2010 TAZ system. 

POP2010: Estimate of 2010 population in TAZ 

POPINHH10: Estimate of 2010 populatoin living in households in TAZ 

PPH10: Estimate of average persons-per-household (household size) for TAZ in 2010 

POPINGQ10: Estimate of 2010 popluation living in group quarters in TAZ 

HH2010: Estimate of 2010 number of households living in TAZ 

EMP2010: Estimate of 2010 employment in TAZ 

RETAIL2010: Estimate of 2010 retail employment in TAZ 

NRET2010: Estimate of 2010 nonretail employment in TAZ 

POP2014: Estimate of 2014 population in TAZ 

POPINHH14: Estimate of 2014 populatoin living in households in TAZ 

PPH14: Estimate of average persons-per-household (household size) for TAZ in 2014 

POPINGQ14: Estimate of 2014 popluation living in group quarters in TAZ 

HH2014: Estimate of 2014 number of households living in TAZ 

EMP2014: Estimate of 2014 employment in TAZ 

RETAIL2014: Estimate of 2014 retail employment in TAZ 

NRET2014: Estimate of 2014 nonretail employment in TAZ 

POP2020: Most current 2020 population forecast for TAZ 

POPINHH20: Most current 2020 forecast for populatoin living in households 

PPH20: Estimate of average persons-per-household (household size) for TAZ in 2020 

POPINGQ20: Most current 2020 forecast for population living in group quarters 

HH2020: Most current 2020 household forecast in TAZ 

EMP2020: Most current 2020 employment forecast in TAZ 

RETAIL2020: Most current 2020 retail employment forecast in TAZ 

NRET2020: Most current 2020 nonretail employment forecast in TAZ 

POP2030: Most current 2030 population forecast for TAZ 

POPINHH30: Most current 2030 forecast for populatoin living in households 

PPH30: Estimate of average persons-per-household (household size) for TAZ in 2030 

POPINGQ30: Most current 2030 forecast for population living in group quarters 

HH2030: Most current 2030 household forecast in TAZ 

EMP2030: Most current 2030 employment forecast in TAZ 

RETAIL2030: Most current 2030 retail employment forecast in TAZ 

POP2040: Most current 2040 population forecast for TAZ 

POPINHH40: Most current 2040 forecast for populatoin living in households 

PPH40: Estimate of average persons-per-household (household size) for TAZ in 2040 

POPINGQ40: Most current 2040 forecast for population living in group quarters 

HH2040: Most current 2040 household forecast in TAZ 

EMP2040: Most current 2040 employment forecast in TAZ 

RETAIL2040: Most current 2040 retail employment forecast in TAZ 

NRET2040: Most current 2040 nonretail employment forecast in TAZ 

RETAIL2040: Most current 2040 TAZ retail employment forecast.

TCFLAG: Field designating if TAZ is in the 7-County Metropolitan Area (=1) or in adjacent counties (=0).  </eaover></overview></eainfo><idinfo><citation><citeinfo><origin>Metropolitan Council</origin><title>Transportation Analysis Zones (Official TAZ System w/3,030 Zones) with Current Forecasts</title><pubinfo><publish>Metropolitan Council</publish></pubinfo><pubdate>periodically revised</pubdate><onlink>https://gisdata.mn.gov/dataset/us-mn-state-metc-trans-anlys-zones-offical-curent</onlink></citeinfo></citation><descript><abstract>This file shows the most current Metropolitan Council Transportation Analysis Zone (TAZ) 2020-2040 forecasts for cities and townships within the 7-County Metropolitan Area.  The TAZ system in this shapefile is the most recent, official TAZ system (with 3,030 zones).  

This shapefile title has been renamed; the previous name was Transportation Analysis Zones (TAZ) 2010 with Current Forecasts

Note:forecasts for the older TAZ system with 1,568 zones are available in theTransportation Analysis Zones (Legacy TAZ System w/1,568 Zones) with Current Forecasts shapefile.

IMPORTANT NOTES: 

These TAZ forecasts will change multiple times over the next few years. 

The Metropolitan Council will ask cities and townships to allocate their TAZ forecasts as part of their 2018 Comprehensive Plan Update (go to  http://www.metrocouncil.org/Handbook/Plan-Elements/Transportation.aspx 
for more information about this process). Communities may also revise their current TAZ forecasts before the 2018 Comprehensive Plan Update.   In the meantime, the Council provides these Current TAZ forecasts for transportation planning.

If you are using TAZ forecasts for analysis and/or transportation planning, please download the latest version of this shapefile to ensure you are using the most up-to-date data.

If you represent a community that wants to revise your TAZ forecasts, please contact your community's sector representative or  Dennis Farmer (see contact information at the end of this document).</abstract><supplinf>The Twin Cities 7 county Metropolitan Area and the 12 adjacent Counties</supplinf></descript><timeperd><current>TAZ forecasts will be updated periodically as cities and townships review and comment on the TAZ forecasts, or as new data becomes available.  The Council will ask all cities to review their TAZ forecasts as part of their Comprehensive Plan Update in 2018.

Household/population data is based on 2010 US decennial Census.  2014 houshold and population estimates are based on the Council's building permit data.   Employment data is based on MN DEED data and on US Census Longitudinal Employer-Household Dynamics data.

These 2010 TAZ forecasts were originally published on December 21, 2014.  Subsequent revisions are shown below.

-1/14/2016: 

--Revised forecasts and estimates for adjacent county TAZs.  TAZ forecasts and estimates within the 7-County Metropolitan Area not affected by changes.  

-1/26/2016:

--Shapefile renamed and retitled

--Revisions made to adjacent county forecasts based on changes in how Census block groups were assigned to TAZs.  Affected some TAZ household projections in adjacent county TAZs.

--Revisions to adjacent county employment due to corrections to 2014 employment estimates .  Affected adjacent county employment projections.

--Revisions to 7-county area household and employment projections to prevent TAZs from losing households or employment between 2014 and 2040.  Affects some TAZs that experienced high growth from 2010-2014.

--Some revisions to 7-county area employment projections based on changes in how growth was distributed between TAZs.  Affected employment growth in some TAZs that shared by multiple cities.

</current><timeinfo><sngdate><caldate>20151221</caldate></sngdate></timeinfo></timeperd><status><progress>In work</progress><update>As needed</update></status><spdom><bounding><westbc>-94.012</westbc><eastbc>-92.732</eastbc><northbc>45.415</northbc><southbc>44.471</southbc></bounding></spdom><useconst>By acceptance of this data, the user agrees to include a copy of this metadata record, including the liability disclaimer, whenever the user transmits or provides the GIS Data (or any portion of it) to another user.</useconst><keywords><theme><themekey>TAZ, Transportation Analysis Zones, forecasts, comprehensive plan</themekey></theme><place><placekey>Twin Cities Metro</placekey></place></keywords><accconst>None</accconst><ptcontac><cntinfo><cntperp><cntorg>Metropolitan Council</cntorg><cntper>Dennis Farmer, AICP</cntper></cntperp><cntpos>Research Analyst</cntpos><cntaddr><addrtype>mailing and physical</addrtype><address>390 Robert Street North</address><city>St. Paul</city><state>MN</state><postal>55101-1805</postal></cntaddr><cntvoice>651.602.1552</cntvoice><cntemail>dennis.farmer@metc.state.mn.us</cntemail></cntinfo></ptcontac></idinfo><distinfo><distliab>NOTICE:  The Geographic Information System (GIS) Data to which this notice is attached are made available pursuant to the Minnesota Government Data Practices Act (Minnesota Statutes Chapter 13).  THE GIS DATA ARE PROVIDED TO YOU AS IS AND WITHOUT ANY WARRANTY AS TO THEIR PERFORMANCE, MERCHANTABILITY, OR FITNESS FOR ANY PARTICULAR PURPOSE.  The GIS Data were developed by the Metropolitan Council for its own internal business purposes.  The Metropolitan Council does not represent or warrant that the GIS Data or the data documentation are error-free, complete, current, or accurate.  You are responsible for any consequences resulting from your use of the GIS Data or your reliance on the GIS Data.  You should consult the data documentation for this particular GIS Data to determine the limitations of the GIS Data and the precision with which the GIS Data may depict distance, direction, location, or other geographic features.  If you transmit or provide the GIS Data (or any portion of it) to another user, it is recommended that the GIS Data include a copy of this disclaimer and this metadata.</distliab><stdorder><ordering>See Online Linkage Below</ordering></stdorder><distrib><cntinfo><cntperp><cntorg>Metropolitan Council</cntorg><cntper>Dennis Farmer, AICP</cntper></cntperp><cntpos>Research Analyst</cntpos><cntaddr><addrtype>mailing and physical</addrtype><address>390 Robert Street North</address><city>St. Paul</city><state>MN</state><postal>55101-1805</postal></cntaddr><cntvoice>651.602.1552</cntvoice><cntemail>dennis.farmer@metc.state.mn.us</cntemail></cntinfo></distrib></distinfo><metainfo><metd>20151221</metd><metstdn>Minnesota Geographic Metadata Guidelines</metstdn><metstdv>1.2</metstdv><metextns><onlink>http://www.mngeo.state.mn.us/committee/standards/mgmg/metadata.htm</onlink></metextns><metc><cntinfo><cntperp><cntorg>Metropolitan Council</cntorg><cntper>Dennis Farmer, AICP</cntper></cntperp><cntpos>Research Analyst</cntpos><cntaddr><addrtype>mailing and physical</addrtype><address>390 Robert Street North</address><city>St. Paul</city><state>MN</state><postal>55101-1805</postal></cntaddr><cntvoice>651.602.1552</cntvoice><cntemail>dennis.farmer@metc.state.mn.us</cntemail></cntinfo></metc></metainfo><dataqual><lineage><procstep><procdesc>The city and township boundaries are taken from the Counties and Cities &amp; Townships, Twin Cities Metropolitan Area shapefile, available on MetroGIS Datafinder

</procdesc></procstep></lineage></dataqual><spref><horizsys><planar><gridsys><gridsysn>Universal Transverse Mercator</gridsysn><utm><utmzone>15</utmzone></utm></gridsys><planci><plandu>meters</plandu></planci></planar><geodetic><horizdn>NAD83</horizdn><ellips>GRS80</ellips></geodetic></horizsys></spref></metadata>