<?xml version="1.0"?><!--  <!DOCTYPE metadata SYSTEM "metadata.dtd">  --><metadata><idinfo><citation><citeinfo><origin>United States Geological Survey</origin><pubdate>20151201</pubdate><title>Geographic Names,  Minnesota </title><mgmg1cid></mgmg1cid><pubinfo><publish>Minnesota Geospatial Information Office (MnGeo)</publish></pubinfo><onlink>https://gisdata.mn.gov/dataset/loc-geographic-names-usgs-gnis</onlink></citeinfo></citation><descript><abstract>The source data for the Minnesota Geographic Names point file is the USGS-GNIS data base, 'National Geographic Names Database', maintained by the United States Geological Survey for the U.S. Board of Geographic Names.  State extracts are available from the Board of Geographic Names as ascii text files, and converted locally to GIS format.  According to USGS metadata: 'A geographic feature is any relatively permanent part of the natural or manmade landscape or seascape that has recognizable identity within a particular cultural context. The primary attributes of a geographic feature are name and location.'

The Geographic Names Information System file contains all geographic names in the Minnesota state extract.  Layer files have also been created to represent the 'Populated Places' feature, and the 'Dams' feature, from GNIS. A 'Populated Place' is defined by USGS as a 'Place or area with clustered or scattered buildings a nd a permanent human population (city, settlement, town, village)'.  A 'Populated Place' may or not be legally incorporated. Incorporated places also appear as separate features with a feature code of 'Civil'. 

For more information see: http://geonames.usgs.gov/</abstract><purpose>The Geographic Names Information System (GNIS) is the Federal standard for geographic nomenclature. The U.S. Geological Survey developed the GNIS for the U.S. Board on Geographic Names, a Federal inter-agency body chartered by public law to maintain uniform feature name usage throughout the Government and to promulgate standard names to the public. The GNIS is the official repository of domestic geographic names data, the official vehicle for geographic names use by all departments of the Federal Government, and the source for applying geographic names to Federal electronic and printed products of all types.

For more information see  http://geonames.usgs.gov/domestic/faqs.htm 
</purpose><supplinf>Minnesota, Statewide. A few points are located outside of the state boundaries since rivers are represented by their outflow points. </supplinf></descript><timeperd><timeinfo><sngdate><caldate>20151201</caldate></sngdate></timeinfo><current>Date on latest ASCII text state file downloaded from USGS  Bureau of Geographic Names web site. </current></timeperd><status><progress>Complete</progress><update>The national GNIS database is updated continually.  New state download data sets are provided every two months.  MnGeo will update the state GIS file on the Commons annually. Most updates now are corrections, or additions of building locations to the data set.  Users wishing more up-to-date state GIS data sets can create from the USGS ASCII file using the methodology described under Lineage.  </update></status><spdom><bounding><westbc>-98.9</westbc><eastbc>-76.0</eastbc><northbc>50.4</northbc><southbc>29.1</southbc></bounding></spdom><keywords><theme><themekt>ISO 19115 Topic Category</themekt><themekey>location, geographic names, placenames, features, map features, places, areas, GNIS, dams</themekey></theme><place><placekey>Minnesota, Statewide</placekey></place></keywords><accconst>None</accconst><browse><browsen>ftp://ftp.gisdata.mn.gov/pub/gdrs/data/pub/us_mn_state_mngeo/loc_geographic_names_usgs_gnis/metadata/preview.jpg</browsen></browse><native>Arc/INFO 7.1.1</native><crossref><citeinfo><title>Federal data sets within the Geographic Names Information System include:

National Geographic Names Data Base (the source of this GIS coverage)
USGS Topographic Names Bata Base
Reference Data Base
Board of Geographic Names Data Base
USGS Digital Gazetteer

Most names are represented on the Digital Raster Geographic (DRG) versions of the topographic map series. The National Hydrography Dataset (NHD) names lakes and rivers using the GNIS ID.  This dataset provides a full geometric representation of lake boundaries and river traces. 
</title></citeinfo></crossref><useconst>None. Acknowledgement of the U.S. Geological Survey would be appreciated in products derived from these data. </useconst><ptcontac><cntinfo><cntperp><cntorg>Minnesota Geospatial Information Office (MnGeo)</cntorg><cntper>Nancy Rader</cntper></cntperp><cntpos>GIS Data Coordinator</cntpos><cntaddr><addrtype>Mailing and Physical</addrtype><address>658 Cedar Street, Room 300</address><city>St. Paul</city><state>MN</state><postal>55155</postal></cntaddr><cntvoice>651-201-2489</cntvoice><cntemail>gisinfo.mngeo@state.mn.us</cntemail></cntinfo></ptcontac></idinfo><dataqual><complete>Contains all names of areal, linear, and point features appearing on USGS 7.5-minute topographic maps, with the exception that only the primary occurrence of each feature is contained on the GIS file.  (See lineage for a description of what was extracted). </complete><posacc><horizpa><horizpar>Point location is based upon the Latitude/Longitude reported on the USGS file, in degrees, minutes, and seconds.  USGS reports that the Latitude/Longitude value of each point is accurate to plus or minus 5 seconds.  If the point represents an areal feature such as a city, the primary point is generally located in the center of the area. The determination of 'center' was subjective.  In other situations, the location of a major town feature such as the town hall was used to locate the point.   For linear features such as rivers, the primary locator point is at the mouth of the river. A secondary point represents the headwaters of the river.  In creating the GIS coverage, MnGeo extracted only the primary location features.</horizpar></horizpa><vertacc><vertaccr>Elevation information is reported only if it is reported on the USGS 7.5-minute topographic map.  Vertical positional accuracy reflects that of the National Mapping Program.</vertaccr></vertacc></posacc><lineage><srcinfo><srcscale>24000</srcscale></srcinfo><procstep><procdesc>Download domestic names from the federal Bureau of Geographic Names website  
Under the 'Domestic' page, which contains states, territories, and associated areas of the United States, select Minnesota from the  pulldown list.  The most recent update is available here.

For the 12/1/2015 version, MnGeo created the GIS data using the following process:

1.  Downloaded 'MN_Features_20151201.zip' from the USGS-BGN website.  The unzipped file is an ascii text file  'MN_Features_20151201.txt'.  Data fields within the ASCII text file are pipe-delimited ( '|').

2. Create Excel spreadsheet from BGN ascii table:

- Create Excel Spreadsheet MN_Features_20151201.xlsx
- To import: Data&gt;Get External Data&gt;From Text  (ID text file as MN_Features_20151201.txt)
- Import process: Delimited&gt;Delimiter=Other ( Enter '|' for delimiter)&gt;Column Data Format=General&gt;Finish
- Save

3. Create point shapefile in ArcMap:

- Bring MN_Features_20151201.xlsx into ArcMap (Add data)
- Highlight the table acess ‘Display xy data’. 
- Pick the correct fields (primary longitude or 'PRIM_LONG1'  for x-value, primary latitude for 'PRIM_LAT_D' for y-value). Use the fields containing decimal degrees to create the points.
-  Display.
- Save out as a shapefile (MN_GNIS_Features_20151201.shp). 
- Shapefile is still in Geographic Coordinates. 

Note that lakes are represented by a single centroid point. 

Note also that the primary point for rivers is the mouth of the river.  Therefore, not all river points extracted actually fall within Minnesota's boundaries. For example, the primary point for the Mississippi River (mouth of river) falls in Plaquemines Parish, Louisiana. Within the ascii file there is another point set, populated for streams only, which identifies the stream's source  ('source_l_2', 'source_l_1'). MnGeo did not use this to create the GIS file. 

4. Create UTM Zone 15 NAD83 version:  Use Projection tools to create utm version (shapefile is MN_GNIS_Features_20151201_utm)

5. Load into file geodatabase:
Import shapefile into the current file geodatabase (loc_geographic_names_gnis.gdb)
Delete previous version of the dataset, and rename the imported dataset to "geographic_names_information_system".

6. Recreate .lyr files.

The Bureau of Geographic Names website is located at http://geonames.usgs.gov/domestic/download_data.htm 
</procdesc></procstep></lineage><logic>Not applicable </logic><attracc><attraccr>Varies by region of U.S.  See http://geonames.usgs.gov/domestic/metadata.htm</attraccr></attracc></dataqual><spdoinfo><indspref></indspref><direct>Point</direct><mgmg3obj>Point</mgmg3obj><mgmg3til>None (statewide cover)</mgmg3til></spdoinfo><eainfo><detailed><enttyp><enttypl>geographic_names_information_system</enttypl></enttyp><attr><attrlabl>FID</attrlabl><attrdef>Object ID</attrdef><attrdefs>Esri</attrdefs></attr><attr><attrlabl>Shape</attrlabl><attrdef>Geometry of feature</attrdef><attrdefs>Esri</attrdefs></attr><attr><attrlabl>FEATURE_ID</attrlabl><attrdef>GNIS - ID Principal Identifier for Geographic Names Information System</attrdef><attrdefs>USGS - GNIS</attrdefs></attr><attr><attrlabl>FEATURE_NA</attrlabl><attrdef>Feature Name</attrdef><attrdefs>USGS - GNIS</attrdefs></attr><attr><attrlabl>FEATURE_CL</attrlabl><attrdef>Feature Class</attrdef><attrdefs>USGS - GNIS</attrdefs><attrdomv><edom><edomvd>http://geonames.usgs.gov/apex/f?p=gnispq:8</edomvd></edom></attrdomv></attr><attr><attrlabl>STATE_ALPH</attrlabl><attrdef>State Alphanumeric Code</attrdef><attrdefs>USGS - GNIS</attrdefs></attr><attr><attrlabl>STATE_NUME</attrlabl><attrdef>State Numeric Code (MN is 27)</attrdef><attrdefs>USGS - GNIS/FIPS</attrdefs></attr><attr><attrlabl>COUNTY_NAM</attrlabl><attrdef>County Name</attrdef><attrdefs>USGS _ GNIS</attrdefs></attr><attr><attrlabl>COUNTY_NUM</attrlabl><attrdef>County Number (FIPS Code)</attrdef><attrdefs>USGS - GNIS/FIPS</attrdefs></attr><attr><attrlabl>PRIMARY_LA</attrlabl><attrdef>Primary Latitude (Degress, Minutes, Seconds)</attrdef><attrdefs>USGS - GNIS</attrdefs></attr><attr><attrlabl>PRIM_LONG_</attrlabl><attrdef>Primary Longitude (Degrees, Minutes, Seconds)</attrdef><attrdefs>USGS - GNIS</attrdefs></attr><attr><attrlabl>PRIM_LAT_D</attrlabl><attrdef>Primary Latitude, Decimal Degrees</attrdef><attrdefs>USGS - GNIS</attrdefs></attr><attr><attrlabl>PRIM_LONG1</attrlabl><attrdef>Primary Longitude (Decimal Degrees)</attrdef><attrdefs>USGS - GNIS</attrdefs></attr><attr><attrlabl>SOURCE_LAT</attrlabl><attrdef>Source Latitude - Degrees, Minutes, Seconds (rivers and other linear features only)</attrdef><attrdefs>USGS - GNIS</attrdefs></attr><attr><attrlabl>SOURCE_LON</attrlabl><attrdef>Source Longitude, Degrees, Minutes, Seconds (rivers and other linear features only)</attrdef><attrdefs>USGS - GNIS</attrdefs></attr><attr><attrlabl>Source_L_1</attrlabl><attrdef>Source latitude, Decimal Degrres (rivers and linear features only)</attrdef><attrdefs>USGS - GNIS</attrdefs></attr><attr><attrlabl>SOURCE_L_2</attrlabl><attrdef>Source Longitude, Decimal Degrees (rivers and linear features only)</attrdef><attrdefs>USGS - GNIS</attrdefs></attr><attr><attrlabl>ELEV_IN_M</attrlabl><attrdef>Elevation of feature in meters (if known)</attrdef><attrdefs>USGS - GNIS</attrdefs></attr><attr><attrlabl>ELEV_IN_FEET</attrlabl><attrdef>Elevation of feature in feet (if known)</attrdef><attrdefs>USGS - GNIS</attrdefs></attr><attr><attrlabl>MAP_NAME</attrlabl><attrdef>Name of USGS 1:24,000-scale topographic map on which this feature appears</attrdef><attrdefs>USGS - GNIS</attrdefs></attr><attr><attrlabl>DATE_CREAT</attrlabl><attrdef>Date this feature location was created inthe digital file</attrdef><attrdefs>USGS - GNIS</attrdefs></attr><attr><attrlabl>DATE_EDITE</attrlabl><attrdef>Date this feature location was last edited in the digital file</attrdef><attrdefs>USGS - GNIS</attrdefs></attr></detailed><overview><eaover>Feature class values and definitions for the Geographic Names Information System are described at http://geonames.usgs.gov/apex/f?p=gnispq:8 
</eaover><eadetcit>US GeoData: Geographic Names Information System  Data Users Guide
Data Citation:  U.S. Geological Survey, 19810501, U.S. Geographic Names Information System (GNIS): U.S. Geological Survey, Reston, VA.

Policy Document: U.S. Board of Geographic Names, 'Principles, Policies, and Procedures: Domestic Geographic Names', Reston, VA, 1997.

http://geonames.usgs.gov/docs/pro_pol_pro.pdf 

http://geonames.usgs.gov/domestic/metadata.htm
</eadetcit></overview></eainfo><distinfo><resdesc>gnis-mn  (loc_geographic_names_usgs_gnis)</resdesc><stdorder><digform><digtinfo><formname>Arc Export</formname><formvern>7.1.1</formvern><transize>1.4 MB in self-extracting zip (.exe) format; 7.2 MB when expanded</transize></digtinfo></digform><ordering>Download GIS formatted data via the Minnesota Geospatial Commons.

If you need to the more frequent updates made at the federal level (approximately every two months), you can go to the federal site, download the latest ascii text file, and convert to GIS points as outlined under the Lineage section inthis metadata.  State ascii text files are available from the Bureau of Geographic Names site: http://geonames.usgs.gov/domestic/download_data.htm


</ordering></stdorder><distliab>MnGeo's data disclaimer is online: http://www.mngeo.state.mn.us/chouse/disclaimer.html 

USGS Disclaimer (from USGS metadata): 'Although these data have been processed successfully on a computer system at the U.S. Geological Survey, no warranty expressed or implied is made by the USGS regarding the utility of the data on any other system, nor shall the act of distribution constitute any such warranty. The Geological Survey will warrant the delivery of this product in computer-readable format. '
</distliab><distrib><cntinfo><cntperp><cntorg>Minnesota Geospatial Information Office (MnGeo)</cntorg><cntper>Nancy Rader</cntper></cntperp><cntpos>GIS Data Coordinator</cntpos><cntaddr><addrtype>mailing and physical</addrtype><address>658 Cedar Street, Room 300</address><city>St. Paul</city><state>MN</state><postal>55155</postal></cntaddr><cntvoice>651-201-2489</cntvoice><cntemail>gisinfo.mngeo@state.mn.us</cntemail></cntinfo></distrib></distinfo><metainfo><metd>20151216</metd><metstdn>Minnesota Geographic Metadata Guidelines</metstdn><metstdv>1.2</metstdv><metextns><onlink>http://www.lmic.state.mn.us/gc/stds/metadata.htm</onlink></metextns><metc><cntinfo><cntperp><cntorg>Minnesota Geospatial Information Office (MnGeo)</cntorg><cntper>Nancy Rader</cntper></cntperp><cntpos>GIS Data Coordinator</cntpos><cntaddr><addrtype>mailing and physical</addrtype><address>658 Cedar Street, Room 300</address><city>St. Paul</city><state>MN</state><postal>55155</postal></cntaddr><cntvoice>651-201-2489</cntvoice><cntemail>gisinfo.mngeo@state.mn.us</cntemail></cntinfo></metc></metainfo><spref><horizsys><planar><gridsys><gridsysn>Universal Transverse Mercator</gridsysn><utm><utmzone>15E</utmzone></utm></gridsys><planci><plandu>meters</plandu></planci></planar><geodetic><horizdn>NAD83</horizdn><ellips>GRS80</ellips></geodetic></horizsys></spref></metadata>