<metadata>
  <eainfo>
    <overview>
      <eaover>NAME: Name of WD/WMO. 

TYPE: This is either WD = Watershed District, WMO= water management organization, COU=county administered planning. 

ESTABLISH: This is a date field, if available it refers to the date of establishment. 

METROSTATE: Indicates whether the management organization is in the seven county metro area or outstate.</eaover>
    </overview>
  </eainfo>
  <idinfo>
    <citation>
      <citeinfo>
        <origin>Minnesota Board of Water and Soil Resources (BWSR)</origin>
        <title>Watershed Management Districts and Organizations</title>
        <pubinfo>
          <publish>Minnesota Board of Water and Soil Resources (BWSR)</publish>
        </pubinfo>
      </citeinfo>
    </citation>
    <descript>
      <abstract>This data set depicts watershed district and watershed management organization boundaries throughout the state of Minnesota. 

Watershed districts are local units of government that work to solve and prevent water-related problems. The boundaries of the districts closely follow those of a natural watershed (an area in which all water drains to one point). Minnesota has 46 watershed districts, most of which are named after the primary lake or river within the watershed. Minnesota's watershed districts do not cover the entire state. They are created through a local petition process. Minnesota Statute Chapter 103D governs the formation and operation of watershed districts. 

In 1982, the Minnesota Legislature approved the Metropolitan Area Surface Water Management Act (Minnesota Statutes 103B.201 to 255), which requires local units of government in the seven-county Metro Area to prepare and implement comprehensive surface water management plans through membership in a watershed management organization (WMO).A watershed management organization (WMO) is defined as a watershed district wholly within the seven-county, Twin Cities Metropolitan Area or a joint powers entity established wholly or partly in the metropolitan area by special law or agreement to perform some or all of the functions of a watershed district. 

NOTES: 
- MANY BOUNDARY DISCREPANCIES EXIST WITH THIS DATA SET. See Lineage in Section 2 of this metadata for more details. 

This layer represents BWSR's most current information on watershed districts and WMOs in the State of MN. The dataset is NOT error free, and boundaries are frequently being updated and changed, so these should be used for reference only. 

Water planning is either the responsibility of a watershed district or a water management org. If neither of these exist, then responsibility falls onto the county. For a more precise boundary determination, check with the BWSR board conservationist for the area in question.</abstract>
      <purpose>General planning purposes only.</purpose>
    </descript>
    <timeperd>
      <current>April, 2015</current>
      <timeinfo>
        <sngdate>
          <caldate>20150415</caldate>
        </sngdate>
      </timeinfo>
    </timeperd>
    <status>
      <progress>In work</progress>
      <update>As needed</update>
    </status>
    <spdom>
      <bounding>
        <westbc>-97.23</westbc>
        <eastbc>-89.53</eastbc>
        <northbc>49.37</northbc>
        <southbc>43.5</southbc>
      </bounding>
    </spdom>
    <keywords>
      <place>
        <placekey>Minnesota, MN</placekey>
      </place>
      <theme>
        <themekey>Watershed, Watershed District, Watershed Management Organization, WD, WMO</themekey>
      </theme>
    </keywords>
    <useconst>There are many areas of potential boundary discrepancies which can be attributed to one of two factors: 1) real boundary discrepancies that resulted from delineations done at various times by various agencies or consultants with little or no coordination, or 2) interpretational errors. For this reason reason this layer should be used for general planning purposes only, and is not intended to be used for parcel level planning or determination.</useconst>
    <ptcontac>
      <cntinfo>
        <cntperp>
          <cntorg>Minnesota Board of Water and Soil Resources</cntorg>
          <cntper>Aaron Spence</cntper>
        </cntperp>
        <cntpos>GIS Specialist</cntpos>
        <cntaddr>
          <addrtype>mailing and physical</addrtype>
          <address>520 Lafayette Rd. N</address>
          <city>St. Paul</city>
          <state>MN</state>
          <postal>55155</postal>
        </cntaddr>
        <cntvoice>651-296-0660</cntvoice>
        <cntfax>651-297-5615</cntfax>
        <cntemail>aaron.spence@bwsr.state.mn.us</cntemail>
      </cntinfo>
    </ptcontac>
  </idinfo>
  <dataqual>
    <posacc>
      <horizpa>
        <horizpar>The horizontal accuracy of this data set is unknown. See lineage for more information.</horizpar>
      </horizpa>
    </posacc>
    <lineage>
      <procstep>
        <procdesc>In 1995 LMIC digitized this data from boundaries that were hand-drawn by the Metropolitan Council on 7.5-minute topo hardcopy. The hand-drawn lines were derived from the watershed plans that came to the Council for review over a period of many years as a result of MN Chapter 509 legislation. 

There are many areas of potential boundary discrepancies which can be attributed to one of two factors: 1) real boundary discrepancies that resulted from delineations done at various times by various agencies or consultants with little or no coordination, or 2) interpretational errors. 

Boundaries presumably follow parcel lines, but some of these data predate the availability of digital parcel information and have not been updated with county parcel data. 

This data layer has been maintained at the Board of Water and Soil Resources (BWSR) since 1997. We have not attempted an exhaustive effort to resolve boundary conflicts, however we do make periodic updates to the data by dissolving boundaries or editing attribute info as necessary. Occasionally we recieve notification from local governments about pending changes to a boundary, and sometimes receive geospatial files that are incorporated with this statewide layer.</procdesc>
      </procstep>
    </lineage>
  </dataqual>
  <distinfo>
    <stdorder>
      <ordering>The layer may be downloaded from MnGEO Geospatial Commons. If necessary contact BWSR by phone or email. </ordering>
    </stdorder>
    <distrib>
      <cntinfo>
        <cntperp>
          <cntorg>Minnesota Board of Water and Soil Resources</cntorg>
          <cntper>Aaron Spence</cntper>
        </cntperp>
        <cntpos>GIS Specialist</cntpos>
        <cntaddr>
          <addrtype>mailing and physical</addrtype>
          <address>520 Lafayette Rd. N</address>
          <city>St. Paul</city>
          <state>MN</state>
          <postal>55155</postal>
        </cntaddr>
        <cntvoice>651-296-0660</cntvoice>
        <cntfax>651-297-5615</cntfax>
        <cntemail>aaron.spence@bwsr.state.mn.us</cntemail>
      </cntinfo>
    </distrib>
  </distinfo>
  <metainfo>
    <metd>20150415</metd>
    <metstdn>Minnesota Geographic Metadata Guidelines</metstdn>
    <metstdv>1.2</metstdv>
    <metextns>
      <onlink>http://www.gis.state.mn.us/stds/metadata.htm</onlink>
    </metextns>
    <metc>
      <cntinfo>
        <cntperp>
          <cntorg>Minnesota Board of Water and Soil Resources</cntorg>
          <cntper>Aaron Spence</cntper>
        </cntperp>
        <cntpos>GIS Specialist</cntpos>
        <cntaddr>
          <addrtype>mailing and physical</addrtype>
          <address>520 Lafayette Rd. N</address>
          <city>St. Paul</city>
          <state>MN</state>
          <postal>55155</postal>
        </cntaddr>
        <cntvoice>651-296-0660</cntvoice>
        <cntfax>651-297-5615</cntfax>
        <cntemail>aaron.spence@bwsr.state.mn.us</cntemail>
      </cntinfo>
    </metc>
  </metainfo>
  <spref>
    <horizsys>
      <planar>
        <gridsys>
          <gridsysn>Universal Transverse Mercator</gridsysn>
          <utm>
            <utmzone>15</utmzone>
          </utm>
        </gridsys>
        <planci>
          <plandu>meters</plandu>
        </planci>
      </planar>
      <geodetic>
        <horizdn>NAD83</horizdn>
        <ellips>GRS80</ellips>
      </geodetic>
    </horizsys>
  </spref>
</metadata>
