<?xml version="1.0"?><metadata><idinfo><citation><citeinfo><title>Planned Land Use</title><origin>Metropolitan Council</origin><pubinfo><publish>Metropolitan Council</publish></pubinfo><pubdate>20150923</pubdate><onlink>https://gisdata.mn.gov/dataset/us-mn-state-metc-plan-pland-land-use</onlink></citeinfo></citation><descript><abstract>The Metropolitan Council routinely compiles individual land use plans and plan amendments from communities within the seven-county Twin Cities metropolitan area into a single regional data layer. A principal goal of the Regional Planned Land Use dataset is to allow users to view, analyze and display planned land use data for anywhere in the seven county metropolitan area with a consistent land use classification scheme. The Metropolitan Council uses the Regional Planned Land Use (PLU) data to help monitor growth and plan for regional services such as regional parks, transit service, and wastewater collection and treatment. 

Although the planned land use data is based on the locally adopted land use plans and designations for each community, it represent only data that has been submitted to the Metropolitan Council for review per the Metropolitan Land Planning Act of 1995 (Minn. Stat 473.864, Subd 2 and 473.175, Subd 1). See Data Quality Information (Section 2 of this metadata) for specifics about the Metropolitan Land Planning Act of 1995 under Completeness information. 

Since there is no official State or Regional land use coding scheme that communities must conform with, the variability of content and codes between communities' land use plans is nearly as vast as the number of communities themselves (187). Differences among communities can range from the implementation of different land use categories to conflicting definitions of similar categories. The PLU dataset attempts to effectively level out the variability among communities by translating communities land use categories and descriptions into a common classification scheme developed and endorsed by MetroGIS (a regional GIS data sharing consortium) participants while retaining each communities' original categories. Although the comparability of land use plans between communities has greatly improved as a result of this translation or "regionalization" of communities' land use codes, it is possible that not all community land use definitions have been precisely translated into the most appropriate regional land use category. 

In conjunction with other regional information (i.e., land use trend data, households and jobs forecasts), the PLU data can help communities more easily understand regional and sub-regional planning goals and Council staff, working with individual local units of government, can better plan for the future needs and financing of regional services. 

- Contact individual communities for more information on their locally adopted planned land use categories. 

- See Data Quality Information (Section 2 of this metadata) for specifics about the development of the regional dataset and its accuracy. 

- See Entities and Attributes Information (Section 5 of this metadata) for specifics about the regional land use codes and categories.</abstract><purpose>To view, analyze and display planned land use (PLU) data for anywhere in the seven-county Twin Cities metropolitan area with a consistent land use classification scheme. 

In conjunction with other regional information (i.e., land use trend data, households and jobs forecasts), the PLU data can help communities more easily understand regional and sub-regional planning goals and Metropolitan Council staff, working with individual local units of government, can better monitor growth and plan for the future needs and financing of regional services such as regional parks, transit service, and wastewater collection and treatment.</purpose><supplinf>Twin Cities 7 County Metropolitan Area.  This includes the counties of Anoka, Carver, Dakota, Hennepin, Ramsey, Scott and Washington in Minnesota.</supplinf></descript><timeperd><timeinfo><sngdate><caldate>20150923</caldate></sngdate></timeinfo><current>Initial planned land use data was received between June, 2000 and April, 2002. Communities reviewed the currentness of the Planned Land Use Information between March 8, 2002 and May 10, 2002. The actual date of a community's locally adopted plan is not known but the regional data are current as of the date that the Comprehensive Plan was reviewed and subsequent amendments by the Metropolitan Council per the Metropolitan Land Planning Act of 1995 (Minn. Stat 473.864, Subd 2 and 473.175, Subd 1). The Metropolitan Land Planning Act of 1995 requires communities in the seven-county Twin Cities metropolitan area to submit a Comprehensive Plan and subsequent plan amendments to the Metropolitan Council for review and consideration of the impact, if any the plan or plan amendment may have on the regional systems (i.e., roads, parks, wastewater collection and treatment. 

All communities' 2008 Comprehensive Plan information HAVE been incorporated into the Regional Planned Land Use dataset with the exception of the following: 

Fort Snelling (Unorganized) - Does not need to submit a plan 
Landfall 
Lexington 
Shakopee Mdewakanton Sioux Community (lands included in Prior Lake and Shakopee) - Does not need to submit a plan 

NOTE: Some municipalities have Orderly Annexation Agreements (OAA) with surrounding township. This means that parts of the township may be incorporated into the municipalities at any time in the future. Carver and Scott County has acknowledged that communities with OAA with surrounding townships have planning authority. As such, land use designation in the OAA areas following the adjacent community land use definitions. </current></timeperd><status><progress>Complete</progress><update>As needed</update></status><spdom><bounding><westbc>-94.012</westbc><eastbc>-92.732</eastbc><northbc>45.415</northbc><southbc>44.471</southbc></bounding></spdom><keywords><place><placekey>Twin Cities, Anoka County, Carver County, Dakota County, Hennepin County, Ramsey County, Scott County, Washington County</placekey></place><theme><themekey>Planned land use, regional planned land use, regional parcel data, future land use, planning and development</themekey><themekt>None</themekt></theme></keywords><accconst>None</accconst><useconst>This dataset is the result of the compilation of interpreted planned land use for each community in the Twin Cities metropolitan area. Although the data is based on the locally adopted land use designations of each community, they represent those designation that have been submitted to the Metropolitan Council per the Metropolitan Land Planning Act of 1995 (Minn. Stat 473.864, Subd 2 and 473.175, Subd 1). Locally adopted planned land use designations and corresponding regional interpretations are subject to modification through comprehensive plan amendments. Amendment information will be updated quarterly. For more information regarding any locally adopted planned land use designation, contact the individual community. 


By acceptance of this data, the user agrees to include a copy of this metadata record, including the liability disclaimer, whenever the user transmits or provides the GIS Data (or any portion of it) to another user.</useconst><browse><browsen>None available</browsen><browsed>No sample map available</browsed></browse><crossref><citeinfo><title>Planned land use maps or datasets may be available individually from each community.

Parcel data is available for each county.  See https://gisdata.mn.gov/dataset/us-mn-state-metrogis-plan-regonal-prcls-open
Existing land use datasets for various years are also available:
Year 2005: https://gisdata.mn.gov/dataset/us-mn-state-metc-plan-generl-lnduse2005
Year 2000: https://gisdata.mn.gov/dataset/us-mn-state-metc-plan-generl-lnduse2000
Previous years:  https://gisdata.mn.gov/dataset/us-mn-state-metc-plan-generl-lnduse-historical</title></citeinfo></crossref><native>Oracle Version 10g, Release 2</native><ptcontac><cntinfo><cntperp><cntorg>Metropolitan Council</cntorg><cntper>Paul Hanson</cntper></cntperp><cntpos>GIS Coordinator - Community Development</cntpos><cntaddr><addrtype>mailing and physical</addrtype><address>390 Robert Street North</address><city>St. Paul</city><state>Minnesota</state><postal>55101-1805</postal></cntaddr><cntvoice>651-602-1642</cntvoice><cntfax>651-602-1674</cntfax><cntemail>paul.hanson@metc.state.mn.us</cntemail></cntinfo></ptcontac></idinfo><dataqual><attracc><attraccr>Each community's planned land use is subject to review by the Metropolitan Council per the Comprehensive Land Planning Act of 1995 (Minn. Stat 473.864, Subd 2 and 473.175, Subd 1). The accuracy of a community's locally adopted planned land use or land use plan is based on the information that has been submitted to the Metropolitan Council. Any locally adopted land use designation that is not submitted to the Council for review either through their comprehensive plan or subsequent plan amendments may not be incorporated into the Regional Planned Land Use dataset. 

Regional classifications are 'best fit' interpretations of locally adopted designations into the MetroGIS endorsed Regional Coding Scheme. Any error in interpretation is solely the responsibility of the Metropolitan Council. 

Valid code checks have been conducted on the regional classification codes. No known code attribute errors exist. Locally adopted land use designations and therefore corresponding regional classifications are subject to change through comprehensive plan amendments.</attraccr></attracc><logic>The dataset is topologically 'clean'.</logic><complete>This dataset is the result of the compilation of interpreted planned land use for each community in the Twin Cities metropolitan area to the year 2020. Although the data is based on the locally adopted land use designations of each community, they represent those designation that have been submitted to the Metropolitan Council per the Metropolitan Land Planning Act of 1995 (Minn. Stat 473.864, Subd 2 and 473.175, Subd 1). Locally adopted planned land use designations and corresponding regional interpretations are subject to modification through comprehensive plan amendments. Not all communities have adopted their 2008 comprehensive plans (2030 planning horizon). Community's planning year is differentiated with the BENCHMARK data field (i.e., 2020 or 2030). 

For more information regarding any locally adopted planned land use designation, contact the individual community.</complete><posacc><horizpa><horizpar>The horizontal position accuracy is based on the county parcel data. See metadata for individual counties for positional accuracy statements. In areas where counties have improved altered the positional accuracy of their parcels, the planned land use boundaries may not be conterminous with thte parcel boundaries. 

For areas where planned land use delineations foreshadows existing parcel delineation, parcels were split to approximate the locally adopted land use delineation. 

As a general rule when developing this dataset it was the Metropolitan Council's intention to meet or exceed the National Mapping Accuracy Standards at 1:24,000 (within approximately 40 feet of actual location), with the exception of right-of-way for local roads. No testing has been conducted to verify this.</horizpar></horizpa></posacc><lineage><procstep><procdesc>This dataset was assembled by staff at the Metropolitan Council. 

Lineage Outline:
This dataset was assembled by staff at the Metropolitan Council. 

Lineage Outline: 
I. Dataset Goals and Summary 
II. Creation of the Regional Planned Land Use (PLU) Dataset 
A. Land Use Coding Scheme 
B. Geography (Spatial Base) 
C. Data Capture Methodology 
III. Assumptions, Observations and Regionalization Consistencies 
IV. Updates 

I. DATASET GOALS AND SUMMARY 
A principal goal of the Regional Planned Land Use (PLU) dataset is to allow users to view, analyze and display planned land use data for anywhere in the seven-county Twin Cities metropolitan area with a consistent land use classification scheme. In conjunction with other regional information (i.e., land use trend data, households and jobs forecasts), the PLU data can help communities more easily understand regional and sub-regional planning goals and Metropolitan Council staff, working with individual local units of government, can better monitor growth and plan for the future needs and financing of regional services such as regional parks, transit service, and wastewater collection and treatment. 

Since there is no official State or Regional land use coding scheme that communities must conform with, the variability of content and codes between communities' land use plans is nearly as vast as the number of communities themselves (187). Differences among communities can range from the implementation of different land use categories to conflicting definitions of similar categories. The PLU dataset attempts to effectively level out the variability among communities by translating communities land use categories and descriptions into a common classification scheme while retaining the communities' original categories. Although the comparability of land use plans between communities has greatly improved as a result of this translation or "regionalization" of communities' land use codes, it is likely that not all community land use definitions have been precisely translated into the most appropriate regional land use category (see "Summary of Regionalization Consistencies and Assumptions"). 


II. CREATION OFTHE PLANNED LAND USE (PLU) DATASET 

A. LAND USE CODING SCHEME: 
The PLU dataset came to fruition in 2002 based on an original "Information Need" outlined by MetroGIS and the Metropolitan Council's need to collect and compare communities' land use plans across jurisdictional boundaries for planning and servicing regional services (i.e., regional parks, transit, and waste collection and treatment). Derived from communities' individual land use plans and subsequent plan amendments, the data set is displayed utilizing a uniform classification scheme that incorporates the concepts and practices fostered by the American Planners Association. The classification scheme - the Regional Planned Land Use Coding Scheme - is the result of more than 3 ½ years of collaboration between MetroGIS, the North Metro I-35W Corridor Coalition and the Metropolitan Council. The combined, uniform regional vision allows users to visualize information in a variety of ways and make "apples to apples" comparisons between communities which can influence regional and sub-regional planning policies in ways that hadn't been possible in the past. 

Based on the recommendation of MetroGIS, the classification scheme distinguishes between use and "intensity of use." To better explain this distinction, consider the following often-used land use terms: "Multifamily Residential" and "High Density Residential." Both terms are describing a form "Residential" land use. Whereas "Multifamily" defines the type residential land use, "High Density" is a qualitative term reflecting the intensity of use the "Residential" land. Such intensity descriptions are not reserved solely for residential land uses. Although not use as frequently, intensity qualifiers are just as applicable to other types of land use (i.e., "High Intensity Mixed Use", "Medium Performance Industrial" or "Low Density Business - Office Park"). Acknowledging that there is a distinction between a land use and the intensity of that use, an "Intensity of Use" Work Group was formed to refine the proposed Regional Land Use Coding Scheme land use categories and determine what "intensity" measures would be useful to supplement planned land use data, or more specifically, the Regional Coding Scheme. The Work Group outlined several measures but, only "Housing Density" was designated as a priority and addressed by the group as of 2002. As a result, "Housing Density" (i.e., "HSG_DEN") and "Housing Density Range" (i.e., "HSGDEN_RNG") are included as separate data fields in the Regional Planned Land Use dataset to record the community's known allowable housing density range associated with a residential land use category and which standardized density range category is most appropriate for the community's description, respectively (see Definition of the "Intensity of Use" Work Group's Housing Density Ranges list below). 

For more information about the activities and participants involved in the development of MetroGIS's Regional Planned Land Use Coding Scheme or data set, refer to www.metrogis.org/data/info_needs /planned_land_use/index.shtml. To view the land use categories of the Regional Planned Land Use Coding Scheme refer to Definition of Planned Land Use Categories listed below. 

B. GEOGRAPHY (SPATIAL BASE): 
Like all geographic data managed by the Metropolitan Council, a goal of the PLU data is to interoperable with other geographic data. As such, the PLU data is compiled and delineated using a topologically CLEANED spatial database comprising of county-produced city and township boundaries and parcel boundaries for the seven-county Twin Cities metropolitan area (i.e., Anoka, Carver, Dakota, Hennepin, Ramsey, Scott, and Washington Counties), data made available through MetroGIS. As a result, where coterminous, the planned land use designations align with parcel (or property) boundaries. In areas where the planned land use boundaries do not follow parcel boundaries, parcels are split to approximately reflect the land use plan designations. 

Initially, land uses were delineated to parcel boundaries and non-parcels lands (lands not defined as a parcel such as road rights-of-way) were delineated and designated accordingly (i.e., Vehicular Rights-of-Way or Pedestrian Rights-of-Way, etc.). However, due to the structure of some county parcel datasets and the difficulties associated with maintaining the geographic integrity of the Regional Planned Land Use Dataset due to periodic parcel alignment adjustments by counties, the methodology was re-evaluated. When combined with the fact that the data capture methodology of the Council's 5-Year "Existing" land use inventories included land use delineation to rights-of-way centerline and users' desire to compare current land use patterns with planned development, a call to change the way rights-of-ways are classified in the PLU dataset was made. As a result, starting in 2005, only major highways are delineated and classified as "Vehicular Rights-of-Way" in the PLU dataset. The major highways are defined by the Metropolitan Council's Functional Roads classification. All other rights-of ways were delineated from the adjacent land use boundaries to the centerline, using The Lawrence Group (TLG) Street Centerlines as a guide, and assigned the appropriate land use designation. 

C. DATA CAPTURE METHODOLOGY: 
The following general data capture procedures (the translation or "regionalization" of community's land use categories) are used to create the PLU data set: 
1. Quarterly, gather all new community land use plans and plan amendments and incorporate their geography into the existing PLU dataset using current parcel boundaries to guide delineation - starting in 2005, incorporation means delineation to the rights-of-way centerline. 
2. Record communities' land use designations exactly as defined in their land use plans, 
3. Translate or "regionalize" communities' land use designations and housing densities into the detailed Regional Planned Land Use Coding Scheme and Housing Density Ranges through a "best-fit" procedure. See "Summary of Regionalization Consistencies and Assumptions" for more information about "best-fit" procedures. 
4. Dissolve or summarize the geography by land use types per community so that the final PLU dataset contains neither complete, original parcel boundaries nor any original parcel attribution (information) as specified in the current MetroGIS data-sharing agreement for the county parcel data. 
5. Upon completion of the the first version of the Regional PLU dataset (May 2002) and after a major significant data structural change (05/01/05), individual community information was mapped and sent to the communities for review and comments on accuracy of the Council's land use information and their regionalization of community designation into the Regional Planned Land Use Coding Scheme. NOTE: accuracies of the data and concerns regarding the regionalization of data will be continually addressed as they are presented. 

As land is developed and land use plans are "realized," frequently, development occurs with slightly different geography or alignment as speculatively depicted on the land use plan maps. Because of this reality, it was believed that an annual realignment of the preceding PLU data with actual parcel alignment would help achieve and maintain the goal of having geographically aligned regional datasets. To date, an automated, consistent annual realignment procedure has not been developed. As plan amendments are incorporated in the Regional dataset, realignment of previously incorporated planned land use may occur to improve the geographic representation of the data which, in turn, can alter the total land use area for a community's land use category beyond simple growth or land use change. Additionally, periodic review and realignments may occur when resources allow also impact land use area totals. 


III. ASSUMPTIONS, OBSERVATIONS AND REGIONALIZATION CONSISTENCIES: 
Please review the following document to learn more about Assumptions, Observations and Regionalization Consistenties made regarding the Regional Planned Land Use Dataset: www.datafinder.org/metadata/PLU_Consistencies.pdf 

IV. UPDATES:

1)  ADDED COMPREHENSIVE PLAN AMENDMENTS : 09/01/02
2)  DATA STRUCTURE UPDATE IMPLEMENTED : 09/01/02
3)  ADDED COMPREHENSIVE PLAN AMENDMENTS : 01/01/03
4) ADDED COMPREHENSIVE PLAN AMENDMENTS : 3/06/03
5)  DATA STRUCTURE UPDATE IMPLEMENTED : 03/25/03
6)  ADDED COMPREHENSIVE PLAN AMENDMENTS : 05/29/03
7)  ADDED COMPREHENSIVE PLAN AMENDMENTS : 10/13/03
8) DATA STRUCTURE UPDATE IMPLEMENTED : 06/01/05
9) ADDED COMPREHENSIVE PLAN AMENDMENTS : 06/01/05
10) ADDED COMPREHENSIVE PLAN AMENDMENTS : 2/02/06 (add retroactively by PEH)
11) ADDED COMPREHENSIVE PLAN AMENDMENTS : 11/07/06
12)  ADDED COMPREHENSIVE PLAN AMENDMENTS : 12/28/06
13) ADDED NEW COMPREHENSIVE PLANS AND PLAN AMENDMENTS AND DATA STRUCTURE UPDATE IMPLEMENTED : 04/04/07
14) ADDED NEW COMPREHENSIVE PLANS AND PLAN AMENDMENTS AND DATA STRUCTURE UPDATE IMPLEMENTED : 08/21/07
15) ADDED NEW COMPREHENSIVE PLANS AND PLAN AMENDMENTS AND DATA STRUCTURE UPDATE IMPLEMENTED : 01/16/08
16) ADDED NEW COMPREHENSIVE PLANS AND PLAN AMENDMENTS AND DATA STRUCTURE UPDATE IMPLEMENTED : 03/26/08
17) ADDED NEW COMPREHENSIVE PLANS AND PLAN AMENDMENTS AND DATA STRUCTURE UPDATE IMPLEMENTED : 07/07/08
18) ADDED NEW COMPREHENSIVE PLANS AND PLAN AMENDMENTS AND DATA STRUCTURE UPDATE IMPLEMENTED : 10/08/08
19) Added New Comprehensive Plans and Plan Amendments and Data Structure Update Implemented : 12/31/08
20) Added New Comprehensive Plans: 06/11/09
21) Minor correction made to previous release: 07/09/09
22) Added New Comprehensive Plans and Plan Amendments: 01/26/10
23) Added New Comprehensive Plans and Plan Amendments: 05/11/10
24) Added New Comprehensive Plans and Plan Amendments: 08/25/10
25) Added New Comprehensive Plans and Plan Amendments: 11/18/10
26) Added New Comprehensive Plans and Plan Amendments: 6/1/11
27) Added New Comprehensive Plans and Plan Amendments: 2/1/12
28) Added New Comprehensive Plans and Plan Amendments: 7/31/12
29) Added New Comprehensive Plans and Plan Amendments: 3/22/2013
30) Added New Comprehensive Plans and Plan Amendments: 9/11/2013
31) Added New Comprehensive Plans and Plan Amendments: 1/23/2014
32) Added New Comprehensive Plans and Plan Amendments: 5/23/2014
33) Modified structure of the database: 7/2014
34) Added New Comprehensive Plans and Plan Amendments: 11/7/2014
35) Added New Comprehensive Plans and Plan Amendments: 2/5/2015
36) Added New Comprehensive Plans and Plan Amendments: 5/26/2015
37) Added New Comprehensive Plans and Plan Amendments: 9/23/2015

The following communities had Comprehensive Plan Amendments added May 26, 2015:

Andover
Apple Valley
Brooklyn Park
Coon Rapids
Dayton
Eagan
Elko New Market
Golden Valley
Inver Grove Heights
Lakeville
Miesville
Minnetonka
Prior Lake
Richfield
St. Louis Park

</procdesc></procstep><srcinfo><srcscale></srcscale></srcinfo></lineage></dataqual><spdoinfo><indspref></indspref><direct></direct><mgmg3obj></mgmg3obj><mgmg3til></mgmg3til></spdoinfo><eainfo><overview><eaover>PLU_POLYGON feature class attribution 

OBJECTID: Unique polygon identifier 

SHAPE: ArcGIS feature type 

COCTU_CODE: 11 digitunique identifier for each city, township or unorganized 
territory based on 3-digit FIPS county code and the federal Geographic Names
Information System (GNIS)

CO_CODE: 3 digit FIPS code for the county in which the polygon resides; 

CTU_ID: The Geographic Names Information System (GNIS) official federal unique identifier 
for each city, township or unorganized territory ( 9 digit Long Integer) 

CTU_NAME: Minor Civil Division name; e.g. Dahlgren Twp., Blaine 

PLUSE_DESC: Unique community Planned Land Use (PLUSE) description as described
in community's comprehensive plan ; e.g. Single Family,Detached - all descriptions valid 

HSG_DEN: Community's residential density ranges as described in community's
comprehensive plan; e.g. 1 - 4 units per acre - all defined ranges valid 

BENCHMARK: Alphanumeric code for year of community's comprehensive plan (i.e., 2030). 
Communities that have opted out of the Metropolitan Council jurisdiction
are listed as 'NA' (Not Applicable). 

ACRES: Polygon area in acres 

METC_DESC: Metropolitan Council's interpretation of community's planned land use
description based on additional information to develop a more regionally consistent 
dataset. For example, if PLUSE_DESC defines "Public" category, METC_DESC may 
further define category into more specific categories such as "Education",
"Government facilities", or "Park" to better correspond to categorical detail of 
other communties in the region. 

METC_DENS: Residential density ranges that correspond to METC_DESC category; 
e.g. 1 - 4 units per acre - all defined ranges valid 

HSGDEN_RNG: Best-fit regional residential density range to compare
housing density across the region; e.g. LOW - see valid ranges and 
definitions listed in Entity and Attribute Detailed Citation section 

REGIONAL_N: Numeric regional land use code based on METC_DESC; e.g. 211 
- see valid codes listed in Entity and Attribute Detailed Citation section 

SHAPE_LENG: Perimeter length of polygon in meters 

SHAPE_AREA: Polygon area in square meters

CTU_CODE: 5 digit FIPS code for the city, Townships, &amp; Unincorporated areas in which the polygon resides</eaover><eadetcit>SPATIAL DATA (POLYGON) ATTRIBUTES: 

OBJECTID: Unique polygon identifier 
SHAPE: ArcGIS feature type 
COCTU_CODE: 11 digitunique identifier for each city, township or unorganized territory based on 3-digit FIPS county code and the federal Geographic NamesInformation System (GNIS)
CO_CODE: 3 digit FIPS code for the county in which the polygon resides; 
CTU_ID: The Geographic Names Information System (GNIS) official federal unique identifier for each city, township or unorganized territory ( 9 digit Long Integer) 
CTU_NAME: Minor Civil Division name; e.g. Dahlgren Twp., Blaine 
PLUSE_DESC: Unique community Planned Land Use (PLUSE) description as described in community's comprehensive plan ; e.g. Single Family,Detached - all descriptions valid 
HSG_DEN: Community's residential density ranges as described in community's comprehensive plan; e.g. 1 - 4 units per acre - all defined ranges valid 
BENCHMARK: Alphanumeric code for year of community's comprehensive plan (i.e., 2030). Communities that have opted out of the Metropolitan Council jurisdiction are listed as 'NA' (Not Applicable). 
ACRES: Polygon area in acres 
METC_DESC: Metropolitan Council's interpretation of community's planned land use description based on additional information to develop a more regionally consistent dataset - all descriptions valid 
METC_DENS: Residential density ranges that correspond to METC_DESC category; e.g. 1 - 4 units per acre - all defined ranges valid 
HSGDEN_RNG: Best-fit regional residential density range to compare housing density across the region; e.g. LOW - see valid ranges and definitions listed in Entity and Attribute Detailed Citation section 
REGIONAL_N: Numeric regional land use code based on METC_DESC; e.g. 211 - see valid codes listed in Entity and Attribute Detailed Citation section 
SHAPE_LENG: Perimeter length of polygon in meters 
SHAPE_AREA: Polygon area in square meters
CTU_CODE: 5 digit FIPS code for the city, Townships, &amp; Unincorporated areas in which the polygon resides


Valid HSGDEN_RNG Codes - RURAL, EXURBAN, LOW, MEDIUM, HIGH, VERYHIGH, URBAN. See Valid HSGDEN_RNG Codes and Corresponding Density Ranges listed below. 


Valid REGIONAL_N codes - 110, 120, 130, 149, 198, 199, 211, 212, 213, 218, 219, 221, 222, 224, 228, 310. 320, 330, 340, 350, 399, 410, 420, 430, 440, 470, 499, 510, 520, 530, 540, 599, 610, 620, 630, 699, 710, 720, 730, 799, 812, 813, 819, 820, 830, 911, 914, 921, 922, 939, 950, 1029, 1030, 1040, 1100. REGIONAL_N codes relate to Valid 'DETAILED' numeric land use codes as defined in the PLU_Regional_CodesDB.mdb. See Valid 'DETAILED' numeric land use codes and associated description information (i.e., DESC_ or FULLDESCMEMO) are listed below. 

Valid BENCHMARK codes - '2020', '2030', 'NA' for Not Applicable 



================================================== 

Zipfile contains three (3) relational database tables: 
1) PLURegionalGeneralDesignations
2) PLURegionalDetailedDesignations
3) PLURegionalHousingDensityRanges


1) PLURegionalGeneralDesignations table attributes: 
GENERALIZED - 'GENERALIZED' numeric regional land use code associated with 'DETAILED' numeric regional land use code 
DESC_ - Description of 'GENERALIZED' regional numeric land use code (e.g. Single Family Residential) 
FULLDESCMEMO - Full description of 'GENERALIZED' regional numeric land use code 

2) PLURegionalDetailedDesignations table attributes: 
GENERALIZED - 'GENERALIZED' numeric regional land use code associated with 'DETAILED' numeric regional land use code 
DETAILED - 'DETAILED' numeric regional land use code 
DESC_ - Description of 'DETAILED' regional numeric land use code (e.g. Single Family, Detached Residential) 
FULLDESCMEMO - Full description of 'DETAILED' regional numeric land use code 

3) PLURegionalHousingDensityRanges table attributes: 
HSGDEN_RNG - "Best Fit" Regional Housing Density Range 

------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------- 

Valid GENERALIZED Land Use Codes and Corresponding Descriptions (i.e., DESC_ or FULLDESCMEMO) 
100 -- Agricultural - Land used for agricultural purposes, including farming, dairying, pasturage, horticulture, floriculture, viticulture, and animal and poultry husbandry and accessory uses; provided that such accessory uses shall be incidental to the agricultural activities. 

190 -- Rural or Large-Lot Residential - Land containing a building or portion thereof used for residential purposes, including mostly one-family homes but may include some two-family (code 219), but not including hotels, motels, and boarding and lodging houses, nursing homes, or elderly care facilities - may include land used for agricultural purposes, including farming, dairying, pasturage, horticulture, floriculture, viticulture, and animal and poultry husbandry and accessory uses provided that such accessory uses shall be incidental to the agricultural activities. Housing development across the land use designation should not exceed 1 housing unit per 1 acre and no less than 1 housing unit per 40 acres. 

210 -- Single Family Residential - Land containing a building or portion thereof used exclusively for residential purposes, including mostly one-family homes but may include some two-family (code 219), but not including hotels, motels, and boarding and lodging houses, nursing homes, or elderly care facilities - or open space within or related to a residential development, not in individually owned lots or dedicated for public use, but which is designed and intended for the common use or enjoyment of the residents of the development. 

220 -- Multifamily Residential - Land containing a building or portion thereof used exclusively for residential purposes, including two-family, and multiple-family dwellings, but not including hotels, motels, and boarding and lodging houses, nursing homes, or elderly care facilities - or open space within or related to a residential development, not in individually owned lots or dedicated for public use, but which is designed and intended for the common use or enjoyment of the residents of the development. 

300 -- Commercial - Land use primarily engaged in the provision of goods or services for an unspecified market area. 

400 -- Industrial - Land used primarily in the manufacture and/or processing of specified or unspecified products; could include light or heavy industrial land use, large warehouse facilities, or utilities land use. 

500 -- Institutional - Land used for primarily religious, governmental, educational, social or health care facilities excluding clinics. 

600 -- Mixed Use - Land containing or potentially containing a building or buildings with significant amounts of two or more of the following: residential, industrial, commercial and/or office uses. 

700 -- Multi-Optional Development - Land potentially containing a building with a significant amount of only one of the follow land uses: residential, industrial, commercial and/or office uses. 

810 -- Park and Recreation - Land used primarily for public recreation activities improved with playing fields, playground or exercise equipment and associated structures. May include land containing a building(s) developed, used and maintained primarily for recreational activities. 

815-- Open Space or Restrictive Use - Land used and maintained for public or private recreation, resources use (i.e., pasture, woodlot), or resource protection, amenity, or buffer. 

910 -- Rights-of-Way (i.e., Roads) - Land area or strip of land, either public or private, intended to be reserved for vehicular rights-of-way or pedestrian rights-of-way - may include unspecified transportation land use. 

920 -- Railway (inc. LRT) - Land area or strip of land, either public or private, intended to be reserved for rail activities: freight or passenger. 

930 -- Airport - Land area or strip of land, either public or privade, intended to be reserved for airport activities. 

1000 -- Vacant or No Data - Land not currently used for any defined purpose that may or may not contain buildings or other structures or lacks a clearly defined land use. 

1100 -- Water - Permanently flooded open water not including wetlands, or periodically flooded areas. 

------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------- 

Valid DETAILED Land Use codes and Corresponding Descriptions (i.e., DESC_ or FULLDESCMEMO) 
149 -- Agricultural, Undifferentiated - Land used for agricultural purposes, including farming, dairying, pasturage, horticulture, floriculture, viticulture, and animal and poultry husbandry and accessory uses provided that such accessory uses shall be incidental to the agricultural activities. 

110 -- Farmstead - Land used constituting the area comprising of the livable space; house and surrounding agricultural buildings and activities which may include small dairying, and animal or poultry husbandry operations. 

120 -- Cropland - Land used for agricultural purposes, including farming, pasturage, horticulture, floriculture, viticulture, and accessory uses. 

130 -- Agricultural Support &amp; Other - Land used for agricultural purposes, including major dairying, and animal or poultry husbandry operations; other unclassified accessory agricultural activities provided that such accessory uses shall be incidental to the agricultural activities. 

198 -- Rural Residential - Land containing a building or portion thereof used for residential purposes, including mostly one-family homes, but may include some two-family (code 219), but not including hotels, motels, and boarding and lodging houses, nursing homes, or elderly care facilities; may include land used for agricultural purposes, including farming, dairying, pasturage, horticulture, floriculture, viticulture, and animal and poultry husbandry and accessory uses; provided that such accessory uses shall be incidental to the agricultural activities. Housing development across the land use designation should not exceed 1 housing unit per 2.5 acre and no less than 1 housing unit per 40 acres. 

199 -- Large-Lot Residential, Undifferentiated - Land containing a building or portion thereof used for residential purposes, including mostly one-family homes, but may include some two-family (code 219), but not including hotels, motels, and boarding and lodging houses, nursing homes, or elderly care facilities; most likely does not include any land for agricultural purposes. Housing development across the land use designation should not exceed 1 housing unit per 1 acre and no less than 1 housing unit per 2.5 acres. 

211 -- Single Family, Detached Residential - Land meeting the general definition of residential and containing a residential building with not more than one dwelling unit entirely surrounded by open space on the same lot. 

212 -- Seasonal / Vacation Residential - Land that provides seasonal activities that may contain a single dwelling unit residential building that meets the general definition of residential the land and/or residence does not serve as a primary residence of an owner. 

213 -- Manufactured Housing Park - Land meeting the general definition of residential and under single ownership that has been planned and improved for the placement of manufactured housing for dwelling purposes. 

218 -- Single Family Residential, Undifferentiated - Land containing a building or portion thereof used exclusively for residential purposes, including one-family, two family, and multiple-family dwellings, but not including hotels, motels, and boarding and lodging houses, nursing homes, or elderly care facilities; or open space within or related to a residential development, not in individually owned lots or dedicated for public use, but which is designed and intended for the common use or enjoyment of the residents of the development. Residential type are unknown and housing density community designation is unknown or known to be low (approximately less than 4 to 6 units per acre). 

219 -- Single Family, Detached or Attached Residential - Land meeting the general definition of residential and containing a residential building with not more than one dwelling unit entirely surrounded by open space on the same lot - or one or more buildings containing two or more dwelling units, each of which has primary ground floor access to the outside and which are attached to each other by party walls without openings 

221 -- Single Family, Attached Residential - Land meeting the general definition of residential and containing one or more buildings containing two or more dwelling units, each of which has primary ground floor access to the outside and which are attached to each other by party walls without openings. 

222 -- Single Family, Attached or Multifamily Residential - Land meeting the general definition of residential and containing one or more buildings containing one or more buildings containing two or more dwelling units, each of which has primary ground floor access to the outside and which are attached to each other by party walls without openings - or three or more dwelling units, one or more of which does not have primary ground floor access to the outside and which are attached to each other by party walls without openings. 

224 -- Multi-Family - Land meeting the general definition of residential and containing one or more buildings containing three or more dwelling units, one or more of which does not have primary ground floor access to the outside and which are attached to each other by party walls without openings. 

228 -- Multifamily Residential, Undifferentiated - Land containing a building or portion thereof used exclusively for residential purposes, including one-family, two-family, and multiple-family dwellings, but not including hotels, motels, and boarding and lodging houses, nursing homes, or elderly care facilities; or open space within or related to a residential development, not in individually owned lots or dedicated for public use, but which is designed and intended for the common use or enjoyment of the residents of the development. Residential type are unknown and housing density community designation is known to be "higher" (approxiately 4 to 6 units per acre or more). 

399 -- Commercial, Retail or Undifferentiated - Land use primarily engaged in the provision of goods or services for an unspecified market area. 

310 -- Neighborhood Commercial - Land use primarily engaged in the provision of goods or services with a primary service radius of 1 to 1.5 miles. Neighborhood Commercial/Retail Land Uses would typically be located in a predominantly residential area and have a Gross Leasable Area (GLA) of approximately 25,000 square feet or less. 

320 -- Community Commercial - Land use principally engaged in the provision of goods or services with a primary service radius of 3 to 5 miles. Community Commercial/Retail Land Uses would typically be located in a small commercial/retail/rural center with a Gross Leasable Area (GLA) of approximately 50,000 to 150,000 square feet. 

330 -- Regional Commercial - Land use principally engaged in the provision of goods or services with a primary service radius of 10 or more miles. Regional Commercial/Retail Land Uses would typically be located in or near a large commercial/retail center with a Gross Leasable Area (GLA) of approximately 350,000 square feet or more. 

340 -- Highway / Convenience Commercial - Land use principally engaged in the provision of goods or services that primarily services customers attracted from a nearby major transportation arterial in a predominately rural setting located outside the MUSA line. 

350 -- Rural Commercial - Land use principally engaged in the provision of goods or services that primarily services customers attracted from rural communities with a Gross Leasable Area (GLA) of approximately 25,000 square feet or less. 

360 -- Office, Undifferentiated - Land use predominantly involved in administrative, professional, or clerical services; includes medical clinics 

370 -- Marina - Land used for the operation of boating and sailing water sports and related leisure activities. 

499 -- Industrial, Undifferentiated - Land used primarily in the manufacture and/or processing of unspecified products; could be light or heavy industrial land use. 

410 -- Light Industrial - Land used primarily in the manufacture and/or processing, fabrication, assembly, packaging, incidental storage, sales, and distribution of predominantly previously prepared materials, finished products or parts. Light Industrial land uses would typically have all processing within buildings, require exterior storage, generate amounts of truck or rail traffic, and be free of hazardous or objectionable elements such as noise, odor, dust smoke, glare, or other pollutants. 

420 -- Heavy Industrial - Land used primarily in the manufacture and/or processing of products from large bulky, predominantly raw, extracted, or hazardous materials; or use engaged in the storage of flammable, explosive, or other materials that may pose a threat to public health or safety. Heavy Industrial land uses may require exterior storage of large equipment or material, be engaged in outside processing or assembly, generate significant amounts of truck and/or rail traffic, or emit limited amounts of objectionable elements such as noise, odor, dust, smoke, glare, or other pollutants. 

430 -- Extractive - Land used for certain branches of industry which are conveniently designated extractive: e.g., agriculture, pastoral and mining pursuits, cutting of lumber, etc 

440 -- Utility - An area or strip of land, either public or private, occupied by a power plant or substation, electric transmission line, oil or gas pipeline, water tower, municipal well, reservoir, pumping station, water treatment facility, communications tower, or similar use. 

470 -- Water Navigation (i.e., Locks) - Land used for the operation of water navigation and associated accessory uses; predominantly navigational lock and dams. 

599 -- Institutional, Undifferentiated - Land used for primarily religious, governmental, educational, social or health care facilities excluding clinics, use unspecified. 

510 -- Religious - Land used for primarily religious activities, may include churches, synagogues, temples, cemeteries, and other support activities. 

520 -- Educational - Land used for primarily educational activities, may include schools and surrounding recreational facilities. 

530 -- Governmental - Land used for primarily governmental activities. 

540 -- Health - Land used for primarily health care facilities excluding clinics, may include hospitals or other medical/residential care facilities. 

699 -- Mixed Use, Undifferentiated - Land containing or potentially containing a building with significant amounts of residential, industrial, commercial and/or office uses, composition of use unspecified. 

610 -- Residential and Other Mixed Use - Land containing mixed uses comprising of no less than residential and one other land use predominantly contains residential apartments over commercial or office uses, but may contain other land uses. 

620 -- Industrial and Other Mixed Use - Land containing mixed uses comprising of no less than industrial and one other land use but excluding any residential predominantly industrial uses with commercial or office uses. 

630 -- Commercial and Other Mixed Use - Land containing mixed uses comprising of no less than commercial and one other land use but excluding any residential or industrial predominantly commercial and office uses. 

799 -- Multi-Optional Development, Undifferentiated - Land that has yet to develop that potentially will contain a building with only one of the follow land uses: residential, industrial, commercial or office use. 

710 -- Residential or Other Use - Land that has yet to develop that potentially will contain a building with either residential or another land use individual use uncertain. 

720 -- Industrial or Other Use - Land that has yet to develop that potentially will contain a building with either industrial or another land use but excluding residential individual use unspecified. 

730 -- Commercial or Other Use - Land that has yet to develop that potentially will contain a building with either commercial or another land use but excluding residential or industrial, individual use unspecified. 

812 -- Community Park and Recreation - Land used primarily for public recreation activities improved with playing fields, playground or exercise equipment and associated structures. May include land containing a building(s) developed, used and maintained primarily for recreational activities. 

813 -- Golf Course - Land used for the operation of a golf course may include other leisure activities, such as pall-mall, tipcart, croquet and curling. 

819 -- Open Space: Passive or Undifferentiated - Land used and maintained which supports unorganized public or private recreational activities which may contain trails, picnic areas, public fishing/boating docks, etc. May include unspecified open space land use, unprotected wetland areas, or other privately owned lands. 

820 -- Open Space: Natural - Land predominantly undeveloped or unaltered and preserved in its natural state for environmental or aesthetic purposes. 

830 -- Open Space: Restrictive - Land used and maintained for resource protection, amenity, or buffer - Restricted use (i.e., floodplain, conservancy land, etc.). 

914 -- Transportation, Undifferentiated - Land used for any undefined transportation activity. 

911 -- Vehicular Rights-of-Way - An area or strip of land, either public or private, on which an irrevocable right-of-passage has been recorded for the use of vehicles. 

950 -- Pedestrian Rights-of-Way - An area or strip of land, either public or private, on which an irrevocable right-of-passage has been recorded for the use of pedestrians. 

921 -- Railway Corridor - An area or strip of land occupied or intended to be occupied by freight-service rail or other similar use. Includes rail that may support passenger commuter rail. 

922 -- Rail Transit Way - An area or strip of land occupied or intended to be occupied only by passenger rail or other similar uses. Includes light rail transit (LRT) and commuter rail. 

939 -- Airport - Land used for the operation of aircraft and associated accessory uses provided accessory uses are incidental to the airport activity. 

1029 -- Vacant Land - Land not currently used for any defined purpose that may or may not contain buildings or other structures. 

1030 -- No Data - Land use information is missing information not submitted to the Metropolitan Council. 

1040 -- Uncertain - Land use information indistinguishable. 

1199 -- Open Water - Permanently flooded open water not including wetlands, or periodically flooded areas. 

------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------- 

Valid HSGDEN_RNG Codes and Corresponding Density Ranges 
- AG = 1 housing unit per 40 acres or more 
- RURAL = 1 housing unit per 2.51 to 39.9 acres 
- EXURBAN = 1 housing unit per 1.1 to 2.5 acres 
- LOW = 1 to 4 housing units per acre 
- MEDIUM = 4.1 to 8 housing units per acre 
- HIGH = 8.1 to 12 housing units per acre 
- VERYHIGH = 12.1 to 20 housing units per acre 
- URBAN = Greater than 20 housing units per acre</eadetcit></overview></eainfo><distinfo><resdesc>landuse_planned_research</resdesc><distliab>NOTICE:  The Geographic Information System (GIS) Data to which this notice is attached are made available pursuant to the Minnesota Government Data Practices Act (Minnesota Statutes Chapter 13).  THE GIS DATA ARE PROVIDED TO YOU AS IS AND WITHOUT ANY WARRANTY AS TO THEIR PERFORMANCE, MERCHANTABILITY, OR FITNESS FOR ANY PARTICULAR PURPOSE.  The GIS Data were developed by the Metropolitan Council for its own internal business purposes.  The Metropolitan Council does not represent or warrant that the GIS Data or the data documentation are error-free, complete, current, or accurate.  You are responsible for any consequences resulting from your use of the GIS Data or your reliance on the GIS Data.  You should consult the data documentation for this particular GIS Data to determine the limitations of the GIS Data and the precision with which the GIS Data may depict distance, direction, location, or other geographic features.  If you transmit or provide the GIS Data (or any portion of it) to another user, it is recommended that the GIS Data include a copy of this disclaimer and this metadata.</distliab><stdorder><digform><digtinfo><formname>csv file</formname><formvern></formvern><transize></transize></digtinfo></digform><ordering>See Online Linkage Below</ordering></stdorder><distrib><cntinfo><cntperp><cntorg>Metropolitan Council</cntorg><cntper>Paul Hanson</cntper></cntperp><cntpos>GIS Coordinator - Community Developement</cntpos><cntaddr><addrtype>mailing and physical</addrtype><address>390 Robert Street North</address><city>St. Paul</city><state>Minnesota</state><postal>55101-1805</postal></cntaddr><cntvoice>651-602-1644</cntvoice><cntfax>651-602-1674</cntfax><cntemail>paul.hanson@metc.state.mn.us</cntemail></cntinfo></distrib></distinfo><metainfo><metd>20150923</metd><metstdn>Minnesota Geographic Metadata Guidelines</metstdn><metstdv>1.2</metstdv><metextns><onlink>http://www.mngeo.state.mn.us/committee/standards/mgmg/metadata.htm</onlink></metextns><metc><cntinfo><cntperp><cntorg>Metropolitan Council</cntorg><cntper>Paul E. Hanson</cntper></cntperp><cntpos>GIS Coordinator - Community Development</cntpos><cntaddr><addrtype>mailing and physical</addrtype><address>390 Robert Street North</address><city>St. Paul</city><state>Minnesota</state><postal>55101-1805</postal></cntaddr><cntvoice>651-602-1642</cntvoice><cntfax>651-602-1674</cntfax><cntemail>paul.hanson@metc.state.mn.us</cntemail></cntinfo></metc></metainfo><Esri><ModDate>20101213</ModDate><ModTime>10385800</ModTime><CreaDate>20140710</CreaDate><CreaTime>10301200</CreaTime><SyncOnce>TRUE</SyncOnce><DataProperties><itemProps><itemLocation><linkage Sync="TRUE">file://\\rafs2a\gis\devel\data_devel\comp_plans\plu\Data\Processing\PlannedLandUse (1)</linkage><protocol Sync="TRUE">Local Area Network</protocol></itemLocation></itemProps><copyHistory><copy source="L:\Metadata\Layers\PlannedLandUse" dest="\\rafs2a\gis\devel\data_devel\comp_plans\plu\Data\Processing\PlannedLandUse (1)" date="20140710" time="10301200"></copy></copyHistory></DataProperties></Esri><mdDateSt Sync="TRUE">20101213</mdDateSt></metadata>