<metadata>
  <idinfo>
    <citation>
      <citeinfo>
        <origin>Minnesota Department of Natural Resources (DNR)</origin>
        <title>Sensitive Lakeshore Assessment</title>
        <pubinfo>
          <publish>Minnesota DNR - Ecological and Water Resources</publish>
        </pubinfo>
        <pubdate>20140818</pubdate>
        <onlink>http://gisdata.mn.gov/dataset/env-sensitive-lakeshore</onlink>
      </citeinfo>
    </citation>
    <descript>
      <abstract>The Sensitive Lakeshore Assessment Project was initiated to identify lakeshore areas of unique or critical habitat, or high biological diversity, in north-central Minnesota. An ecological model incorporating existing data (including wetlands and hydric soils) and field-collected data (including distribution and abundance of aquatic plants and high-priority animal species) was used to objectively rank lakeshores for sensitive area designation.

&lt;b&gt;Highly sensitive shoreland&lt;/b&gt; is a polygon feature class representing sensitive areas of lakeshore buffered landward by 1/4  mile. The &lt;b&gt;sensitivity index&lt;/b&gt; is a point feature class representing the sum of scores of the data layers at equally-spaced points along the shoreline of a lake. See http://www.dnr.state.mn.us/eco/sli/index.html for more information on attributes and analysis.</abstract>
      <purpose>Areas within highly sensitive shoreland areas or high sensitivity index scores may be afforded greater protection through zoning or other means, or prioritized for conservation via easements.

Highly sensitive shoreland areas and sensitivity indices are available for lakes &gt;500 acres in size in Cass, Crow Wing, Aitkin, Hubbard, and Itasca Counties, as well as a small number of additional lakes. Higher sensitivity index scores represent more sensitive areas of lakeshore. Sensitivity index scores (SUM_IDX) are lake-specific, and are not meant to be compared between lakes.</purpose>
      <supplinf>Cass, Crow Wing, Aitkin, Hubbard, Itasca Counties</supplinf>
    </descript>
    <timeperd>
      <current>Product dates depend on field work dates. Most data used in the analyses were collected between 2006 - 2012.  </current>
    </timeperd>
    <status>
      <progress>Complete</progress>
      <update>As needed</update>
    </status>
    <spdom>
      <bounding>
        <westbc>-97.23</westbc>
        <eastbc>-89.53</eastbc>
        <northbc>49.37</northbc>
        <southbc>43.5</southbc>
      </bounding>
    </spdom>
    <keywords>
      <place>
        <placekey>Minnesota, Cass, Crow Wing, Aitkin, Hubbard, Itasca</placekey>
      </place>
      <theme>
        <themekey>lakeshore, shoreland, protection, sensitive, lake</themekey>
      </theme>
    </keywords>
    <accconst>None</accconst>
    <useconst>None</useconst>
    <browse>
      <browsen>ftp://ftp.gisdata.mn.gov/pub/gdrs/data/pub/us_mn_state_dnr/env_sensitive_lakeshore/preview/preview.jpg</browsen>
    </browse>
    <ptcontac>
      <cntinfo>
        <cntperp>
          <cntorg>Minnesota DNR - Ecological and Water Resources</cntorg>
          <cntper>Paul Radomski</cntper>
        </cntperp>
        <cntpos>Project Consultant</cntpos>
        <cntaddr>
          <address>1601 Minnesota Dr</address>
          <city>Brainerd</city>
          <state>MN</state>
          <postal>56401</postal>
        </cntaddr>
        <cntvoice>218-833-8643</cntvoice>
        <cntemail>paul.radomski@state.mn.us</cntemail>
      </cntinfo>
    </ptcontac>
  </idinfo>
  <dataqual>
    <logic>Quality control has been conducted on the attributes. Data are topologically correct using ESRI ArcGIS 9.x/10.x software.</logic>
    <complete>Data are included for lakes greater than 500 acres in size in the selected counties, as well as several additional (often connecting) water bodies.</complete>
    <lineage>
      <procstep>
        <procdesc>Lake boundaries were derived from the DNR 100K Water Features dataset. </procdesc>
      </procstep>
    </lineage>
  </dataqual>
  <eainfo>
    <overview>
      <eaover>&lt;b&gt;Highly Sensitive Shoreland&lt;/b&gt;
SENS_ACRES are the total number of acres within the highly sensitive shoreland areas.
ANALYSIS refers to the type of analysis used to identify sensitive lakeshore (lakes were analyzed using either a full ecological model or an abbreviated ecological model).

&lt;b&gt;Sensitivity Index&lt;/b&gt;
SUM_IDX is the sum of attribute scores at each point on a particular lake. The sensitivity indices are lake-specific, and are a result of each lake's unique characteristics and habitat. The attributes include a variety of biological (plant and animal) and physical (wetland and soil) data layers.
ANALYSIS refers to the type of analysis used to identify sensitive lakeshore (lakes were analyzed using either a full ecological model or an abbreviated ecological model).
REL_SCORE is the relative SUM_IDX score at that point for a particular lake.</eaover>
    </overview>
  </eainfo>
  <distinfo>
    <distliab>The Minnesota Department of Natural Resources General Geographic Data License Agreement is online: http://www.dnr.state.mn.us/sitetools/data_software_license.html</distliab>
    <stdorder>
      <ordering>See Online Linkage or Distribution Contact</ordering>
    </stdorder>
    <resdesc>env_sensitive_lakeshore</resdesc>
    <distrib>
      <cntinfo>
        <cntperp>
          <cntorg>Minnesota DNR - Ecological and Water Resources</cntorg>
          <cntper>Paul Radomski</cntper>
        </cntperp>
        <cntpos>Project Consultant</cntpos>
        <cntaddr>
          <address>1601 Minnesota Dr</address>
          <city>Brainerd</city>
          <state>MN</state>
          <postal>56401</postal>
        </cntaddr>
        <cntvoice>218-833-8643</cntvoice>
        <cntemail>paul.radomski@state.mn.us</cntemail>
      </cntinfo>
    </distrib>
  </distinfo>
  <metainfo>
    <metd>20140818</metd>
    <metstdn>Minnesota Geographic Metadata Guidelines</metstdn>
    <metstdv>1.2</metstdv>
    <metextns>
      <onlink>http://www.mngeo.state.mn.us/committee/standards/mgmg/metadata.htm</onlink>
    </metextns>
    <metc>
      <cntinfo>
        <cntperp>
          <cntorg>Minnesota DNR - Ecological and Water Resources</cntorg>
          <cntper>Paul Radomski</cntper>
        </cntperp>
        <cntpos>Project Consultant</cntpos>
        <cntaddr>
          <address>1601 Minnesota Dr</address>
          <city>Brainerd</city>
          <state>MN</state>
          <postal>56401</postal>
        </cntaddr>
        <cntvoice>218-833-8643</cntvoice>
        <cntemail>paul.radomski@state.mn.us</cntemail>
      </cntinfo>
    </metc>
  </metainfo>
  <spref>
    <horizsys>
      <planar>
        <gridsys>
          <gridsysn>Universal Transverse Mercator</gridsysn>
          <utm>
            <utmzone>15</utmzone>
          </utm>
        </gridsys>
        <planci>
          <plandu>meters</plandu>
        </planci>
      </planar>
      <geodetic>
        <horizdn>NAD83</horizdn>
        <ellips>GRS80</ellips>
      </geodetic>
    </horizsys>
  </spref>
</metadata>
