<metadata>
  <idinfo>
    <citation>
      <citeinfo>
        <origin>Metropolitan Council</origin>
        <pubdate>periodically revised</pubdate>
        <title>Hi-Frequency Transit Service Network</title>
        <mgmg1cid>N/A</mgmg1cid>
        <pubinfo>
          <publish>Metropolitan Council</publish>
        </pubinfo>
        <onlink>https://gisdata.mn.gov/dataset/us-mn-state-metc-trans-hi-frequency-transit-servc</onlink>
      </citeinfo>
    </citation>
    <descript>
      <abstract>The Hi-Frequency Service Network layer consists of all or part of transit route segments with service ever 15 minutes or better on weekdays from 6:00 AM to 7:00 PM and Saturdays from 9:00 AM to 6:00 PM. The Hi- Transit stops served by Hi-Frequency routes are marked with red signs.

The line work for the dataset was derived from the NCompass Technologies Street Centerline and Address Ranges dataset. A small number of line segments have been added to those available from the NCompass dataset to completely depict all routes traveled by buses.</abstract>
      <purpose>To identify all locations in the Twin Cities metropolitan area where transit service frequency is every 15 minutes or better weekdays from 6:00 AM to 7:00 PM and Saturdays from 9:00 AM to 6:00 PM.</purpose>
      <supplinf>Twin Cities seven county metropolitan area.  This includes the counties of Anoka, Carver, Dakota, Hennepin, Ramsey, Scott and Washington in Minnesota.</supplinf>
    </descript>
    <timeperd>
      <timeinfo>
        <sngdate>
          <caldate>20140226</caldate>
        </sngdate>
      </timeinfo>
      <current>Route, segment, and stop information is accurate as of the Time Period of Content date. </current>
    </timeperd>
    <status>
      <progress>Complete</progress>
      <update>Quarterly</update>
    </status>
    <spdom>
      <bounding>
        <westbc>-94.012</westbc>
        <eastbc>-92.732</eastbc>
        <northbc>45.415</northbc>
        <southbc>44.471</southbc>
      </bounding>
    </spdom>
    <keywords>
      <theme>
        <themekt>None</themekt>
        <themekey>transit, buses, routes, segments, streets, roads, transportation</themekey>
      </theme>
      <place>
        <placekey>Twin Cities, Anoka County, Carver County, Dakota County, Hennepin County, Ramsey County, Scott County, Washington County</placekey>
      </place>
    </keywords>
    <accconst>None</accconst>
    <useconst>None</useconst>
    <native>ArcGIS 9.2</native>
    <crossref>
      <citeinfo>
        <title>NCompass Technologies Street Centerline and Address Ranges, Transit Routes, Transit Stops</title>
      </citeinfo>
    </crossref>
    <ptcontac>
      <cntinfo>
        <cntperp>
          <cntorg>Metropolitan Council - Metro Transit</cntorg>
          <cntper>Steve Baisden</cntper>
        </cntperp>
        <cntpos>Associate Planner</cntpos>
        <cntaddr>
          <addrtype>mailing and physical</addrtype>
          <address>560 6th Ave N</address>
          <city>Minneapolis</city>
          <state>MN</state>
          <postal>55411</postal>
        </cntaddr>
        <cntvoice>612.349.7361</cntvoice>
        <cntemail>stephen.baisden@metrotransit.org</cntemail>
      </cntinfo>
    </ptcontac>
  </idinfo>
  <dataqual>
    <attracc>
      <attraccr>Attributes randomly checked by Metropolitan Council GIS staff.</attraccr>
    </attracc>
    <logic>The dataset is topologically 'clean'.</logic>
    <complete>Entire seven county geographic area is covered.</complete>
    <posacc>
      <horizpa>
        <horizpar>Positional accuracy varies throughout the dataset. Most line work in most counties falls within the road right of way, often near the center. Recent realignments by the the NCompass Technologies Street Centerline and Address Ranges dataset have resulted in increased positional accuracy.</horizpar>
      </horizpa>
    </posacc>
    <lineage>
      <srcinfo>
        <srcscale/>
      </srcinfo>
      <procstep>
        <procdesc>To create this dataset, NCompass and MetCouncil-defined street centerlines were assigned to specific bus route segments.  Checks were performed to insure that the selected street centerlines were contiguous for each segment.  Met Council and Metro Transit GIS staff added new streets to fill gaps in the data, complete missing turns, and add busways not included by NCompass.  Checks were performed to insure the end nodes of these new streets snapped to the end nodes of the NCompass street centerlines, thereby creating a contiguous network.</procdesc>
      </procstep>
    </lineage>
  </dataqual>
  <spdoinfo>
    <indspref>None</indspref>
    <direct>Vector</direct>
    <mgmg3obj>arcs, nodes</mgmg3obj>
    <mgmg3til>One layer for entire seven county region.</mgmg3til>
  </spdoinfo>
  <eainfo>
    <overview>
      <eaover>LINE ATTRIBUTES:
 
LINE_ID:    A number identifying the route number associated with the bus and its schedules.
 
DIRECTION:  0, or 1.  0 is for northbound or eastbound, 1 for southbound or westbound.</eaover>
    </overview>
  </eainfo>
  <distinfo>
    <resdesc>HiFrequencyNetwork</resdesc>
    <distliab>NOTICE:  The Geographic Information System (GIS) Data to which this notice is attached are made available pursuant to the Minnesota Government Data Practices Act (Minnesota Statutes Chapter 13).  THE GIS DATA ARE PROVIDED TO YOU AS IS AND WITHOUT ANY WARRANTY AS TO THEIR PERFORMANCE, MERCHANTABILITY, OR FITNESS FOR ANY PARTICULAR PURPOSE.  The GIS Data were developed by the Metropolitan Council for its own internal business purposes.  The Metropolitan Council does not represent or warrant that the GIS Data or the data documentation are error-free, complete, current, or accurate.  You are responsible for any consequences resulting from your use of the GIS Data or your reliance on the GIS Data.  You should consult the data documentation for this particular GIS Data to determine the limitations of the GIS Data and the precision with which the GIS Data may depict distance, direction, location, or other geographic features.  If you transmit or provide the GIS Data (or any portion of it) to another user, it is recommended that the GIS Data include a copy of this disclaimer and this metadata.</distliab>
    <stdorder>
      <digform>
        <digtinfo>
          <formname>ArcView Shape File</formname>
          <formvern>ArcView: 9.2</formvern>
          <transize>0.03 Meg. for self extracting ZIP file.</transize>
        </digtinfo>
      </digform>
      <ordering>See Online Linkage Below</ordering>
    </stdorder>
    <distrib>
      <cntinfo>
        <cntperp>
          <cntorg>Metropolitan Council</cntorg>
          <cntper>Jon Hoekenga</cntper>
        </cntperp>
        <cntpos>GIS System Administrator</cntpos>
        <cntaddr>
          <addrtype>mailing and physical</addrtype>
          <address>390 Robert Street North</address>
          <city>St. Paul</city>
          <state>MN</state>
          <postal>55101-1805</postal>
        </cntaddr>
        <cntvoice>651.602.1561</cntvoice>
        <cntemail>jonathan.hoekenga@metc.state.mn.us</cntemail>
      </cntinfo>
    </distrib>
  </distinfo>
  <metainfo>
    <metd>20140226</metd>
    <metstdn>Minnesota Geographic Metadata Guidelines</metstdn>
    <metstdv>1.2</metstdv>
    <metextns>
      <onlink>http://www.mngeo.state.mn.us/committee/standards/mgmg/metadata.htm</onlink>
    </metextns>
    <metc>
      <cntinfo>
        <cntperp>
          <cntorg>Metropolitan Council - Metro Transit</cntorg>
          <cntper>Steve Baisden</cntper>
        </cntperp>
        <cntpos>Associate Planner</cntpos>
        <cntaddr>
          <addrtype>mailing and physical</addrtype>
          <address>560 6th Ave N</address>
          <city>Minneapolis</city>
          <state>MN</state>
          <postal>55411</postal>
        </cntaddr>
        <cntvoice>612.349.7361</cntvoice>
        <cntemail>stephen.baisden@metrotransit.org</cntemail>
      </cntinfo>
    </metc>
  </metainfo>
  <Esri>
    <ModDate>20070814</ModDate>
    <ModTime>09501900</ModTime>
  </Esri>
  <mdDateSt Sync="TRUE">20070814</mdDateSt>
  <spref>
    <horizsys>
      <planar>
        <gridsys>
          <gridsysn>Universal Transverse Mercator</gridsysn>
          <utm>
            <utmzone>15</utmzone>
          </utm>
        </gridsys>
        <planci>
          <plandu>meters</plandu>
        </planci>
      </planar>
      <geodetic>
        <horizdn>NAD83</horizdn>
        <ellips>GRS80</ellips>
      </geodetic>
    </horizsys>
  </spref>
</metadata>
