<metadata><idinfo><citation><citeinfo><title>SLC_ENVIRO_Lakes</title><geoform>vector digital data</geoform><origin>St. Louis County</origin><pubinfo><publish>St. Louis County</publish></pubinfo><pubdate>20150827</pubdate><onlink>http://www.stlouiscountymn.gov//DesktopModules/DNNCorp/DocumentLibrary/Components/FileDownloader/FileDownloaderPage.aspx?tabid=2018&amp;did=151230&amp;pid=0&amp;lrf=/DesktopModules/DNNCorp/DocumentLibrary/App_LocalResources/DocumentLibrary&amp;cl=en-US&amp;mcs=%2fDesktopModules%2fDNNCorp%2fDocumentLibrary%2f&amp;uarn=Administrators&amp;cd=false&amp;tmid=16060&amp;ift=1</onlink></citeinfo></citation><spdom><bounding><westbc>-93.114322</westbc><eastbc>-91.077159</eastbc><northbc>48.631541</northbc><southbc>46.646237</southbc></bounding></spdom><accconst>None</accconst><useconst>None.  Acknowledgment of the originating agencies would
be appreciated in products derived from these data.</useconst><native>Microsoft Windows 7 Version 6.1 (Build 7601) Service Pack 1; Esri ArcGIS 10.2.2.3552</native><descript><abstract>The National Hydrography Dataset (NHD) is a feature-based database that interconnects and uniquely identifies the stream segments or reaches that make up the nation's surface water drainage system. NHD data was originally developed at 1:100,000-scale and exists at that scale for the whole country. This high-resolution NHD, generally developed at 1:24,000/1:12,000 scale, adds detail to the original 1:100,000-scale NHD. (Data for Alaska, Puerto Rico and the Virgin Islands was developed at high-resolution, not 1:100,000 scale.)  Local resolution NHD is being developed where partners and data exist. The NHD contains reach codes for networked features, flow direction, names, and centerline representations for areal water bodies. Reaches are also defined on waterbodies and the approximate shorelines of the Great Lakes, the Atlantic and Pacific Oceans and the Gulf of Mexico. The NHD also incorporates the National Spatial Data Infrastructure framework criteria established by the Federal Geographic Data Committee.</abstract><purpose>The NHD is a national framework for assigning reach addresses to water-related entities, such as industrial discharges, drinking water supplies, fish habitat areas, wild and scenic rivers. Reach addresses establish the locations of these entities relative to one another within the NHD surface water drainage network, much like addresses on streets. Once linked to the NHD by their reach addresses, the upstream/downstream relationships of these water-related entities--and any associated information about them--can be analyzed using software tools ranging from spreadsheets to geographic information systems (GIS). GIS can also be used to combine NHD-based network analysis with other data layers, such as soils, land use and population, to help understand and display their respective effects upon one another. Furthermore, because the NHD provides a nationally consistent framework for addressing and analysis, water-related information linked to reach addresses by one organization (national, state, local) can be shared with other organizations and easily integrated into many different types of applications to the benefit of all.</purpose><supplinf>St. Louis County</supplinf></descript><keywords><place><placekey>Saint Louis County (Minn.)</placekey></place><theme><themekt>ISO 19115</themekt><themekey>environment, inlandWaters, location</themekey></theme></keywords><crossref><citeinfo><title>ENVIRO_RiversWide, ENVIRO_Streams, ENVIRO_Lakes</title></citeinfo></crossref></idinfo><spdoinfo><direct>Vector</direct><ptvctinf><sdtsterm><sdtstype>GT-polygon composed of chains</sdtstype><ptvctcnt>7383</ptvctcnt></sdtsterm></ptvctinf></spdoinfo><spref><horizsys><planar><mapproj><mapprojn>NAD 1983 UTM Zone 15N</mapprojn><transmer><sfctrmer>0.9996</sfctrmer><longcm>-93.0</longcm><latprjo>0.0</latprjo><feast>500000.0</feast><fnorth>0.0</fnorth></transmer></mapproj><planci><plance>coordinate pair</plance><coordrep><absres>0.000000002220024164500956</absres><ordres>0.000000002220024164500956</ordres></coordrep><plandu>meter</plandu></planci></planar><geodetic><horizdn>D North American 1983</horizdn><ellips>GRS 1980</ellips><semiaxis>6378137.0</semiaxis><denflat>298.257222101</denflat></geodetic></horizsys></spref><eainfo><detailed><enttyp><enttypl>SLC_ENVIRO_Lakes</enttypl></enttyp><attr><attrlabl>Shape</attrlabl><attrdef>Feature geometry.</attrdef><attrdefs>ESRI</attrdefs><attrdomv><udom>Coordinates defining the features.</udom></attrdomv></attr><attr><attrlabl>ComID</attrlabl></attr><attr><attrlabl>FDate</attrlabl></attr><attr><attrlabl>Resolution</attrlabl></attr><attr><attrlabl>GNIS_ID</attrlabl></attr><attr><attrlabl>GNIS_Name</attrlabl></attr><attr><attrlabl>FID</attrlabl><attrdef>Internal feature number.</attrdef><attrdefs>ESRI</attrdefs><attrdomv><udom>Sequential unique whole numbers that are automatically generated.</udom></attrdomv></attr><attr><attrlabl>AreaSqKm</attrlabl></attr><attr><attrlabl>Elevation</attrlabl></attr><attr><attrlabl>ReachCode</attrlabl></attr><attr><attrlabl>FType</attrlabl></attr><attr><attrlabl>FCode</attrlabl></attr><attr><attrlabl>DOWLKNUM</attrlabl></attr><attr><attrlabl>EZLKNUM</attrlabl></attr><attr><attrlabl>PWICLASS</attrlabl></attr><attr><attrlabl>CLASS</attrlabl></attr><attr><attrlabl>WB_DESC</attrlabl></attr><attr><attrlabl>Shape_area</attrlabl><attrdef>Area of feature in internal units squared.</attrdef><attrdefs>ESRI</attrdefs><attrdomv><udom>Positive real numbers that are automatically generated.</udom></attrdomv></attr><attr><attrlabl>Shape_len</attrlabl></attr></detailed><detailed><enttyp><enttypl>NHDWaterbodyToMeta</enttypl></enttyp></detailed><overview><eaover>The National Hydrography Dataset is a comprehensive set of digital spatial data that encodes information about naturally occurring and constructed bodies of water, paths through which water flows, and related entities.  The information encoded about features includes a feature date, classification by type, other characteristics, a unique common identifier, the feature length or area, and (rarely) elevation of the surface of water pools and a description of the stage of the elevation.  For reaches, encoded information includes a reach code.  Names and their identifiers in the Geographic Names Information System, are assigned to most feature types.  The direction of flow is encoded for networked features.  The data also contains relations that encode metadata, and information that supports the exchange of future updates and improvements to the data.  The names and  definitions of all feature types, characteristics, and values are in the Standards for National Hydrography Dataset:  Reston, Virginia, U.S. Geological Survey, 1999.  The document is available online through http://mapping.usgs.gov/standards/.</eaover><eadetcit>The names and definitions of all feature types, characteristics, and values are in U.S. Geological Survey, 1999, Standards for National Hydrography Dataset High Resolution:  Reston, Virginia, U.S. Geological Survey.  The document is available online through http://mapping.usgs.gov/standards/.  Information about tables and fields in the data are available from the user documentation for the National Hydrography Dataset at http://nhd.usgs.gov.  The National Map - Hydrography Fact Sheet is also available at: http://erg.usgs.gov/isb/pubs/factsheets/fs06002.html.</eadetcit></overview></eainfo><distinfo><distliab>St. Louis County makes no representation or warranties, express or implied, with respect to the use or reuse of data provided herewith, regardless of its format or the means of its transmission. THE DATA IS PROVIDED "AS IS" WITH NO GUARANTEE OR REPRESENTATION ABOUT THE ACCURACY, CURRENCY, SUITABILITY, PERFORMANCE, MERCHANTABILITY, RELIABILITY OR FITNESS OF THIS DATA FOR ANY PARTICULAR PURPOSE. St. Louis County shall not be liable for any direct, indirect, special, incidental, compensatory or consequential damages or third party claims resulting from the use of these data, even if St. Louis County has been advised of the possibility of such potential loss or damage. This data may not be used in states that do not allow the exclusion or limitation of incidental or consequential damages.</distliab><stdorder><digform><digtinfo><formname>SDE Feature Class</formname></digtinfo><digtopt /></digform></stdorder></distinfo><metainfo><metd>20150827</metd><metstdn>Minnesota Geographic Metadata Guidelines</metstdn><metstdv>1.2</metstdv><mettc>local time</mettc><metextns><onlink>http://www.mngeo.state.mn.us/committee/standards/mgmg/metadata.htm</onlink></metextns></metainfo></metadata>