<?xml version="1.0"?><metadata><idinfo><citation><citeinfo><title>CDSTL_HistoryAnno1200</title><pubinfo><publish>Ramsey County Enterprise GIS</publish></pubinfo><pubdate>20140212</pubdate><origin>Ramsey County</origin><onlink>http://www.co.ramsey.mn.us/is/gisdata.htm</onlink></citeinfo></citation><descript><abstract>HistoryAnno1200 contains textual descriptive information about parcel features.  In 1986, the annotation data layer was created from hand drawn 1:2400 half and 1:1200 quarter section maps.  In 1995, the textual information was converted to an ArcINFO annotation class and held in the ArcStrom data base.  The annotation data layer was converted in 2005 to an ESRI ArcGIS GeoDatabase.  

Within the ArcInfo annotation class there were three subclasses.  The "parcel" subclass contains information about parcels that was  gathered from plats, Registered Land Surveys (RLSs) and other recorded documents; it contains text items such as lot and block numbers, plat names and parcel identifiers.  The "road" subclass contains public road names, generally classified as Federal, State, County or Municipal road names.  The "water" subclass contains text items for lakes, rivers and creeks.

With the conversion to an ArcGIS GeoDatabase, the ArcINFO subclasses were further divided.  HistoryAnno1200 includes old or vacated text from the three original subclasses.</abstract><purpose>The annotation data set is primarily utilized for map creation. 

Text features contained within this data set add value to visual presentations making underlying data easier to interpret and understand.  Features held in this database are utilized in the automated creation of half and quarter section maps.</purpose><supplinf>Ramsey County</supplinf></descript><status><progress>Complete</progress><update>Monthly</update></status><spdom><bounding><westbc>-93.228202</westbc><eastbc>-92.982974 </eastbc><northbc>45.124277</northbc><southbc>44.890922</southbc></bounding></spdom><keywords><theme><themekey>Annotation, text, subclass, road, transportation, parcel, water</themekey></theme></keywords><accconst>None.</accconst><useconst>None. Please check sources, scale, accuracy, currentness and other available information. Please confirm that you are using the most recent copy of both data and metadata.  Acknowledgement of the publisher would be appreciated.</useconst><timeperd><timeinfo><sngdate><caldate>20140219</caldate></sngdate></timeinfo><current>Data set is current and complete, but constantly being update to reflect changes.  New versions are released monthly.</current></timeperd><ptcontac><cntinfo><cntperp><cntorg>Ramsey County</cntorg><cntper>Matt Koukol</cntper></cntperp><cntpos>GIS Manager</cntpos><cntaddr><address>121 7th Place E</address><address>Suite 2300</address><city>Saint Paul</city><state>MN</state><postal>55101</postal></cntaddr><cntvoice>651.266.3463</cntvoice><cntemail>RCGISMetaData@co.ramsey.mn.us</cntemail></cntinfo></ptcontac></idinfo><distinfo><distliab>EXCEPT AS EXPRESSLY STATED HEREIN, THIS DATA IS PROVIDED AS IS WITHOUT WARRANTY OF ANY KIND, EXPRESS OR IMPLIED, INCLUDING, BUT NOT LIMITED TO, WARRANTIES OF MERCHANTABILITY OR FITNESS FOR A PARTICULAR PURPOSE. USER BEARS ANY AND ALL RISK RELATING TO QUALITY AND PERFORMANCE OF THIS DATA. 
Limit on Liability:  This data is not a legally recorded map or survey and is not intended to be used as one. This data is a compilation of records and information from various state, county, and city offices, and other sources, and should be used for reference only.
In no event will the County of Ramsey be liable for direct, indirect, special, incidental, or consequential damages arising out of the use of, or inability to use, the data, even if advised of the possibility of such damages.  Specifically, the County of Ramsey is not responsible for any costs including, but not limited to, those incurred as a result of lost profits or revenue, loss of use of data, the costs of recovering such programs or data, the cost of any substitute programs or data, claims by third parties, or for other similar costs.</distliab><resdesc>ISvSQL55.GISWarehouse.Cadastral.CDSTL_HistoryAnno1200</resdesc><distrib><cntinfo><cntperp><cntorg>Ramsey County</cntorg><cntper>Matt Koukol</cntper></cntperp><cntpos>GIS Manager</cntpos><cntaddr><address>121 7th Place E</address><address>Suite 2300</address><city>Saint Paul</city><state>MN</state><postal>55101</postal></cntaddr><cntvoice>651.266.3463</cntvoice><cntemail>RCGISMetaData@co.ramsey.mn.us</cntemail></cntinfo></distrib></distinfo><metainfo><metd>20140219</metd><metstdn>Minnesota Geographic Metadata Guidelines</metstdn><metstdv>1.2</metstdv><metextns><onlink>http://www.mngeo.state.mn.us/committee/standards/mgmg/metadata.htm</onlink></metextns><metc><cntinfo><cntperp><cntorg>Ramsey County</cntorg><cntper>Matt Koukol</cntper></cntperp><cntpos>GIS Manager</cntpos><cntaddr><address>121 7th Place E</address><address>Suite 2300</address><city>Saint Paul</city><state>MN</state><postal>55101</postal></cntaddr><cntvoice>651.266.3463</cntvoice><cntemail>RCGISMetaData@co.ramsey.mn.us</cntemail></cntinfo></metc></metainfo><spref><horizsys><planar><gridsys><gridsysn>Ramsey County Custom Coordinate</gridsysn></gridsys><planci><plandu>feet</plandu></planci></planar><geodetic><horizdn>NAD83</horizdn><ellips>GRS80</ellips></geodetic></horizsys></spref><eainfo><detailed><enttyp><enttypl>HistoryAnno1200</enttypl></enttyp><attr><attrlabl>AnnotationClassID</attrlabl><attrdef>Type of Annotation</attrdef><attrdomv><edom><edomv>Old_Road</edomv><edomvd>Historical Road Text</edomvd></edom></attrdomv><attrdomv><edom><edomv>Old_Text</edomv><edomvd>Misc. Historical Text</edomvd></edom></attrdomv><attrdomv><edom><edomv>Old_Water</edomv><edomvd>Historical Water Text</edomvd></edom></attrdomv><attrdomv><edom><edomv>Vacated_Road</edomv><edomvd>Vacated Road Text</edomvd></edom></attrdomv><attrdomv><edom><edomv>Vacated_Text</edomv><edomvd>Misc. Text Assocated with Vacated Feature</edomvd></edom></attrdomv></attr><attr><attrlabl>TextString</attrlabl><attrdef>The text associated with the location</attrdef></attr></detailed></eainfo><dataqual><posacc><horizpa><horizpar>NA</horizpar></horizpa><vertacc><vertaccr>NA
</vertaccr></vertacc></posacc><attracc><attraccr>Feature attributes are identified using analytical and softcopy photogrammetric compilation methods.  Automated GIS processes supplement the photo identified feature attributing with the numerical parameters.</attraccr></attracc><complete>Entire Ramsey County coverage</complete><lineage><procstep>This layer contains a vector representation of bridges and overpasses.  Color aerial photography and airborne GPS used for aerotriangulation.  Aerotrianglution solution used with analytical and softcopy stereo plotters to collect limited planimetric feature.  LIDAR DEM provide by Ramsey County under separate contract with Waggoner Inc. of Jackson, Mississippi was used to create digital ortho images.
 
 
</procstep></lineage></dataqual></metadata>