<metadata>
  <idinfo>
    <citation>
      <citeinfo>
        <title>ENVIR_SSURGO</title>
        <pubinfo>
          <publish>Ramsey County Enterprise GIS</publish>
        </pubinfo>
        <pubdate>20140924</pubdate>
        <origin>Ramsey County</origin>
        <onlink>http://www.co.ramsey.mn.us/is/gisdata.htm</onlink>
      </citeinfo>
    </citation>
    <descript>
      <abstract>This dataset soil polygons in Ramsey County, as developed from the National Cooperative Soil Survey's Soil Survey Geographic Database (SSURGO).  This data is not intended to be used for detailed engineering or survey work, but is meant to provide a high level overview of soil types in Ramsey County.</abstract>
      <purpose>This data set is an extract of data fields from the digital soil survey and generally is the most detailed level of soil geographic data developed by the National Cooperative Soil Survey. The information was prepared by digitizing maps, by compiling information onto a planimetric correct base and digitizing, or by revising digitized maps using remotely sensed and other information. This data set consists of georeferenced digital map data and computerized attribute data. The map data are in a 7.5-minute quadrangle format and include a detailed, field verified inventory of soils and nonsoil areas that normally occur in a repeatable pattern on the landscape and that can be cartographically shown at the scale mapped. In this data set, selected fields have been appended to the basic Map Units from tables in the SSURGO relational database including mapunit, comp, chorizon, and ctexgrp.</purpose>
      <supplinf>Ramsey County</supplinf>
    </descript>
    <status>
      <progress>Complete</progress>
      <update>None Planned</update>
    </status>
    <spdom>
      <bounding>
        <westbc>-93.228202</westbc>
        <eastbc>-92.982974 </eastbc>
        <northbc>45.124277</northbc>
        <southbc>44.890922</southbc>
      </bounding>
    </spdom>
    <keywords>
      <theme>
        <themekey>SSURGO; Environment; Soils; Soil Survey</themekey>
      </theme>
    </keywords>
    <accconst>None.</accconst>
    <useconst>None. Please check sources, scale, accuracy, currentness and other available information. Please confirm that you are using the most recent copy of both data and metadata.  Acknowledgement of the publisher would be appreciated.</useconst>
    <timeperd>
      <timeinfo>
        <sngdate>
          <caldate>20140212</caldate>
        </sngdate>
      </timeinfo>
      <current>Data is not expected to be updated.</current>
    </timeperd>
    <ptcontac>
      <cntinfo>
        <cntperp>
          <cntorg>Ramsey County</cntorg>
          <cntper>Matt Koukol</cntper>
        </cntperp>
        <cntpos>GIS Manager</cntpos>
        <cntaddr>
          <address>121 7th Place E</address>
          <address>Suite 2300</address>
          <city>Saint Paul</city>
          <state>MN</state>
          <postal>55101</postal>
        </cntaddr>
        <cntvoice>651.266.3463</cntvoice>
        <cntemail>RCGISMetaData@co.ramsey.mn.us</cntemail>
      </cntinfo>
    </ptcontac>
  </idinfo>
  <distinfo>
    <distliab>EXCEPT AS EXPRESSLY STATED HEREIN, THIS DATA IS PROVIDED AS IS WITHOUT WARRANTY OF ANY KIND, EXPRESS OR IMPLIED, INCLUDING, BUT NOT LIMITED TO, WARRANTIES OF MERCHANTABILITY OR FITNESS FOR A PARTICULAR PURPOSE. USER BEARS ANY AND ALL RISK RELATING TO QUALITY AND PERFORMANCE OF THIS DATA. 
Limit on Liability:  This data is not a legally recorded map or survey and is not intended to be used as one. This data is a compilation of records and information from various state, county, and city offices, and other sources, and should be used for reference only.
In no event will the County of Ramsey be liable for direct, indirect, special, incidental, or consequential damages arising out of the use of, or inability to use, the data, even if advised of the possibility of such damages.  Specifically, the County of Ramsey is not responsible for any costs including, but not limited to, those incurred as a result of lost profits or revenue, loss of use of data, the costs of recovering such programs or data, the cost of any substitute programs or data, claims by third parties, or for other similar costs.</distliab>
    <resdesc>ISvSQL55.GISWarehouse.PhysicalEnvironment.ENVIR_SSURGO</resdesc>
    <distrib>
      <cntinfo>
        <cntperp>
          <cntorg>Ramsey County</cntorg>
          <cntper>Matt Koukol</cntper>
        </cntperp>
        <cntpos>GIS Manager</cntpos>
        <cntaddr>
          <address>121 7th Place E</address>
          <address>Suite 2300</address>
          <city>Saint Paul</city>
          <state>MN</state>
          <postal>55101</postal>
        </cntaddr>
        <cntvoice>651.266.3463</cntvoice>
        <cntemail>RCGISMetaData@co.ramsey.mn.us</cntemail>
      </cntinfo>
    </distrib>
  </distinfo>
  <metainfo>
    <metd>20140924</metd>
    <metstdn>Minnesota Geographic Metadata Guidelines</metstdn>
    <metstdv>1.2</metstdv>
    <metextns>
      <onlink>http://www.mngeo.state.mn.us/committee/standards/mgmg/metadata.htm</onlink>
    </metextns>
    <metc>
      <cntinfo>
        <cntperp>
          <cntorg>Ramsey County</cntorg>
          <cntper>Matt Koukol</cntper>
        </cntperp>
        <cntpos>GIS Manager</cntpos>
        <cntaddr>
          <address>121 7th Place E</address>
          <address>Suite 2300</address>
          <city>Saint Paul</city>
          <state>MN</state>
          <postal>55101</postal>
        </cntaddr>
        <cntvoice>651.266.3463</cntvoice>
        <cntemail>RCGISMetaData@co.ramsey.mn.us</cntemail>
      </cntinfo>
    </metc>
  </metainfo>
  <spref>
    <horizsys>
      <planar>
        <gridsys>
          <gridsysn>Ramsey County Custom Coordinate</gridsysn>
        </gridsys>
        <planci>
          <plandu>feet</plandu>
        </planci>
      </planar>
      <geodetic>
        <horizdn>NAD83</horizdn>
        <ellips>GRS80</ellips>
      </geodetic>
    </horizsys>
  </spref>
  <eainfo>
    <detailed>
      <enttyp>
        <enttypl>new_entity</enttypl>
      </enttyp>
    </detailed>
    <detailed>
      <enttyp>
        <enttypl>ENVIR_SSURGO</enttypl>
      </enttyp>
      <attr>
        <attrlabl>mukey</attrlabl>
        <attrdef>MapUnit Key</attrdef>
      </attr>
      <attr>
        <attrlabl>muname</attrlabl>
        <attrdef>MapUnit Name</attrdef>
      </attr>
      <attr>
        <attrlabl>mukind</attrlabl>
        <attrdef>MapUnit Kind</attrdef>
        <attrdomv>
          <edom>
            <edomv>Association</edomv>
            <edomvd>Association</edomvd>
          </edom>
        </attrdomv>
        <attrdomv>
          <edom>
            <edomv>Complex</edomv>
            <edomvd>Complex</edomvd>
          </edom>
        </attrdomv>
        <attrdomv>
          <edom>
            <edomv>Consociation</edomv>
            <edomvd>Consociation</edomvd>
          </edom>
        </attrdomv>
        <attrdomv>
          <edom>
            <edomv>Undifferntiated</edomv>
            <edomvd>Undifferntiated Group</edomvd>
          </edom>
        </attrdomv>
      </attr>
      <attr>
        <attrlabl>cokey</attrlabl>
        <attrdef>Component Key</attrdef>
      </attr>
      <attr>
        <attrlabl>compname</attrlabl>
        <attrdef>Component Name</attrdef>
      </attr>
      <attr>
        <attrlabl>comppct_r</attrlabl>
        <attrdef>Component Percent of Map Unit</attrdef>
      </attr>
      <attr>
        <attrlabl>hydricrating</attrlabl>
        <attrdef>Is the component hydric?</attrdef>
      </attr>
      <attr>
        <attrlabl>geomdesc</attrlabl>
        <attrdef>Geomorphic Description</attrdef>
      </attr>
      <attr>
        <attrlabl>hydgrp</attrlabl>
        <attrdef>Hydrological Group</attrdef>
        <attrdomv>
          <edom>
            <edomv>A</edomv>
            <edomvd>Soils in this group have low runoff potential when thoroughly wet. Water is transmitted freely through the soil.</edomvd>
          </edom>
        </attrdomv>
        <attrdomv>
          <edom>
            <edomv>B</edomv>
            <edomvd>Soils in this group have moderately low runoff potential when thoroughly wet. Water transmission through the soil is unimpeded.</edomvd>
          </edom>
        </attrdomv>
        <attrdomv>
          <edom>
            <edomv>C</edomv>
            <edomvd>Soils in this group have moderately high runoff potential when thoroughly wet. Water transmission through the soil is somewhat restricted.</edomvd>
          </edom>
        </attrdomv>
        <attrdomv>
          <edom>
            <edomv>D</edomv>
            <edomvd>Soils in this group have high runoff potential when thoroughly wet. Water movement through the soil is restricted or very restricted.</edomvd>
          </edom>
        </attrdomv>
        <attrdomv>
          <edom>
            <edomv>A/D</edomv>
            <edomvd>These soils have low runoff potential when drained and high runoff potential when undrained.</edomvd>
          </edom>
        </attrdomv>
        <attrdomv>
          <edom>
            <edomv>B/D</edomv>
            <edomvd>These soils have moderately low runoff potential when drained and high runoff potential when undrained.</edomvd>
          </edom>
        </attrdomv>
        <attrdomv>
          <edom>
            <edomv>C/D</edomv>
            <edomvd>These soils have moderately high runoff potential when drained and high runoff potential when undrained.</edomvd>
          </edom>
        </attrdomv>
      </attr>
      <attr>
        <attrlabl>chkey</attrlabl>
        <attrdef>Component Horizon Key</attrdef>
      </attr>
      <attr>
        <attrlabl>kffact</attrlabl>
        <attrdef>An erodibility factor which quantifies the susceptibility of soil particles to detachment by water.</attrdef>
      </attr>
      <attr>
        <attrlabl>chtgkey</attrlabl>
        <attrdef>Component Horizon Texture Group Key</attrdef>
      </attr>
      <attr>
        <attrlabl>texture</attrlabl>
        <attrdef>Texture Mod &amp; Class</attrdef>
      </attr>
      <attr>
        <attrlabl>texdesc</attrlabl>
        <attrdef>Texture Description</attrdef>
      </attr>
    </detailed>
  </eainfo>
  <dataqual>
    <posacc>
      <horizpa>
        <horizpar>The accuracy of these digital data is based upon their compilation to base maps that meet National Map Accuracy Standards at a scale of 1 inch equals 1,000 feet. The difference in positional accuracy between the soil boundaries and special soil features locations in the field and their digitized map locations is unknown. The locational accuracy of soil delineations on the ground varies with the transition between map units.    For example, on long gently sloping landscapes the transition occurs gradually over many feet. Where landscapes change abruptly from steep to level, the transition will be very narrow. Soil delineation boundaries and special soil features generally were digitized within 0.01 inch of their locations on the digitizing source. The digital map elements are edge matched between data sets. The data along each quadrangle edge are matched against the data for the adjacent quadrangle. Edge locations generally do not deviate from centerline to centerline by more than 0.01 inch.</horizpar>
      </horizpa>
    </posacc>
    <attracc>
      <attraccr>Attribute accuracy is tested by manual comparison of the source with hard copy plots and/or symbolized display of the map data on an interactive computer graphic system.  Selected attributes that cannot be visually verified on plots or on screen are interactively queried and verified on screen. In       addition, the attributes are tested against a master set of valid attributes. All attribute data conform to the attribute codes in the signed classification and correlation document and amendment(s).</attraccr>
    </attracc>
    <complete>A map unit is a collection of areas defined and named in terms of their soil components or miscellaneous areas or both. Each map unit differs in some respect from all others in a survey area and each map unit has a symbol that uniquely identifies the map unit on a soil map. Each individual area, point, or line so identified on the map is a delineation.  Soil Scientists identify small areas of soils or miscellaneous areas that have properties and behavior significantly different than the named soils in the surrounding map unit. These minor components may be indicated as special features. If they have a minimal effect on use and management, or could not be precisely located, they may not be indicated on the map.    A map unit has specified kinds of soils or miscellaneous areas (map unit components), each with a designated range in proportionate extent. Map units include one or more kinds of soil or miscellaneous area. Miscellaneous areas are areas that have little or no recognizable soil.  Specific National Cooperative Soil Survey standards and procedures were used in the classification of soils, design and name of map units, and location of special soil features. These standards are outlined in Agricultural Handbook 18, Soil Survey Manual, 1993, USDA, NRCS; Agricultural Handbook 436, Soil Taxonomy, 1995, USDA, NRCS; and all Amendments; Keys to Soil Taxonomy, (current issue) USDA, NRCS; National Soil Survey Handbook, title 430-VI,(current issue) USDA, NRCS.  The actual composition and interpretive purity of the map unit delineations were based on data collected by scientists during the course of preparing the soil maps. Adherence to National Cooperative Soil Survey standards and procedures is based on peer review, quality control, and quality assurance. Quality control is outlined in the memorandum of understanding for the soil survey area and in documents that reside with the Natural Resources Conservation Service state soil scientist. Four kinds of map units are used in soil surveys: consociations, complexes, associations, and undifferentiated groups.      Consociations - Consociations are named for the dominant soil. In a consociation, delineated areas use a single name from the dominant component in the map unit. Dissimilar components are     minor in extent. The soil component in a consociation may be identified at any taxonomic level. Soil series is the lowest     taxonomic level. A consociation that is named as a miscellaneous area is dominantly that kind of area and minor components do not significantly affect the of the map unit. The total amount of dissimilar inclusions of other components in a map unit generally does not exceed about 15 percent if limiting and 25 percent if nonlimiting. A single component of a dissimilar limiting inclusion generally does not exceed 10 percent if very contrasting. Complexes and associations - Complexes and associations consist of two or mor  dissimilar components that occur in a regularly repeating pattern. The total amount of other dissimilar components is minor extent. The following arbitrary rule determines whether complex or association is used in the name. The major components of an association can be separated at the scale of mapping. In either case, because the major components are sufficiently different in morphology or behavior, the map unit cannot be called a consociation. In each delineation of a complex or an association, each major component is normally present though their proportions may vary appreciably from one delineation to another. The total amount of inclusions in a map unit that are dissimilar to any of the major components does not exceed 15 percent if limiting and     25 percent if nonlimiting. A single kind of dissimilar limiting inclusion usually does not exceed 10 percent.      Undifferentiated groups - Undifferentiated groups consist of two or more components that are not consistently associated     geographically and, therefore, do not always occur together in the same map delineation. These components are included in the same named map unit because their use and management are the same or very similar for common uses. Generally they are grouped together because some common feature, such as steepness, stoniness, or flooding, determines their use and management. If two or more additional map units would serve no useful purpose, they may be included in the same unit. Each delineation has at least one of the major components, and some may have all of them. The same principles regarding the proportion of minor components that apply to consociations also apply to undifferentiated groups. The same principles regarding proportion of inclusion apply to undifferentiated groups as to consociations. The survey is a subset of MLRA 90B, 91A, and 91B. Profile descriptions and transects from the entire MLRA supplement documentation from within the subset. Minimum documentation consists of three or more complete soil profile descriptions for each series added to the legend. In addition, transects were recorded as needed to support correlation decisions. The number of stops in each transect was dependent on the size of the particular map unit and the soil properties involved.  A defined standard or level of confidence in the interpretive     purity of the map unit delineations is attained by adjusting the kind and intensity of field investigations. Field investigations and data collection are carried out in sufficient detail to name map units and to identify accurately and consistently areas of about 2 acres.</complete>
    <lineage>
      <procstep>This layer contains a vector representation of bridges and overpasses.  Color aerial photography and airborne GPS used for aerotriangulation.  Aerotrianglution solution used with analytical and softcopy stereo plotters to collect limited planimetric feature.  LIDAR DEM provide by Ramsey County under separate contract with Waggoner Inc. of Jackson, Mississippi was used to create digital ortho images.
 
 
<procdesc>SSURGO database for Ramsey County was downloaded from USDA's Natural Resource Conservation Service Soil's web site.  MapUnit polygons were joined with the following tables in sequence: mapunits, comp, chorizon, texgrp.  The results were exported to a Featureclass and the unwanted fields were removed.  The featureclass was then imported into a featuredataset in the Ramsey County Projection. </procdesc></procstep>
    </lineage>
  </dataqual>
</metadata>
