<metadata>
  <idinfo>
    <citation>
      <citeinfo>
        <title>MCES Rain Gauge Sites</title>
        <origin>Metropolitan Council</origin>
        <pubinfo>
          <publish>Metropolitan Council</publish>
        </pubinfo>
        <pubdate>periodically revised</pubdate>
        <onlink>https://gisdata.mn.gov/dataset/us-mn-state-metc-env-mces-rain-gauge-sites</onlink>
      </citeinfo>
    </citation>
    <descript>
      <abstract>This layer contains point locations for each of the Metropolitan Council's rain gauge sites (existing and previous).</abstract>
      <purpose>To show the general location of rain gauge sites.</purpose>
      <supplinf>East-central Minnesota.  Coverage is primarily centered on Twin Cities Metropolitan Area, but the coverage also includes MCES monitoring sites in the Minnesota River Watershed near Mankato and sites along the Mississippi River down to Lake Pepin.</supplinf>
    </descript>
    <timeperd>
      <timeinfo>
        <sngdate>
          <caldate>20070213</caldate>
        </sngdate>
      </timeinfo>
      <current>Dataset shows all rain gauge sites, historical and active, as of the Time Period of Content date.</current>
    </timeperd>
    <status>
      <progress>Complete</progress>
      <update>As needed</update>
    </status>
    <spdom>
      <bounding>
        <westbc>-94.22</westbc>
        <eastbc>-92.10</eastbc>
        <northbc>45.42</northbc>
        <southbc>43.99</southbc>
      </bounding>
    </spdom>
    <keywords>
      <place>
        <placekey>Minnesota, Twin Cities, Mississippi River, Minnesota River, St. Croix River, Anoka County, Carver County, Dakota County, Hennepin County, Ramsey County, Scott County, Washington County</placekey>
      </place>
      <theme>
        <themekey>rain, water resources
rain gauge
precipitation</themekey>
        <themekt>None</themekt>
      </theme>
    </keywords>
    <accconst>None</accconst>
    <useconst>None</useconst>
    <browse>
      <browsen>ftp://ftp.gisdata.mn.gov/pub/gdrs/data/pub/us_mn_state_metc/env_mces_rain_gauge_sites/metadata/preview.jpg</browsen>
      <browsed>Sample map showing the MCES Rain Gauge Sites layer.</browsed>
    </browse>
    <native>ArcGIS 9x</native>
    <ptcontac>
      <cntinfo>
        <cntperp>
          <cntorg>Metropolitan Council</cntorg>
          <cntper>Lori Sand</cntper>
        </cntperp>
        <cntpos>Environmental Services Division</cntpos>
        <cntaddr>
          <address>3565 Kennebec Drive</address>
          <city>Eagan</city>
          <state>MN</state>
          <postal>55122</postal>
          <addrtype>mailing and physical</addrtype>
        </cntaddr>
        <cntvoice>651.602.4516</cntvoice>
        <cntemail>lori.sand@metc.state.mn.us</cntemail>
      </cntinfo>
    </ptcontac>
  </idinfo>
  <dataqual>
    <logic>The dataset is topologically 'clean'.</logic>
    <complete>All Metropolitan Council rain gauge sites are included as of 2/13/2007.</complete>
    <posacc>
      <horizpa>
        <horizpar>Estimated to be 5 meter accuracy.</horizpar>
      </horizpa>
      <vertacc>
        <vertaccr>NA</vertaccr>
      </vertacc>
    </posacc>
    <lineage>
      <procstep>
        <procdesc>Original Publication: 3/21/2002

MCES rain gauges are typically located adjacent to MCES infrastructure elements such as lift stations, interceptor meters, and wastewater treatment plants. Rain gauges were GPSed in 2005 and 2006 using Trimble GeoXT units with 3 ot 5 meter accuracy.</procdesc>
      </procstep>
      <srcinfo>
        <srcscale/>
      </srcinfo>
    </lineage>
  </dataqual>
  <spdoinfo>
    <indspref>None</indspref>
    <direct>Point</direct>
    <mgmg3obj>points</mgmg3obj>
    <mgmg3til>One layer for entire region.</mgmg3til>
  </spdoinfo>
  <spref>
    <horizsys>
      <geodetic>
        <ellips>GRS80</ellips>
        <horizdn>NAD83</horizdn>
      </geodetic>
    </horizsys>
  </spref>
  <eainfo>
    <overview>
      <eaover>SITE_ID:    A unique short code for the rain gauge
 
SITE_NAME:  A short name for the monitoring site.

STATUS:     Status of a rain gauge (Active or Removed)
 
SITE_DESCR: A longer description of the monitoring site.
 
CITY:       The city in which the rain gauge is located.
 
MAJ_NAME:   The name of the major watershed within which the rain gauge is 
            located.
 
SEC_NAME:   The name of the secondary watershed within which the rain gauge is 
            located.

ADDRESS:    Interceptor Services given address for rain gauge.

COUNTY:     County in which the rain gauge is located.

UNIQUE_ID:  7-digit unique number given to some rain gauges to be used for 
            linking to current interceptor_points shapefile. 

MCES_INT:   Closest MCES Interceptor to the rain gauge.

WWTP:       Closest MCES waste water treatment plant to the rain gauge.

GPS:        Was the rain gauge located with GPS equipment? (Y or N)

GPS_X:      The x-coordinate of the monitoring site in UTM, zone 15, NAD 83,




            meters recorded to two decimal places. 

GPS_Y:      The y-coordinate of the monitoring site in UTM, zone 15, NAD 83,
            meters recorded to two decimal places.</eaover>
    </overview>
  </eainfo>
  <distinfo>
    <resdesc>RainGaugeSites</resdesc>
    <distliab>NOTICE:  The Geographic Information System (GIS) Data to which this notice is attached are made available pursuant to the Minnesota Government Data Practices Act (Minnesota Statutes Chapter 13).  THE GIS DATA ARE PROVIDED TO YOU AS IS AND WITHOUT ANY WARRANTY AS TO THEIR PERFORMANCE, MERCHANTABILITY, OR FITNESS FOR ANY PARTICULAR PURPOSE.  The GIS Data were developed by the Metropolitan Council for its own internal business purposes.  The Metropolitan Council does not represent or warrant that the GIS Data or the data documentation are error-free, complete, current, or accurate.  You are responsible for any consequences resulting from your use of the GIS Data or your reliance on the GIS Data.  You should consult the data documentation for this particular GIS Data to determine the limitations of the GIS Data and the precision with which the GIS Data may depict distance, direction, location, or other geographic features.  If you transmit or provide the GIS Data (or any portion of it) to another user, it is recommended that the GIS Data include a copy of this disclaimer and this metadata.</distliab>
    <stdorder>
      <digform>
        <digtinfo>
          <formname>ArcView Shape files</formname>
          <formvern>ArcGIS 9x</formvern>
          <transize>Less than 1 MB for self extractin zip file.</transize>
        </digtinfo>
      </digform>
      <ordering>See Online Linkage Below</ordering>
    </stdorder>
    <distrib>
      <cntinfo>
        <cntperp>
          <cntorg>Metropolitan Council</cntorg>
          <cntper>Jon Hoekenga</cntper>
        </cntperp>
        <cntpos>GIS System Administrator</cntpos>
        <cntaddr>
          <address>390 Robert Street North</address>
          <city>St. Paul</city>
          <state>MN</state>
          <postal>55101-1805</postal>
          <addrtype>mailing and physical</addrtype>
        </cntaddr>
        <cntvoice>651.602.1561</cntvoice>
        <cntemail>jonathan.hoekenga@metc.state.mn.us</cntemail>
      </cntinfo>
    </distrib>
  </distinfo>
  <metainfo>
    <metd>20070213</metd>
    <metstdn>Minnesota Geographic Metadata Guidelines</metstdn>
    <metstdv>1.2</metstdv>
    <metextns>
      <onlink>http://www.mngeo.state.mn.us/committee/standards/mgmg/metadata.htm</onlink>
    </metextns>
    <metc>
      <cntinfo>
        <cntperp>
          <cntorg>Metropolitan Council</cntorg>
          <cntper>Lori Sand</cntper>
        </cntperp>
        <cntpos>Environmental Services Division</cntpos>
        <cntaddr>
          <address>3565 Kennebec Drive</address>
          <city>Eagan</city>
          <state>MN</state>
          <postal>55122</postal>
          <addrtype>mailing and physical</addrtype>
        </cntaddr>
        <cntvoice>651.602.4516</cntvoice>
        <cntemail>lori.sand@metc.state.mn.us</cntemail>
      </cntinfo>
    </metc>
  </metainfo>
  <Esri>
    <ModDate>20110721</ModDate>
    <ModTime>15093600</ModTime>
  </Esri>
  <mdDateSt Sync="TRUE">20110721</mdDateSt>
</metadata>
