<metadata><idinfo><citation><citeinfo><origin>Metropolitan Council</origin><pubdate>20050523</pubdate><title catid="f3fbfb2a-1234-4463-8799-112ac1850d15">Agricultural Preserves 2006</title><pubinfo><publish>Metropolitan Council</publish></pubinfo><onlink>ftp://gisftp.metc.state.mn.us/AgriculturalPreserves2006.zip</onlink></citeinfo></citation><native>ArcGIS 9x</native><descript><abstract>This dataset includes parcels that are enrolled in the Metropolitan Agricultural Preserves Act, Minnesota Statute 473H. The goal of this act is to encourage preservation of agricultural lands by providing a package of benefits to keep land in long-term agricultural use. At the request of the Metropolitan Council, a table is created by each county to reflect the status of parcels in the program at the end of each calendar year. The Council links these tables to the MetroGIS Regional Parcel Dataset to create a shape file of Agricultural Preserves.</abstract><purpose>To track lands involved in the Agricultural Preserves Program</purpose><supplinf>Twin Cities 7 County Metropolitan Area. This includes the counties of Anoka, Carver, Dakota, Hennepin, Ramsey, Scott and Washington in Minnesota.</supplinf></descript><timeperd><current>December 2006</current><timeinfo><sngdate><caldate>2006</caldate></sngdate></timeinfo></timeperd><status><progress>Complete</progress><update>Annually</update></status><spdom><bounding><westbc>-94.022081</westbc><eastbc>-92.749020</eastbc><northbc>45.392369</northbc><southbc>44.467198</southbc></bounding></spdom><keywords><theme><themekey>farming, agriculture, Agricultural Preserves</themekey></theme><place><placekey>Anoka County, Carver County, Dakota County, Hennepin County, Scott County, Washington County</placekey></place></keywords><accconst>None</accconst><useconst>None</useconst><browse><browsen>http://www.datafinder.org/metadata/bg/agricultural_preserves_2006.jpg</browsen><browsed>A sample map of the agricultural preserves 2006 dataset</browsed></browse><crossref><citeinfo><title>Regional Parcel Dataset - Seven County Twin Cities Metropolitan Area http://www.datafinder.org/metadata/metrogis_regional_parcels.htm</title></citeinfo></crossref><ptcontac><cntinfo><cntperp><cntorg>Metropolitan Council</cntorg><cntper>Victoria Dupre</cntper></cntperp><cntaddr><addrtype> mailing and physical address </addrtype><address>390 Robert Street North</address><city>St. Paul</city><state>MN</state><postal>55101</postal></cntaddr><cntvoice>651-602-1621</cntvoice><cntemail>victoria.dupre@metc.state.mn.us</cntemail></cntinfo></ptcontac></idinfo><dataqual><lineage><procstep><procdesc>This dataset includes parcels that are enrolled in the Metropolitan Agricultural Preserves Act, Minnesota Statute 473H. The goal of this act is to encourage preservation of agricultural lands by providing a package of benefits to keep land in long-term agricultural use.

DATA SOURCE
The Metropolitan Council Office of Local Assistance gets data from each county listing parcels enrolled in the Agricultural Preserves program. The Metropolitan Council then creates a shape file showing the parcels involved in the program. Users may relate the tabular data recieved from each county to this metro-wide agricultural preserve parcels layer.

DATA PROCESSING STEPS
In response to the Council request for a list of parcels enrolled in the Agricultural Preserves program, each county sent a list either as a Word document, Excel Spreadsheet or ESRI Shapefile.  We received files from all but Ramsey County, which has no parcels enrolled in the agricultural preserves program.  Each list was moved in to a DBF table and joined to the current (1/1/2007) county parcel database, then matching parcels were exported to a new shape file for each county.  All attributes except for PIN were stripped from the new shapefile and the 6 shape files were APPENDed together using the Geoprocessing Wizard from ArcToolBox.  

We received 2770 PINS listed as enrolled in the agricultural preserves program, 2646 matched (99.1% match) and 24 PINS did not match (2 in Carver Co., 14  in Dakota County, 4 in Hennepin, 3 in Scott County and 1 in Washington).  This shape file can be joined with each of the agricultural preserve DBF tables with the original data provided by each of the counties.  Anoka County = 53 parcels, Carver County = 1136 parcels, Dakota County = 1033 parcels, Hennepin County = 219 parcels, Scott County = 111 parcels, and Washington County = 218 parcels.


ABOUT THE PROGRAM
Before land can be enrolled in the Agricultural Preserves Program, it must meet certification for enrollment eligibility. The local unit of government must adopt a comprehensive plan that designates long-term agricultural land and establishes zoning for those areas at a density of no more than one dwelling unit per forty acres. If all requirements are met, the land is considered certified and eligible for enrollment into the program. The land owner may then enroll the land to receive the program's bennifits. Enrolled lands will have a restrictive covenanat recorded with the property deed. Enrollment status may be indefinite, or may have an expiration date (which must be at least 8 years after the date notice is given by the landowner). When an expiration date is reached, the enrollment status expires and the benefits terminate. At such a time, the landowner must re-enroll the land into the program to continue receiving the program's benefits. All or a portion of a Public Land Survey (PLS) quarter quarter section (forty') may be enrolled in the program but the active enrollment acreage cannot exceed the corresponding certified acreage.'</procdesc></procstep><srcinfo><srcscale /></srcinfo><procstep><procdesc>This dataset includes parcels that are enrolled in the Metropolitan Agricultural Preserves Act, Minnesota Statute 473H. The goal of this act is to encourage preservation of agricultural lands by providing a package of benefits to keep land in long-term agricultural use.

DATA SOURCE
The Metropolitan Council Office of Local Assistance gets data from each county listing parcels enrolled in the Agricultural Preserves program. The Metropolitan Council then creates a shape file showing the parcels involved in the program. Users may relate the tabular data recieved from each county to this metro-wide agricultural preserve parcels layer.

DATA PROCESSING STEPS
In response to the Council request for a list of parcels enrolled in the Agricultural Preserves program, each county sent a list either as a Word document, Excel Spreadsheet or ESRI Shapefile.  We received files from all but Ramsey County, which has no parcels enrolled in the agricultural preserves program.  Each list was moved in to a DBF table and joined to the current (1/1/2007) county parcel database, then matching parcels were exported to a new shape file for each county.  All attributes except for PIN were stripped from the new shapefile and the 6 shape files were APPENDed together using the Geoprocessing Wizard from ArcToolBox.  

We received 2770 PINS listed as enrolled in the agricultural preserves program, 2646 matched (99.1% match) and 24 PINS did not match (2 in Carver Co., 14  in Dakota County, 4 in Hennepin, 3 in Scott County and 1 in Washington).  This shape file can be joined with each of the agricultural preserve DBF tables with the original data provided by each of the counties.  Anoka County = 53 parcels, Carver County = 1136 parcels, Dakota County = 1033 parcels, Hennepin County = 219 parcels, Scott County = 111 parcels, and Washington County = 218 parcels.


ABOUT THE PROGRAM
Before land can be enrolled in the Agricultural Preserves Program, it must meet certification for enrollment eligibility. The local unit of government must adopt a comprehensive plan that designates long-term agricultural land and establishes zoning for those areas at a density of no more than one dwelling unit per forty acres. If all requirements are met, the land is considered certified and eligible for enrollment into the program. The land owner may then enroll the land to receive the program's bennifits. Enrolled lands will have a restrictive covenanat recorded with the property deed. Enrollment status may be indefinite, or may have an expiration date (which must be at least 8 years after the date notice is given by the landowner). When an expiration date is reached, the enrollment status expires and the benefits terminate. At such a time, the landowner must re-enroll the land into the program to continue receiving the program's benefits. All or a portion of a Public Land Survey (PLS) quarter quarter section (forty') may be enrolled in the program but the active enrollment acreage cannot exceed the corresponding certified acreage.'</procdesc><srcused Sync="TRUE">L:\Metadata\Layers\agricultural_preserves_2005</srcused><date Sync="TRUE">20070515</date><time Sync="TRUE">13284200</time></procstep></lineage><complete>Entire seven county geographic area is covered.</complete></dataqual><spdoinfo><direct>Vector</direct><indspref>PIN number</indspref><mgmg3obj>Polygon</mgmg3obj><mgmg3til /></spdoinfo><eainfo><overview><eaover>PIN:   Unique regional parcel ID comprised of the county PIN with the county 
       code and dash appended to the front.</eaover></overview></eainfo><distinfo><resdesc>AgriculturalPreserves2006</resdesc><stdorder><digform><digtinfo><transize>Less than 2MB for ZIP file</transize><formname>Shapefile</formname><formvern>ArcGIS 9x</formvern></digtinfo></digform><ordering>This dataset is distributed on the internet by clicking below after 'Online Linkage'.  Doing so will tell your browser to download a 'ZIP' file which will contain the following:

- ArcView shape files
- metadata for the dataset (.htm)
- NOTICE.RTF, an important notice about this dataset that can be read by any word processing software.

Additionally, this dataset is available for direct use via one or more map services.  More information about what a map service is can be found at http://www.datafinder.org/services/.  The specific map service and layer name for this dataset can be found by clicking the "Services" link for this dataset in the DataFinder Catalog at http://www.datafinder.org/catalog/ .</ordering></stdorder><distliab>NOTICE:  The Geographic Information System (GIS) Data to which this notice is attached are made available pursuant to the Minnesota Government Data Practices Act (Minnesota Statutes Chapter 13).  THE GIS DATA ARE PROVIDED TO YOU AS IS AND WITHOUT ANY WARRANTY AS TO THEIR PERFORMANCE, MERCHANTABILITY, OR FITNESS FOR ANY PARTICULAR PURPOSE.  The GIS Data were developed by the Metropolitan Council for its own internal business purposes.  The Metropolitan Council does not represent or warrant that the GIS Data or the data documentation are error-free, complete, current, or accurate.  You are responsible for any consequences resulting from your use of the GIS Data or your reliance on the GIS Data.  You should consult the data documentation for this particular GIS Data to determine the limitations of the GIS Data and the precision with which the GIS Data may depict distance, direction, location, or other geographic features.  If you transmit or provide the GIS Data (or any portion of it) to another user, it is recommended that the GIS Data include a copy of this disclaimer and this metadata.</distliab><availabl><timeinfo><sngdate><caldate>2006</caldate></sngdate></timeinfo></availabl><distrib><cntinfo><cntperp><cntorg>Metropolitan Council</cntorg><cntper>Mark Kotz</cntper></cntperp><cntpos>GIS Database Administrator</cntpos><cntaddr><addrtype> mailing and physical address </addrtype><address>390 Robert Street North</address><city>St. Paul</city><state>MN</state><postal>55101</postal></cntaddr><cntvoice>651-602-1644</cntvoice><cntemail>mark.kotz@metc.state.mn.us</cntemail></cntinfo></distrib></distinfo><metainfo><metstdn>Minnesota Geographic Metadata Guidelines</metstdn><metstdv>1.2</metstdv><metd>20120315</metd><metextns><onlink>http://www.gis.state.mn.us/stds/metadata.htm</onlink></metextns><metc><cntinfo><cntperp><cntorg>Metropolitan Council</cntorg><cntper>Tanya Mayer</cntper></cntperp><cntpos>GIS Coordinator</cntpos><cntaddr><addrtype> mailing and physical address </addrtype><address>390 Robert Street North</address><city>St. Paul</city><state>MN</state><postal>55101</postal></cntaddr><cntvoice>651-602-1604</cntvoice><cntemail>tanya.mayer@metc.state.mn.us</cntemail></cntinfo></metc></metainfo><Esri><ModDate>20070613</ModDate><ModTime>14570100</ModTime><MetaID>{484A3B21-C218-45EE-A042-73FD4DAEB3DB}</MetaID><CreaDate>20070515</CreaDate><CreaTime>13284200</CreaTime><SyncOnce>TRUE</SyncOnce></Esri><mdDateSt Sync="TRUE">20070613</mdDateSt><distInfo><distributor><distorTran><onLineSrc><linkage Sync="TRUE">file://\\rafs\gis\devel\staff\gu_tanya\Projects\cd\pta\Tori_Dupre\AgPres\Data_2006\2006shape_files\agricultural_preserves_2005</linkage><protocol Sync="TRUE">Local Area Network</protocol></onLineSrc></distorTran></distributor></distInfo><spref><horizsys><planar><gridsys><gridsysn>Universal Transverse Mercator</gridsysn><utm><utmzone>15</utmzone></utm></gridsys><planci><plandu>meters</plandu></planci></planar><geodetic><horizdn>NAD83</horizdn><ellips>GRS80</ellips></geodetic></horizsys></spref></metadata>