<metadata><idinfo><citation><citeinfo><origin>Metropolitan Council</origin><pubdate>2008</pubdate><title catid="cecd89ed-8692-4e80-8537-a1465a238d0a">Airports</title><mgmg1cid>N/A</mgmg1cid><pubinfo><publish>Metropolitan Council</publish></pubinfo><onlink>ftp://gisftp.metc.state.mn.us/Airports.zip</onlink></citeinfo></citation><descript><abstract>This layer attempts to depicts approximate airport ownership boundaries, (not the area actually used for the airport) for the Twin Cities metropolitan area.  For example, MSP includes an area that is a golf course.  Also, as of 3/3/97, boundaries are not up-to-date for MSP, Airlake, Flying Cloud and Anoka County/Blaine.  A point file is also included with one point for each airport.

NOTES:
-  Only airports in the Regional Airport System are included.  Small, private airports are not included.
-  The original airports layer came from the 1990 land use data.  Then modifications were made to include approximate airport ownership boundaries.  This additonal boundary information was digitized from county plat maps and comprehensive plans.  The MSP boundary was digitized from the Airport Layout Plan (ALP).</abstract><purpose>General metro-wide airport and transportation planning.</purpose><supplinf>Twin Cities 7 County Metropolitan Area.  This includes the counties of Anoka, Carver, Dakota, Hennepin, Ramsey, Scott and Washington in Minnesota.</supplinf></descript><timeperd><timeinfo><sngdate><caldate>1996</caldate></sngdate></timeinfo><current>The last update to this layer was 1996, although boundary information may not be up to date as of that year.</current></timeperd><status><progress>Complete</progress><update>Irregular</update></status><spdom><bounding><westbc>-94.012</westbc><eastbc>-92.732</eastbc><northbc>45.415</northbc><southbc>44.471</southbc></bounding></spdom><keywords><theme><themekt>None</themekt><themekey>Airports, Transportation, Regional Airport System</themekey></theme><place><placekey>Twin Cities, Anoka County, Carver County, Dakota County, Hennepin County, Ramsey County, Scott County, Washington County</placekey></place></keywords><accconst>None</accconst><useconst>None</useconst><browse><browsen>None available</browsen><browsed>Sample map showing the airports layer.</browsed></browse><native>ArcGIS 10x</native><ptcontac><cntinfo><cntperp><cntorg>Metropolitan Council</cntorg></cntperp><cntaddr><addrtype> mailing and physical address </addrtype><address>390 Robert Street North</address><city>St. Paul</city><state>Minnesota</state><postal>55101-1805</postal></cntaddr></cntinfo></ptcontac></idinfo><dataqual><complete>Entire seven county geographic area is covered.</complete><posacc><horizpa><horizpar>The positional accuracy of the dataset is UNKNOWN.</horizpar></horizpa></posacc><lineage><srcinfo><srcscale /></srcinfo><procstep><procdesc>Only airports in the Regional Airport System are included.  Small, private airports are not included nor is the former international airport search area.  That information can be found in the airpts-oth layer.

The original airports layer came from the land use data.  Then modifications were made to include actual airport ownership boundaries.  This additonal boundary information was digitized from county plat maps and comprehensive plans.  The MSP boundary was digitized from the Airport Layout Plan (ALP).</procdesc></procstep></lineage></dataqual><spdoinfo><indspref>None</indspref><direct>Vector</direct><mgmg3obj>arcs, nodes, polygons, label points</mgmg3obj><mgmg3til>One layer for entire seven county region.</mgmg3til></spdoinfo><eainfo><overview><eaover>Polygons and Point Attributes:
 
APNAME:  airport name
APABRV:  official 3 character airport abbreviation, if applicable
APCLASS: airport classification (e.g. major, minor, special purpose)</eaover><eadetcit>None</eadetcit></overview></eainfo><distinfo><resdesc>Airports</resdesc><distliab>NOTICE:  The Geographic Information System (GIS) Data to which this notice is attached are made available pursuant to the Minnesota Government Data Practices Act (Minnesota Statutes Chapter 13).  THE GIS DATA ARE PROVIDED TO YOU AS IS AND WITHOUT ANY WARRANTY AS TO THEIR PERFORMANCE, MERCHANTABILITY, OR FITNESS FOR ANY PARTICULAR PURPOSE.  The GIS Data were developed by the Metropolitan Council for its own internal business purposes.  The Metropolitan Council does not represent or warrant that the GIS Data or the data documentation are error-free, complete, current, or accurate.  You are responsible for any consequences resulting from your use of the GIS Data or your reliance on the GIS Data.  You should consult the data documentation for this particular GIS Data to determine the limitations of the GIS Data and the precision with which the GIS Data may depict distance, direction, location, or other geographic features.  If you transmit or provide the GIS Data (or any portion of it) to another user, it is recommended that the GIS Data include a copy of this disclaimer and this metadata.</distliab><stdorder><digform><digtinfo><formname>Shapefile</formname><formvern>ArcGIS 9x</formvern><transize>0.1 meg. for ZIP file.</transize></digtinfo></digform><ordering>This dataset is distributed on the internet by clicking below after 'Online Linkage'.  Doing so will tell your browser to download a 'ZIP' file which will contain the following:

- ArcView shape files
- metadata for the dataset (.htm  and .xml)
- NOTICE.RTF, an important notice about this dataset that can be read by any word processing software.
 
Additionally, this dataset is available for direct use via one or more map services.  More information about what a web mapping service is can be found at http://www.datafinder.org/services/.  The specific map service and layer name for this dataset can be found by clicking the blue or green boxes under the map service column of the DataFinder Catalog at http://www.datafinder.org/catalog/ .</ordering></stdorder><distrib><cntinfo><cntperp><cntorg>Metropolitan Council</cntorg><cntper>Jon Hoekenga</cntper></cntperp><cntpos>GIS System Administrator</cntpos><cntaddr><address>390 Robert Street North</address><city>St. Paul</city><state>MN</state><postal>55101-1805</postal></cntaddr><cntvoice>651.602.1561</cntvoice><cntemail>jonathan.hoekenga@metc.state.mn.us</cntemail></cntinfo></distrib></distinfo><metainfo><metd>20110617</metd><metstdn>Minnesota Geographic Metadata Guidelines</metstdn><metstdv>1.2</metstdv><metextns><onlink>http://www.gis.state.mn.us/stds/metadata.htm</onlink></metextns><metc><cntinfo><cntperp><cntorg>Metropolitan Council</cntorg><cntper>Jon Hoekenga</cntper></cntperp><cntpos>GIS System Administrator</cntpos><cntaddr><address>390 Robert Street North</address><city>St. Paul</city><state>MN</state><postal>55101-1805</postal></cntaddr><cntvoice>651.602.1561</cntvoice><cntemail>jonathan.hoekenga@metc.state.mn.us</cntemail></cntinfo></metc></metainfo><spref><horizsys><planar><gridsys><gridsysn>Universal Transverse Mercator</gridsysn><utm><utmzone>15</utmzone></utm></gridsys><planci><plandu>meters</plandu></planci></planar><geodetic><horizdn>NAD83</horizdn><ellips>GRS80</ellips></geodetic></horizsys></spref></metadata>