<metadata><idinfo><citation><citeinfo><title catid="04cf8ef1-dbe3-43b1-a9a2-7429cb7852f2">Census 2010 Geography - Blocks, Block Groups, Tracts, TAZs, Counties, County Subdivisions and Water</title><origin>U.S. Census Bureau and the Metropolitan Council</origin><pubinfo><publish>Metropolitan Council</publish></pubinfo><pubdate>20110131</pubdate><onlink>ftp://gisftp.metc.state.mn.us/Census2010Tiger.zip</onlink></citeinfo></citation><descript><abstract>This 'Redistricting' version of the census data is the first release of the data.

This 2010 census redistricting geography database of the 7 county metropolitan area and the additional 12 collar county area was developed from the U.S. Census Bureau's Redistricting Census 2010 TIGER/Line files.

The Metropolitan Council downloaded this data from the Census Bureau's FTP site and added a few attributes, then created block, block group, tract, county subdivision (city), county, taz and water datasets from the original data.

For block level data, this is the Census Bureau's March 2012 re-release with additional attributes added by the Met Council.</abstract><purpose>For mapping and analysis of data from the U. S. Census Bureau.</purpose><supplinf>Seven County Twin Cities Metropolitan Area and it's 12 collar counties.</supplinf></descript><timeperd><timeinfo><sngdate><caldate>20100101</caldate></sngdate></timeinfo><current>2010 U.S. Census</current></timeperd><status><progress>Complete</progress><update>None Planned</update></status><spdom><bounding><westbc>-94.664</westbc><eastbc>-92.117</eastbc><northbc>45.736</northbc><southbc>44.183</southbc></bounding></spdom><keywords><place><placekey>Twin Cities, Anoka County, Carver County, Dakota County, Hennepin County, Ramsey County, Scott County, Washington County, Chisago County, Isanti County, Sherburne County, Wright County, McLeod County, Sibley County, Le Sueur County, Rice County, Goodhue County, Pierce County, St. Croix County, Polk County</placekey></place><theme><themekey>census, demographics, census boundaries, 2010 census, blocks, block boundaries, census blocks, census block groups, census tracts, counties, county subdivisions, FIPS Place, MCDs, TAZs, water</themekey></theme></keywords><accconst>None</accconst><useconst>None</useconst><browse><browsen>http://www.datafinder.org/metadata/bg/Census2010Tiger.jpg</browsen><browsed>Sample map showing the census 2010 Tiger datasets</browsed></browse><crossref><citeinfo><title>Census 2010 Redistricting (PL-94-171) Summary File Data (A Subset of Population Data)</title></citeinfo></crossref><native>TIGER; ArcGIS 9.x</native><ptcontac><cntinfo><cntperp><cntorg>Metropolitan Council</cntorg><cntper>Tanya Mayer</cntper></cntperp><cntpos>GIS Coordinator</cntpos><cntaddr><address>390 Robert Street North</address><city>St. Paul</city><state>Minnesota</state><postal>55101</postal></cntaddr><cntvoice>651-602-1604</cntvoice><cntfax>651-602-1674</cntfax><cntemail>tanya.mayer@metc.state.mn.us</cntemail></cntinfo></ptcontac></idinfo><dataqual><attracc><attraccr>Unknown</attraccr></attracc><logic>Each county polygon file is topologically 'clean'.</logic><complete>All counties are included.</complete><posacc><horizpa><horizpar>Presumed to meet source material standards: for 1:100,000-scale mapping, National Map Accuracy Standards state a horizontal positional accuracy of not less than +/- 167 feet for 90% of points tested.</horizpar></horizpa><vertacc><vertaccr>Not applicable</vertaccr></vertacc></posacc><lineage><procstep><procdesc>Data originated at the U.S. Bureau of the Census, as 2010 Census Redistricting TIGER/Line files (01/31/2011).
 
7-County FIPS
27-003  Anoka
27-019  Carver
27-037  Dakota
27-053  Hennepin
27-123  Ramsey
27-139  Scott
27-163  Washington
 
Collar County FIPS
27-025  Chisago
27-049  Goodhue
27-059  Isanti
27-079  LeSueur
27-085  McLeod
27-131  Rice
27-141  Sherburne
27-143  Sibley
27-171  Wright
55-093  Pierce
55-095  Polk
55-109  St. Croix

Statewide shape files were downloaded from the Census Bureau TIGER FTP site (ftp://ftp2.census.gov/geo/pvs/tiger2010st/27_Minnesota/27/) for the following 2010 boundaries: County, County Subdivisions, Tract, Block Group and Block.  7-county metro area was selected from each statewide shapefile and saved as a new shapefile.  9 MN collar counties and 3 WI collar counties were selected from each statewide shapefile and saved as a new shapefile - then Appended to 1-collar county shape file.
 
Individual County Shapefiles were downloaded from the same site for Area Water features.  These shape files were Appended in to 2 new shape files: 7-county area water and a 12-county collar county area water
 
County_2010 - from state-based file - selected
Cousub_2010 - from state-based file - selected
Tract_2010 - from state-based file - selected
Blkgrp_2010 - from state-based file - selected
Block_2010 - from state-based file - selected
Water_2010 - from county-based files - append</procdesc></procstep><srcinfo><srcscale>100000</srcscale></srcinfo></lineage></dataqual><spdoinfo><indspref>2010 Census Block, Block Group or Tract</indspref><direct>Vector</direct><mgmg3obj>arcs, nodes, polygons, label points</mgmg3obj><mgmg3til>For each themes, one layer for entire seven county region and another layer for the 12 collar counties of the 7-county region.</mgmg3til></spdoinfo><eainfo><overview><eaover>Block
     State-based Shapefile Record Layout (2010 Census)
     File Name:  tl_2010_&lt;state FIPS&gt;_tabblock10.shp

Field Name, Length, Type, Description
STATEFP10,  2,  String,  2010 Census state FIPS code
COUNTYFP10,  3,  String,  2010 Census county FIPS code
TRACTCE10,  6,  String,  2010 Census census tract code
BLOCKCE10,   4,  String,  2010 Census tabulation block number
GEOID10,  15,  String,  Block identifier; a concatenation of 2010 Census state FIPS code, county FIPS code, census tract code and tabulation block number.
NAME10, 10,  String,  2010 Census tabulation block name; a concatenation of 'Block' and the current tabulation block number
MTFCC10,   5,  String,  MAF/TIGER feature class code (G5040)
UR10,         1,  String,  2010 Census urban/rural indicator
UACE10,       5,  String,  2010 Census urban area code
FUNCSTAT10,   1,  String,  2010 Census functional status
ALAND10,     14,  Number,  2010 Census land area (square meters)
AWATER10,    14,  Number,  2010 Census water area (square meters) 
INTPTLAT10,  11,  String,  2010 Census latitude of the internal point
INTPTLON10,  12,  String,  2010 Census longitude of the internal point
GOID, 25, String, Block identifier; a concatenation of 2010 Census state FIPS code, county FIPS code, census tract code and tabulation block number.
PLACEFP10, 5, String, 5-digit FIPS code for Census place or city. From Census SF1.
COUSUBFP10, 5, String, 5-digit FIPS code for county subdivision; in cities, this field will be identical to PLACEFP. From Census SF1.
COUSUBNS10, 8, String, 8-digit ANSI code for county subdivision. From Census SF1.
COUSUBNAME, 40, String, Name label for county subdivision. From Census SF1.
TAZ2012, 5, Number, Transport Analysis Zone code, post-2010. Metropolitan Council assigned. Available in all 19 counties.
TAZ2000, 5, Number, Transport Analysis Zone code, post-2000. Metropolitan Council assigned. Available only in metro 7 counties.
MUSA_CODE, 2, String, 2-digit code of MUSA membership and staging. Metropolitan Council assigned. Available only in metro 7 counties.
MC_PLANT, 1, String, Yes/No indicating location in sewershed of a Met Council-operated treatment plant. Metropolitan Council assigned. Available only in metro 7 counties.
MUSA_GEN, 30, String, Description of MUSA membership and staging. Metropolitan Council assigned. Available only in metro 7 counties.



Block Group
     State-based Shapefile Record Layout (2010 Census)
     File Name:  tl_2010_&lt;state FIPS&gt;_bg10.shp

Field   Length  Type    Description
STATEFP10,    2,  String,  2010 Census state FIPS code
COUNTYFP10,   3,  String,  2010 Census county FIPS code
TRACTCE10,    6,  String,  2010 Census census tract code
BLOCKCE10,    4,  String,  2010 Census tabulation block number
GEOID10,     15,  String,  Block identifier; a concatenation of 2010 Census state FIPS code, county FIPS code, census tract code and tabulation block number. 
NAME10,  10,  String,  2010 Census tabulation block name; a concatenation of 'Block' and the current tabulation block number
MTFCC10,      5,  String,  MAF/TIGER feature class code (G5040)
UR10,         1,  String,  2010 Census urban/rural indicator
UACE10,       5,  String,  2010 Census urban area code
FUNCSTAT10,   1,  String,  2010 Census functional status
ALAND10,     14,  Number,  2010 Census land area (square meters)
AWATER10,    14,  Number,  2010 Census water area (square meters)
INTPTLAT10,  11,  String,  2010 Census latitude of the internal point
INTPTLON10,  12,  String,  2010 Census longitude of the internal point


Census Tract
     State-based Shapefile Record Layout (2010 Census)
     File Name: tl_2010_&lt;state FIPS&gt;_tract10.shp

Field   Length  Type    Description
STATEFP10,    2,  String,  2010 Census state FIPS code
COUNTYFP10,   3,  String,  2010 Census county FIPS code
TRACTCE10,    6,  String,  2010 Census census tract code
GEOID10,     11,  String,  Census tract identifier; a concatenation of 2010 Census state FIPS code, county FIPS code, and census tract code
NAME10,       7,  String,  2010 Census census tract name, this is the census tract code converted to an integer or integer plus two-digit decimal if the last two characters of the code are not both zeros.
NAMELSAD10,  20,  String,  2010 Census translated legal/statistical area  description and the census tract name
MTFCC10,      5,  String,  MAF/TIGER feature class code (G5020)
FUNCSTAT10,   1,  String,  2010 Census functional status
ALAND10,     14,  Number,  2010 Census land area (square meters)
AWATER10,    14,  Number,  2010 Census water area (square meters)
INTPTLAT10,  11,  String,  2010 Census latitude of the internal point
INTPTLON10,  12,  String,  2010 Census longitude of the internal point


County and Equivalent Entity
     State-based Shapefile Record Layout (2010 Census)
     File Name:  tl_2010_&lt;state FIPS&gt;_county10.shp

Field   Length  Type    Description
STATEFP10,    2,  String,  2010 Census state FIPS code
COUNTYFP10,   3,  String,  2010 Census county FIPS code
COUNTYNS10,   8,  String,  2010 Census county ANSI code
GEOID10,      5,  String,  County identifier; a concatenation of 2010 Census state FIPS code and county FIPS code
NAME10,     100,  String,  2010 Census county name
NAMELSAD10, 100,  String,  2010 Census name and the translated legal/statistical area description for county
LSAD10,       2,  String,  2010 Census legal/statistical area description code for county
CLASSFP10,    2,  String,  2010 Census FIPS class code
MTFCC10,      5,  String,  MAF/TIGER feature class code (G4020)
CSAFP10,      3,  String,  2010 Census combined statistical area code
CBSAFP10,     5,  String,  2010 Census metropolitan statistical area/micropolitan statistical area code
METDIVFP10,   5,  String,  2010 Census metropolitan division code
FUNCSTAT10,   1,  String,  2010 Census functional status
ALAND10,     14,  Number,  2010 Census land area (square meters)
AWATER10    14  Number  2010 Census water area (square meters)
INTPTLAT10  11  String  2010 Census latitude of the internal point
INTPTLON10  12  String  2010 Census longitude of the internal point


County Subdivision
     State-based Shapefile Record Layout (2010 Census)
     File Name:  tl_2010_&lt;state FIPS&gt;_cousub10.shp

Field   Length  Type    Description
STATEFP10    2  String  2010 Census state FIPS code
COUNTYFP10   3  String  2010 Census county FIPS code
COUSUBFP10   5  String  2010 Census county subdivision FIPS code
COUSUBNS10   8  String  2010 Census county subdivision ANSI code
GEOID10     10  String  County subdivision identifier; a concatenation of 2010 Census state FIPS code, county FIPS code, and county subdivision FIPS code.
NAME10     100  String  2010 Census county subdivision name
NAMELSAD10 100  String  2010 Census name and the translated legal/statistical area description code for county subdivision
LSAD10       2  String  2010 Census legal/statistical area description code for county subdivision
CLASSFP10    2  String  2010 Census FIPS class code
MTFCC10      5  String  MAF/TIGER feature class code (G4040)
CNECTAFP10   3  String  2010 Census combined New England city and town area code
NECTAFP10    5  String  2010 Census New England city and town area code
NCTADVFP10   5  String  2010 Census New England city and town area division code
FUNCSTAT10   1  String  2010 Census functional status
ALAND10     14  Number  2010 Census land area (square meters)
AWATER10    14  Number  2010 Census water area (square meters)
INTPTLAT10  11  String  2010 Census latitude of the internal point
INTPTLON10  12  String  2010 Census longitude of the internal point


Hydrography 
     Shapefile Record Layout
     File Name:  tl_2010_&lt;state-county FIPS&gt;_areawater.shp

Field   Length  Type    Description
STATEFP      2  String  State FIPS code
COUNTYFP     3  String  County FIPS code
ANSICODE     8  String  Official code for the water body for use by federal agencies for data transfer and dissemination, if applicable
HYDROID     22  String  Area hydrography identifier
FULLNAME   100  String  Concatenation of expanded text for prefix qualifier, prefix direction, prefix type, base name, suffix type, suffix direction, and suffix qualifier (as available) with a space between each expanded text field
MTFCC        5  String  MAF/TIGER feature class code
ALAND       14  Number  Land area
AWATER      14  Number  Water area
INTPTLAT    11  String  Latitude of the internal point
INTPTLON    12  String  Longitude of the internal point</eaover><eadetcit>Redistricting Census 2010 TIGER/Line Files

http://www.census.gov/geo/www/tiger/

Redistricting Census 2010 TIGER/Line Technical Documentation and Metadata</eadetcit></overview></eainfo><distinfo><resdesc>Census2010Tiger</resdesc><distliab>NOTICE: The Geographic Information System (GIS) Data to which this notice is attached are made available pursuant to the Minnesota Government Data Practices Act (Minnesota Statutes Chapter 13). THE GIS DATA ARE PROVIDED TO YOU AS IS AND WITHOUT ANY WARRANTY AS TO THEIR PERFORMANCE, MERCHANTABILITY, OR FITNESS FOR ANY PARTICULAR PURPOSE. The GIS Data were developed by the Metropolitan Council for its own internal business purposes. The Metropolitan Council does not represent or warrant that the GIS Data or the data documentation are error-free, complete, current, or accurate. You are responsible for any consequences resulting from your use of the GIS Data or your reliance on the GIS Data. You should consult the data documentation for this particular GIS Data to determine the limitations of the GIS Data and the precision with which the GIS Data may depict distance, direction, location, or other geographic features. If you transmit or provide the GIS Data (or any portion of it) to another user, it is recommended that the GIS Data include a copy of this disclaimer and this metadata.</distliab><stdorder><digform><digtinfo><formname>ArcView Shape File</formname><formvern>9x</formvern><transize /></digtinfo></digform><ordering>This dataset is distributed on the internet.  

By clicking below after 'Online Linkage' you will be able to download the 7-county metro shape files.

To download the shape files for the collar counties, click on this link:  ftp://gisftp.metc.state.mn.us/Census2010TigerCollar.zip

Doing so will tell your browser to download a 'ZIP' file which will contain the following:

- ArcView shape files
- metadata for the dataset (.htm)
- NOTICE.RTF, an important notice about this dataset that can be read by any word processing software.
 
Additionally, this dataset is available for direct use via one or more map services.  More information about what a web mapping service is can be found at http://www.datafinder.org/services/.  The specific map service and layer name for this dataset can be found by clicking the blue or green boxes under the map service column of the DataFinder Catalog at http://www.datafinder.org/catalog/ .</ordering></stdorder><distrib><cntinfo><cntperp><cntorg>Metropolitan Council</cntorg><cntper>Tanya Mayer</cntper></cntperp><cntpos>GIS Coordinator</cntpos><cntaddr><address>390 Robert Street North</address><city>St. Paul</city><state>Minnesota</state><postal>55101</postal></cntaddr><cntvoice>651-602-1604</cntvoice><cntfax>651-602-1674</cntfax><cntemail>tanya.mayer@metc.state.mn.us</cntemail></cntinfo></distrib></distinfo><metainfo><metd>20120830</metd><metstdn>Minnesota Geographic Metadata Guidelines</metstdn><metstdv>1.2</metstdv><metextns><onlink>http://www.gis.state.mn.us/stds/metadata.htm</onlink></metextns><metc><cntinfo><cntperp><cntorg>Metropolitan Council</cntorg><cntper>Tanya Mayer</cntper></cntperp><cntpos>GIS Coordinator</cntpos><cntaddr><address>390 Robert Street North</address><city>St. Paul</city><state>Minnesota</state><postal>55101-1805</postal></cntaddr><cntvoice>651-602-1604</cntvoice><cntfax>651-602-1674</cntfax><cntemail>tanya.mayer@metc.state.mn.us</cntemail></cntinfo></metc></metainfo><Esri><ModDate>20110722</ModDate><ModTime>16250000</ModTime></Esri><mdDateSt Sync="TRUE">20110722</mdDateSt><spref><horizsys><planar><gridsys><gridsysn>Universal Transverse Mercator</gridsysn><utm><utmzone>15</utmzone></utm></gridsys><planci><plandu>meters</plandu></planci></planar><geodetic><horizdn>NAD83</horizdn><ellips>GRS80</ellips></geodetic></horizsys></spref></metadata>