<metadata><idinfo><citation><citeinfo><origin>Metropolitan Council</origin><pubdate>Unpublished material</pubdate><title catid="4d25e98c-9939-4664-823c-f1ca9174e5ca">Mississippi River Critical Area and MNRRA Boundaries</title><mgmg1cid>N/A</mgmg1cid><pubinfo><publish>Metropolitan Council</publish></pubinfo><onlink>ftp://gisftp.metc.state.mn.us/MNRRA.zip</onlink></citeinfo></citation><descript><abstract>This dataset shows the boundaries of the state designated Mississipi River Critical Area program as well as the federally designated Mississippi National River and Recreation Area within the Twin Cities metropolitan area.  

The Mississippi River Critical Area (CA) program was established in 1976 by the State of Minnesota and is currently administered by the Minnesota Department of Natural Resources.  An external boundary was established for the Critical Area as well as internal district boundaries (e.g. rural open space, urban diversified, etc).

The Mississippi National River and Recreation Area (MNRRA) is a federally designated unit of the National Park Service and was established in 1988.  MNRRA adopted the same external boundary as the state Mississippi River Critical Area (CA).  Though MNRRA and CA use the same legal description to define exterior boundaries, the internal corridor districts included in this dataset are components of the Critical Area only--not MNRRA.  While the MNRRA Comprehensive Management Plan adopts by reference the state CA program, MNRRA has no specially designated districts.  

This dataset is derived from a digital file received from the National Park Service and modified to more closely match existing public land survey and street centerline datasets where the lines appeared to be coincident.

NOTES:
-  This dataset is a hybrid layer.  It takes lines from several different base files in an attempt to define the Critical Area boundaries.  The sources used are either more positionally accurate than the coverage received from the federal government, or are datasets that are commonly used within the Twin Cities metropolitan area.
-  Some users have noted that some Critical Area boundary lines are noticeably positionally off from where they believe the correct location of the boundary to be.  (e.g. In the MSP airport area, one user thought the line was to go down between the lanes of the freeway, while the line in the MNRRA layer does not even appear to be within the freeway right of way.)</abstract><purpose>To be used as a general reference for the Mississippi River Critical Area and  MNRRA boundaries for regional planning purposes.</purpose><supplinf>Twin Cities 7 County Metropolitan Area.  This includes the counties of Anoka, Carver, Dakota, Hennepin, Ramsey, Scott and Washington in Minnesota.</supplinf></descript><timeperd><timeinfo><sngdate><caldate>1997</caldate></sngdate></timeinfo><current>The dataset was developed in 1997.</current></timeperd><status><progress>Complete</progress><update>None Planned</update></status><spdom><bounding><westbc>-94.012</westbc><eastbc>-92.732</eastbc><northbc>45.415</northbc><southbc>44.471</southbc></bounding></spdom><keywords><theme><themekt>None</themekt><themekey>Mississippi River Critical Area, Mississippi National River and Recreation Area, administrative boundaries</themekey></theme><place><placekey>Twin Cities, Anoka County, Carver County, Dakota County, Hennepin County, Ramsey County, Scott County, Washington County</placekey></place></keywords><accconst>None</accconst><useconst>None</useconst><browse><browsen>http://www.datafinder.org/metadata/bg/MNRRA.jpg</browsen><browsed>Sample map showing the Mississippi River Critical Area layer.</browsed></browse><native>ArcInfo Version 7x, UNIX platform</native><ptcontac><cntinfo><cntperp><cntorg>Metropolitan Council</cntorg><cntper>Jon Hoekenga</cntper></cntperp><cntpos>GIS System Administrator</cntpos><cntaddr><address>390 Robert Street North</address><city>St. Paul</city><state>MN</state><postal>55101-1805</postal></cntaddr><cntvoice>651.602.1561</cntvoice><cntemail>jonathan.hoekenga@metc.state.mn.us</cntemail></cntinfo></ptcontac></idinfo><dataqual><logic>The dataset is topologically 'clean'.</logic><complete>Entire seven county geographic area is covered.</complete><posacc><horizpa><horizpar>The positional accuracy of the dataset has not been tested under the National Standards for Spatial Data Accuracy.  The positional accuracy of the dataset is UNKNOWN.</horizpar></horizpa></posacc><lineage><srcinfo><srcscale /></srcinfo><procstep><procdesc>Data Source:  Metropolitan Council developed from data from National Park Service, The Lawrence Group, DNR, DOT and the Metropolitan Council

Things to Know:
This dataset is a hybrid layer.  It takes lines from several different base files in an attempt to define the Critical Area boundaries.  The sources used are either more positionally accurate than the coverage received from the federal government, or are datasets that are commonly used within the Twin Cities metropolitan area.

Where lines from the various sources did not intersect, connecting lines were added (SOURCE = TLG-SNAP or FEDS-SNAP).  This was done either by snapping directly between existing nodes, or by extending one line until it intersected another.

No tests have been made of the positional differences between the original boundary received from the National Park Service and other layers, but between the NPS layer and the TLG dataset, positional difference of 10 to 30 meters were common.

Some users have noted that some Critical Area boundary lines are noticeably positionally off from where they believe the correct location of the boundary to be.  (e.g. In the MSP airport area, one user thought the line was to go down between the lanes of the freeway, while the line in the MNRRA layer does not even appear to be within the freeway right of way.)</procdesc></procstep></lineage></dataqual><spdoinfo><indspref>None</indspref><direct>Vector</direct><mgmg3obj>arcs, nodes, polygons, label points</mgmg3obj><mgmg3til>One layer for entire seven county region.</mgmg3til></spdoinfo><spref><vertdef><altsys><altdatum>Not applicable</altdatum><altunits /></altsys><depthsys><depthdn>Not applicable</depthdn><depthdu /></depthsys></vertdef><horizsys><planar><gridsys><gridsysn>Universal Transverse Mercator</gridsysn><utm><utmzone>15</utmzone></utm></gridsys><planci><plandu>meters</plandu></planci></planar><geodetic><horizdn>NAD83</horizdn><ellips>GRS80</ellips></geodetic></horizsys></spref><eainfo><overview><eaover>Polygon Attributes:
 
DISTRICT:    The state Mississippi River Critical Area district designation
 
 
Line Attributes:
 
STREET_NAM:  Street name  (only available for some lines)
 
ALT_NAM1:    Alternate street name 1
 
ALT_NAM2:    Alternate street name 2 
 
SOURCE:      Source of the line (e.g. DNR, DOT, Feds, etc)</eaover><eadetcit>None</eadetcit></overview></eainfo><distinfo><resdesc>MNRRA</resdesc><distliab>NOTICE:  The Geographic Information System (GIS) Data to which this notice is attached are made available pursuant to the Minnesota Government Data Practices Act (Minnesota Statutes Chapter 13).  THE GIS DATA ARE PROVIDED TO YOU AS IS AND WITHOUT ANY WARRANTY AS TO THEIR PERFORMANCE, MERCHANTABILITY, OR FITNESS FOR ANY PARTICULAR PURPOSE.  The GIS Data were developed by the Metropolitan Council for its own internal business purposes.  The Metropolitan Council does not represent or warrant that the GIS Data or the data documentation are error-free, complete, current, or accurate.  You are responsible for any consequences resulting from your use of the GIS Data or your reliance on the GIS Data.  You should consult the data documentation for this particular GIS Data to determine the limitations of the GIS Data and the precision with which the GIS Data may depict distance, direction, location, or other geographic features.  If you transmit or provide the GIS Data (or any portion of it) to another user, it is recommended that the GIS Data include a copy of this disclaimer and this metadata.</distliab><stdorder><digform><digtinfo><formname>Arc Export files and ArcView Shape files</formname><formvern>ArcInfo: 7x,  ArcView: 3x</formvern><transize>0.1 meg. for zip file.</transize></digtinfo></digform><ordering>This dataset is distributed on the internet by clicking below after 'Online Linkage'.  Doing so will tell your browser to download a 'ZIP' file which will contain the following:

- ArcView shape files
- metadata for the dataset (.htm)
- NOTICE.RTF, an important notice about this dataset that can be read by any word processing software.

 
Additionally, this dataset is available for direct use via one or more map services.  More information about what a web mapping service is can be found at http://www.datafinder.org/services/.  The specific map service and layer name for this dataset can be found by clicking the blue or green boxes under the map service column of the DataFinder Catalog at http://www.datafinder.org/catalog/ .</ordering></stdorder><distrib><cntinfo><cntperp><cntorg>Metropolitan Council</cntorg><cntper>Jon Hoekenga</cntper></cntperp><cntpos>GIS System Administrator</cntpos><cntaddr><address>390 Robert Street North</address><city>St. Paul</city><state>MN</state><postal>55101-1805</postal></cntaddr><cntvoice>651.602.1561</cntvoice><cntemail>jonathan.hoekenga@metc.state.mn.us</cntemail></cntinfo></distrib></distinfo><metainfo><metd>20030718</metd><metstdn>Minnesota Geographic Metadata Guidelines</metstdn><metstdv>1.2</metstdv><metextns><onlink>http://www.gis.state.mn.us/stds/metadata.htm</onlink></metextns><metc><cntinfo><cntperp><cntorg>Metropolitan Council</cntorg><cntper>Jon Hoekenga</cntper></cntperp><cntpos>GIS System Administrator</cntpos><cntaddr><address>390 Robert Street North</address><city>St. Paul</city><state>MN</state><postal>55101-1805</postal></cntaddr><cntvoice>651.602.1561</cntvoice><cntemail>jonathan.hoekenga@metc.state.mn.us</cntemail></cntinfo></metc></metainfo><Esri><ModDate>20110729</ModDate><ModTime>14492000</ModTime></Esri><mdDateSt Sync="TRUE">20110729</mdDateSt></metadata>