<metadata>
	<idinfo><citation><citeinfo><title catid="8bb753e3-d504-42f0-98be-0c16ec884c60">2005 MARKHURD Digital Orthophotos, Twin Cities Metropolitan Area</title><origin>Metropolitan Council and MARKHURD</origin><pubinfo><publish>MARKHURD</publish></pubinfo><pubdate>200511</pubdate><onlink /></citeinfo></citation><descript><abstract>This licensed dataset from MARKHURD contains 267 black and white, color, and color near-infrared (CIR) orthophoto quarter-quadrangles (DQQs), 3.75' x 3.75' covering the 7-county Minneapolis - St. Paul Twin Cities Metropolitan Area in Minnesota.  A quarter-quadrangle is included if its coverage includes any portion of the Twin Cities 7-county area.  The orthophotos are in UTM, Zone 15, NAD83 projection with a resolution of 0.6 meter (2 ft pixel).  The DOQs were delivered in TIFF and MrSID formats with associated world files.  MrSID files are available to MetroGIS participants, upon completion of a license agreement.  All others must contact MARKHURD for copies.  MrSID black and white DOQs are 11 MB each for a total of 3 GB on 1-DVD.   Color and CIR DOQs are 17 MB each for a total of 4.5 GB on 2-DVDs for each, color and CIR.  These orthophotos were produced using the USGS DOQ specifications as a guideline.  The original imagery was collected at approximately 20,000 ft. using a Zeiss Digital Mapping Camera (DMC).

Samples of the photos can be found at these links:
Black and white: http://www.datafinder.org/metadata/bg/orthos2005_markhurd_sample_mrsid_bw.jpg
Color: http://www.datafinder.org/metadata/bg/orthos2005_markhurd_sample_mrsid_color.jpg
CIR: http://www.datafinder.org/metadata/bg/orthos2005_markhurd_sample_mrsid_cir.jpg</abstract><purpose>The digital orthophotos will be used for developing the Metropolitan Council's 2005 Generalized Land Use dataset as will as for many other mapping and analysis functions.

A note about zooming: Generally photogrammetrists suggest that the integrity of a traditional film photo image degrades noticeably after 5 times the negative scale, and that 10 times the negative scale is the absolute maximum one should enlarge a photo.  For this dataset, zooming beyond a 1:4,000 scale is not recommended. This applies to the original uncompressed TIFF format orthophoto images. The results for compressed images are more severe.</purpose><supplinf>Twin Cities 7 County Metropolitan Area. This includes the counties of Anoka, Carver, Dakota, Hennepin, Ramsey, Scott and Washington in Minnesota.</supplinf></descript><timeperd><timeinfo><sngdate><caldate>200504</caldate></sngdate></timeinfo><current>The dates of the original aerial photography were April 8, 13 and 14, 2005.</current></timeperd><status><progress>Complete</progress><update>Unknown</update></status><spdom><bounding><westbc>-94.06</westbc><eastbc>-92.69</eastbc><northbc>45.44</northbc><southbc>44.44</southbc></bounding></spdom><keywords><place><placekey>Twin Cities, Anoka County, Carver County, Dakota County, Hennepin County, Ramsey County, Scott County, Washingtion County.</placekey></place><theme><themekey>orthophotography, ortho, orthophotos, DOQ, DOQQ, imagery, images, digital ortho, aerial photography, aerial photos, digital aerial photography</themekey><themekt /></theme></keywords><accconst>Subject to License Agreement with the Metropolitan Council and Markhurd.</accconst><useconst>Subject to License Agreement with the Metropolitan Council and Markhurd.  
Copyright and credit to Markhurd is required on all products that include the 2005 Digital Orthophotos.
Licensed MetroGIS participants may not distribute or place the orthophotos on the internet.
Contact MARKHURD for requests, questions or concerns.</useconst><ptcontac><cntinfo><cntperp><cntper>Tanya Mayer</cntper><cntorg>Metropolitan Council, GIS</cntorg></cntperp><cntpos>GIS Coordinator</cntpos><cntaddr><address>390 Robert Street North</address><city>St. Paul</city><state>MN</state><postal>55101</postal></cntaddr><cntvoice>651-602-1604</cntvoice><cntfax /><cntemail>tanya.mayer@metc.state.mn.us</cntemail></cntinfo></ptcontac><browse><browsen>http://www.datafinder.org/metadata/bg/orthos2005_markhurd_sample_mrsid_color.jpg</browsen><browsed /></browse><crossref><citeinfo><title>2000 Metropolitan Council Digital Orthophotos
1997 Metropolitan Council Digital Orthophotos
1991 USGS DOQs</title></citeinfo></crossref><native /></idinfo><dataqual><attracc><attraccr /></attracc><logic /><complete>The Twin Cities Metropolitan Area, which includes the counties of Anoka, Carver, Dakota, Hennepin, Ramsey, Scott and Washington in Minnesota.</complete><posacc><horizpa><horizpar>NMAS @ 1:12,000 scale, 90% of well-defined points fall within 33.3 ft</horizpar></horizpa><vertacc><vertaccr>Not applicable</vertaccr></vertacc></posacc><lineage><procstep><procdesc>The 2005 Digital Orthophotos were developed under contract for license with MARKHURD.

MARKHURD acquired new vertical, digital black and white, color, and color infrared, photography at an altitude of 20,000 ft  photo scale of 1''= 4,233' (1:50,796) with a 0.6m pixel (2 ft) with  Ziess DMC (Digital Mapping Camera) flight lines were N-S with a 60% forward overlap and a 30% side Lap.  There were 22 flight lines, 1,132 exposures and exposures were centered at the quarter quad edges, quarter quad center, and one in between with a 12um (0.6 meter) pixel.

 The DMC camera consists of 8 sensors: 4 panchromatic sensors and 4 multi-spectral sensors.  The multi-spectral sensors are 3K x 2K in size, with one sensor capturing red data, one capturing blue data, one capturing green data, and one capturing near-infrared data (band pass 740-850nm).  The four panchromatic sensors each capture one image of a particular area (7K x 4K), which slightly overlap one to another and are used to produce one large mosaic image, 7680 x 13824 in size.   
 
A Fully Analytical Aerotriangulation (AT) of the aerial images was developed to be used in the orthorectification process. The original photo targets were recaptured along with probed data points from the Metropolitan Council's 2000 digital orthophoto project to complete the AT-solution.  
 
The Council provided the USGS 30 Meter DEM to MARKHURD in UTM, NAD83, horizontal units in meters, vertical units (Z-units) in feet, tiled by USGS quadrangle.  The DEM files are used in the orthorectification process.
 
MARKHURD used a softcopy process to create the final digital orthophotos.  Digital Orthophoto Quarter-Quads were developed following the USGS standards for digital orthophotos (DOQs) with the exception of pixel resolution 0.6 meters (2 ft) and file format (TIFF with world files).  USGS header (.hdr) file were not included as a deliverable.
 
Each black and white image is approximately 115 Mb with a 0.6 meter image pixel (2 ft).  
 Each black and white MrSID image is compressed at a 10:1 ratio and is approximately 11 MB.
 
Each color and CIR image is approximately 350 Mb with a 0.6 meter image pixel (2').     
Each color and CIR MrSID image is compressed at a 20:1 ratio and is approximately 17 MB.

For LICENSED MetroGIS Participants
All the black and white MrSID files are available on 1 DVD (3 GB).
All the color MrSID files are available on 2 DVDs (5 GB).
All the CIR MrSID files are available on 2 DVDs (5 GB).</procdesc></procstep><srcinfo><srcscale>51000</srcscale></srcinfo></lineage></dataqual><spdoinfo><indspref /><direct>Raster</direct><mgmg3obj /><mgmg3til>3.75 minute quadrangle sheets (USGS 7.5 minute 'quarter quads')</mgmg3til></spdoinfo><spref><horizsys><geograph><latres /><longres /><geogunit /></geograph><planar><gridsys><gridsysn>UTM</gridsysn><utm><utmzone>15</utmzone></utm><spcs><spcszone /></spcs><mgmg4coz /><mgmg4adj /></gridsys><mapproj><mapprojn /><mgmg4par /><otherprj /></mapproj><planci><plandu>Meters</plandu><coordrep><absres>.6</absres><ordres>.6</ordres></coordrep></planci></planar><geodetic><ellips>GRS80</ellips><horizdn>NAD83</horizdn></geodetic></horizsys><vertdef><altsys><altdatum>NAVD88</altdatum><altunits>Meters</altunits></altsys></vertdef></spref><eainfo><overview><eaover /><eadetcit /></overview></eainfo><distinfo><distrib><cntinfo><cntperp><cntper>Tanya Mayer</cntper><cntorg>Metropolitan Council, GIS</cntorg></cntperp><cntpos /><cntaddr><address>390 Robert Street North</address><city>St. Paul</city><state>MN</state><postal>55101</postal></cntaddr><cntvoice>651-602-1604</cntvoice><cntfax /><cntemail>maps@metc.state.mn.us</cntemail></cntinfo></distrib><resdesc>2005 Digital Orthophotos, Twin Cities Metropolitan Area</resdesc><distliab>See MetroGIS License Agreement and instructions</distliab><stdorder><digform><digtinfo><formname>MrSID</formname><formvern /><transize>Black &amp; White - 1 DVD; Color - 2 DVDs; CIR - 2 DVDs</transize></digtinfo></digform><ordering>MetroGIS Participants
Go to http://gis.metc.state.mn.us/data.asp or call the Metropolitan Council GIS at 651-602-1604. 


All Others 
Contact MARKHURD at markhurd.com or 763-420-9606</ordering></stdorder></distinfo><metainfo><metd>20060224</metd><metc><cntinfo><cntperp><cntper>Tanya Mayer</cntper><cntorg>Metropolitan Council, GIS</cntorg></cntperp><cntpos>GIS Coordinator</cntpos><cntaddr><address>390 Robert Street North</address><city>St. Paul</city><state>MN</state><postal>55101</postal></cntaddr><cntvoice>651-602-1604</cntvoice><cntfax /><cntemail>tanya.mayer@metc.state.mn.us</cntemail></cntinfo></metc><metstdn>Minnesota Geographic Metadata Guidelines</metstdn><metstdv>1.2</metstdv><metextns><onlink>http://www.gis.state.mn.us/stds/metadata.htm</onlink></metextns></metainfo><Esri><ModDate>20080731</ModDate><ModTime>10374800</ModTime></Esri><mdDateSt Sync="TRUE">20080731</mdDateSt></metadata>