<metadata>
	<eainfo>
		<overview>
			<eaover>Attributes for Tabular Data: 

YEAR: The year the permit was issued. 

CO_CODE: 3 digit FIPS and state standard county ID code 
003 = Anoka County 
019 = Carver County 
037 = Dakota County 
053 = Hennepin County 
123 = Ramsey County 
139 = Scott County 
163 = Washington County 

CTU_ID: The Geographic Names Information System (GNIS) official federal unique identifier for each city, township or unorganized territory. 

CTU_CODE: 5 digit FIPS55 'Place' code for CTU. As of 2006 these codes have been officially retired by the federal government. They are replaced by the GNIS codes below. The Census Bureau will continue to create FIPS55 Place codes for new cities and townships through the 2010 Census. After that, no new FIPS55 codes will be created. Note that for townships that wholly incorporate into cities, the same FIPS55 code for 
the former township will usually be used for the new city. Conversely, GNIS creates a new ID for the new city. 

CTU_NAME: Name of the city, township or unorganized territory, e.g. Benton Twp., Blaine. 

CO_NAME: Name of county.

Address: Address of residential units.

TYPE: Designation of project into one of 3 building type categories. 

UNITS: Number of units.

			</eaover>
		</overview>
	</eainfo>
	<idinfo>
		<citation>
			<citeinfo>
				<origin>Metropolitan Council</origin>
				<title catid="034e67cb-ddc8-4574-8983-241bf212f7c2">Residential Attached Units, 2009 to 2011</title>
				<pubinfo>
					<publish>Metropolitan Council</publish>
				</pubinfo>
				<pubdate>20130529</pubdate>
				<onlink>ftp://gisftp.metc.state.mn.us/ResidentialAttachedBuildingPermits.zip</onlink>
			</citeinfo>
		</citation>
		<descript>
			<abstract>This dataset consists of summary data for attached residential permitted units, based on building permits issued during each calendar year by cities and townships within the Region. Data is collected via an annual survey of building officials, in conjunction with collection of data on non-residential building permits. </abstract>
			<purpose>This dataset was created to summarize and analyze residential development trends of attached units in the seven-county Twin Cities Region. </purpose>
			<supplinf>Twin Cities 7 county metropolitan area. This includes the counties of Anoka, Carver, Dakota, Hennepin, Ramsey, Scott and Washington.</supplinf>
		</descript>
		<crossref>
			<citeinfo>
				<title>Commercial, Industrial, and Public and Institutional Construction, Twin Cities Metropolitan Area 
				</title>
			</citeinfo>
		</crossref>
		<timeperd>
			<current>This dataset reflects permit information collected annually from 2009 through 2011.</current>
			<timeinfo>
				<sngdate>
					<caldate>20130529</caldate>
				</sngdate>
			</timeinfo>
		</timeperd>
		<status>
			<progress>Complete</progress>
			<update>Annually</update>
		</status>
		<spdom>
			<bounding>
				<westbc>-94.012</westbc>
				<eastbc>-92.732</eastbc>
				<northbc>45.415</northbc>
				<southbc>44.471</southbc>
			</bounding>
		</spdom>
		<keywords>
			<theme>
				<themekey>Attached, residential building permits, building permits, permits</themekey>
			</theme>
		</keywords>
		<accconst>None</accconst>
		<useconst>None</useconst>
		<ptcontac>
			<cntinfo>
				<cntperp>
					<cntorg>Metropolitan Council</cntorg>
					<cntper>Joel Nyhus</cntper>
				</cntperp>
				<cntpos>Reseacher</cntpos>
				<cntaddr>
					<address>390 Robert Street North</address>
					<city>St. Paul</city>
					<state>MN</state>
					<postal>55101-1805</postal>
				</cntaddr>
				<cntvoice>651.602.1634</cntvoice>
				<cntemail>joel.nyhus@metc.state.mn.us</cntemail>
			</cntinfo>
		</ptcontac>
	</idinfo>
	<dataqual>
		<complete>Entire 7 county area is covered.</complete>
		<lineage>
			<procstep>
				<procdesc>The data were obtained through an annual survey sent to communities by the Metropolitan Council in conjunction with collection of non-residential building permits. Respondents are asked to provide project information for new residential units.

For this shapefile, only attached housing units are included. 

A small number of communities each year may not provide data. These are typically places with no residential construction occurring. 

The data on returned surveys were verified by Metropolitan Council staff through various means including: contact with community staff, community websites, and comparison to data in the Council's Service Availability Charge (SAC) reports where possible. 

For this data, projects are counted at the time local units of government issue building permits. 






				</procdesc>
			</procstep>
		</lineage>
	</dataqual>
	<distinfo>
		<resdesc>Residential Attached Building Permits</resdesc>
		<distliab>NOTICE: The Geographic Information System (GIS) Data to which this notice is attached are made available pursuant to the Minnesota Government Data Practices Act (Minnesota Statutes Chapter 13). THE GIS DATA ARE PROVIDED TO YOU AS IS AND WITHOUT ANY WARRANTY AS TO THEIR PERFORMANCE, MERCHANTABILITY, OR FITNESS FOR ANY PARTICULAR PURPOSE. The GIS Data were developed by the Metropolitan Council for its own internal business purposes. The Metropolitan Council does not represent or warrant that the GIS Data or the data documentation are error-free, complete, current, or accurate. You are responsible for any consequences resulting from your use of the GIS Data or your reliance on the GIS Data. You should consult the data documentation for this particular GIS Data to determine the limitations of the GIS Data and the precision with which the GIS Data may depict distance, direction, location, or other geographic features. If you transmit or provide the GIS Data (or any portion of it) to another user, it is recommended that the GIS Data include a copy of this disclaimer and this metadata.</distliab>
		<stdorder>
			<ordering>This dataset is distributed on the internet by clicking below after 'Online Linkage'. Doing so will tell your browser to download a 'ZIP' file which will contain the following: 

- ArcView shape files 
- metadata for the dataset (.htm) 
- NOTICE.RTF, an important notice about this dataset that can be read by any word processing software. 

Additionally, this dataset is available for direct use via one or more map services. More information about what a map service is can be found at www.datafinder.org/services/. The specific map service and layer name for this dataset can be found by clicking the "Services" link for this dataset in the DataFinder Catalog at www.datafinder.org/catalog/ .</ordering>
		</stdorder>
		<distrib>
			<cntinfo>
				<cntperp>
					<cntorg>Metropolitan Council</cntorg>
					<cntper>Baris Gumus-Dawes</cntper>
				</cntperp>
				<cntpos>Senior Researcher</cntpos>
				<cntaddr>
					<address>390 Robert Street North</address>
					<city>St. Paul</city>
					<state>MN</state>
					<postal>55101-1805</postal>
				</cntaddr>
				<cntvoice>651.602.1331</cntvoice>
				<cntemail>baris.dawes@metc.state.mn.us</cntemail>
			</cntinfo>
		</distrib>
	</distinfo>
	<metainfo>
		<metd>20130529</metd>
		<metstdn>Minnesota Geographic Metadata Guidelines</metstdn>
		<metstdv>1.2</metstdv>
		<metextns>
			<onlink>http://www.mngeo.state.mn.us/committee/standards/mgmg/metadata.htm</onlink>
		</metextns>
		<metc>
			<cntinfo>
				<cntperp>
					<cntorg>Metropolitan Council</cntorg>
					<cntper>Jon Hoekenga</cntper>
				</cntperp>
				<cntpos>GIS Specialist</cntpos>
				<cntaddr>
					<address>390 Robert Street North</address>
					<city>St. Paul</city>
					<state>MN</state>
					<postal>55101-1805</postal>
				</cntaddr>
				<cntvoice>651.602.1561</cntvoice>
				<cntemail>jonathan.hoekenga@metc.state.mn.us</cntemail>
			</cntinfo>
		</metc>
	</metainfo>
	<spref>
		<horizsys>
			<planar>
				<gridsys>
					<gridsysn>Universal Transverse Mercator</gridsysn>
					<utm>
						<utmzone>15</utmzone>
					</utm>
				</gridsys>
				<planci>
					<plandu>meters</plandu>
				</planci>
			</planar>
			<geodetic>
				<horizdn>NAD83</horizdn>
				<ellips>GRS80</ellips>
			</geodetic>
		</horizsys>
	</spref>
</metadata>