<metadata>
	<idinfo>
		<citation>
			<citeinfo>
				<title catid="e0c0aa45-b1d0-41a1-9e12-cb4d62530b20">Metropolitan Council Sector Representatives</title>
				<origin>Metropolitan Council</origin>
				<pubinfo>
					<publish>Metropolitan Council</publish>
				</pubinfo>
				<pubdate>20130628</pubdate>
				<onlink>ftp://gisftp.metc.state.mn.us/SectorRepresentatives.zip</onlink>
			</citeinfo>
		</citation>
		<descript>
			<abstract>This is a general reference layer defining the Metropolitan Council's Planning Sector Representative boundaries and the representatives assigned to each sector.  It was derived from the Council's city and township boundary layer.</abstract>
			<purpose>General reference.</purpose>
			<supplinf>Twin Cities 7 County Metropolitan Area.  This includes the counties of Anoka, Carver, Dakota, Hennepin, Ramsey, Scott and Washington in Minnesota.</supplinf>
		</descript>
		<timeperd>
			<timeinfo>
				<sngdate>
					<caldate>20130628</caldate>
				</sngdate>
			</timeinfo>
			<current>Sector representatives are current as of the Time Period of Content date above.   

The city and township boundaries used to create this dataset were derived from the metro wide city and township boundary dataset described at http://www.datafinder.org/metadata/CountiesAndCTUs.htm That dataset is updated on a quarterly basis. This dataset is then recreated quarterly from those boundaries.</current>
		</timeperd>
		<status>
			<progress>Complete</progress>
			<update>As Needed</update>
		</status>
		<spdom>
			<bounding>
				<westbc>-94.012</westbc>
				<eastbc>-92.732</eastbc>
				<northbc>45.415</northbc>
				<southbc>44.471</southbc>
			</bounding>
		</spdom>
		<keywords>
			<place>
				<placekey>Twin Cities, Anoka County, Carver County, Dakota County, Hennepin County, Ramsey County, Scott County, Washington County</placekey>
			</place>
			<theme>
				<themekey>community development, sector representatives, administrative boundaries</themekey>
				<themekt>None</themekt>
			</theme>
		</keywords>
		<accconst>None</accconst>
		<useconst>None</useconst>
		<browse>
			<browsen>http://www.datafinder.org/metadata/bg/SectorRepresentatives.jpg</browsen>
			<browsed>Sample map showing what the SectorRepresentatives layer looks like.  This map shows an older version of the dataset.</browsed>
		</browse>
		<crossref>
			<citeinfo>
				<title>City and township boundaries dataset http://www.datafinder.org/metadata/CountiesAndCTUs.htm</title>
			</citeinfo>
		</crossref>
		<native>ArcGIS Version 10x</native>
		<ptcontac>
			<cntinfo>
				<cntperp>
					<cntorg>Metropolitan Council</cntorg>
					<cntper>LisaBeth Barajas</cntper>
				</cntperp>
				<cntpos>Manager</cntpos>
				<cntaddr>
					<address>390 Robert Street North</address>
					<city>St. Paul</city>
					<state>MN</state>
					<postal>55101-1805</postal>
				</cntaddr>
				<cntvoice>651.602.1895</cntvoice>
				<cntemail>lisa.barajas@metc.state.mn.us</cntemail>
			</cntinfo>
		</ptcontac>
	</idinfo>
	<dataqual>
		<logic>The dataset is topologically 'clean'.</logic>
		<complete>Entire seven county geographic area is covered.</complete>
		<posacc>
			<horizpa>
				<horizpar>This boundaries for this dataset are derived from the MetroGIS regional city and township boundary dataset.  See http://www.datafinder.org/metadata/CountiesAndCTUs.htm#dataqual for positional accuracy information.</horizpar>
			</horizpa>
		</posacc>
		<lineage>
			<procstep>
				<procdesc>Dissolved from the Counties Cities and Townships boundary layer (county_ctu.shp).

Note that these ''Sectors'' are different than the ''Research Sectors'' used by the Met. Council Research Dept. or the "Development Sectors" used by the Council Office of Policy Development.</procdesc>
			</procstep>
			<srcinfo>
				<srcscale />
			</srcinfo>
		</lineage>
	</dataqual>
	<spdoinfo>
		<indspref>None</indspref>
		<direct>Vector</direct>
		<mgmg3obj>polygon shapes</mgmg3obj>
		<mgmg3til>One layer for entire seven county region.</mgmg3til>
	</spdoinfo>
	<eainfo>
		<overview>
			<eaover>Polygon Attributes:

SECTOR_REP:  The name of the Sector Representative assigned to the sector</eaover>
			<eadetcit>None</eadetcit>
		</overview>
	</eainfo>
	<distinfo>
		<resdesc>SectorRepresentatives</resdesc>
		<distliab>NOTICE:  The Geographic Information System (GIS) Data to which this notice is attached are made available pursuant to the Minnesota Government Data Practices Act (Minnesota Statutes Chapter 13).  THE GIS DATA ARE PROVIDED TO YOU AS IS AND WITHOUT ANY WARRANTY AS TO THEIR PERFORMANCE, MERCHANTABILITY, OR FITNESS FOR ANY PARTICULAR PURPOSE.  The GIS Data were developed by the Metropolitan Council for its own internal business purposes.  The Metropolitan Council does not represent or warrant that the GIS Data or the data documentation are error-free, complete, current, or accurate.  You are responsible for any consequences resulting from your use of the GIS Data or your reliance on the GIS Data.  You should consult the data documentation for this particular GIS Data to determine the limitations of the GIS Data and the precision with which the GIS Data may depict distance, direction, location, or other geographic features.  If you transmit or provide the GIS Data (or any portion of it) to another user, it is recommended that the GIS Data include a copy of this disclaimer and this metadata.</distliab>
		<stdorder>
			<digform>
				<digtinfo>
					<formname>ArcView Shape files</formname>
					<formvern>ArcGIS 10x</formvern>
					<transize>1 MB for zip file.</transize>
				</digtinfo>
			</digform>
			<ordering>This dataset is distributed on the internet by clicking below after 'Online Linkage'.  Doing so will tell your browser to download a 'ZIP' file which will contain the following:

- ArcView shape files
- metadata for the dataset (.htm)
- NOTICE.RTF, an important notice about this dataset that can be read by any word processing software.

Additionally, this dataset is available for direct use via one or more map services.  More information about what a web mapping service is can be found at http://www.datafinder.org/services/.  The specific map service and layer name for this dataset can be found by clicking the blue or green boxes under the map service column of the DataFinder Catalog at http://www.datafinder.org/catalog/ .</ordering>
		</stdorder>
		<distrib>
			<cntinfo>
				<cntperp>
					<cntorg>Metropolitan Council</cntorg>
					<cntper>Jon Hoekenga</cntper>
				</cntperp>
				<cntpos>GIS System Administrator</cntpos>
				<cntaddr>
					<address>390 Robert Street North</address>
					<city>St. Paul</city>
					<state>MN</state>
					<postal>55101-1805</postal>
				</cntaddr>
				<cntvoice>651.602.1561</cntvoice>
				<cntemail>jonathan.hoekenga@metc.state.mn.us</cntemail>
			</cntinfo>
		</distrib>
	</distinfo>
	<metainfo>
		<metd>20130628</metd>
		<metstdn>Minnesota Geographic Metadata Guidelines</metstdn>
		<metstdv>1.2</metstdv>
		<metextns>
			<onlink>http://www.gis.state.mn.us/stds/metadata.htm</onlink>
		</metextns>
		<metc>
			<cntinfo>
				<cntperp>
					<cntorg>Metropolitan Council</cntorg>
					<cntper>Jon Hoekenga</cntper>
				</cntperp>
				<cntpos>GIS System Administrator</cntpos>
				<cntaddr>
					<address>390 Robert Street North</address>
					<city>St. Paul</city>
					<state>MN</state>
					<postal>55101-1805</postal>
				</cntaddr>
				<cntvoice>651.602.1561</cntvoice>
				<cntemail>jonathan.hoekenga@metc.state.mn.us</cntemail>
			</cntinfo>
		</metc>
	</metainfo>
	<Esri>
		<ModDate>20120509</ModDate>
		<ModTime>15181100</ModTime>
	</Esri>
	<mdDateSt Sync="TRUE">20110811</mdDateSt>
	<spref>
		<horizsys>
			<planar>
				<gridsys>
					<gridsysn>Universal Transverse Mercator</gridsysn>
					<utm>
						<utmzone>15</utmzone>
					</utm>
				</gridsys>
				<planci>
					<plandu>meters</plandu>
				</planci>
			</planar>
			<geodetic>
				<horizdn>NAD83</horizdn>
				<ellips>GRS80</ellips>
			</geodetic>
		</horizsys>
	</spref>
</metadata>