<metadata>
	<idinfo>
		<citation>
			<citeinfo>
				<origin>Metropolitan Council</origin>
				<title catid="f89f5e0a-70a8-4469-be92-7802ac927eef">Transit Market Areas</title>
				<pubinfo>
					<publish>Metropolitan Council - Metro Transit</publish>
				</pubinfo>
				<pubdate>20130624</pubdate>
				<onlink>ftp://gisftp.metc.state.mn.us/TransitMarketAreas.zip</onlink>
			</citeinfo>
		</citation>
		<spdom>
			<bounding>
				<westbc>-94.012</westbc>
				<eastbc>-92.732</eastbc>
				<northbc>45.415</northbc>
				<southbc>44.471</southbc>
			</bounding>
		</spdom>
		<timeperd>
			<timeinfo>
				<sngdate>
					<caldate>20130624</caldate>
				</sngdate>
			</timeinfo>
			<current>This dataset is scheduled to be updated in 2013</current>
		</timeperd>
		<descript>
			<abstract>At the regional level, transit market areas approximate the level of transit service an area can support. The concept was initially developed in 1996 Transit Redesign to provide general guidelines on the mix of transit services that may be appropriate for a given area. This guidance is provided for broad regional context; appropriate transit services are defined through professional transit service planning processes.

The existing market area definitions identify four market areas, with area 1 having the highest densities and area 4 having the lowest densities. These market areas were developed in the 1996 Transit Redesign report produced by the Metropolitan Council.
In 2008, this measure was updated to better reflect census geography and to redefine areas of transit dependence (population over 16 minus available autos). Market index scores were aggregated to contiguous areas and adopted into the Metropolitan Council&#8217;s 2030 Transportation Policy Plan. 
			</abstract>
			<supplinf>Twin Cities 7 county metropolitan area.  This includes the counties of Anoka, Carver, Dakota, Hennepin, Ramsey, Scott and Washington.</supplinf>
			<purpose>To identify service levels and area can support</purpose>
		</descript>
		<status>
			<progress>Complete</progress>
			<update>As Needed</update>
		</status>
		<accconst>None</accconst>
		<useconst>None</useconst>
		<crossref>
			<citeinfo>
				<title>Transportation Analysis Zones</title>
			</citeinfo>
		</crossref>
		<ptcontac>
			<cntinfo>
				<cntperp>
					<cntorg>Metropolitan Council - Metro Transit</cntorg>
					<cntper>Charles Carlson</cntper>
				</cntperp>
				<cntpos>Senior Manager, BRT/Small Starts Projects</cntpos>
				<cntaddr>
					<address>707 16th Ave South</address>
					<city>Minneapolis</city>
					<state>MN</state>
					<postal>55101-1805</postal>
				</cntaddr>
				<cntvoice>612.349-7639</cntvoice>
				<cntemail>charles.carlson@metrotransit.org</cntemail>
			</cntinfo>
		</ptcontac>
	</idinfo>
	<distinfo>
		<distliab>NOTICE:  The Geographic Information System (GIS) Data to which this notice is attached are made available pursuant to the Minnesota Government Data Practices Act (Minnesota Statutes Chapter 13).  THE GIS DATA ARE PROVIDED TO YOU AS IS AND WITHOUT ANY WARRANTY AS TO THEIR PERFORMANCE, MERCHANTABILITY, OR FITNESS FOR ANY PARTICULAR PURPOSE.  The GIS Data were developed by the Metropolitan Council for its own internal business purposes.  The Metropolitan Council does not represent or warrant that the GIS Data or the data documentation are error-free, complete, current, or accurate.  You are responsible for any consequences resulting from your use of the GIS Data or your reliance on the GIS Data.  You should consult the data documentation for this particular GIS Data to determine the limitations of the GIS Data and the precision with which the GIS Data may depict distance, direction, location, or other geographic features.  If you transmit or provide the GIS Data (or any portion of it) to another user, it is recommended that the GIS Data include a copy of this disclaimer and this metadata.</distliab>
		<stdorder>
			<ordering>This dataset is distributed on the internet by clicking below after 'Online Linkage'.  Doing so will tell your browser to download a 'ZIP' file which will contain the following:

- ArcView shape files
- metadata for the dataset (.htm)
- NOTICE.RTF, an important notice about this dataset that can be read by any word processing software.

Additionally, this dataset is available for direct use via one or more map services.  More information about what a map service is can be found at http://www.datafinder.org/services/.  The specific map service and layer name for this dataset can be found by clicking the "Services" link for this dataset in the DataFinder Catalog at http://www.datafinder.org/catalog/ .</ordering>
		</stdorder>
		<distrib>
			<cntinfo>
				<cntperp>
					<cntorg>Metropolitan Council</cntorg>
					<cntper>Jon Hoekenga</cntper>
				</cntperp>
				<cntpos>GIS System Administrator</cntpos>
				<cntaddr>
					<address>390 Robert Street North</address>
					<city>St. Paul</city>
					<state>MN</state>
					<postal>55101-1805</postal>
				</cntaddr>
				<cntvoice>651.602.1561</cntvoice>
				<cntemail>jonathan.hoekenga@metc.state.mn.us</cntemail>
			</cntinfo>
		</distrib>
	</distinfo>
	<metainfo>
		<metd>20130624</metd>
		<metstdn>Minnesota Geographic Metadata Guidelines</metstdn>
		<metstdv>1.2</metstdv>
		<metextns>
			<onlink>http://www.mngeo.state.mn.us/committee/standards/mgmg/metadata.htm</onlink>
		</metextns>
		<metc>
			<cntinfo>
				<cntperp>
					<cntorg>Metropolitan Council</cntorg>
					<cntper>Jon Hoekenga</cntper>
				</cntperp>
				<cntpos>GIS System Administrator</cntpos>
				<cntaddr>
					<address>390 Robert Street North</address>
					<city>St. Paul</city>
					<state>MN</state>
					<postal>55101-1805</postal>
				</cntaddr>
				<cntvoice>651.602.1561</cntvoice>
				<cntemail>jonathan.hoekenga@metc.state.mn.us</cntemail>
			</cntinfo>
		</metc>
	</metainfo>
	<eainfo>
		<overview>
			<eaover>Market Areas:  Numerical market area designation</eaover>
		</overview>
	</eainfo>
	<dataqual>
		<lineage>
			<procstep>
				<procdesc>The base geography used to develop transit market areas is the 
census block group. Block groups were aggregated to census tracts, which roughly approximates transportation analysis zones (TAZs). Aggregation and smoothing applied to the geographies and may not match other data set boundaries.

				</procdesc>
			</procstep>
		</lineage>
	</dataqual>
	<spdoinfo>
		<direct>Vector</direct>
		<indspref />
		<mgmg3obj>polygon</mgmg3obj>
		<mgmg3til />
</spdoinfo>
	<spref>
		<horizsys>
			<planar>
				<gridsys>
					<gridsysn>Universal Transverse Mercator</gridsysn>
					<utm>
						<utmzone>15</utmzone>
					</utm>
				</gridsys>
				<planci>
					<plandu>meters</plandu>
				</planci>
			</planar>
			<geodetic>
				<horizdn>NAD83</horizdn>
				<ellips>GRS80</ellips>
			</geodetic>
		</horizsys>
	</spref>
</metadata>