<metadata><idinfo><citation><citeinfo><origin>Minnesota Department of Revenue</origin><pubdate>2009</pubdate><title catid="bd7e96e5-3579-41b3-bffc-585ee70ed64f">Twin Cities 7 County ZIP Codes </title><mgmg1cid>N/A</mgmg1cid><pubinfo><publish>Minnesota Department of Revenue</publish></pubinfo><onlink>ftp://gisftp.metc.state.mn.us/ZipCodesMNRev.zip</onlink></citeinfo></citation><descript><abstract>This layer defines the boundaries of United States Postal Service (USPS) ZIP code delivery areas.  These ZIP code areas are based on actual delivery areas used by mail carriers and geographically defined by Metro GIS parcel boundaries.  This differs from other commercially produced ZIP code areas which are generalized polygons based on  administrative subdivisions, main thoroughfares, or other topological features.</abstract><purpose>This layer was developed for the Streamlined Sales and Use Tax Agreement (SSUTA).  SSUTA requires precise ZIP code and taxing jurisdictions boundaries to determine tax liability.  For further information see, http://www.streamlinedsalestax.org.</purpose><supplinf>Twin Cities 7 County Metropolitan Area.  This includes the counties of Anoka, Carver, Dakota, Hennepin, Ramsey, Scott and Washington in Minnesota.</supplinf></descript><timeperd><timeinfo><sngdate><caldate>20090901</caldate></sngdate></timeinfo><current>The attributes and ZIP boundaries within this layer are up to date as of the currentness reference date above.</current></timeperd><status><progress>Complete</progress><update>As Needed</update></status><spdom><bounding><westbc>-94.012</westbc><eastbc>-92.732</eastbc><northbc>45.415</northbc><southbc>44.471</southbc></bounding></spdom><keywords><theme><themekt>None</themekt><themekey>United States Postal Service, USPS, ZIP, ZIP codes </themekey></theme><place><placekey>Twin Cities, Anoka County, Carver County, Dakota County, Hennepin County, Ramsey County, Scott County, Washington County</placekey></place></keywords><accconst>None</accconst><useconst>None</useconst><browse><browsed>Sample map showing the ZIP code layer</browsed></browse><native>MapInfo 9.5</native><crossref><citeinfo><title>None</title></citeinfo></crossref><ptcontac><cntinfo><cntperp><cntorg>Minnesota Revenue</cntorg><cntper>Brian Udell</cntper></cntperp><cntpos>Research Analyst - GIS</cntpos><cntaddr><addrtype> mailing and physical address </addrtype><address>600 Robert Street North</address><city>St. Paul</city><state>Minnesota</state><postal>55146-2230</postal></cntaddr><cntvoice>651-556-4930</cntvoice><cntfax>651-556-3103</cntfax><cntemail>brian.udell@state.mn.us</cntemail></cntinfo></ptcontac></idinfo><dataqual><attracc><attraccr>Attributes for all ZIP codes have been checked and are accurate as of the Currentness Reference date. </attraccr></attracc><logic>The dataset is topologically 'clean'.</logic><complete>Entire seven county geographic area is covered.</complete><posacc><horizpa><horizpar>The positional accuracy of the dataset has not been tested under the National Standards for Spatial Data Accuracy.</horizpar></horizpa></posacc><lineage><srcinfo><srcscale /></srcinfo><procstep><procdesc>Line work for the ZIP codes layer is derived primarily from the parcel layers for each county.  Each polygon was drawn using heads up digitizing.  In areas of ambiguity, due to non residential parcels, additional data sources were used to derive the line work.  This included the TLG street centerline data, the 2003 FSA Ortho-imagery, and the current Metropolitan Council city and township boundaries.

Parcel data from April 2009 was downloaded and appended into a single file.  This file was geocoded utilizing two geocoders, MapMarker v14 and ZP4.  The parcel addresses which matched and met the USPS designation of Delivery Point Validation (DPV) became the source for the ZIP polygons.  DPV addresses by definition return a 9 digit ZIP code.  A choropleth map was created using all DPV addresses and their 5 digit ZIP code.  This provided a visual representation of the actual 5 digit ZIP code delivery area used by the USPS.  The heads up digitizing was completed over this color coded map.
</procdesc></procstep><procstep><procdesc Sync="TRUE">Dataset copied.</procdesc><srcused Sync="TRUE">L:\Metadata\Layers\county_ctu</srcused><date Sync="TRUE">20080320</date><time Sync="TRUE">12050300</time></procstep><procstep><procdesc Sync="TRUE">Dataset copied.</procdesc><srcused Sync="TRUE">L:\Metadata\Layers\county_ctu</srcused><date Sync="TRUE">20080506</date><time Sync="TRUE">12083400</time></procstep></lineage></dataqual><spdoinfo><indspref>None</indspref><direct>Vector</direct><mgmg3obj>polygon shapes</mgmg3obj><mgmg3til>One layer for entire seven county region.</mgmg3til></spdoinfo><eainfo><overview><eaover>zip5:       5 digit ZIP identifier   Character      5
prefname:   Preferred ZIP name       Character     28
name2:      Additional name          Character     28
nametyp2:   ZIP code type            Character      3
name3:      Additional name          Character     28
nametyp3:   ZIP code type            Character      3
name4:      Additional name          Character     28
nametyp4:   ZIP code type            Character      3
name5:      Additional name          Character     28
nametyp5:   ZIP code type            Character      3
</eaover></overview></eainfo><distinfo><resdesc>ZIP Master</resdesc><distliab>NOTICE The Geographic Information System (GIS) Data to which this notice is attached are made available pursuant to the Minnesota Government Data Practices Act (Minnesota Statutes Chapter 13). THE GIS DATA ARE PROVIDED TO YOU AS IS AND WITHOUT ANY WARRANTY AS TO THEIR PERFORMANCE, MERCHANTABILITY, OR FITNESS FOR ANY PARTICULAR PURPOSE. The GIS Data were developed by Minnesota Revenue  for its own internal business purposes. Minnesota Revenue does not represent or warrant that the GIS Data or the data documentation are error-free, complete, current, or accurate. You are responsible for any consequences resulting from your use of the GIS Data or your reliance on the GIS Data. You should consult the data documentation for this particular GIS Data to determine the limitations of the GIS Data and the precision with which the GIS Data may depict distance, direction, location, or other geographic features. If you transmit or provide the GIS Data (or any portion of it) to another user, it is recommended that the GIS Data include a copy of this disclaimer and this metadata. </distliab><stdorder><digform><digtinfo><formname>Shapefile</formname><formvern>MapInfo Universal Transla</formvern><transize>1  MB for zip file.</transize></digtinfo></digform><ordering>This dataset is distributed on the internet by clicking below after 'Online Linkage'.  Doing so will tell your browser to download a 'ZIP' file which will contain the following:

- ArcView shape files
- metadata for the dataset (.htm)
- NOTICE.RTF, an important notice about this dataset that can be read by any word processing software.

 
Additionally, this dataset is available for direct use via one or more map services.  More information about what a web mapping service is can be found at http://www.datafinder.org/services/.  The specific map service and layer name for this dataset can be found by clicking the blue or green boxes under the map service column of the DataFinder Catalog at http://www.datafinder.org/catalog/ .</ordering></stdorder><distrib><cntinfo><cntperp><cntorg>Minnesota Revenue</cntorg><cntper>Brian Udell</cntper></cntperp><cntpos>Research Analyst - GIS</cntpos><cntaddr><addrtype> mailing and physical address </addrtype><address>600 Robert Street North</address><city>St. Paul</city><state>Minnesota</state><postal>55146-2230</postal></cntaddr><cntvoice>651-556-4930</cntvoice><cntfax>651-556-3103</cntfax><cntemail>brian.udell@state.mn.us</cntemail></cntinfo></distrib></distinfo><metainfo><metd>20120625</metd><metstdn>Minnesota Geographic Metadata Guidelines</metstdn><metstdv>1.2</metstdv><metextns><onlink>http://www.gis.state.mn.us/stds/metadata.htm</onlink></metextns><metc><cntinfo><cntperp><cntorg>Minnesota Revenue</cntorg><cntper>Brian Udell</cntper></cntperp><cntpos>Research Analyist - GIS</cntpos><cntaddr><addrtype> mailing and physical address </addrtype><address>600 Robert Street North</address><city>St. Paul</city><state>Minnesota</state><postal>55146-2230</postal></cntaddr><cntvoice>651-556-4930</cntvoice><cntfax>651-556-3103</cntfax><cntemail>brian.udell@state.mn.us</cntemail></cntinfo></metc></metainfo><Esri><ModDate>20091221</ModDate><ModTime>11122900</ModTime><CreaDate>20080506</CreaDate><CreaTime>12083400</CreaTime><SyncOnce>TRUE</SyncOnce><MetaID>{84A9E186-0664-425C-A8A1-6AB4D9F31FB5}</MetaID></Esri><mdDateSt Sync="TRUE">20091221</mdDateSt><distInfo><distributor><distorTran><onLineSrc><linkage Sync="TRUE">file://\\rafs\gis\devel\data_devel\ctu\Derivative_Dataset_Processing\county_ctu</linkage><protocol Sync="TRUE">Local Area Network</protocol></onLineSrc></distorTran></distributor></distInfo><spref><horizsys><planar><gridsys><gridsysn>Universal Transverse Mercator</gridsysn><utm><utmzone>15</utmzone></utm></gridsys><planci><plandu>meters</plandu></planci></planar><geodetic><horizdn>NAD83</horizdn><ellips>GRS80</ellips></geodetic></horizsys></spref></metadata>