<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?><!DOCTYPE metadata SYSTEM "http://www.fgdc.gov/metadata/fgdc-std-001-1998.dtd"[]><metadata><idinfo><citation><citeinfo><title>Transit Taxing District</title><origin>Metropolitan Council</origin><pubinfo><publish>Metropolitan Council</publish></pubinfo><pubdate>unpublished material</pubdate><onlink>https://gisdata.mn.gov/dataset/us-mn-state-metc-trans-transit-taxing-district</onlink></citeinfo></citation><descript><abstract>NOTE:  As part of the Omnibus Tax Bill which was listed as 2001 Special Session, Chapter 5, the transit taxing district is no longer used for tax assessment purposes.

NOTE: As of November 6, 2012 this boundary has changed due to boundary adjustment between Prior Lake and Spring Lake Township

The transit taxing district was the area in which all taxable property was assessed a tax to be used for payment of transit and paratransit services per Minn. Stat. 473.446.  This area was comprised of whole cities, townships and unorganized territories.

While the Transit Taxing District has not changed since 2001, additional communities have agreed to levy for transit capital, beginning in 2009.  For this reason, a new dataset was created and  is referred to as the Transit Capital Levy Communities.  For the most accurate list of communities that participate in the transit capital levy, please consult this dataset since the legislatively defined boundary has not changed but the communities that participate in transit capital levy have changed.</abstract><purpose>To depict the extent of the transit taxing district as established in the 2001 state legislation for general mapping and analysis purposes.</purpose><supplinf>Twin Cities 7 County Metropolitan Area.  This includes the counties of Anoka, Carver, Dakota, Hennepin, Ramsey, Scott and Washington in Minnesota.</supplinf></descript><timeperd><timeinfo><sngdate><caldate>20151001</caldate></sngdate></timeinfo><current>NOTE: As part of the Omnibus Tax Bill which was listed as 2001 Special Session, Chapter 5, the transit taxing district is no longer used for tax assessment purposes.  Thus the communities included in this dataset have not changed since 2001.

The city and township boundaries used to create this dataset were derived from the metro wide city and township boundary dataset: Counties and Cities &amp; Townships - Twin Cities Metropolitan Area. That dataset is updated on a quarterly basis. This dataset is then recreated quarterly from those boundaries. The time period of content date is the last update based on a municipality change.</current></timeperd><status><progress>Complete</progress><update>As needed</update></status><spdom><bounding><westbc>-93.697348</westbc><eastbc>-92.760689</eastbc><northbc>45.240721</northbc><southbc>44.627016</southbc></bounding></spdom><keywords><place><placekey>Twin Cities, Anoka County, Carver County, Dakota County, Hennepin County, Ramsey County, Scott County, Washington County</placekey></place><theme><themekey>transit taxing district, transit system, buses, Metro Transit, administrative boundaries, Transit Capita lLevy Communities</themekey><themekt>transit taxing district</themekt></theme></keywords><accconst>None</accconst><useconst>None</useconst><crossref><citeinfo><title>Transit Capital Levy Communities, Transit Routes, Counties and Cities &amp; Townships, Twin Cities Metropolitan Area</title></citeinfo></crossref><native>ArcGIS 9x</native><ptcontac><cntinfo><cntperp><cntorg>Metropolitan Council</cntorg><cntper>Rachel Wiken</cntper></cntperp><cntpos>GIS Technician</cntpos><cntaddr><addrtype>mailing and physical</addrtype><address>390 Robert Street North</address><city>St. Paul</city><state>MN</state><postal>55101-1805</postal></cntaddr><cntvoice>651.602.1572</cntvoice><cntemail>rachel.wiken@metc.state.mn.us</cntemail></cntinfo></ptcontac></idinfo><dataqual><attracc><attraccr>All cities have been verified to be in the transit taxing district.  Please note that communities not specifically identified in the original legislation do not show up in this dataset.  Communities who agree to levy for transit capital after 2001 are part of the Regional Transit Capital Communities dataset.</attraccr></attracc><logic>The dataset is topologically 'clean'.</logic><complete>Entire seven county geographic area is covered.</complete><posacc><horizpa><horizpar>Because this dataset is derived directly from the MetroGIS regional municipal boundary layer, it's positional accuracy is identical to the Counties and Cities &amp; Townships, Twin Cities Metropolitan Area dataset.  </horizpar></horizpa></posacc><lineage><procstep><procdesc>This layer was created by relating a table of municipalities within the Transit Taxing District to the municipal boundary layer and dissolving the boundaries.</procdesc></procstep><srcinfo><srcscale></srcscale></srcinfo></lineage></dataqual><spdoinfo><indspref>None</indspref><direct>Vector</direct><mgmg3obj></mgmg3obj><mgmg3til></mgmg3til></spdoinfo><eainfo><overview><eaover>None</eaover><eadetcit>None</eadetcit></overview></eainfo><distinfo><resdesc>TransitTaxingDistrict</resdesc><distliab>NOTICE:  The Geographic Information System (GIS) Data to which this notice is attached are made available pursuant to the Minnesota Government Data Practices Act (Minnesota Statutes Chapter 13).  THE GIS DATA ARE PROVIDED TO YOU AS IS AND WITHOUT ANY WARRANTY AS TO THEIR PERFORMANCE, MERCHANTABILITY, OR FITNESS FOR ANY PARTICULAR PURPOSE.  The GIS Data were developed by the Metropolitan Council for its own internal business purposes.  The Metropolitan Council does not represent or warrant that the GIS Data or the data documentation are error-free, complete, current, or accurate.  You are responsible for any consequences resulting from your use of the GIS Data or your reliance on the GIS Data.  You should consult the data documentation for this particular GIS Data to determine the limitations of the GIS Data and the precision with which the GIS Data may depict distance, direction, location, or other geographic features.  If you transmit or provide the GIS Data (or any portion of it) to another user, it is recommended that the GIS Data include a copy of this disclaimer and this metadata.</distliab><stdorder><digform><digtinfo><formname>Shapefile</formname><formvern>ArcGIS 9x</formvern><transize>0.7 Mb for zip file.</transize></digtinfo></digform><ordering>See Online Linkage Below</ordering></stdorder><distrib><cntinfo><cntperp><cntorg>Metropolitan Council</cntorg><cntper>Jon Hoekenga</cntper></cntperp><cntpos>GIS Specialist</cntpos><cntaddr><addrtype>mailing and physical</addrtype><address>390 Robert Street North</address><city>St. Paul</city><state>MN</state><postal>55101-1805</postal></cntaddr><cntvoice>651.602.1561</cntvoice><cntemail>jonathan.hoekenga@metc.state.mn.us</cntemail></cntinfo></distrib></distinfo><metainfo><metd>20151020</metd><metstdn>Minnesota Geographic Metadata Guidelines</metstdn><metstdv>1.2</metstdv><metextns><onlink>http://www.gis.state.mn.us/stds/metadata.htm</onlink></metextns><metc><cntinfo><cntperp><cntorg>Metropolitan Council</cntorg><cntper>Rachel Wiken</cntper></cntperp><cntpos>GIS Technician</cntpos><cntaddr><addrtype>mailing and physical</addrtype><address>390 Robert Street North</address><city>St. Paul</city><state>MN</state><postal>55101-1805</postal></cntaddr><cntvoice>651.602.1572</cntvoice><cntemail>rachel.wiken@metc.state.mn.us</cntemail></cntinfo></metc></metainfo><Esri><ModDate>20110729</ModDate><ModTime>15381000</ModTime></Esri><mdDateSt Sync="TRUE">20110729</mdDateSt><spref><horizsys><planar><gridsys><gridsysn>Universal Transverse Mercator</gridsysn><utm><utmzone>15</utmzone></utm></gridsys><planci><plandu>meters</plandu></planci></planar><geodetic><horizdn>NAD83</horizdn><ellips>GRS80</ellips></geodetic></horizsys></spref></metadata>