<metadata><idinfo><citation><citeinfo><origin>U.S. Department of Agriculture (USDA), Farm Service Agency (FSA), Aerial Photography Field Office (APFO)</origin><pubdate>20091001</pubdate><title>National Agricultural Imagery Program (NAIP), Minnesota, 2009,  Digital Orthorectified Images (DOQ)</title><mgmg1cid/><pubinfo><publish>Minnesota Geospatial Information Office (MnGeo)</publish></pubinfo><onlink>http://www.mngeo.state.mn.us/chouse/airphoto/naip09.html</onlink></citeinfo></citation><descript><abstract>This data set contains 3-band natural color imagery from the National Agricultural Imagery Program (NAIP). NAIP acquires digital ortho imagery during the agricultural growing seasons in the continental U.S. A primary goal of the NAIP program is to enable availability of ortho imagery within one year of acquisition.

The source files are 1 meter ground sample distance (GSD) ortho imagery rectified to a horizontal accuracy of within +/- 5 meters of reference digital ortho quarter quads (DOQQ's) from the National Digital Ortho Program (NDOP) or from NAIP. The tiling format of NAIP imagery is based on a 3.75' x 3.75' quarter quadrangle with a 300 meter buffer on all four sides. NAIP imagery is formatted to the UTM coordinate system using NAD83. NAIP imagery may contain as much as 10% cloud cover per tile.

This file was generated by compressing NAIP imagery that cover the county extent. MrSID compression was used. Target values for the compression ratio are (15:1).

(Note: The Minnesota Geospatial Information Office (MnGeo) has created this metadata record to describe the entire NAIP2009 dataset, using information from Farm Service Agency metadata. Each county file is accompanied by the original FSA metadata for that county.)</abstract><purpose>NAIP imagery is available for distribution within 60 days of the end of a flying season and is intended to provide current information of agricultural conditions in support of USDA farm programs. For USDA Farm Service Agency, the 1 meter GSD product provides an ortho image base for Common Land Unit boundaries and other data sets. The 1 meter NAIP imagery is generally acquired in projects covering full states in cooperation with state government and other federal agencies who use the imagery for a variety of purposes including land use planning and natural resource assessment. NAIP is also used for disaster response often providing the most current pre-event imagery.</purpose><supplinf>Minnesota</supplinf></descript><timeperd><timeinfo><sngdate><caldate>2009</caldate></sngdate></timeinfo><current>June through August 2009. See the  IDATE attribute in the accompanying seamline shapefile for each county to find out the date(s) that the source imagery was acquired.</current></timeperd><status><progress>Complete</progress><update>Irregular</update></status><spdom><bounding><westbc>-97.5</westbc><eastbc>-89.00</eastbc><northbc>49.5</northbc><southbc>43.0</southbc></bounding></spdom><keywords><theme><themekt>ISO 19115 Topic Category</themekt><themekey>imageryBaseMapsEarthCover, Digital Orthorectified Image, Digital Orthophoto Quad, Ortho, Orthophoto, DOQ, NAIP, Compliance, Air Photo, Air Photography, Aerial Photo, Aerial Photography</themekey></theme><place><placekey>Minnesota, MN</placekey></place></keywords><accconst>None</accconst><useconst>The Aerial Photography Field Office asks to be credited in derived products.

If defects are found in the NAIP imagery during the warranty period such as horizontal offsets, replacement imagery may be provided. Imagery containing defects that require the acquisition of new imagery, such as excessive cloud cover, specular reflectance, etc., will not be replaced within a NAIP project year.

MnGeo's Redistribution Conditions: If you obtain data from MnGeo, it is understood that you and/or your organization have the right to use them for any internal purpose. If you modify them, you should document those changes in a metadata record that should accompany all redistributed data.  If you transmit or provide these data in any form to another user, the data MUST be accompanied by a copy of MnGeo's disclaimer NOTICE.TXT and all documentation provided with the original data set including the full metadata record.</useconst><browse><browsen>None available</browsen></browse><native>Microsoft Windows 2000 Version 5.0 (Build 2195) Service Pack 6; ESRI ArcCatalog 9.2</native><crossref><citeinfo><title>A shapefile, with its associated metadata, is included with this dataset. It shows seamline polygons delineating the boundary between DOQQ imagery used in the creation of the county NAIP file and attributes such as the source date of the imagery.

For information on other air photos available for Minnesota, including other years of NAIP imagery, see  http://www.mngeo.state.mn.us/chouse/airphoto/index.html</title></citeinfo></crossref><ptcontac><cntinfo><cntperp><cntorg>USDA-FSA</cntorg><cntper>Aerial Photography Field Office</cntper></cntperp><cntaddr><addrtype>Mailing and Physical</addrtype><address>2222 West 2300 South</address><city>Salt Lake City</city><state>UT</state><postal>84119-2020</postal></cntaddr><cntvoice>801-956-2922</cntvoice><cntfax>801-956-3653</cntfax><cntemail>apfo.sales@slc.usda.gov</cntemail></cntinfo></ptcontac></idinfo><dataqual><attracc><attraccr>NAIP imagery may contain as much as 10% cloud cover per tile.</attraccr></attracc><logic>N/A</logic><complete>No report.</complete><posacc><horizpa><horizpar>FSA Digital Orthophoto Specs. The quarter-quad files are 1 meter ground sample distance (GSD) ortho imagery rectified to a horizontal accuracy of within 5 meters of reference digital ortho quarter quads (DOQQ's) from the National Digital Ortho Program (NDOP) or from NAIP.</horizpar></horizpa><vertacc><vertaccr>N/A</vertaccr></vertacc></posacc><lineage><srcinfo><srcscale/></srcinfo><procstep><procdesc>No report.</procdesc></procstep></lineage></dataqual><spdoinfo><indspref/><direct>Raster</direct><mgmg3obj/><mgmg3til>County</mgmg3til></spdoinfo><spref><vertdef><altsys><altdatum>not applicable</altdatum></altsys><depthsys><depthdn>not applicable</depthdn></depthsys></vertdef><horizsys><planar><gridsys><gridsysn>Universal Transverse Mercator</gridsysn><utm><utmzone>15</utmzone></utm></gridsys><planci><plandu>meters</plandu><coordrep><absres>1</absres><ordres>1</ordres></coordrep></planci></planar><geodetic><horizdn>NAD83</horizdn><ellips>GRS80</ellips></geodetic></horizsys></spref><eainfo><overview><eaover>Imagery has 24-bit pixels, 3 band color, reg, green, blue (RGB), represent brightness values 0 - 255.</eaover><eadetcit>None</eadetcit></overview></eainfo><distinfo><resdesc>NAIP 2009</resdesc><distliab>1.  FSA Liability Statement:  In no event shall the creators, custodians, or distributors of this information be liable for any damages arising out of its use (or the inability to use it).

2.  MnGeo's data disclaimer is online: http://www.mngeo.state.mn.us/chouse/disclaimer.html</distliab><stdorder><digform><digtinfo><formname>MrSID</formname><formvern/><transize>Varies by county. Each county file is several hundred megabytes; the size is listed on the download page. Large counties may be distributed as 2 or more files.</transize></digtinfo></digform><ordering>The county mosaics are available free online by clicking below after Online Linkage.  This link will take you to a webpage that explains more about the MrSID file format and contains direct links to:

1. View the files seamlessly via a WMS service without having to download the files.

2. Download each county file from either MnGeo or the Natural Resources Conservation Service. The files will be in either UTM zone 14 or 15, depending on which zone covers the majority of the county. </ordering></stdorder><distrib><cntinfo><cntperp><cntorg>Minnesota Geospatial Information Office (MnGeo)</cntorg><cntper>Nancy Rader</cntper></cntperp><cntpos>GIS Data Coordinator</cntpos><cntaddr><addrtype>mailing and physical</addrtype><address>658 Cedar Street</address><city>St. Paul</city><state>MN</state><postal>55155</postal></cntaddr><cntvoice>651-201-2489</cntvoice><cntemail>gisinfo.mngeo@state.mn.us</cntemail></cntinfo></distrib></distinfo><metainfo><metd>20141027</metd><metstdn>Minnesota Geographic Metadata Guidelines</metstdn><metstdv>1.2</metstdv><metextns><onlink>http://www.mngeo.state.mn.us/committee/standards/mgmg/metadata.htm</onlink></metextns><metc><cntinfo><cntperp><cntorg>Minnesota Geospatial Information Office (MnGeo)</cntorg><cntper>Nancy Rader</cntper></cntperp><cntpos>GIS Data Coordinator</cntpos><cntaddr><addrtype>mailing and physical</addrtype><address>658 Cedar Street</address><city>St. Paul</city><state>MN</state><postal>55155</postal></cntaddr><cntvoice>651-201-2489</cntvoice><cntemail>gisinfo.mngeo@state.mn.us</cntemail></cntinfo></metc></metainfo><Esri><ModDate>20091211</ModDate><ModTime>11550500</ModTime></Esri><mdDateSt Sync="TRUE">20091211</mdDateSt></metadata>