<metadata><idinfo><citation><citeinfo><origin>U.S. Geological Survey</origin><pubdate>2003-09-01 00:00:00.0</pubdate><title>NLCD 2001 Land Cover</title><mgmg1cid/><pubinfo><publish>Minnesota Department of Natural Resources (DNR)</publish></pubinfo><onlink>http://gisdata.mn.gov/dataset/biota-landcover-nlcd-mn-2001</onlink></citeinfo></citation><descript><abstract>The National Land Cover Database 2001 for Minnesota was produced through a cooperative project conducted by the Multi-Resolution Land Characteristics (MRLC) Consortium. One of the primary goals of the project is to generate a current, consistent, seamless, and accurate National Land cover Database (NLCD) circa 2001 for the United States at medium spatial resolution. This landcover map and all documents pertaining to it are considered "provisional" until a formal accuracy assessment can be conducted. For a detailed definition and discussion on MRLC and the NLCD 2001 products, refer to Homer et al. (2004).

Three layers are included:
- Land Cover (mapping zones 31-51)
- Imperviousness Surface (mapping zones 39, 40-42, and 50-51)
- Tree Canopy (mapping zones 39-42, 50-51)</abstract><purpose>The goal of this project is to provide the Nation with complete, current and consistent public domain information on its land use and land cover. Imperviousness relates to the degree to which land is impervious to water runoff. Undeveloped land has no (or very little) imperviousness. Development such as roads, sidewalks, driveways, homes, increases the imperviousness of the land.</purpose><supplinf>Minnesota</supplinf></descript><timeperd><timeinfo><sngdate><caldate>1990-09-23 / 2004-07-26</caldate></sngdate></timeinfo><current>ground condition

- Land Cover: 1999-10-31 / 2003-07-18
- Imperviousness: 1990-09-23 / 2004-07-26
- Tree Canopy: 1999-04-28/2004-07-26</current></timeperd><status><progress>In work</progress><update>As needed</update></status><spdom><bounding><westbc>-96.925259</westbc><eastbc>-89.225883</eastbc><northbc>49.366132</northbc><southbc>43.375491</southbc></bounding></spdom><keywords><theme><themekey>Land Cover, U.S. Geological Survey, USGS, digital spatial data, Base Maps, Earth Cover, tree canopy, imagery</themekey></theme><place><placekey>United States, U.S., US, Minnesota, MN, South Dakota, SD, North Dakota, ND, Iowa, IA, Michigan, MI, Wisconsin, WI, Illinois, IL, Indiana, IN, Great Lakes</placekey></place></keywords><accconst>None</accconst><useconst>None</useconst><native>Arc/Info Grid</native><browse><browsen>ftp://gdrs.dnr.state.mn.us/gdrs/data/pub/us_mn_state_dnr/biota_landcover_nlcd_mn_2001/metadata/preview.jpg</browsen></browse><ptcontac><cntinfo><cntperp><cntorg>U.S. Geological Survey</cntorg><cntper>Cutomer Service  Representative</cntper></cntperp><cntaddr><addrtype>Mailing and Physical</addrtype><address>USGS/EROS
47914 252nd Street</address><city>Sioux Falls</city><state>SD</state><postal>57198-0001</postal></cntaddr><cntvoice>(605) 594-6151</cntvoice><cntfax>(605) 594-6589</cntfax><cntemail>custserv@usgs.gov</cntemail></cntinfo></ptcontac></idinfo><dataqual><logic>Not Applicable</logic><complete>Complete over the State of Minnesota</complete><posacc><horizpa><horizpar>Not Applicable</horizpar></horizpa><vertacc><vertaccr>Not Applicable
</vertaccr></vertacc></posacc><lineage><srcinfo><srcscale>Source layer nlcd_mnisra2:  0
</srcscale></srcinfo></lineage></dataqual><spdoinfo><indspref/><direct>raster</direct><mgmg3obj>grid</mgmg3obj><mgmg3til>state</mgmg3til></spdoinfo><spref><vertdef><altsys><altdatum>Not Applicable</altdatum><altunits>Not Applicable</altunits></altsys><depthsys><depthdn>Not Applicable</depthdn><depthdu>Not Applicable</depthdu></depthsys></vertdef><horizsys><planar><gridsys><gridsysn>Universal Transverse Mercator</gridsysn><utm><utmzone>15</utmzone></utm></gridsys><planci><plandu>meters</plandu><coordrep><absres>30</absres><ordres>30</ordres></coordrep></planci></planar><geodetic><horizdn>NAD83</horizdn><ellips>GRS80</ellips></geodetic></horizsys></spref><eainfo><detailed><enttyp><enttypl>nlcd_mn_2001_imperviousness</enttypl><enttypd>This table provides information on the band colors for the Minnesota Imperviousness layer.</enttypd></enttyp><attr><attrlabl>VALUE</attrlabl><attrdef>Percent Imperviousness</attrdef><attrdomv><edom><edomv>0-100</edomv><edomvd>Percent Impervious Surface</edomvd></edom></attrdomv><attrdomv><edom><edomv>127</edomv><edomvd>No Data</edomvd></edom></attrdomv></attr><attr><attrlabl>COUNT</attrlabl><attrdef>A nominal integer value that designates the number of pixels that have each value in the file; histogram column in ERDAS Imagine raster attributes table</attrdef></attr></detailed><detailed><enttyp><enttypl>nlcd_mn_2001_land_cover</enttypl></enttyp><attr><attrlabl>VALUE</attrlabl><attrdef>Land Cover Class Code Value</attrdef><attrdomv><edom><edomv>11</edomv><edomvd>Open Water - All areas of open water, generally with less than 25% cover of vegetation or soil.</edomvd></edom></attrdomv><attrdomv><edom><edomv>21</edomv><edomvd>Developed, Open Space - Areas with a mixture of some constructed materials, but mostly vegetation in the form of lawn grasses, and impervious surfaces accounting for less than 20% of total cover. These areas most commonly include large-lot single-family housing units, parks, golf courses, and vegetation planted in developed settings for recreation, erosion control, or aesthetic purposes.</edomvd></edom></attrdomv><attrdomv><edom><edomv>22</edomv><edomvd>Developed, Low Intensity - Areas with a mixture of constructed materials and vegetation, impervious surfaces accounting for 20-49% of total cover. These areas most commonly include single-family housing units.</edomvd></edom></attrdomv><attrdomv><edom><edomv>23</edomv><edomvd>Developed, Medium Intensity - Areas with a mixture of constructed materials and vegetation, impervious surfaces accounting for 50-79% of the total cover. These areas most commonly include single-family housing units.</edomvd></edom></attrdomv><attrdomv><edom><edomv>24</edomv><edomvd>Developed, High Intensity - Highly developed areas where people live or work in high numbers, including apartment complexes, row houses and commercial/industrial zones. Impervious surfaces account for 80-100% of total cover.</edomvd></edom></attrdomv><attrdomv><edom><edomv>31</edomv><edomvd>Barren Land (Rock/Sand/Clay) - Bedrock, desert pavement, scarps, talus, slides, volcanic material, glacial debris, sand dunes, strip mines, gravel pits and other accumulations of earthen material. Vegetation generally accounts for less than 15% of total cover.</edomvd></edom></attrdomv><attrdomv><edom><edomv>41</edomv><edomvd>Deciduous Forest - Dominated by trees generally over 5 meters tall, and more than 20% of total vegetation cover. More than 75% of the tree species shed foliage simultaneously in response to seasonal change.</edomvd></edom></attrdomv><attrdomv><edom><edomv>42</edomv><edomvd>Evergreen Forest - Dominated by trees generally over 5 meters tall, and more than 20% of total vegetation cover. More than 75% of the tree species remain in leaf all year. Canopy is never without green foliage.</edomvd></edom></attrdomv><attrdomv><edom><edomv>43</edomv><edomvd>Mixed Forest - Dominated by trees generally over 5 meters tall, and more than 20% of total vegetation cover. Neither deciduous nor evergreen species are more than 75% of total tree cover.</edomvd></edom></attrdomv><attrdomv><edom><edomv>52</edomv><edomvd>Shrub/Scrub - Areas dominated by shrubs under 5 meters tall with shrub canopy typically more than 20% of total vegetation. This class includes true shrubs, young trees in an early successional stage or trees stunted from environmental conditions.</edomvd></edom></attrdomv><attrdomv><edom><edomv>71</edomv><edomvd>Grassland/Herbaceous - Areas dominated by graminoid or herbaceous vegetation, generally more than 80% of total vegetation. These areas are not subject to intensive management or tilling, but can be utilized for grazing.</edomvd></edom></attrdomv><attrdomv><edom><edomv>81</edomv><edomvd>Pasture/Hay - Areas of grasses, legumes, or grass-legume mixtures planted for livestock grazing or production of seed or hay crops, typically on a perennial cycle. Pasture/hay accounts for more than 20% of total vegetation.</edomvd></edom></attrdomv><attrdomv><edom><edomv>82</edomv><edomvd>Cultivated Crops - Areas used for the production of annual crops, such as corn, soybeans, vegetables, tobacco, and cotton, and also perennial woody crops such as orchards and vineyards. Crop vegetation accounts for more than 20% of total vegetation. Includes all land being actively tilled.</edomvd></edom></attrdomv><attrdomv><edom><edomv>90</edomv><edomvd>Woody Wetlands - Areas where forest or shrub land vegetation accounts for more than 20% of vegetative cover and the soil or substrate is periodically saturated with or covered with water.</edomvd></edom></attrdomv><attrdomv><edom><edomv>95</edomv><edomvd>Emergent Herbaceous Wetlands - Areas where perennial herbaceous vegetation accounts for more than 80% of vegetative cover and the soil or substrate is periodically saturated with or covered with water.</edomvd></edom></attrdomv></attr><attr><attrlabl>COUNT</attrlabl><attrdef>A nominal integer value that designates the number of pixels that have each value in the file; histogram column in ERDAS Imagine raster attributes table</attrdef></attr><attr><attrlabl>RED</attrlabl><attrdef>Red color code for RGB slice by value for canopy image display purposes. The value is arbitrarily assigned by the display software package, unless defined by user. Standard user defined ramp for NLCD project is start color light gray, end color red.</attrdef></attr><attr><attrlabl>GREEN</attrlabl><attrdef>Green color code for RGB slice by value for canopy image display purposes. The value is arbitrarily assigned by the display software package, unless defined by user. Standard user defined ramp for NLCD project is start color light gray, end color green.</attrdef></attr><attr><attrlabl>BLUE</attrlabl><attrdef>Blue color code for RGB slice by value for canopy image display purposes. The value is arbitrarily assigned by the display software package, unless defined by user. Standard user defined ramp for NLCD project is start color light gray, end color blue.</attrdef></attr><attr><attrlabl>OPACITY</attrlabl><attrdef>A measure of how opaque, or solid, a color is displayed in a layer.</attrdef></attr><attr><attrlabl>SHORT_DEF</attrlabl><attrdef>Land Cover Class Code Short Description</attrdef></attr><attr><attrlabl>LONG_DEF</attrlabl><attrdef>Land Cover Class Code Long Description</attrdef></attr></detailed><detailed><enttyp><enttypl>nlcd_mn_2001_tree_canopy</enttypl></enttyp><attr><attrlabl>COUNT</attrlabl><attrdef>A nominal integer value that designates the number of pixels that have each value in the file; histogram column in ERDAS Imagine raster attributes table</attrdef></attr><attr><attrlabl>VALUE</attrlabl><attrdef>Percent Canopy</attrdef></attr></detailed></eainfo><distinfo><resdesc>biota_landcover_nlcd_mn_2001</resdesc><distliab>The Minnesota Department of Natural Resources General Geographic Data License Agreement is online: http://www.dnr.state.mn.us/sitetools/data_software_license.html</distliab><stdorder><digform><digtinfo><formname>Arc/Info Grid</formname><formvern>9.2</formvern><transize>1024</transize></digtinfo></digform><ordering>Please visit the download page for this dataset on the Minnesota Geospatial Commons website using the web link below (Online Linkage).</ordering></stdorder><distrib><cntinfo><cntperp><cntorg>Minnesota Department of Natural Resources</cntorg><cntper>Zeb Thomas</cntper></cntperp><cntpos>GIS Data Systems Coordinator</cntpos><cntaddr><address>500 Lafayette Rd</address><city>Saint Paul</city><state>MN</state><postal>55155</postal></cntaddr><cntvoice>651-259-5637</cntvoice><cntemail>zeb.thomas@state.mn.us</cntemail></cntinfo></distrib></distinfo><metainfo><metd>20141023</metd><metstdn>Minnesota Geographic Metadata Guidelines</metstdn><metstdv>1.2</metstdv><metextns><onlink>http://www.mngeo.state.mn.us/committee/standards/mgmg/metadata.htm</onlink></metextns><metc><cntinfo><cntperp><cntorg>U.S. Geological Survey</cntorg><cntper>Cutomer Service  Representative</cntper></cntperp><cntaddr><addrtype>Mailing and Physical</addrtype><address>USGS/EROS
47914 252nd Street</address><city>Sioux Falls</city><state>SD</state><postal>57198-0001</postal></cntaddr><cntvoice>(605) 594-6151</cntvoice><cntfax>(605) 594-6589</cntfax><cntemail>custserv@usgs.gov</cntemail></cntinfo></metc></metainfo></metadata>