<metadata><idinfo><citation><citeinfo><origin>Minnesota Geospatial Information Office (MnGeo)</origin><pubdate>2004</pubdate><title>Minnesota's Original Public Land Survey (PLS) Maps - Conversion to Digital Images (TIFF, JPEG and PDF formats)</title><mgmg1cid/><pubinfo><publish>Minnesota Office of the Secretary of State and MnGeo</publish></pubinfo><onlink>http://www.lmic.state.mn.us/glo</onlink></citeinfo></citation><descript><abstract>This dataset includes high quality (800 Dots Per Inch - DPI), 24 bit color images of Minnesota's original Public Land Survey (PLS) plats created during the first government land survey of the state from 1848 to 1907. Currently housed at the Office of the Secretary of State, these plats were created by the U.S. Surveyor General's Office. This collection of more than 3,600 maps also includes later General Land Office (GLO) and the Bureau of Land Management (BLM) maps - up to the year 2001. 

Minnesota's survey plat maps serve as the fundamental legal records for real estate in the state; all property titles and descriptions stem from them. They also serve as an essential resource for surveyors and as an analytical tool for the state's physical geography prior to European settlement. Finally, they serve as a testimony to years and years of hard work by the surveying community, often under challenging conditions. 

In recent years the deteriorating physical condition of the older maps and the needs of technologically more sophisticated researchers, who require access to the maps, have made handling the original paper records increasingly less practical. To meet this challenge, the Office of the Secretary of State, the State Archives of the Minnesota Historical Society, the Minnesota Department of Transportation, MnGeo (formerly the Land Management Information Center - LMIC) and the Minnesota Association of County Surveyors collaborated in a digitization project which produced images of the maps in standard TIFF, JPEG and PDF formats - nearly 1.5 terabytes worth of data.   Funding was provided by the Minnesota Department of Transportation.</abstract><purpose>Minnesota's Public Land Survey maps were converted to digital imagery due to: 

1. Protect the original maps from further deterioration.
2. Meet the needs of the more technologically sophisticated researchers by providing direct access to digital images.
3. Provide greater public access to the maps and the information they convey.</purpose><supplinf>Minnesota, Statewide</supplinf></descript><timeperd><current>The original map documents (3,609) were scanned and saved in a variety of digital formats (TIFF, JPEG and PDF) formats during the period of May through August, 2003. These maps range in date from 1848 through 2002.</current></timeperd><status><progress>Complete</progress><update>Irregular</update></status><spdom><bounding><westbc>-97.5</westbc><eastbc>-89.0</eastbc><northbc>49.5</northbc><southbc>43.0</southbc></bounding></spdom><keywords><theme><themekt>ISO 19115 Topic Category</themekt><themekey>planningCadastre, Original Survey Maps, GLO Maps, Plat Maps, Public Land Survey,  Cultural Features, General Land Office</themekey></theme><place><placekey>Minnesota, MN, Statewide, Township, Range</placekey></place></keywords><accconst>None</accconst><useconst>These images have NOT been certified by the Minnesota Office of the Secretary of State as exact, digital copies of the original source documents. These images are NOT geo-referenced.</useconst><browse><browsen>ftp://ftp.lmic.state.mn.us/pub/data/admin_poli/browseglo.gif</browsen><browsed>A portion of Township 48, Range 16 W. (Jay Cook State Park) at 800 DPI, dated 1858 (MHS ID: 390)</browsed></browse><native>TIFF</native><crossref><citeinfo><title>1. The original survey maps (paper, linen, etc.,) of Minnesota are currently housed at the Minnesota Office of the Secretary of State.
2. The original surveyors field notes are housed at the Minnesota Historical Society
3. GIS files derived from original survey information are available from the Minnesota Department of Natural Resources:
a.)  Bearing trees used as references of landmarks during the original Minnesota Public Land Survey http://deli.dnr.state.mn.us/metadata/pveg_btreept3.html 
b.) Public Land Survey Corners with Presettlement Vegetation information - http://deli.dnr.state.mn.us/metadata/pveg_btvegpt3.html 
c.) Marschner's Original Presettlement Vegetation Map of Minnesota - http://deli.dnr.state.mn.us/metadata/pveg_mrschpy1.html</title></citeinfo></crossref><ptcontac><cntinfo><cntperp><cntorg>Minnesota Historical Society (MHS)</cntorg></cntperp><cntaddr><addrtype>Mailing and Physical</addrtype><address>345 Kellogg Blvd W</address><city>St. Paul</city><state>MN</state><postal>55102</postal></cntaddr><cntvoice>651-259-3300</cntvoice><cntfax>651-297-7436</cntfax><cntemail>reference@mnhs.org</cntemail></cntinfo></ptcontac></idinfo><dataqual><complete>Every effort was made to ensure that all available PLS plat maps for Minnesota were scanned and that every township in the state was accounted for. For townships in adjacent states that border Minnesota, please contact the appropriate state agency.</complete><lineage><srcinfo><srcscale/></srcinfo><procstep><procdesc>Step 1. MAP INVENTORY AND PROJECT MANAGEMENT 

The digitization process began first with an inventory of the map collection currently stored at the Minnesota Office of the Secretary of State (SOS). The inventory was conducted by the Minnesota Historical Society's (MHS) State Archives staff during the summer of 2002. Each map was examined and assigned (and marked - on the back) a unique MHS ID. 

Step 2. SCANNING 

In late 2002, the Minnesota Department of Transportation (MnDOT) contracted with the Minnesota Department of Administration's Land Management Information Center (LMIC, now MnGeo) to prepare the scanning bid specifications (working with Administration's Contract Management Division), oversee the scanning process and provide final QA/QC support and create PDF versions of the scanned maps. A contract to scan the maps was awarded to: 

Access Imagery Inc. 
1180 South 800 East 
Orem, UT 84097 

Tel: 1-800-687-1265 

Access Imagery performed all scanning at the Office of the Secretary of State. Access Imagery's project manager was Scott Wheelhouse; principal scanning operator was Lee Ann Lavender. 

During the period of May through July of 2003, Access Imagery Inc. scanned 3,605 maps using the following equipment and specifications: 

Files: 3,605 (of 3,609) maps were scanned by Access Imagery Inc. 

Scanner: Vidar TruScan Atlas Color Scanner, 40 wide-format scanner 
4WD&amp;#174; document transport (top and bottom traction) 
Geometric accuracy of the document transport mechanism = +/-0.10% 
3 Charge-Coupled Device (CCD) Cameras - 4 rows of sensors per CCD (R/G/B/Grayscale) 
5333 pixels per CCD row 
Direct optical path from scan aperture to cameras, no mirrors 
Small Computer System Interface (SCSI)-2 interface 

Scanner Software: Vidar TruScan2 ver. 1.2.4.5 with Vidar SCSI Toolkit ver. 2.2 

Resolution: 800 Dots Per Inch (DPI) horizontal (interpolated) x 800 DPI vertical (optical) 

Color Output: scanned at 36-bit Red-Green-Blue (RGB), color output = 24-bit RGB 

Product #1: TIFF images 

File Processing - TIFF: Each image was de-skewed using the Image &gt; 
Rotate Canvas &gt; Arbitrary option within Adobe PhotoShop 7. The measure 
tool allows the user to mark a vertical or horizontal line and automatically 
populates the rotate option with the appropriate correction value. 

File Storage - TIFF: Images were saved on local hard drives and later written to DVD (two copies) using a Primera Bravo Disc Publisher and Veritas' Prassi PrimoDVD ver. 2.0.837 software. DVD Media was Mitsui 4x speed, 4.7GB, white, inkjet printable, Ver. 2.0 spec, general purpose, silver DVD-R (Mitsui Part# 00041752). DVDs were labeled using a SureThing CD Labeler, Primera Edition, ver. 3.11. 

Product #2: JPEG images 

File Processing: JPEG: Using the TIFF file as the source, Access Imagery Inc. prepared a JPEG version of each image using the following procedures: 

Using Adobe PhotoShop 7.0, an Unsharp Mask (USM) was applied to each TIFF image. USM settings could vary from map to map, as the appropriate level of USM is subjective. Baseline settings are given, with probable ranges in parentheses. 

Amount: 300% (200% - 500%) 
Radius: .3 pixels (.3 - .5 pixels) 
Threshold: 0 levels 

The enhanced image was then saved in a JPEG format using a Medium (5) compression. 

File Storage - JPEG: Images were saved on a Maxtor 250 gigabyte portable hard drive and later written to DVD (four copies) using a Primera Bravo Disc Publisher and Veritas' Prassi PrimoDVD ver. 2.0.837 software. DVD Media were Mitsui 4x speed, 4.7GB, white, inkjet printable, Ver. 2.0 spec, general purpose, silver DVD-R (Mitsui Part# 00041752). DVDs were labeled using a SureThing CD Labeler, Primera Edition, ver. 3.11. 

Step 3. QA/QC 

Access Imagery Inc.: All TIFF and JPEG images were reviewed for quality purposes prior to being burned to a DVD. Each of the 291 DVD-Rs containing TIFF images were verified by the Disc Publisher software with the exception of the last 35 which were manually loaded on a separate PC and visually reviewed for readability. This change was done to allow the burner to spend 100% of its time burning discs. A similar process was used for the 5 DVDs containing JPEG images. 

MnGeo: A random sample (~2%) of TIFF and JPEG images produced by Access Imagery was conducted by staff. This process included opening the file with Adobe Photoshop 6, enlarging the image (to actual pixel size) and panning around the image to ensure it met the quality specifications. During this review process, 15 corrupt DVDs containing TIFF images were discovered. Access Imagery staff returned to Minnesota in July, 2003 to rescan the affected maps. Corrected TIFF and JPEG DVDs were delivered to MnGeo in early August and re-checked. 

Step 4. MISCELLANEOUS SCANNING: 

A total of four maps were scanned by two other organizations (see the database for TIFF image source): 

During the quality control process conducted by MnGeo in early August, 2003, staff discovered that one map had not been scanned by Access Imagery staff. To save time, the map was sent to Historical Information Gatherers located in the Twin Cities and scanned using the following equipment and specification: 

Historical Information Gatherers, Inc. 
1589 Highway 7, Suite B-2 
Hopkins, MN 55305 

Tel: 952-253-2004 

File: t101r45w5fi0.tif (Township 101, Range 45 West, 5th Principal Meridian) 

Scanner: Titan Atlas 12mm Color Scanner consisting of Tri-linear CCD arrays 

Scanning software: Vidar TruScan version 1.4.2 

Resolution: Optical 400 dpi (horizontal / vertical). The image was interpolated to be 500 dpi (horizontal / vertical) 

Color output : 24 bit 

Product #1: TIFF (unaltered) 

File Processing (TIFF): MnGeo staff cropped the raw TIFF file from HIG using Adobe Photoshop 6. No de-skewing was performed. 

File Storage - TIFF: Images were saved on a local hard drive and later written to a DVD (two copies) using a Primera Composer Pro DVD writer, Prassi version 2 software. DVD Media was Mitsui 4x speed, 4.7GB, white, inkjet printable, general purpose, silver DVD-R (Mitsui Part# 00041752). DVDs were labeled using a Primera's Signature Pro labeler.

Product #2: JPEG 

File Processing JPEG: MnGeo staff used Adobe PhotoShop 6.0 to create the JPEG version. First a Sharpen filter (regular) was applied to the cropped TIFF file and saved as a JPEG (medium; Level 5). 

File Storage - JPEG: Images were saved on a Maxtor 250 gigabyte portable hard drive and later written to a DVD (four copies) using a Primera Composer Pro DVD writer, Prassi version 2 software. DVD Media was Mitsui 4x speed, 4.7GB, white, inkjet printable, general purpose, silver DVD-R (Mitsui Part# 00041752). DVDs were labeled using a Primera's Signature Pro labeler.

Minnesota Historical Society (MHS) 

During the inventory conducted by MHS staff and subsequent work performed by Access Imagery, it became apparent that the original survey maps for three townships in Minnesota were missing from the Office of the Secretary of State's map drawers. To complete the scanning project, hand drawn duplicates housed at the Minnesota Department of Natural Resources were scanned by MHS staff using the following specifications. 

Files: 

t041r23w4fi01 (Township 41, Range 23 West, 4th Principal Meridian) 
t156r51w5fi01 (Township 156, Range 51 West, 5th Principal Meridian) 
t160r35w5fi01 (Township 160, Range 35 West, 5th Principal Meridian) 

Scanner: Zeutschel Omniscan 5000, CCD-line with 5150 pixels 

Scanning software: Omniscan 5.0 

Resolution: Optical 300 dpi (horizontal / vertical). No interpolation was performed. 

Color output : 8 bit (256 levels) Grayscale 

Product #1: TIFF (unaltered) 

File Processing - TIFF: MnGeo staff cropped the raw TIFF file from HIG using Adobe Photoshop 6. No de-skewing was performed. 

File Storage - TIFF: Images were saved on local hard drives and later written to a DVD (four copies) using a Primera Composer Pro DVD writer, Prassi version 2 software. DVD Media was Mitsui 4x speed, 4.7GB, white, inkjet printable, general purpose, silver DVD-R (Mitsui Part# 00041752). DVDs were labeled using a Primera's Signature Pro labeler.

Product #2: JPEG 

File Processing - JPEG: To create the JPEG and PDF versions, MnGeo staff applied a Sharpen filter (regular) to the cropped TIFF file which was then saved in a JPEG (medium; Level 5) format. 

File Storage - JPEG: Images were saved on a Maxtor 250 gigabyte portable hard drive and later written to a DVD (four copies) using a Primera Composer Pro DVD writer, Prassi version 2 software. DVD Media was Mitsui 4x speed, 4.7GB, white, inkjet printable, general purpose, silver DVD-R (Mitsui Part# 00041752). DVDs were labeled using a Primera's Signature Pro labeler.

QA/QC: MnGeo staff reviewed each image type during processing and publishing on DVD. 


Step 5. PDF IMAGE CREATION 

Files: All 3,609 JPEG images were converted by MnGeo staff from a JPEG to a PDF format. 

File Processing PDF: Two programs were used to convert the JPEG images a PDF format. JPG2PDF (a shareware product developed by SANFACE Software Version 2.4, 25th April 2002) was used to convert 3,369 JPEG images. Adobe PhotoShop 6.0 was used to convert 240 JPEG images using a medium (Level 5) compression. 

File Storage - PDF: Images were saved on a Maxtor 250 gigabyte portable hard drive and later written to a DVD (four copies) using a Primera Composer Pro DVD writer, Prassi version 2 software. DVD Media was Mitsui 4x speed, 4.7GB, white, inkjet printable, general purpose, silver DVD-R (Mitsui Part# 00041752). DVDs were labeled using a Primera's Signature Pro labeler. 

QA/QC: MnGeo staff visually reviewed 2% random sample of 3,609 PDF images. All 3,609 PDF images were opened with Adobe PhotoShop 6.0 in a batch operation.</procdesc></procstep></lineage></dataqual><spdoinfo><indspref/><direct>Raster</direct><mgmg3obj/><mgmg3til>Public Land Survey Township</mgmg3til></spdoinfo><eainfo><overview><eaover>The file is an image made up of a combination of features arranged cartographically. The individual elements such as roads and section lines cannot be extracted from the image.  See the lineage section of this document, step 1, for a description of the image attributes.</eaover></overview></eainfo><distinfo><resdesc>GLO Plat Maps</resdesc><distliab>MnGeo's data disclaimer is online: http://www.mngeo.state.mn.us/chouse/disclaimer.html </distliab><stdorder><digform><digtinfo><formname>JPEG, PDF</formname><formvern/><transize/></digtinfo></digform><ordering>1. Electronic PDF files of all images are available for download through an interactive selection tool at: www.lmic.state.mn.us/glo. 

2. For bulk downloads using FTP tools, browse:  ftp://ftp.lmic.state.mn.us/pub/data/basemaps/glo/

Files are organized by county.  Each directory contains:

- High-resolution PDF maps -- one township PDF map per zipfile.
- Low-resolution PDF version, in a directory folder labelled 'LowResolution'.
- Georeferenced JPG version, in a directory folder labelled 'Georeferenced'.

Note that there may be multiple versions per township in each of the above folders.

3. For printed copies or to order DVD collections, see details at:  http://www.mngeo.state.mn.us/glo/Order.htm</ordering></stdorder><distrib><cntinfo><cntperp><cntorg>Minnesota Geospatial Information Office (MnGeo)</cntorg><cntper>John Hoshal</cntper></cntperp><cntpos>Supervisor - GIS Project Services</cntpos><cntaddr><addrtype>mailing and physical</addrtype><address>658 Cedar Street</address><city>St. Paul</city><state>MN</state><postal>55155</postal></cntaddr><cntvoice>651-201-2482</cntvoice><cntemail>gisinfo.mngeo@state.mn.us</cntemail></cntinfo></distrib></distinfo><metainfo><metd>20141009</metd><metstdn>Minnesota Geographic Metadata Guidelines</metstdn><metstdv>1.2</metstdv><metextns><onlink>http://www.mngeo.state.mn.us/committee/standards/mgmg/metadata.htm</onlink></metextns><metc><cntinfo><cntperp><cntorg>Minnesota Geospatial Information Office (MnGeo)</cntorg><cntper>Nancy Rader</cntper></cntperp><cntpos>GIS Data Coordinator</cntpos><cntaddr><addrtype>mailing and physical</addrtype><address>658 Cedar Street</address><city>St. Paul</city><state>MN</state><postal>55155</postal></cntaddr><cntvoice>651-201-2489</cntvoice><cntemail>gisinfo.mngeo@state.mn.us</cntemail></cntinfo></metc></metainfo></metadata>