<!--  <!DOCTYPE metadata SYSTEM "metadata.dtd">  -->
<metadata>
  <idinfo>
    <citation>
      <citeinfo>
        <origin>Minnesota Department of Education</origin>
        <pubdate>20151029</pubdate>
        <title>School Program Locations, Minnesota, SY2015-2016</title>
        <mgmg1cid/>
        <pubinfo>
          <publish>Minnesota Department of Education</publish>
        </pubinfo>
        <ftname Sync="TRUE">schools1011</ftname>
        <geoform Sync="TRUE">vector digital data</geoform>
        <onlink>https://gisdata.mn.gov/dataset/struc-school-program-locs</onlink>
      </citeinfo>
    </citation>
    <descript>
      <abstract>The point locations of school programs are a result of an ongoing project to identify current school program locations where Food and Nutrition Services Office (FNS) programs are utilized. The FNS Office is in the Minnesota Department of Education (MDE).  GIS at MDE modified the data set using school building locations provided by the school districts and program locations from an MDE database. School District buildings are annually updated but there may remain errors due to the number of program locations and the frequency with which they move from building to building in a District.

The records in this dataset cover all school program locations that MDE currently has in a spatial format. Beginning in SY2009-10, separate files for different school programs (public, nonpublic, charter, and public school district center) were combined into one file and attributes are used to distinguish the school types.  Note that multiple programs may occur at the same location and are represented as separate points. For example, a junior and a senior high school may be in the same building, but each has a separate record and point in the data layer.</abstract>
      <purpose>MnGeo (formerly LMIC) and the Minnesota Department of Education have been in contact with Minnesota school districts since 1998, identifying school program locations. These locations are used by MDE to help identify where appropriate funds should be used for that school year. Beginning in 2006, MDE took over sole responsibility for all editing and metadata.</purpose>
      <supplinf>Minnesota</supplinf>
      <langdata Sync="TRUE">en</langdata>
    </descript>
    <timeperd>
      <current>School year 2015-2016</current>
      <timeinfo>
        <sngdate>
          <caldate>2015</caldate>
        </sngdate>
      </timeinfo>
    </timeperd>
    <status>
      <progress>Complete</progress>
      <update>Annually</update>
    </status>
    <spdom>
      <lboundng>
        <leftbc Sync="TRUE">190972.952900</leftbc>
        <rightbc Sync="TRUE">747256.479300</rightbc>
        <bottombc Sync="TRUE">4817260.998400</bottombc>
        <topbc Sync="TRUE">5468873.997700</topbc>
      </lboundng>
      <bounding>
        <westbc>-97.250680</westbc>
        <eastbc>-89.597207</eastbc>
        <northbc>49.372570</northbc>
        <southbc>43.444465</southbc>
      </bounding>
    </spdom>
    <keywords>
      <theme>
        <themekey>structure, school, public school, nonpublic school, non-public school, charter school, public school district center</themekey>
        <themekt>ISO 19115 Topic Category</themekt>
      </theme>
      <place>
        <placekey>Minnesota, MN</placekey>
      </place>
    </keywords>
    <accconst>None</accconst>
    <useconst>In obtaining this data from MDE and MnGeo, it is understood that you and/or your organization have the right to use it for any purpose.  If you modify it, you are encouraged to apply responsible best practices by documenting those changes in a metadata record.  If you transmit or provide the data to another user, it is your responsibility to provide appropriate content, limitation, warranty and liability information as you see fit.</useconst>
    <browse>
      <browsen>ftp://ftp.gisdata.mn.gov/pub/gdrs/data/pub/us_mn_state_mde/struc_school_program_locs/metadata/preview.jpg</browsen>
    </browse>
    <native>Microsoft Windows XP Version 5.1 (Build 2600) Service Pack 3; ESRI ArcCatalog 9.3.1.3500</native>
    <crossref>
      <citeinfo>
        <title>See related school datasets at:
http://www.mngeo.state.mn.us/chouse/metalong.html#admin</title>
      </citeinfo>
    </crossref>
    <natvform Sync="TRUE">Shapefile</natvform>
    <ptcontac>
      <cntinfo>
        <cntperp>
          <cntorg>Minnesota Department of Education</cntorg>
          <cntper>Scott Freburg</cntper>
        </cntperp>
        <cntpos>GIS Administrator</cntpos>
        <cntaddr>
          <addrtype>mailing and physical</addrtype>
          <address>1500 Hwy 36 W.</address>
          <city>Roseville</city>
          <state>MN</state>
          <postal>55113</postal>
        </cntaddr>
        <cntvoice>651-582-8789</cntvoice>
        <cntemail>scott.freburg@state.mn.us</cntemail>
      </cntinfo>
    </ptcontac>
  </idinfo>
  <dataqual>
    <attracc>
      <attraccr>Each school district checks the previous year's map for accuracy of school names, district boundaries and public school building locations. Locations are modified per request by the school district or through a process of checking locations against various sources (aerial photography, geocoding).

All other school locations (charters, nonpublic, post-secondary, etc.) were brought forward from database records at MDE and spatially located using address matching techniques and most current aerial photography (per previous paragraph).</attraccr>
    </attracc>
    <logic>Not applicable</logic>
    <complete>Public and non-public school program locations in Minnesota.</complete>
    <posacc>
      <horizpa>
        <horizpar>See Lineage.</horizpar>
      </horizpa>
    </posacc>
    <lineage>
      <srcinfo>
        <srcscale/>
      </srcinfo>
      <procstep>
        <procdesc>The Land Management Information Center (LMIC, now MnGeo) created this data set for the Food and Nutrition Services Office (FNS) of the Minnesota Department of Education to help MDE determine eligibility status in the FNS food programs.

In 1998-99, LMIC provided maps to school districts and asked the districts to locate school buildings.  LMIC then digitized these points and added the school names that appeared on the maps to the database.  In order to add the ID used by CFL, LMIC obtained the public school database from the CFL webpage, rawdata.html, on 6/19/99.  It contained 2192 school site records.  The schools that were digitized from the maps were matched to the records in the public school database.  For those records that did not match any point, a point location was determined.  A variety of methods were used to locate these records including phone calls to the schools and address matching.

Note that these CFL records are for school programs and not school buildings.  Multiple programs may occur at the same location and are represented as separate points.  For example, a K-6 program and an alternative learning center, or a junior and a senior high school, may be in the same building, but each has a separate record and ID in the CFL database.  They will, therefore, have separate points in the data layer.  The records cover traditional K-12 programs as well as alternative learning centers and other special programs.

As part of the FNS project, the school districts have been asked each year to provide any changes to the educational facilities. The changes may include elimination of school programs no longer in service, the addition of new school programs and the correction of the program locations. School districts have been the main source for annual changes to the traditional K-12 program locations.

Each year, LMIC made the changes provided by the school districts to the point file (the work for SY2002-2003 started with the SY1999-2000 database). In addition, the CFL public school database was retrieved from the CFL web site. All of the programs that matched by the ID_STRING to this database were identified. For the traditional K-12 programs, the attributes such as ID, address, school class and grades were compared to the CFL database. If there were any new traditional K-12 programs which were not provided by the school districts, a point location was determined and added to the data layer. All other programs that did not match to the CFL database were deleted. One should note that the CFL public school program database changes throughout the school year and other program changes could have occurred that are not reflected in these databases.

Work was not done to change any locations to programs not used by the FNS project or not identified by the school districts as a new or changed location.  This includes any programs that may been originally located based on the same address as one of the traditional K-12 programs and subsequently that K-12 program location was edited.

SY2002-2003 SUMMARY:
The PUBSCH03 point file is a fairly complete representation of the traditional K-12 public schools programs. The school districts have had the most input in providing, correcting and updating these locations, although there may still be some positional problems not yet identified.

SY2003-2004 SUMMARY:
Each year LMIC has sent a large format School District map (36 inches x 52 inches) to each school district. For SY2003-04, LMIC also included a larger scale map for each school in the District. By adding these larger scale maps, school administrators were able to more accurately mark the locations of each school.

SY2004-2005 SUMMARY:
Three attributes were added:  (LEVEL, SCH_TYPE, SCH_TYPE1) and one attribute name was changed (CFL_ID_STRING was changed to ORGID).

SY2005-2009 SUMMARY:
School locations were modified according to 2003 NAIP aerial phography from the Farm Service Agency:  http://www.mngeo.state.mn.us/chouse/metadata/naip03.html . Each location was moved to match the photographic location.

SY2009-2010 SUMMARY: All school locations were brought into the same geodatabase spatial file. Locations were checked using prior methods. Differentiation of schools is made through reselection based on SCH_TYPE and SCH_TYPE1 or by UNI_TYPE attributes.

SY2010-2011 SUMMARY: Modified dataset using MDE's ORGUNIT school database. Added county code number.

SY2011-2012 Summary: Modified 35-50 district attendance boundaries based on annual district review. Also began an update process based on the Department of Education's ORG database. This database holds all school programs in Minnesota reported by Districts. By downloading and updating the school program locations using this file (annually), the current file now holds ALL school programs, not just those associated with the Food and Nutrition Division at MDE.

SY2012-2013 Summary: Modified 40-50 district attendance boundaries based on annual district review. Compared to MDE-ORG for completeness.

SY2013-2014 Summary: Modified around 60 district attendance boundaries based on annual district review and county parcel information. Compared to MDE-ORG for completeness.

SY2014-2015 Summary: Modified around 45 district attendance boundaries based on annual district review. No parcel data was used in this update. Compared to MDE-ORG for completeness.

SY2015-2016 Summary: Modified around 45 district attendance boundaries based on annual district review. No parcel data was used in this update. Compared to MDE-ORG for completeness.</procdesc>
        <proccont>
          <cntinfo>
            <cntperp>
              <cntper>Scott Freburg</cntper>
              <cntorg>Land Management Information Center</cntorg>
            </cntperp>
            <cntpos>Senior GIS Specialist</cntpos>
            <cntaddr>
              <addrtype>mailing address</addrtype>
              <address>658 Cedar Street</address>
              <city>St. Paul</city>
              <state>MN</state>
              <postal>55155</postal>
              <country>USA</country>
            </cntaddr>
            <cntvoice>651-201-2485</cntvoice>
            <cntemail>scott.freburg@state.mn.us</cntemail>
            <hours>0700 - 1530</hours>
          </cntinfo>
        </proccont>
        <procsv>ArcMAP 9.1</procsv>
        <procdate>May 2006</procdate>
      </procstep>
    </lineage>
  </dataqual>
  <spdoinfo>
    <direct>Point</direct>
    <mgmg3obj>Point</mgmg3obj>
    <mgmg3til>State</mgmg3til>
    <ptvctinf>
      <esriterm Name="schools1011">
        <efeatyp Sync="TRUE">Simple</efeatyp>
        <efeageom Sync="TRUE">Point</efeageom>
        <esritopo Sync="TRUE">FALSE</esritopo>
        <efeacnt Sync="TRUE">4244</efeacnt>
        <spindex Sync="TRUE">TRUE</spindex>
        <linrefer Sync="TRUE">FALSE</linrefer>
      </esriterm>
      <sdtsterm Name="schools1011">
        <sdtstype Sync="TRUE">Entity point</sdtstype>
        <ptvctcnt Sync="TRUE">4244</ptvctcnt>
      </sdtsterm>
    </ptvctinf>
    <indspref/>
  </spdoinfo>
  <spref>
    <vertdef>
      <altsys>
        <altdatum>not applicable</altdatum>
      </altsys>
      <depthsys>
        <depthdn>not applicable</depthdn>
      </depthsys>
    </vertdef>
    <horizsys>
      <planar>
        <gridsys>
          <gridsysn>Universal Transverse Mercator</gridsysn>
          <utm>
            <utmzone>15</utmzone>
          </utm>
        </gridsys>
        <planci>
          <plandu>meters</plandu>
        </planci>
      </planar>
      <geodetic>
        <horizdn>NAD83</horizdn>
        <ellips>GRS80</ellips>
      </geodetic>
    </horizsys>
  </spref>
  <eainfo>
    <overview>
      <eaover>UNI_TYPE (2,2,C)
UNI_MAJ (4,4,C)
UNI_IMD (3,3,C)
ORGID (12, 12, C)
ORGID_NUM (12,12,I)
SCHNAME (40,40,C)
ADDRESS (40,40,C)
CITY (24,24,C)
ZIP (5,5,C)
SCH_TYPE (10,10,C)
SCH_TYPE1 (20,20,C)
SCH_TYPE2 (30,30,C)
SCH_LEVEL (10,10,C)
GRADE (10,10,C)
CLASS (4,4,I)
SDNUM (4,4,I)
SDNAME (40,40,C)
CTYNUM (4,4,I)
CTYNAME (20,20,C)
FIPSNUM (3,3,I)
MAGNET (3,3,C)
DATE_ENTRY (10,10,C)
FED_SCHNUM (10,10,I)
ALT_NAME (50,50,C)
YEAR (12,12,CI)
URL (150,150,C)</eaover>
      <eadetcit>UNI_TYPE - MDE classification.
   1 - Independent districts
   2 - Common districts
   3 - Special Districts (Minneapolis and South St. Paul only)
   4 - Technical college
   6 - Intermediate districts and Schools
   7 - Charter school
   8 - MDE multi-district school designation
  21 - Community colleges
  22 - State universities
  23 - University of Minnesota system
  24 - Private colleges
  25 - Community/Technical Colleges
  31 - Nonpublic School in Independent Districts
  32 - Nonpublic School in Common Districts
  33 - Nonpublic School in Special Districts
  34 - Bureau of Indian Affairs (BIA) Tribal Schools
  36 - NonPublic Archdiocese
  50 - Miscellaneous Cooperatives
  51 - Vocational Cooperatives
  52 - Special Education Cooperatives
  60 - Correctional Facilities
  61 - Education Districts
  62 - Secondary Facilities Cooperatives
  70 - State Operated Schools
  75 - Residential Facilities-Neglected/Delinquent
  80 - Adult Basic Education (ABE)
  82 - Regional Mgmt Information Center-RMIC
  83 - Service Cooperative-ECSU
  86 - Library Minitex Location
  88 - Library Network/Cooperative
  89 - Library

UNI_MAJ - MDE school district number

UNI_IMD - MDE school number

ORGID - A  twelve character combination of the UNI_TYPE (1 or 2), UNI_MAJ (4) and UNI_IMD (3) followed at the end by '000'

ORGID_NUM - A  twelve numeric combination of the UNI_TYPE (2), UNI_MAJ (4) and UNI_IMD (3) followed at the end by '000. Utilized by MDE as unique identifier for all programs.
  example:  01 0497 020 000 is concatenated as 010497020000 Lyle Secondary 7-12
  example:   01 0518 008 000 is concatenated as 010518008000 Worthington High School 9-12

SCHNAME - School name

ADDRESS - School address

CITY - City

ZIP - 5 digit zipcode

SCH_TYPE - School classifier
   NONPUBLIC - All locations with UNI_TYP = 31-34
   PUBLIC - All locations NOT defined as NONPUBLIC

SCH_TYPE1 - 'PUBLIC' or 'NONPUBLIC'

SCH_TYPE1 indicators for NONPUBLIC
   COMMON - schools in Common Districts (Franconia and Prinsburg only)
   INDEPENDENT - schools in Independent Districts

SCH_TYPE1 indicators for PUBLIC
   ALC - Area Learning Centers
   ALP - Area Learning Programs
   CHARTER - Charter schools
   COLLEGE-COMMUNITY - Community college
   COLLEGE-PRIVATE - Private college
   COLLEGE-STATE UNIV - State University
   COLLEGE-TECHNICAL - Technical college and campus
   COLLEGE-U OF MN - University of Minnesota
   COOP - Miscellaneous, vocational and special education
   CORRECTIONAL - Dept. of Corrections Facility
   ECSE - Early Childhood Special Education
   EDUCATION_DISTRICT - Education District
   ELEM - Public elementary school
   MIDD - Public middle or junior high school 
   HIGH - Public high school
   INTERMEDIATE DIST - Intermediate District and school
   LIBRARY - Library
   OFFICE - School District office locations
   OTHER - Programs with designations that are not broken out separately
   SECOND FACILITY COOP - MDE designation
   SPECIAL - Special Districts (Minneapolis or South St. Paul)

SCH_TYPE2 - Future holder for School classifier

SCH_LEVEL - Attempt to identify those programs that are a "District" level program versus "School" level. Used mainly within the Minnesota Department of Education. "District" identification has NO UNI_IMD or UNI_MNR, meaning the last six numbers will be "000000". This designation only has a UNI_TYP or UNI_MAJ designated number. Main examples are:

1. School district offices have an ORGID of "000000" at the end because of the District designation. Examples  Minneapolis (030001000000), Fridley (010013000000) or St. Paul (010625000000).

2. Charter schools - Charters are their own district, therefore there is a location for each charter license that is "000 000". There may be 2, 3, 4 or more locations based on the charter but there will always be 1 record for each charter with these numbers. The charters may also be housed on a single location or in several locations. Examples:
  
   Metro Deaf (District)  07 4000 000 000, 1471 Brewster St., St. Paul
   Metro Deaf (School)  07 4000 010 000, 1471 Brewster St., St. Paul
   Metro Deaf (School)  07 4000 020 000, 1471 Brewster St., St. Paul

There are other schools with a "District' designation but District offices and Charter schools are the majority. To reselect all Charter schools by District you would use this identifier to reselect only those. If you want all charters but not the District designation, just locations, then reselect OUT the District designation.

GRADE - Grade levels (Example)
   EC - Early Childhood Program
   PK - Pre-Kindergarten
   KG - Kindergarten
   1 to 12 - Grades 1 to 12

CLASS - MDE school classification
    0 - No number
   10 - Elem (PK-6)
   20 - Midd (5-8)
   31 - Junior High (7-8 or 7-9)
   32 - Senior High (9-12)
   33 - Secondary (7-12)
   40 - Elem/Sec Combo
   41 - ALC
   42 - ALP
   43 - PrivateAlternative Program
   45 - Targeted Services
   46 - Distance Learning
   50 - Special Education
   51 - Special Education ESY
   55 - Combined Spec Ed * Voc Ed Programs
   60 - Secondary Vocational Program
   70 - Delinquent Student/Correctional Program
   71 - Miscellaneous Program
   72 - Neglected Student Program, Title 1
   73 - Homeless Student Program, Title 1
   74 - Hospital/Medical Program
   75 - Telecommunications District
   76 - Educational Oversight to Private Res Care
   77 - Educational Oversight to Public Res Care
   78 - Educational Oversight to Private Day Treatment
   79 - Educational Oversight to Public Day Treatment
   82 - Community &amp; Adult Education Program
   84 - Early Childhood and Family Education
   90 - Administrative Program
   99 - Reserved

SDNUM - School district number that program is located.

SDNAME - School district name that program is located.

CTYNUM - County numbers from 1 to 87, where program site located.

CTYNAME - County name where program site located.

FIPSNUM - County numbers from 1 to 173 based on U.S. Census, where program site located.

MAGNET - Magnet school (YES/NO)

DATE_ENTRY - date school location was entered or modified in the database.

FEDSCHNUM - National Center for Educational Statistics (NCES) school identification number. The first 2 digits are Minnesota's state number (27). The next 5 digits are the District school designation. This will be the same for each school in that district. The final 5 numbers are the school identifier.

Example: Aitkin School District
   Office              01 0001 000 000  FED_SCHNUM=27 02760              (2702760)
   Aitkin High      01 0001 001 000  FED_SCHNUM=27 02760 00057   (270276000057)
   Rippleside El.  01 0001 002 000  FED_SCHNUM=27 02760 00059   (270276000059)
   Palisade El.     01 0001 003 000  FED_SCHNUM=27 02760 00058   (270276000058)

   City Academy Charter  (District)  01 4000 000 000 FED_SCHNUM=27 08955             (2708955)
   City Academy Charter  (School)  01 4000 010 000 FED_SCHNUM=27 08955 00016  (270895500016)

ALT_NAME - If a building has a name (such as XXX Early Childhood Center), it may be easier for labeling purposes to label using this field versus labeling individual points. In some locations there are 2, 3, 4 or more programs at one location.

YEAR - School year of data.

URL - website address for the school/district</eadetcit>
    </overview>
  </eainfo>
  <distinfo>
    <resdesc>School program locations 2015-16</resdesc>
    <distliab>The Minnesota Department of Education (MDE) does not warrant the results you may obtain by using this dataset. This dataset is provided ''as is'' without express or implied warranties, including warranties of merchantability and fitness. In no event will MDE be liable for any consequential, incidental or special damages, including any lost profits or lost savings, even if an MDE  representative has been advised of the possibility of such damages or any other claim by any third party.

In obtaining this data from MDE and MnGeo, it is understood that you and/or your organization have the right to use it for any purpose.  If you modify it, you are encouraged to apply responsible best practices by documenting those changes in a metadata record.  If you transmit or provide the data to another user, it is your responsibility to provide appropriate content, limitation, warranty and liability information as you see fit.

MnGeo's disclaimer is online:  http://www.mngeo.state.mn.us/chouse/disclaimer.html</distliab>
    <stdorder>
      <digform>
        <digtinfo>
          <formname>Shapefile</formname>
          <transize>less than 1 megabyte</transize>
          <dssize Sync="TRUE">0.113</dssize>
          <formvern/>
        </digtinfo>
      </digform>
      <ordering>The GIS data and maps are distributed on the internet by clicking below after Online Linkage.</ordering>
    </stdorder>
    <distrib>
      <cntinfo>
        <cntperp>
          <cntorg>Minnesota Department of Education</cntorg>
          <cntper>Scott Freburg</cntper>
        </cntperp>
        <cntpos>GIS Administrator</cntpos>
        <cntaddr>
          <addrtype>mailing and physical</addrtype>
          <address>1500 Hwy 36 W.</address>
          <city>Roseville</city>
          <state>MN</state>
          <postal>55113</postal>
        </cntaddr>
        <cntvoice>651-582-8789</cntvoice>
        <cntemail>scott.freburg@state.mn.us</cntemail>
      </cntinfo>
    </distrib>
  </distinfo>
  <metainfo>
    <metd>20151118</metd>
    <metstdn>Minnesota Geographic Metadata Guidelines</metstdn>
    <metstdv>1.2</metstdv>
    <metextns>
      <onlink>http://www.mngeo.state.mn.us/committee/standards/mgmg/metadata.htm</onlink>
    </metextns>
    <langmeta Sync="TRUE">en</langmeta>
    <mettc Sync="TRUE">local time</mettc>
    <metextns>
      <onlink Sync="TRUE">http://www.esri.com/metadata/esriprof80.html</onlink>
      <metprof Sync="TRUE">ESRI Metadata Profile</metprof>
    </metextns>
    <metc>
      <cntinfo>
        <cntperp>
          <cntorg>Minnesota Department of Education</cntorg>
          <cntper>Scott Freburg</cntper>
        </cntperp>
        <cntpos>GIS Administrator</cntpos>
        <cntaddr>
          <addrtype>mailing and physical</addrtype>
          <address>1500 Hwy 36 W.</address>
          <city>Roseville</city>
          <state>MN</state>
          <postal>55113</postal>
        </cntaddr>
        <cntvoice>651-582-8789</cntvoice>
        <cntemail>scott.freburg@state.mn.us</cntemail>
      </cntinfo>
    </metc>
  </metainfo>
  <Esri>
    <ModDate>20110923</ModDate>
    <ModTime>11091800</ModTime>
    <CreaDate>20100913</CreaDate>
    <CreaTime>14593300</CreaTime>
    <SyncOnce>FALSE</SyncOnce>
    <SyncDate>20100913</SyncDate>
    <SyncTime>15163400</SyncTime>
    <MetaID>{51BD1B95-1CE3-4118-B365-E1AB0E3BE08A}</MetaID>
  </Esri>
  <mdDateSt Sync="TRUE">20110923</mdDateSt>
  <dataIdInfo>
    <envirDesc Sync="TRUE">Microsoft Windows XP Version 5.1 (Build 2600) Service Pack 3; ESRI ArcCatalog 9.3.1.3500</envirDesc>
    <dataLang>
      <languageCode Sync="TRUE" value="en"/>
    </dataLang>
    <idCitation>
      <resTitle Sync="TRUE">schools1011</resTitle>
      <presForm>
        <PresFormCd Sync="TRUE" value="005"/>
      </presForm>
    </idCitation>
    <spatRpType>
      <SpatRepTypCd Sync="TRUE" value="001"/>
    </spatRpType>
    <dataExt>
      <geoEle>
        <GeoBndBox esriExtentType="native">
          <westBL Sync="TRUE">190972.9529</westBL>
          <eastBL Sync="TRUE">747256.4793</eastBL>
          <northBL Sync="TRUE">5468873.9977</northBL>
          <southBL Sync="TRUE">4817260.9984</southBL>
          <exTypeCode Sync="TRUE">1</exTypeCode>
        </GeoBndBox>
      </geoEle>
    </dataExt>
    <geoBox esriExtentType="decdegrees">
      <westBL Sync="TRUE">-97.25068</westBL>
      <eastBL Sync="TRUE">-89.597207</eastBL>
      <northBL Sync="TRUE">49.37257</northBL>
      <southBL Sync="TRUE">43.444465</southBL>
      <exTypeCode Sync="TRUE">1</exTypeCode>
    </geoBox>
  </dataIdInfo>
  <mdLang>
    <languageCode Sync="TRUE" value="en"/>
  </mdLang>
  <mdStanName Sync="TRUE">ISO 19115 Geographic Information - Metadata</mdStanName>
  <mdStanVer Sync="TRUE">DIS_ESRI1.0</mdStanVer>
  <mdChar>
    <CharSetCd Sync="TRUE" value="004"/>
  </mdChar>
  <mdHrLv>
    <ScopeCd Sync="TRUE" value="005"/>
  </mdHrLv>
  <mdHrLvName Sync="TRUE">dataset</mdHrLvName>
  <distInfo>
    <distributor>
      <distorTran>
        <onLineSrc>
          <orDesc Sync="TRUE">002</orDesc>
          <linkage Sync="TRUE">file://\\8HP25J1\E$\MDEFNS_Data\Spatial_Data\SD_Data\SY2010-11\Final_Datasets\MNGEO\schools1011.shp</linkage>
          <protocol Sync="TRUE">Local Area Network</protocol>
        </onLineSrc>
        <transSize Sync="TRUE">0.113</transSize>
      </distorTran>
      <distorFormat>
        <formatName Sync="TRUE">Shapefile</formatName>
      </distorFormat>
    </distributor>
  </distInfo>
  <spatRepInfo>
    <VectSpatRep>
      <topLvl>
        <TopoLevCd Sync="TRUE" value="001"/>
      </topLvl>
      <geometObjs Name="schools1011">
        <geoObjTyp>
          <GeoObjTypCd Sync="TRUE" value="004"/>
        </geoObjTyp>
        <geoObjCnt Sync="TRUE">4244</geoObjCnt>
      </geometObjs>
    </VectSpatRep>
  </spatRepInfo>
  <refSysInfo>
    <RefSystem>
      <refSysID>
        <identCode Sync="TRUE">NAD_1983_UTM_Zone_15N</identCode>
      </refSysID>
    </RefSystem>
  </refSysInfo>
</metadata>
