<?xml version="1.0"?><!--  <!DOCTYPE metadata SYSTEM "metadata.dtd">  --><metadata><idinfo><citation><citeinfo><origin>Minnesota Department of Natural Resources (MnDNR), Surdex Corporation</origin><pubdate>201112</pubdate><title>Digital Orthoimagery, Southern Minnesota, Spring 2011; Meeker County, Spring 2013; 0.5-m Resolution</title><mgmg1cid></mgmg1cid><pubinfo><publish>Minnesota Department of Natural Resources</publish></pubinfo><onlink>http://www.mngeo.state.mn.us/chouse/wms/geo_image_server.html</onlink></citeinfo></citation><descript><abstract>This dataset contains leaf-off 4-band red, green, blue, infrared (RGBI) digital orthophoto imagery produced at half-meter (50 cm) resolution from new aerial photography captured in Spring 2011 (Meeker Co., Spring 2013). The imagery covers 38 counties in southern Minnesota: Dodge, Faribault, Fillmore, Freeborn, Goodhue, Houston, Jackson, Kandiyohi, Lac qui Parle, Le Sueur, Lincoln, Lyon, Martin, McLeod, Meeker, Mower, Murray, Nicollet, Nobles, Olmsted, Pipestone, Redwood, Renville, Rice, Rock, Sibley, Steele, Swift, Wabasha, Waseca, Watonwan, Winona and Yellow Medicine.

Funding for this data was provided by the Minnesota Natural Heritage Fund, the Minnesota Clean Water Legacy Act, and The Environmental and Natural Resources Trust Fund. 

This metadata record was created by the Minnesota Geospatial Information Office (MnGeo) using information supplied by Surdex Corporation.</abstract><purpose>The orthophotos will be used by the Minnesota DNR to update the National Wetland Inventory maps and as a base layer for mapping wetlands and other business needs. This type of leaf-off photography is a critical component for a variety of land management applications including transportation planning, wetland mapping, urban planning, forest management, soil mapping, and utility siting.</purpose><supplinf>38 counties in southern Minnesota - see Place Keywords</supplinf></descript><timeperd><current>Ground condition. All counties flown mid-April, 2011 except for Meeker County flown on 5/7/2013 and 5/10/2013.</current><timeinfo><sngdate><caldate>201104</caldate></sngdate></timeinfo></timeperd><status><progress>Complete</progress><update>Unknown</update></status><spdom><bounding><westbc>-97</westbc><eastbc>-91</eastbc><northbc>45.75</northbc><southbc>43.5</southbc></bounding></spdom><keywords><theme><themekt>ISO 19115 Topic Category</themekt><themekey>imageryBaseMapsEarthCover, Orthophotography, Digital Orthophotography, Ortho, Orthophotos, Digital Orthorectified Images, Digital Orthophotos, DOQ, DOQQ, Imagery, Images, Aerial Photography, Aerial Photos, Digital Aerial Photography, Air Photo, Color Infrared, Four Band Imagery</themekey></theme><place><placekey>Minnesota, MN, Big Stone, Blue Earth, Brown, Chippewa, Cottonwood, Dodge, Faribault, Fillmore, Freeborn, Goodhue, Houston, Jackson, Kandiyohi, Lac qui Parle, Le Sueur, Lincoln, Lyon, Martin, McLeod, Meeker, Mower, Murray, Nicollet, Nobles, Olmsted, Pipestone, Redwood, Renville, Rice, Rock, Sibley, Steele, Swift, Wabasha, Waseca, Watonwan, Winona, Yellow Medicine, Minnesota</placekey></place></keywords><accconst>Unrestricted</accconst><useconst>Imagery is the property of the State of Minnesota.

MnGeo Redistribution conditions: In obtaining this data from the Minnesota Geospatial Information Office (MnGeo), it is understood that you and/or your organization have the right to use it for any purpose. If you modify it, you are encouraged to apply responsible best practices by documenting those changes in a metadata record. If you transmit or provide the data to another user, it is your responsibility to provide appropriate content, limitation, warranty and liability information as you see fit.</useconst><browse><browsen>None available</browsen></browse><native>Microsoft Windows XP Version 5.1 (Build 2600) Service Pack 3; ESRI ArcCatalog 9.3.1.4000</native><crossref><citeinfo><title>For information on other air photos available for Minnesota, see: http://www.mngeo.state.mn.us/chouse/airphoto/</title></citeinfo></crossref><ptcontac><cntinfo><cntperp><cntorg>Minnesota Department of Natural Resources</cntorg><cntper>Steve Kloiber</cntper></cntperp><cntpos>Wetland Monitoring Coordinator</cntpos><cntaddr><addrtype>Mailing</addrtype><address>500 Lafayette Road</address><city>St. Paul</city><state>MN</state><postal>55155</postal></cntaddr><cntvoice>651-259-5164</cntvoice><cntemail>steve.kloiber@state.mn.us</cntemail></cntinfo></ptcontac></idinfo><dataqual><attracc><attraccr>N/A</attraccr></attracc><logic>N/A</logic><complete>The half-meter project area was slightly scaled back in mid-May 2011 due to rapidly changing foliage conditions on the ground site. The state elected to delay acquisition in Meeker County until leaf-off Spring 2013.</complete><posacc><horizpa><horizpar>An overall accuracy for this product was targeted for 2.4 meters, CE90. Surdex collected Airborne GPS data at the time of image acquisition and supplemented with several control points surveyed by ground crews. Surdex used these ground control points and additionally some QC points dropped out of the Triangulation in order to validate the accuracy of the final digital orthophoto quarter quad (DOQQ) product. Of all the points collected, 71 were easily readable in the final product and were used to calculate the stated residual.

Minnesota Dept. of Transportation staff independently tested the horizontal positional accuracy of the DOQs.
Total number of targets = 171
Root Mean Square Error (RMSE) = 0.819
National Standard for Spatial Data Accuracy (NSSDA) = 1.418 (95% confidence level)
Their full accuracy report is at:  http://www.mngeo.state.mn.us/chouse/airphoto/DOQ_Accuracy_Report_MnDOT_southmn2011.pdf</horizpar></horizpa><vertacc><vertaccr>None - this is a horizontal only product.</vertaccr></vertacc></posacc><lineage><srcinfo><srcscale>41666</srcscale></srcinfo><procstep><procdesc>Multiple aircraft were deployed to southern Minnesota in early April 2011 for digital image acquisition during leaf-off conditions. Cessna Conquests equipped with Intergraph DMC (Digital Mapping Cameras) captured 4 band imagery over the project sites. Imagery was captured at an altitude of 16,500 feet above mean terrain, allowing up to 5% cloud conditions per frame. All four bands (RGB natural color plus near infrared) of raw camera data were processed by Surdex using Intergraph PPS software coupled with Surdex proprietary image handling software for color correction and dodging. Post processing of Airborne and Ground GPS data was performed with Waypoint Consulting's GrafNav software. Aerial Triangulation was completed using Intergraph ImageStation Automatic Triangulation and rectification of imagery to the state supplied 10 meter digital elevation model (DEM) was completed using Surdex proprietary software. Image mosaicking, quality control, and final DOQQ products were produced using proprietary Surdex software.

Additional information for Meeker County:  Data was captured in May 2013 using 10 flight lines and 295 exposures.  The direction of the flight lines were oriented N-S.  The overall GSD of the final product was 0.5 meters and tiled out into quarter quads which are approximately 800 mb in size.</procdesc></procstep></lineage></dataqual><spdoinfo><indspref></indspref><direct>Raster</direct><mgmg3obj></mgmg3obj><mgmg3til></mgmg3til></spdoinfo><eainfo><overview><eaover>Imagery has 4 Bands with the order of Red, Green, Blue and Near Infrared</eaover></overview></eainfo><distinfo><resdesc>South MN DOQs, Spring 2011; Meeker County DOQs, Spring 2013</resdesc><distliab>MnGeo's full disclaimer is here:  http://www.mngeo.state.mn.us/chouse/disclaimer.html</distliab><stdorder><digform><digtinfo><formname></formname><formvern></formvern><transize>0.000</transize></digtinfo></digform><ordering>These air photos are very large and thus are not provided online for download. Instead, they are available to view as a web map service (WMS), part of MnGeo's Geospatial Image Service. Click on the link below for more information about the Geospatial Image Service and how to use web map services.</ordering></stdorder><distrib><cntinfo><cntperp><cntorg>Minnesota Geospatial Information Office (MnGeo)</cntorg><cntper>Nancy Rader</cntper></cntperp><cntpos>GIS Data Coordinator</cntpos><cntaddr><addrtype>mailing and physical</addrtype><address>658 Cedar Street</address><city>St. Paul</city><state>MN</state><postal>55155</postal></cntaddr><cntvoice>651-201-2489</cntvoice><cntemail>gisinfo.mngeo@state.mn.us</cntemail></cntinfo></distrib></distinfo><metainfo><metd>20150121</metd><metstdn>Minnesota Geographic Metadata Guidelines</metstdn><metstdv>1.2</metstdv><metextns><onlink>http://www.mngeo.state.mn.us/committee/standards/mgmg/metadata.htm
</onlink></metextns><metc><cntinfo><cntperp><cntorg>Minnesota Geospatial Information Office (MnGeo)</cntorg><cntper>Nancy Rader</cntper></cntperp><cntpos>GIS Data Coordinator</cntpos><cntaddr><addrtype>mailing and physical</addrtype><address>658 Cedar Street</address><city>St. Paul</city><state>MN</state><postal>55155</postal></cntaddr><cntvoice>651-201-2489</cntvoice><cntemail>gisinfo.mngeo@state.mn.us</cntemail></cntinfo></metc></metainfo><spref><horizsys><planar><gridsys><gridsysn>Universal Transverse Mercator</gridsysn><utm><utmzone>15</utmzone></utm></gridsys><planci><plandu>meters</plandu><coordrep><absres>0.500000</absres><ordres>0.500000</ordres></coordrep></planci></planar><geodetic><horizdn>NAD83</horizdn><ellips>GRS80</ellips></geodetic></horizsys></spref></metadata>