<?xml version="1.0"?><metadata><idinfo><citation><citeinfo><origin>Minnesota Department of Natural Resources (DNR)</origin><pubdate>2008-08-18 00:00:00.0</pubdate><title>Calcareous Fens - Source Feature Points</title><mgmg1cid></mgmg1cid><pubinfo><publish>Minnesota DNR - Division of Ecological Resources - Natural Heritage &amp; Nongame Research Program</publish></pubinfo><onlink>http://gisdata.mn.gov/dataset/biota-nhis-calcareous-fens</onlink></citeinfo></citation><descript><abstract>Pursuant to the provisions of Minnesota Statutes, section 103G.223, this database contains points that represent calcareous fens as defined in Minnesota Rules, part 8420.1020.  The calcareous fens in this shapefile correspond to the fens listed in Identification Order No. 08-001, which was published in the State Register on June 2, 2008 (32 SR 2148-2154).  The current list of fens is posted on the DNR web site at http://files.dnr.state.mn.us/publications/waters/calcareous_fen_list_nov_2009.pdf


This data set is a GIS point shapefile derived from the Natural Heritage "Biotics" Database.  Data in the Biotics Database are maintained according to established Natural Heritage Methodology developed by NatureServe and The Nature Conservancy.  The core of the Biotics Database is made up of Element Occurrence (EO) records of rare plant and animal species, animal aggregations, native plant communities, and geologic features.  An Element is a unit of biological diversity, such as a species, subspecies, or a native plant community.  An EO is an area of land and/or water in which an Element is, or was, present, and which has practical conservation value for the Element (e.g. species or community) as evidenced by potential continued (or historical) presence and/or regular recurrence at a given location.  Source Features are the mapped representation of observations of rare features.  Source Features are then evaluated using biological standards, and grouped into EOs as appropriate.


This data set contains a point for each Calcareous Fen (DNR List of Known Calcareous Fens) Source Feature in the Biotics database, and selected attributes from the Source Feature record and its linked Element Occurrence (EO) record.</abstract><purpose>It is anticipated that this data set will primarily be used as a screening tool for clients that need to comply with the Wetland Conservation Act.</purpose><supplinf>Minnesota</supplinf></descript><timeperd><timeinfo><sngdate><caldate>1800s to present</caldate></sngdate></timeinfo><current>Date of original observation of rare feature at the mapped location</current></timeperd><status><progress>Complete</progress><update>As needed</update></status><spdom><bounding><westbc>-96.375526</westbc><eastbc>-91.377939</eastbc><northbc>49.023203</northbc><southbc>43.485622</southbc></bounding></spdom><keywords><theme><themekey>Calcareous Fens, Spring Fens, Rare Features, Native Plant Communities, Natural Heritage, Biological Survey</themekey></theme><place><placekey>Minnesota</placekey></place></keywords><accconst>No constraints</accconst><useconst>In order to protect the DNR's copyright interest in these data, any product derived from this GIS data set should include an appropriate copyright notice.  The user should also acknowledge the DNR's Division of Ecological Resources as the source of the information. This can be accomplished by printing the following statement on any product containing these data. "Calcareous Fen locations were provided by the Division of Ecological Resources, Minnesota Department of Natural Resources (DNR), and were current as of [date delivered]."</useconst><browse><browsed>Calcarious Fen Example</browsed><browsen>ftp://ftp.gisdata.mn.gov/pub/gdrs/data/pub/us_mn_state_dnr/biota_nhis_calcareous_fens/metadata/preview.jpg</browsen></browse><native>ArcView Shapefile</native><ptcontac><cntinfo><cntperp><cntorg>Minnesota DNR - Division of Ecological Resources - Natural Heritage and Nongame Research Program</cntorg><cntper>Lisa Joyal</cntper></cntperp><cntpos>NHIS Data Distribution Coordinator</cntpos><cntaddr><addrtype>Mailing and Physical</addrtype><address>500 Lafayette Road, Box 25</address><city>St. Paul</city><state>MN</state><postal>55155</postal></cntaddr><cntvoice>651-259-5109</cntvoice><cntfax>651-296-1811</cntfax><cntemail>lisa.joyal@state.mn.us</cntemail></cntinfo></ptcontac></idinfo><dataqual><attracc><attraccr>Source table NHIS_MNFENPT3.DBF:  All data go through a quality control process after entry.
</attraccr></attracc><logic>Not Applicable</logic><complete>Subject to future revisions as the official DNR List of Known Calcareous Fens is subject to revisions.  This shapefile will be updated when the official list is updated.


This data set contains only fens reported to the Division of Ecological Resources.  Other fens may occur in Minnesota for which we have no observation record.</complete><posacc><horizpa><horizpar>Source layer nhis_mnfenpt3:  Horizontal positional accuracy varies greatly due to the varying level of precision in data submitted for entry.  Accuracy is reflected in the LU_DIST and LUDISTUNIT fields.
</horizpar></horizpa><vertacc><vertaccr>Source layer nhis_mnfenpt3:  Not Applicable
</vertaccr></vertacc></posacc><lineage><srcinfo><srcscale>Source layer nhis_mnfenpt3:  24000
</srcscale></srcinfo><procstep><procdesc>Attribute Lineage for source table NHIS_MNFENPT3.DBF:  Tabular data are entered into an ORACLE database. Output views are generated by Structured Query Language (SQL) scripts.
</procdesc></procstep></lineage></dataqual><spdoinfo><indspref>Calcareous Fen Element Occurrence</indspref><direct>point</direct><mgmg3obj>point</mgmg3obj><mgmg3til>state</mgmg3til></spdoinfo><spref><vertdef><altsys><altdatum>Not Applicable</altdatum><altunits>Not Applicable</altunits></altsys><depthsys><depthdn>Not Applicable</depthdn><depthdu>Not Applicable</depthdu></depthsys></vertdef><horizsys><planar><gridsys><gridsysn>Universal Transverse Mercator</gridsysn><utm><utmzone>15</utmzone></utm></gridsys><planci><plandu>meters</plandu></planci></planar><geodetic><horizdn>NAD83</horizdn><ellips>GRS80</ellips></geodetic></horizsys></spref><eainfo><detailed><enttyp><enttypl>calcareous_fens</enttypl><enttypd>Feature Class Attribute Table</enttypd></enttyp><attr><attrlabl>SF_ID</attrlabl><attrdef>Unique ID for each Source Feature tabular record within the database.</attrdef></attr><attr><attrlabl>SF_SHAPEID</attrlabl><attrdef>Unique ID for each Source Feature shape within the shapefile.</attrdef></attr><attr><attrlabl>COMM_NAME</attrlabl><attrdef>The primary common name used in the Natural Heritage Information System for the Element.</attrdef></attr><attr><attrlabl>MCBS_NPC_C</attrlabl><attrdef>Native Plant Community Classification Code based on the DNR?s Field Guide to the Native Plant Communities of Minnesota.</attrdef></attr><attr><attrlabl>S_RANK</attrlabl><attrdef>Subnational Rank; rank that best characterizes the relative rarity or endangerment of the community in Minnesota.</attrdef><attrdomv><edom><edomv>S1</edomv><edomvd>Critically imperiled in Minnesota because of extreme rarity or because of some factor(s) making it especially vulnerable to extirpation from the state.</edomvd></edom></attrdomv><attrdomv><edom><edomv>S2</edomv><edomvd>Imperiled in Minnesota because of rarity or because of some factor(s) making it very vulnerable to extirpation from the state.</edomvd></edom></attrdomv><attrdomv><edom><edomv>S3</edomv><edomvd>Vulnerable in Minnesota either because rare or uncommon, or found in a restricted range, or because of other factors making it vulnerable to extirpation.</edomvd></edom></attrdomv><attrdomv><edom><edomv>S4</edomv><edomvd>Apparently secure in Minnesota, usually widespread.</edomvd></edom></attrdomv><attrdomv><edom><edomv>S5</edomv><edomvd>Demonstrably secure in  Minnesota, essentially ineradicable under present conditions.</edomvd></edom></attrdomv></attr><attr><attrlabl>CNTY_NAME</attrlabl><attrdef>The name of the county that the fen point falls in.  The actual fen boundary may be located within more than one county.</attrdef></attr><attr><attrlabl>TRS</attrlabl><attrdef>Legal Description.  The Township, Range, and Section that the fen point falls in.  The actual fen boundary may be located within more than one section.</attrdef></attr><attr><attrlabl>LU_DIST</attrlabl><attrdef>Estimated or known distance of the fen point's locational uncertainty.  The recorded (i.e., mapped) location of an observation may vary from its true location due to many factors, including the level of expertise of the data collector, differences in survey techniques and equipment used, and the amount and type of information obtained.  This inaccuracy is characterized as locational uncertainty.</attrdef></attr><attr><attrlabl>LUDISTUNIT</attrlabl><attrdef>Measurement unit associated with the entry in the Locational Uncertainty Distance field.</attrdef><attrdomv><edom><edomv>Feet</edomv><edomvd>Feet</edomvd></edom></attrdomv><attrdomv><edom><edomv>Kilometers</edomv><edomvd>Kilometers</edomvd></edom></attrdomv><attrdomv><edom><edomv>Meters</edomv><edomvd>Meters</edomvd></edom></attrdomv><attrdomv><edom><edomv>Miles</edomv><edomvd>Miles</edomvd></edom></attrdomv></attr><attr><attrlabl>FENSITENAM</attrlabl><attrdef>Calcareous Fen Site Name as listed in Identification Order No. 08-001, which was published in the State Register on June 2, 2008 (32 SR 2148-2154).</attrdef></attr><attr><attrlabl>OBS_DATES</attrlabl><attrdef>Observation Dates.</attrdef></attr><attr><attrlabl>EO_VER_DAT</attrlabl><attrdef>Version Date; date of the current version of the EO record (i.e., the date that the EO record was first completed, or since then, comprehensively revised).</attrdef></attr><attr><attrlabl>EO_ID</attrlabl><attrdef>Unique identifier for the EO to which the Source Feature belongs. Fen ID No. as listed in Identification Order No. 08-001, which was published in the State Register on June 2, 2008 (32 SR 2148-2154).</attrdef></attr></detailed></eainfo><distinfo><distliab>The Minnesota Department of Natural Resources General Geographic Data License Agreement is online: http://www.dnr.state.mn.us/sitetools/data_software_license.html</distliab><stdorder><digform><digtinfo><formname>ArcView Shapefile</formname><formvern>Not Applicable</formvern><transize>1024</transize></digtinfo></digform><ordering>Please visit the download page for this dataset on the Minnesota Geospatial Commons website using the web link below (Online Linkage).</ordering></stdorder><resdesc>biota_nhis_calcareous_fens</resdesc><distrib><cntinfo><cntperp><cntorg>Minnesota DNR - Division of Ecological Resources - Natural Heritage and Nongame Research Program</cntorg><cntper>Lisa Joyal</cntper></cntperp><cntpos>NHIS Data Distribution Coordinator</cntpos><cntaddr><addrtype>Mailing and Physical</addrtype><address>500 Lafayette Road, Box 25</address><city>St. Paul</city><state>MN</state><postal>55155</postal></cntaddr><cntvoice>651-259-5109</cntvoice><cntfax>651-296-1811</cntfax><cntemail>lisa.joyal@state.mn.us</cntemail></cntinfo></distrib></distinfo><metainfo><metd>20141218</metd><metstdn>Minnesota Geographic Metadata Guidelines</metstdn><metstdv>1.2</metstdv><metextns><onlink>http://www.mngeo.state.mn.us/committee/standards/mgmg/metadata.htm</onlink></metextns><metc><cntinfo><cntperp><cntorg>Minnesota DNR - Division of Ecological Resources - Natural Heritage and Nongame Research Program</cntorg><cntper>Lisa Joyal</cntper></cntperp><cntpos>NHIS Data Distribution Coordinator</cntpos><cntaddr><addrtype>Mailing and Physical</addrtype><address>500 Lafayette Road, Box 25</address><city>St. Paul</city><state>MN</state><postal>55155</postal></cntaddr><cntvoice>651-259-5109</cntvoice><cntfax>651-296-1811</cntfax><cntemail>lisa.joyal@state.mn.us</cntemail></cntinfo></metc></metainfo></metadata>