<!--  <!DOCTYPE metadata SYSTEM "metadata.dtd">  -->
<metadata>
  <idinfo>
    <citation>
      <citeinfo>
        <origin>Minnesota Geological Survey </origin>
        <pubdate>1999</pubdate>
        <title>Quaternary Geology - Upper Minnesota River Basin, Minnesota (Part A)</title>
        <mgmg1cid/>
        <pubinfo>
          <publish>Minnesota Geological Survey</publish>
        </pubinfo>
        <onlink>http://conservancy.umn.edu/handle/11299/59765</onlink>
      </citeinfo>
    </citation>
    <descript>
      <abstract>A County Geologic Atlas is a systematic study of a county's geologic and ground water resources. Geologic studies include both near-surface deposits and bedrock.  Ground water studies include flow systems, aquifer capacity, and ground water chemistry.  In some areas sand and gravel deposits, sinkholes, or other features are studied.  Interpretation of sensitivity to pollution is also part of an atlas.  The information is organized, analyzed, and displayed using geographic information technology.

A Regional Hydrogeologic Assessment (RHA) is similar to a County Geologic Atlas in that both geology and ground water are studied.  However, a Regional Hydrogeologic Assessment covers a larger area, typically four to nine counties, in less detail.  The  RHA emphasizes near-surface geologic, ground water, and pollution sensitivity mapping.</abstract>
      <purpose>County Geologic Atlas and Regional Hydrogeologic Assessment information is used in planning and environmental protection efforts at all levels of government.  Wellhead protection and well-sealing programs are examples of local programs that need geologic and ground water information. The information is also used by businesses and the general public.</purpose>
      <supplinf>Upper Minnesota River Basin</supplinf>
    </descript>
    <timeperd>
      <timeinfo>
        <sngdate>
          <caldate>1998</caldate>
        </sngdate>
      </timeinfo>
      <current>Duration of Study, approx. 1996-1998; published in July, 1999. Content reflects the geologic information available at the time of study.</current>
    </timeperd>
    <status>
      <progress>Complete</progress>
      <update>None Planned</update>
    </status>
    <spdom>
      <bounding>
        <westbc>-95.25</westbc>
        <eastbc>-96.00</eastbc>
        <northbc>45.41</northbc>
        <southbc>44.50</southbc>
      </bounding>
    </spdom>
    <keywords>
      <theme>
        <themekt>ISO 19115 Topic Category</themekt>
        <themekey>geoscienficInformation, Geology, Surficial Geology, Bedrock Topography, Drift Thickness, Well Locations, Wells,  Regional Hydrogeologic Assessment</themekey>
      </theme>
      <place>
        <placekey>Minnesota, MN, Upper Minnesota River Basin, Southwestern Minnesota, Big Stone County (partial), Chippewa County, Lac Qui Parle County, Lincoln County (partial), Lyon County (partial), Redwood County (partial), Renville County (partial), Swift County, Yellow Medicine County</placekey>
      </place>
    </keywords>
    <accconst>None</accconst>
    <useconst>Credit to Minnesota Geological Survey for use of data in map products.</useconst>
    <browse>
      <browsen>None available</browsen>
    </browse>
    <native>Arc/Info 7.0.4</native>
    <crossref>
      <citeinfo>
        <title>Paper map and report are available from MGS Map Sales Office (2609 Territorial Road, St. Paul, Minnesota, 55114, 612-626-2969.)

Paper Report: RHA-4, Part A. C.J. Patterson, project manager, Regional hydrogeologic assessment: Quaternary geology--Upper Minnesota River basin, Minnesota. 1999. 2 pls. Scale 1:200,000. Pl 1, surficial geology; pl. 2, Quaternary stratigraphy. $8.00. 

For the U of M Libraries Digital Conservancy listing of map products see: http://conservancy.umn.edu/handle/11299/708

Paper Report: RHA-4, Part B. Upper Minnesota River basin, Minnesota. J. Falteisek, Minnesota Dept. of Natural Resources, Division of Waters, editor and project supervisor. 2000. 2 pls. Scale 1:200,000. Continues numbering of RHA-4, Part A. Plate 3, surficial hydrogeology; plate 4, geologic sensitivity to pollution of near-surface ground water. $8.00. 

Digital data for part B is available from:
http://www.dnr.state.mn.us/waters/groundwater_section/mapping/index.html

For additional information on the Department of Natural Resources (DNR) Ground Water Mapping Program, visit: 
http://www.dnr.state.mn.us/waters/groundwater_section/mapping/index.html

</title>
      </citeinfo>
    </crossref>
    <ptcontac>
      <cntinfo>
        <cntperp>
          <cntorg>Minnesota Geological Survey</cntorg>
          <cntper>General Information</cntper>
        </cntperp>
        <cntpos>Administrative Staff</cntpos>
        <cntaddr>
          <addrtype>Mailing and Physical</addrtype>
          <address>2609 Territorial Road</address>
          <city>St. Paul</city>
          <state>MN</state>
          <postal>55114</postal>
        </cntaddr>
        <cntvoice>612-626-2969</cntvoice>
        <cntemail>mgs@umn.edu</cntemail>
      </cntinfo>
    </ptcontac>
  </idinfo>
  <dataqual>
    <attracc>
      <attraccr>See file RHA4meta.pdf on ftp site for metadata records for individual data layers.</attraccr>
    </attracc>
    <logic>See file RHA4meta.pdf on ftp site for metadata records for individual data layers.</logic>
    <complete>See file RHA4meta.pdf on ftp site for metadata records for individual data layers.</complete>
    <posacc>
      <horizpa>
        <horizpar>See file RHA4meta.pdf on ftp site for metadata records for individual data layers.</horizpar>
      </horizpa>
    </posacc>
    <lineage>
      <srcinfo>
        <srcscale>200000</srcscale>
      </srcinfo>
      <procstep>
        <procdesc>Investigations begin with a review of existing information, such as earlier geologic maps, soil maps, and hydrologic reports. Drillers send water well logs to the Minnesota Geological Survey, where they are reviewed, interpreted, and entered into the County Well Index (CWI), an interactive data base of water-well information.  Building on the previous data, field studies are conducted to improve the understanding of local geologic and hydrologic conditions. Linework is created based upon the field studies and base data, and digitized.  Background GIS data layers such as roads, surface hydrography, township grids, etc., are obtained from various sources. Production information for individual layers is reports in RHA4meta.pdf</procdesc>
      </procstep>
    </lineage>
  </dataqual>
  <spdoinfo>
    <indspref/>
    <direct>Vector</direct>
    <mgmg3obj>Point, Vector</mgmg3obj>
    <mgmg3til>Upper Minnesota River Basin</mgmg3til>
  </spdoinfo>
  <eainfo>
    <overview>
      <eaover>The following is an index of covers and related files used in 
the Upper Minnesota River Basin (UMRB) regional assessment.
Compilation scale is 1:200,000

COVERS:
BGOC = poly cover of bedrock outcrops
BTLN = line cover of bedrock topography
COAN = annotation cover for project area
COPG = poly cover of county boundaries
DTPG = poly cover of dtift thickness
GDPT = point cover of gidding's points
KPG = poly cover of Cretaceous rocks
SGCT = line cover of cartogrphic flags/surf. units
SGLNLS = line cover of geomorphic line symbols
SGPG = poly cover of surficial geology
WWPT = point cover of water well locations

GEOGRAPHIC BASE LAYERS:
HYLNCT = line cover of hydro cartigraphic altered
MCDPG = poly cover of municipal districts
RDLN1 = line cover of major highways
RDLN2 = line cover of minor roads

INFO:
cwinfo = County Well Index tabular well record
cwirel = relate between cover wwpt and cwinfo</eaover>
      <eadetcit>See file RHA4meta.pdf on ftp site for metadata records for individual data layers.</eadetcit>
    </overview>
  </eainfo>
  <distinfo>
    <resdesc>RHA-4A (http://conservancy.umn.edu/handle/11299/59765)</resdesc>
    <stdorder>
      <digform>
        <digtinfo>
          <formname>Arc Export</formname>
          <formvern>Arc 7.0.4</formvern>
          <transize>Zipfile size is 8.4 MB</transize>
        </digtinfo>
      </digform>
      <ordering>Digital data and PDF files representing map plates are available for download from the University of Minnesota Libraries Digital Conservancy. All digital data for RHA-4A s is provided in the "Supplementary Files" download. The direct Digital Conservancy Link to this product is http://conservancy.umn.edu/handle/11299/59765

To obtain the digital data on DVD, or to obtain paper copies of the geologic map plates, contact the MGS Map Sales Office at 612-626-2969.</ordering>
    </stdorder>
    <distrib>
      <cntinfo>
        <cntperp>
          <cntorg>Minnesota Geological Survey</cntorg>
          <cntper>Timothy E. Wahl</cntper>
        </cntperp>
        <cntpos>Geologic Information Systems</cntpos>
        <cntaddr>
          <addrtype>mailing and physical</addrtype>
          <address>2609 Territorial Road</address>
          <city>St. Paul</city>
          <state>MN</state>
          <postal>55114</postal>
        </cntaddr>
        <cntvoice>612-626-0992</cntvoice>
        <cntemail>tewahl@umn.edu</cntemail>
      </cntinfo>
    </distrib>
  </distinfo>
  <metainfo>
    <metd>20150418</metd>
    <metstdn>Minnesota Geographic Metadata Guidelines</metstdn>
    <metstdv>1.2</metstdv>
    <metextns>
      <onlink>http://www.mngeo.state.mn.us/committee/standards/mgmg/metadata.htm
</onlink>
    </metextns>
    <metc>
      <cntinfo>
        <cntperp>
          <cntorg>Minnesota Geospatial Information Office (MnGeo)</cntorg>
          <cntper>Nancy Rader</cntper>
        </cntperp>
        <cntpos>GIS Data Coordinator</cntpos>
        <cntaddr>
          <addrtype>mailing and physical</addrtype>
          <address>658 Cedar Street</address>
          <city>St. Paul</city>
          <state>MN</state>
          <postal>55155</postal>
        </cntaddr>
        <cntvoice>651-201-2489</cntvoice>
        <cntemail>gisinfo.mngeo@state.mn.us</cntemail>
      </cntinfo>
    </metc>
  </metainfo>
  <spref>
    <horizsys>
      <planar>
        <gridsys>
          <gridsysn>Universal Transverse Mercator</gridsysn>
          <utm>
            <utmzone>15E</utmzone>
          </utm>
        </gridsys>
        <planci>
          <plandu>meters</plandu>
        </planci>
      </planar>
      <geodetic>
        <horizdn>NAD83</horizdn>
        <ellips>GRS80</ellips>
      </geodetic>
    </horizsys>
  </spref>
</metadata>
