<?xml version="1.0"?><!--  <!DOCTYPE metadata SYSTEM "metadata.dtd">  --><metadata><idinfo><citation><citeinfo><origin>Minnesota Geological Survey (MGS)</origin><pubdate>1998</pubdate><title>Geologic Atlas of Mower County, Minnesota (Part A)</title><mgmg1cid></mgmg1cid><pubinfo><publish>Minnesota Geological Survey</publish></pubinfo><onlink>http://conservancy.umn.edu/handle/11299/58549</onlink></citeinfo></citation><descript><abstract>A County Geologic Atlas is a systematic study of a county's geologic and ground water resources. Geologic studies include both near-surface deposits and bedrock. Ground water studies include flow systems, aquifer capacity, and ground water chemistry. In some areas sand and gravel deposits, sinkholes, or other features are studied. Interpretation of sensitivity to pollution is also part of an atlas. The information is organized, analyzed, and displayed using geographic information technology.

Most Geologic Atlas and Regional Hydrogeologic Assessment projects are done in two parts. The Minnesota Geological Survey covers basic geology and creates databases of information such as wells and soil borings in part A. The Minnesota Department of Natural Resources (DNR) handles hydrogeology and ground water sensitivity layers in Part B. Completion of a project's two parts is staggered: Part A is completed about two years before Part B, compiling information used to create part B. Parts A and B are published and distributed as two separate products.</abstract><purpose>County Geologic Atlas and Regional Hydrogeologic Assessment information is used in planning and environmental protection efforts at all levels of government. Wellhead protection and well-sealing programs are examples of local programs that need geologic and ground water information. The information is also used by businesses and the general public.</purpose><supplinf>Mower County, Minnesota</supplinf></descript><timeperd><timeinfo><sngdate><caldate>1998</caldate></sngdate></timeinfo><current>The GIS files were generated in support of the Mower County Geologic Atlas, 1996-1998.  Geologic maps were derived based on information available during the period 1996-1998.</current></timeperd><status><progress>Complete</progress><update>None Planned</update></status><spdom><bounding><westbc>-93.05</westbc><eastbc>-92.44</eastbc><northbc>43.85</northbc><southbc>43.49</southbc></bounding></spdom><keywords><theme><themekt>ISO 19115 Topic Category</themekt><themekey>geoscientificInformation, Bedrock Geology, Surficial Geology, Quaternary Stratigraphy, Bedrock Topography, Wells, Geologic Resources</themekey></theme><place><placekey>Minnesota, MN, Mower County</placekey></place></keywords><accconst>None</accconst><useconst>Credit given to the Minnesota Geological Survey and Mower County for use of data in map products.</useconst><browse><browsen>None available</browsen></browse><native>Arc/INFO Unix environment</native><crossref><citeinfo><title>C-11, Part A. Geologic atlas of Mower County, Minnesota. J.H. Mossler, project manager. 1998. Color. Scale 1:100,000. 6 plates. Plates: 1, Data Base map; 2, Bedrock geology; 3, Surficial geology; 4, Quaternary stratigraphy; 5, Depth to bedrock and bedrock topography; 6, Geologic resources. $16.00.  Paper map and report available from the MGS Map Sales Office (2609 Territorial Road, St. Paul, Minnesota, 55114, 612-626-2969).

For a listing of all geologic maps go to the Minnesota Geological Survey website at: http://www.mngs.umn.edu/mgsdocs.html

For a complete listing of MGS State Map Series Maps, Reports, and GIS Data, see http://conservancy.umn.edu/handle/11299/708

For other County Atlas and Regional Hydrogeologic Assessment data see: http://www.mngs.umn.edu/county_atlas/countyatlas.htm 

For a listing of the status of the DNR Ground Water Mapping Program (Part B), go to: http://www.dnr.state.mn.us/waters/groundwater_section/mapping/index.html
</title></citeinfo></crossref><ptcontac><cntinfo><cntperp><cntorg>Minnesota Geological Survey</cntorg><cntper>General Information</cntper></cntperp><cntpos>Administrative Staff</cntpos><cntaddr><addrtype>Mailing and Physical</addrtype><address>2609 Territorial Road</address><city>St. Paul</city><state>MN</state><postal>55114</postal></cntaddr><cntvoice>612-626-2969</cntvoice><cntemail>mgs@umn.edu</cntemail></cntinfo></ptcontac></idinfo><dataqual><lineage><srcinfo><srcscale>100000</srcscale></srcinfo><procstep><procdesc>Investigations begin with a review of existing information, such as earlier geologic maps, soil maps, and hydrologic reports. Drillers send water well logs to the Minnesota Geological Survey, where they are reviewed, interpreted, and entered into the County Well Index (CWI), an interactive data base of water-well information. Building on the previous data, field studies are conducted to improve the understanding of local geologic and hydrologic conditions. Linework is created based upon the field studies and base data, and digitized. Background GIS data layers such as roads, surface hydrography, township grids, etc., are obtained from various sources. 

Base layers (except township) modified from TIGER census data.   Township grid &amp; annotation, line symbols, fonts, markers, and map layout and plot generation aml prepared by Joyce Meints.

Bedrock related geology linework by John Mossler, Surficial geology related linework by Gary Meyer, ARCINFO cover creation, with digital  editing done predominantly by Emily Bower, Joyce Meints, Phil Heywood  &amp; final editing and cleanup by Joyce Meints.

The majority of geologic linework was scanned off mylar stable base, made into a TIFF image, the image was registered and converted into a GRID  which was then vectorized via VTrace in the Arcedit environment. 
All covers are registered in UTM coordinates, zone 15, NAD83 projection.

See metadata for individual layers (.pdf file). </procdesc></procstep></lineage><logic>See metadata for individual layers (.pdf file). </logic><complete>See metadata for individual layers (.pdf file). </complete><posacc><horizpa><horizpar>See metadata for individual layers (.pdf file). </horizpar></horizpa></posacc><attracc><attraccr>See metadata for individual layers (.pdf file). </attraccr></attracc></dataqual><spdoinfo><indspref></indspref><direct>Vector</direct><mgmg3obj>Point, Vector, Polygon</mgmg3obj><mgmg3til>Mower County</mgmg3til></spdoinfo><eainfo><overview><eaover>This index lists the significant covers and associated files constructed for the Mower County Geologic Atlas, 1996-1998.

BASE LAYERs:
pls =   net cover of public land survey sections
mcd =   net cover of municiple city boundaries
rdln1 =   line cover of major roads
rdln2 =   line cover of minor roads
county =   net cover of county border
cnty =   net cover of county border
hwpt =   point cover of locations for highway symbols
hyln =   line cover of rivers
lkpg =   poly cover of lakes
bsan =   anno. cover for TRS, latlon, city, rivers, township identification
 =   point cover for latlon tics

DATA BASE:
WWPT  =   point cover of located water wells
P1PT =   point cover of cutting sample
SBPT =   point cover of soil boring locations
GRPT =   point cover of gravity station locations
GDPT =   point cover of gidding's hole samples
l1ln =   line/point cover of seismic line trace/symbol
OCPG =   poly cover of outcrop locations
DBCT =   anno cover of rotosonic holes

BEDROCK GEOLOGY:
BGPG  =   net cover of bedrock geology polys and linear structure elements 
BGLN =   line cover of fold axes and cross section traces
BGLNMQ   =  line cover of Maquoketa FM bedrock elevation
KPG  =   poly cover of Cretaceous unit bedrock geology

DRIFT THICKNESS:
DTPG  =   poly cover of drift thickness conotur intervals (in feet)

BEDROCK TOPOGRAPHY:
BTLN  =   line cover of bedrock elevation contours (in feet)

SURFICIAL GEOLOGY:
SGPG =   poly cover of surficial geology 
SGPGSM =   poly cover of sand mantle layer overlying surficial geology
SGLNLS =   line cover of geomorphic line symbols
SGCT  =   anno/line cover of surf. geol. unit labels and flags

SUBSTRATIGRAPHY:
SSPGDT =   poly cover of drift thickness 
SSPGUT =   poly cover of upper till designation

RESOURCE PLATES:
RSPGLS =   poly cover of carbonate resources
RSPGCLAY =  poly cover of Cretaceous clay
RSPGSG =   poly cover of sand and gravel resources
RSPTLS =   point/line cover of pit/quarry locations, mining property boundary
RSPTSG =   point/line cover of gravel pit locations, esker symbol</eaover><eadetcit>See metadata for individual layers (.pdf file). </eadetcit></overview></eainfo><distinfo><resdesc>c11 (http://conservancy.umn.edu/handle/11299/58549)</resdesc><stdorder><digform><digtinfo><formname>Arc/Info Export (uncompressed) in dos or unix formats</formname><formvern></formvern><transize>14.9 MB as zipped tarfile (unix);</transize></digtinfo></digform><ordering>Data download is from the U of M Libraries Digital Conservancy. All GIS data and metadata for the Mower County Geologic Atlas is provided in the zip file C11 Part A Extras.zip. (Supplementary Files). GIS distribution format for most data in this dataset is Esri .e00 (arc interchange format). The direct Digital Conservancy link to PDF map products and GIS data projects (Supplementary Files) for this data set is: http://conservancy.umn.edu/handle/11299/58549 

If you would prefer to have the digital data on DVD, or paper copies of the geologic plates, contact the MGS Map Sales office at 612-626-2969 and specify publication County Atlas Series C-11, part A, or County Geologic Atlas of Mower County.</ordering></stdorder><distrib><cntinfo><cntperp><cntorg>Minnesota Geological Survey</cntorg><cntper>Timothy E. Wahl</cntper></cntperp><cntpos>Geologic Information Systems</cntpos><cntaddr><addrtype>mailing and physical</addrtype><address>2609 Territorial Road</address><city>St. Paul</city><state>MN</state><postal>55114</postal></cntaddr><cntvoice>612-626-0992</cntvoice><cntemail>tewahl@umn.edu</cntemail></cntinfo></distrib></distinfo><metainfo><metd>20150416</metd><metstdn>Minnesota Geographic Metadata Guidelines</metstdn><metstdv>1.2</metstdv><metextns><onlink>http://www.mngeo.state.mn.us/committee/standards/mgmg/metadata.htm</onlink></metextns><metc><cntinfo><cntperp><cntorg>Minnesota Geospatial Information Office (MnGeo)</cntorg><cntper>Nancy Rader</cntper></cntperp><cntpos>GIS Data Coordinator</cntpos><cntaddr><addrtype>mailing and physical</addrtype><address>658 Cedar Street, Room 300</address><city>St. Paul</city><state>MN</state><postal>55155</postal></cntaddr><cntvoice>651-201-2489</cntvoice><cntemail>gisinfo.mngeo@state.mn.us</cntemail></cntinfo></metc></metainfo><spref><horizsys><planar><gridsys><gridsysn>Universal Transverse Mercator</gridsysn><utm><utmzone>15E</utmzone></utm></gridsys><planci><plandu>meters</plandu></planci></planar><geodetic><horizdn>NAD83</horizdn><ellips>GRS80</ellips></geodetic></horizsys></spref></metadata>