<metadata>
	<idinfo>
		<citation>
			<citeinfo>
				<origin>Minnesota Department of Natural Resources (MNDNR)</origin>
				<title catid="5b357c21-90b7-4420-9019-7ec3dad0b8da">Digital Elevation Model - 10 Meter Resolution Covering Minnesota Watersheds</title>
				<pubinfo>
					<publish>Minnesota Department of Natural Resources (MNDNR)</publish>
				</pubinfo>
				<pubdate>20090101</pubdate>
				<onlink>http://gisdata.mn.gov/dataset/elev-10m-digital-elevation-model</onlink>
			</citeinfo>
		</citation>
		<descript>
			<abstract>This 10 Meter Digital Elevation Model (DEM) is derived from the USGS National Elevation Dataset (NED), edition 2.  It covers the state of Minnesota and the portions of surrounding states and Canadian provinces which contribute to watersheds within Minnesota.

The source rasters used by USGS vary in resolution, from 30m to 10m and in limited areas 3 meters.  These source data have been resampled to a consistent 10 meter product for use at intermediate scales. 

Please note that there is a file geodatabase with a metadata feature class that includes the source data information for each tile that was used to create this DEM.</abstract>
			<purpose>Landscape analysis, hillshade generation for cartographic products, slope determination </purpose>
			<supplinf>Minnesota and portions of North Dakota, South Dakota, Iowa, Wisconsin, Michigan, Ontario, Manitoba</supplinf>
		</descript>
		<timeperd>
			<current>Time Period of Content Date indicates when dataset was last updated.</current>
			<timeinfo>
				<sngdate>
					<caldate>20090101</caldate>
				</sngdate>
			</timeinfo>
		</timeperd>
		<status>
			<progress>Complete</progress>
			<update>None Planned</update>
		</status>
		<spdom>
			<bounding>
				<westbc>-97.23</westbc>
				<eastbc>-89.53</eastbc>
				<northbc>49.37</northbc>
				<southbc>43.5</southbc>
			</bounding>
		</spdom>
		<keywords>
			<place>
				<placekey>Minnesota, MN</placekey>
			</place>
			<theme>
				<themekt>ISO 19115 Category</themekt>
				<themekey>elevation, model, slope</themekey>
			</theme>
		</keywords>
		<browse>
			<browsen>ftp://gdrs.dnr.state.mn.us/gdrs/data/pub/us_mn_state_dnr/elev_10m_digital_elevation_model/preview/preview.jpg</browsen>
		</browse>
		<accconst>None</accconst>
		<useconst>Use of the data are constrained only by the DNR GIS Data License Agreement. See the Distribution Liability section below for a link.</useconst>
		<ptcontac>
			<cntinfo>
				<cntperp>
					<cntorg>Minnesota Department of Natural Resources</cntorg>
					<cntper>Hal Watson</cntper>
				</cntperp>
				<cntpos>GIS Section Manager</cntpos>
				<cntaddr>
					<addrtype>Mailing</addrtype>
					<address>500 Lafayette Rd</address>
					<address>Central Office - Box 29</address>
					<city>St. Paul</city>
					<state>MN</state>
					<postal>55155-4025</postal>
				</cntaddr>
				<cntvoice>651-259-5508</cntvoice>
				<cntemail>hal.watson@state.mn.us</cntemail>
			</cntinfo>
		</ptcontac>
	</idinfo>
	<distinfo>
		<resdesc>elev_10m_digital_elevation_model</resdesc>
		<distliab>The Minnesota Department of Natural Resources General Geographic Data License Agreement is online: http://www.dnr.state.mn.us/sitetools/data_software_license.html</distliab>
		<stdorder>
			<ordering>Please visit the download page for this dataset on the Minnesota Geospatial Commons website using the web link below (Online Linkage).</ordering>
		</stdorder>
		<distrib>
			<cntinfo>
				<cntperp>
					<cntorg>Minnesota Department of Natural Resources</cntorg>
					<cntper>Zeb Thomas</cntper>
				</cntperp>
				<cntpos>GIS Data Systems Coordinator</cntpos>
				<cntaddr>
					<addrtype>Mailing and Physical</addrtype>
					<address>500 Lafayette Rd</address>
					<city>St. Paul</city>
					<state>MN</state>
					<postal>55155-4011</postal>
				</cntaddr>
				<cntvoice>651-259-5637</cntvoice>
				<cntemail>zeb.thomas@state.mn.us</cntemail>
			</cntinfo>
		</distrib>
	</distinfo>
	<dataqual>
		<logic>The data exists within a data structure consistent with ESRI GRID format requirements.</logic>
		<posacc>
			<horizpa>
				<horizpar>USGS does not make claims as to the horizontal positional accuracy of this data, however it is fair to assume that this data meets national map accuracy standards for data at scales of 1:24,000 or smaller.  The horizontal standard at that scale is +/- 40 feet. 

Nonetheless, There is no guarantee or warranty concerning the accuracy of the data.  Users should be aware that temporal changes may have occurred since this data set was collected and that some parts of this data may no longer represent actual surface conditions.  Users should not use this data for critical applications without a full awareness of its limitations.</horizpar>
			</horizpa>
			<vertacc>
				<vertaccr>Vertical accuracy specifications for dem DEM data depend on the production methodology, photogrammetric source, and degree of editing. A vertical root mean square error (RMSE) of 7 meters or less is the desired accuracy standard. A RMSE of 15 meters is the maximum permitted. Distinct north-south tonal banding is visible in quads with larger RMSE's. This data noise becomes especially prevalent in derived products, such as hillshades, aspect, and slope layers. Because this dataset is comprised of various sources, if you need specific information please look at the metadata.gdb geodatabase for detail on the original source tiles for your area of interest.</vertaccr>
			</vertacc>
		</posacc>
		<lineage>
			<procstep>
				<procdesc>This data is based on the USGS NED dataset, edition 2 published in 2009.  Source data is older and varies in age across the DEM.

There are three quadrangles known be be Level 1 DEM data: Town Line Lake (q1925), Grand Portage (q1261) and Grand Portage OE N (q1161).</procdesc>
			</procstep>
		</lineage>
		<complete>Data are complete over the area of the State of Minnesota</complete>
		<attracc>
			<attraccr>There is no guarantee or warranty concerning the accuracy of the data.  Users should be aware that temporal changes may have occurred since this data set was collected and that some parts of this data may no longer represent actual surface conditions.</attraccr>
		</attracc>
	</dataqual>
	<spdoinfo>
		<indspref>Not Applicable</indspref>
		<direct>vector</direct>
		<mgmg3obj>line</mgmg3obj>
		<mgmg3til />
	</spdoinfo>
	
	<metainfo>
		<metd>20140725</metd>
		<metstdn>Minnesota Geographic Metadata Guidelines</metstdn>
		<metstdv>1.2</metstdv>
		<metextns>
			<onlink>http://www.mngeo.state.mn.us/committee/standards/mgmg/metadata.htm</onlink>
		</metextns>
		<metc>
			<cntinfo>
				<cntperp>
					<cntorg>Minnesota Department of Natural Resources</cntorg>
					<cntper>Zeb Thomas</cntper>
				</cntperp>
				<cntpos>GIS Data Systems Coordinator</cntpos>
				<cntaddr>
					<addrtype>Mailing and Physical</addrtype>
					<address>500 Lafayette Rd</address>
					<city>St. Paul</city>
					<state>MN</state>
					<postal>55155-4011</postal>
				</cntaddr>
				<cntvoice>651-259-5637</cntvoice>
				<cntemail>zeb.thomas@state.mn.us</cntemail>
			</cntinfo>
		</metc>
	</metainfo>
	<eainfo>
		<overview>
			<eaover>Please note that the vertical datum for grid cell (altitude) values is:  North American Vertical Datum of 1988</eaover>
		</overview>
	</eainfo>
	<spref>
		<horizsys>
			<planar>
				<gridsys>
					<gridsysn>Universal Transverse Mercator</gridsysn>
					<utm>
						<utmzone>15</utmzone>
					</utm>
				</gridsys>
				<planci>
					<plandu>meters</plandu>
					<coordrep>
						<absres>10</absres>
						<ordres>10</ordres>
					</coordrep>
				</planci>
			</planar>
			<geodetic>
				<horizdn>NAD83</horizdn>
				<ellips>GRS80</ellips>
			</geodetic>
		</horizsys>
	</spref>
</metadata>