<?xml version="1.0"?><metadata xml:lang="en"><idinfo><native>Microsoft Windows XP Version 5.1 (Build 2600) Service Pack 3; ESRI ArcCatalog 9.3.1.4000</native><descript><abstract>This is a set of the impaired lakes as determined by MPCA in 2011 for the 2012 reporting cycling to US EPA.

The lakes are a subset and enhancement of the 1:24,000 scale National Hydrography Dataset (NHD). MPCA adds additional lakes. Since the impaired lakes are a small subset of the NHD lakes, only that subset is included in the dataset.  This dataset includes impaired lakes which have not yet had a TMDL plan approved by the US EPA, those that have a US EPA approved TMDL plan as well as those lakes that do not need a TMDL plan.</abstract><purpose>The data set was created as part of the Minnesota Pollution Control Agency's Environmental Data Access System, which allows for public access to surface water monitoring data.</purpose><supplinf>State of Minnesota</supplinf></descript><citation><citeinfo><origin>Minnesota Pollution Control Agency</origin><pubdate>20130823</pubdate><title>Impaired Lakes 2012</title><geoform>vector digital data</geoform><pubinfo><publish>Minnesota Pollution Control Agency</publish></pubinfo></citeinfo></citation><timeperd><current>August 23, 2013</current><timeinfo><sngdate><caldate>20130823</caldate></sngdate></timeinfo></timeperd><status><progress>Complete</progress><update>None Planned</update></status><spdom><bounding><westbc>-97.140714</westbc><eastbc>-89.389596</eastbc><northbc>49.394786</northbc><southbc>43.439806</southbc></bounding></spdom><keywords><theme><themekey>surface water, water chemistry, water quality, impaired waters, TMDL, 303(d)</themekey></theme><place><placekey>Minnesota</placekey></place></keywords><accconst>None</accconst><browse><browsen>None available</browsen><browsed /></browse><crossref><citeinfo><title>Minnesota 2012 Inventory of Impaired Lakes, August 2013
Minnesota 2012 Inventory of Impaired Wetlands, August 2013</title></citeinfo></crossref><ptcontac><cntinfo><cntperp><cntorg>Minnesota Pollution Control Agency</cntorg><cntper>Kris Parson</cntper></cntperp><cntpos>GIS Specialist</cntpos><cntaddr><address>520 Lafayette Road</address><city>St Paul</city><state>MN</state><postal>55155</postal></cntaddr><cntvoice>(651) 757-2639</cntvoice><cntfax>(651) 282-5446</cntfax><cntemail>kristofor.parson@state.mn.us</cntemail></cntinfo></ptcontac></idinfo><dataIdInfo><envirDesc>Microsoft Windows 7 Version 6.1 (Build 7601) Service Pack 1; Esri ArcGIS 10.1.1.3143</envirDesc><dataLang><languageCode value="eng" /><countryCode value="USA" /></dataLang><idCitation><resTitle>impaired_2012_lakes</resTitle><presForm><PresFormCd value="005" /></presForm></idCitation><spatRpType><SpatRepTypCd value="001" /></spatRpType><dataExt><geoEle><GeoBndBox esriExtentType="native"><westBL>199125.3915</westBL><eastBL>762254.478025</eastBL><northBL>5471343.775427</northBL><southBL>4816373.296348</southBL><exTypeCode>1</exTypeCode></GeoBndBox></geoEle></dataExt><geoBox esriExtentType="decdegrees"><westBL>-97.140714</westBL><eastBL>-89.389596</eastBL><northBL>49.394786</northBL><southBL>43.439806</southBL><exTypeCode>1</exTypeCode></geoBox><dataExt><geoEle><GeoBndBox esriExtentType="search"><exTypeCode>1</exTypeCode><westBL>-97.140714</westBL><eastBL>-89.389596</eastBL><northBL>49.394786</northBL><southBL>43.439806</southBL></GeoBndBox></geoEle></dataExt></dataIdInfo><metainfo><metstdn>Minnesota Geographic Metadata Guidelines</metstdn><metstdv>1.2</metstdv><mettc>local time</mettc><metd>20130823</metd><metextns><onlink>http://www.gis.state.mn.us/stds/metadata.htm</onlink><metprof>ESRI Metadata Profile</metprof></metextns><metc><cntinfo><cntperp><cntorg>Minnesota Pollution Control Agency</cntorg><cntper>Kris Parson</cntper></cntperp><cntpos>GIS Specialist</cntpos><cntaddr><address>520 Lafayette Road North</address><city>St Paul</city><state>MN</state><postal>55155</postal></cntaddr><cntvoice>(651) 757-2639</cntvoice><cntfax>(651) 282-5446</cntfax><cntemail>kristofor.parson@state.mn.us</cntemail></cntinfo></metc></metainfo><mdLang><languageCode value="eng" /><countryCode value="USA" /></mdLang><mdStanName>ISO 19115 Geographic Information - Metadata</mdStanName><mdStanVer>DIS_ESRI1.0</mdStanVer><mdChar><CharSetCd value="004" /></mdChar><mdHrLv><ScopeCd value="005" /></mdHrLv><mdHrLvName>dataset</mdHrLvName><distinfo><stdorder><digform><digtinfo><transize>12.423</transize><formname>Shapefile</formname><formvern /></digtinfo></digform></stdorder><distliab>NOTICE: The Geographic Information System (GIS) Data to which this notice is attached are made available pursuant to the Minnesota Government Data Practices Act (Minnesota Statutes Chapter 13). THE GIS DATA ARE PROVIDED TO YOU AS IS AND WITHOUT ANY WARRANTY AS TO THEIR PERFORMANCE, MERCHANTABILITY, OR FITNESS FOR ANY PARTICULAR PURPOSE. The GIS Data were developed by the Minnesota Pollution Control Agnecy for its own internal business purposes. The Minnesota Pollution Control Agency does not represent or warrant that the GIS Data or the data documentation are error-free, complete, current, or accurate. You are responsible for any consequences resulting from your use of the GIS Data or your reliance on the GIS Data. You should consult the data documentation for this particular GIS Data to determine the limitations of the GIS Data and the precision with which the GIS Data may depict distance, direction, location, or other geographic features. If you transmit or provide the GIS Data (or any portion of it) to another user, the GIS Data must include a copy of this disclaimer.</distliab><distrib><cntinfo><cntperp><cntorg>Minnesota Pollution Control Agency</cntorg><cntper>Kris Parson</cntper></cntperp><cntpos>GIS Specialist</cntpos><cntaddr><address>520 Lafayette Road</address><city>St Paul</city><state>MN</state><postal>55125</postal></cntaddr><cntvoice>(651) 757-2639</cntvoice><cntfax>(651) 282-5446</cntfax><cntemail>kristofor.parson@state.mn.us</cntemail></cntinfo></distrib></distinfo><distInfo><distributor><distorTran><onLineSrc><orDesc>002</orDesc><linkage>file://\\s-sp07\GISlib\Projects\KParson\Water\303d\2012_EPA_Submission\draft_spatial\shapefiles\tmdl12_draft_lakes.shp</linkage><protocol>Local Area Network</protocol></onLineSrc><transSize>16.130</transSize></distorTran><distorFormat><formatName>Shapefile</formatName></distorFormat></distributor><distFormat><formatName>Shapefile</formatName></distFormat><distTranOps><transSize>16.134</transSize></distTranOps></distInfo><spdoinfo><direct>Vector</direct><indspref /><mgmg3obj /><mgmg3til /><ptvctinf /></spdoinfo><spref><horizsys><planar><planci><plance>coordinate pair</plance><plandu>Meters</plandu></planci></planar><geodetic><horizdn /><ellips>Geodetic Reference System 80</ellips><semiaxis>6378137.000000</semiaxis><denflat>298.257222</denflat></geodetic></horizsys></spref><refSysInfo><RefSystem><refSysID><identCode value="26915" code="26915">NAD_1983_UTM_Zone_15N</identCode><idCodeSpace>EPSG</idCodeSpace><idVersion>7.11.2</idVersion></refSysID></RefSystem></refSysInfo><spatRepInfo><VectSpatRep><geometObjs><geoObjTyp><GeoObjTypCd value="002" /></geoObjTyp><geoObjCnt>1463</geoObjCnt></geometObjs><topLvl><TopoLevCd value="001" /></topLvl></VectSpatRep></spatRepInfo><eainfo><detailed><enttyp><enttypl>impaired_2012_lakes</enttypl></enttyp><attr><attrlabl>FID</attrlabl><attrdef>Internal feature number.</attrdef><attrdefs>ESRI</attrdefs><attrdomv><udom>Sequential unique whole numbers that are automatically generated.</udom></attrdomv></attr><attr><attrlabl>Shape</attrlabl><attrdef>Feature geometry.</attrdef><attrdefs>ESRI</attrdefs><attrdomv><udom>Coordinates defining the features.</udom></attrdomv></attr><attr><attrlabl>AUID</attrlabl></attr><attr><attrlabl>WATER_NAME</attrlabl></attr><attr><attrlabl>LOCATION</attrlabl></attr><attr><attrlabl>NEEDSPLN</attrlabl></attr><attr><attrlabl>WATER_SIZE</attrlabl></attr><attr><attrlabl>HUC8</attrlabl></attr><attr><attrlabl>IMPAIR_PAR</attrlabl></attr><attr><attrlabl>NEW_2012</attrlabl></attr><attr><attrlabl>Cl_</attrlabl></attr><attr><attrlabl>PFOS</attrlabl></attr><attr><attrlabl>HGF</attrlabl></attr><attr><attrlabl>HGW</attrlabl></attr><attr><attrlabl>PCBF</attrlabl></attr><attr><attrlabl>CAT</attrlabl></attr><attr><attrlabl>Nutrients</attrlabl></attr><attr><attrlabl>APPROVED</attrlabl></attr><attr><attrlabl>NOPLN</attrlabl></attr><attr><attrlabl>BASIN</attrlabl></attr><attr><attrlabl>HUC8_NAME</attrlabl></attr><attr><attrlabl>DELISTED</attrlabl></attr><attr><attrlabl>AFFECTED_U</attrlabl></attr><attr><attrlabl>WDWMO_NAME</attrlabl></attr><attr><attrlabl>WDWMO_TYPE</attrlabl></attr></detailed><overview><eaover>All lakes contained in this shapefile are on the approved 2012 Impaired Waters list prepared by the Minnesota Pollution Control Agency, have a TMDL plan approved by EPA or have been delisted.</eaover><eadetcit>AUID:  Assessment Unit ID, a waterbody identifer that is the eight digit subbasin code and the three digit reach number. This AUID constitutes a unique identifer for each reach in the dataset. 

WATER_NAME: Name of the waterbody associated with the AUID

LOCATION: A rough description of the lake's location

CAT: EPA Consolidation Assessment and Listing Methodology [CALM] which integrates the 305(b) Report with the 303(d) TMDL List. 
   The five categories in CALM are as follows: 
   Category 1: all designated uses are meeting water quality standards 
   Category 2: some uses are meeting water quality standards and there are insufficient data to assess other uses 
   Category 3: there are insufficient data to assess any uses 
   Category 4: at least one use is impaired, but a TMDL is not required 
   Category 5: at least one use is impaired and a TMDL is required. These become the List of impaired waters. 

   A reach can only be placed into one Category. For example, if a reach is impaired for one pollutant but the other uses are being  met, and a TMDL is required, that reach would be placed into Category 5. Furthermore, if the reach is impaired for more than one pollutant, the reach must stay in Category 5 until ALL pollutants have EPA-approved TMDL plans. 

   For 'bookkeeping' purposes, these Categories can be sub-divided. Category 4 has the following four sub-categories: 
   4A: Impaired, but a TMDL study has been approved by EPA 
   4B: Impaired, but a TMDL study is not required because water quality standards are expected to be met in the near future 
   4C: Impaired, but a TMDL study is not required because the impairment is not caused by a pollutant 
   4D: An assessment unit is impaired or threatened but doesn't require a TMDL because the impairment is due to natural conditions with only insignificant anthropogenic influence. To be considered 'insignificant', the elimination of the anthropogenic influence would not lead to the attainment of water quality standards and it would not be included in formal pollution reduction goal-setting  activities. A reach-specific water quality standard based on local natural conditions has yet to be determined. Upon determination,    the assessment unit will be considered non-impaired for the natural conditions and re-categorized to an appropriate category. 
   4E: Impaired or threatened but existing data indicates a TMDL is not required because impairment is solely a result of natural    sources; a final determination of Category 4D will be made in the next assessment cycle pending confirmation from additional    information (i.e. water quality or land use). 

   Category 5 has the following three sub-categories: 
   5A: Impaired by multiple pollutants and no TMDL study plans are approved by EPA 
   5B: Impaired by multiple pollutants and at least one TMDL study plan is approved by EPA 
   5C: Impaired by one pollutant and no TMDL study plan is approved by EPA 

WATER_SIZE: The acreage of the lake

Affected_U:  Impaired Use(s)
   Values: 
   AQC = Aquatic Consumption
   AQR = Aquatic Recreation
   a combination of these values

NOPLN: The parameter(s) for which no TMDL plans is required

APPROVED: The parameter(s) for which TMDL plans have been approved
   Values:
   HgF= Mercury in Fish Tissue
   HgW= Mercury in Water Column
   Nutrients = Nutrients

NEEDSPLN: The pollutant(s) for which TMDL plans must be developed and approved
   Values:
   CL- = Chloride
   HgF= Mercury in Fish Tissue
   HgW= Mercury in Water Column
   Nutrients = Nutrients
   PCBF = PCBs in Fish
   PFOS = Perfluorooctane Sulfonate (PFOS) in Fish Tissue
   
IMPAIR_PAR: Parameters listed in APPROVED and NEEDSPLN that cause the stream to be impaired

NEW2012: Parameters proposed to be listed for the first time in 2010

CL_: The target start year for a TMDL project addressing this parameter - Chloride

HgF: The target start year for a TMDL project addressing this parameter - Mercury in fish tissue

HgW: The target start year for a TMDL project addressing this parameter - Mercury in the water xolumn

Nutrients: The target start year for a TMDL project addressing this parameter - Nutrients

PCBF: The target start year for a TMDL project addressing this parameter - Polychlorinated Biphenyls in fish tissue

PFOS: The target start year for a TMDL project addressing this parameter - Perfluorooctane sulfonate

DELISTED: The parameter(s) have been removed (delisted) from the 303(d) list

HUC8: 8-digit Federal Hydrologic Unit Code (Subbasin)

HUC8_NAME: Name of the 8 digit HUC the waterbody is in

BASIN: The name of the 4 digit HUC the waterbody is in

WDWMO_NAME = Watershed District(s) or Watershed Management Organization Name(s).  Reaches that intersect multiple entities will have multiple organizations listed.

WDWMO_TYPE = Type of Organization.  Where multiple entities are listed, their corresponding types are listed in the same order as WDWMO_NAME.
    Values:
     COU = County
     WD = Watershed District
     WMO = Watershed Management Organization</eadetcit></overview></eainfo><mdDateSt>20130813</mdDateSt><dataqual><attracc><attraccr>These data have been reviewed and approved by EPA.</attraccr></attracc><lineage><srcinfo><srcscale>24000</srcscale></srcinfo></lineage></dataqual></metadata>