<?xml version="1.0"?><!--  <!DOCTYPE metadata SYSTEM "metadata.dtd">  --><metadata><idinfo><citation><citeinfo><origin>Minnesota Geospatial Information Office</origin><pubdate>unknown</pubdate><title>Public Land Survey API Service, Minnesota</title><mgmg1cid></mgmg1cid><pubinfo><publish>Minnesota Geospatial Information Office</publish></pubinfo><onlink>http://www.mngeo.state.mn.us/chouse/pls/pls_api.html</onlink></citeinfo></citation><descript><abstract>The PLS (public land survey) API (application programming interface) service provides public land survey descriptions, UTM coordinates, and some place names for point locations in Minnesota. An interactive webpage lets you type in coordinates (UTM, geographic, or PLS) or place names (county, quad name, township name) for a point location and then displays all of those coordinates and place names for that point.

The PLS API homepage links to the interactive webpage and to a technical description of the API service.</abstract><purpose>PLS API partially replaces the SECTIC-24K software program (which does not run on Windows 7 64-bit computers). SECTIC-24K, last revised in the 1990s, is a database of public land survey section corners of Minnesota as recorded on the most recent edition of the U.S. Geological Survey's 1:24,000-scale 7.5-minute quadrangle maps available at that time. The database attempts to best fit the section corner locations shown on the published maps, even though better real world data for the locations of the section corners might be available elsewhere. Note that the PLS API service does not do NAD27 &lt;-&gt; NAD83 translations as SECTIC did.</purpose><supplinf>Minnesota</supplinf></descript><timeperd><current>The API uses section corner data as recorded on the most recent edition of the U.S. Geological Survey's 1:24,000-scale 7.5-minute quadrangle maps available. Map dates ranged from the late 1940s to the late 1970s.</current></timeperd><status><progress>Complete</progress><update>None Planned</update></status><spdom><bounding><westbc>-97.23</westbc><eastbc>-89.53</eastbc><northbc>49.37</northbc><southbc>43.5</southbc></bounding></spdom><keywords><theme><themekt>ISO 19115 Topic Category</themekt><themekey>planningCadastre, PLS, PLSS, public land survey</themekey></theme><place><placekey>Minnesota, MN</placekey></place></keywords><accconst>None.</accconst><useconst>In obtaining this service from MnGeo, it is understood that you and/or your organization have the right to use it for any purpose. If you use the service to transmit or provide data to another user, it is your responsibility to provide appropriate content, limitation, warranty and liability information as you see fit.</useconst><browse><browsen>http://geoint.lmic.state.mn.us/pete/pls.html</browsen><browsed>An interactive webpage that uses the PLS API service</browsed></browse><native></native><crossref><citeinfo><title>1. SECTIC-24K:  http://www.mngeo.state.mn.us/chouse/metadata/sectic.html 

2. Township, Range, and Section (TRS) Boundaries, Minnesota: https://gisdata.mn.gov/dataset/plan-mngeo-trs</title></citeinfo></crossref><ptcontac><cntinfo><cntperp><cntorg>Minnesota Geospatial Information Office (MnGeo)</cntorg><cntper>Pete Olson</cntper></cntperp><cntpos>Systems Programmer</cntpos><cntaddr><addrtype>mailing and physical</addrtype><address>658 Cedar Street, Room 300</address><city>St. Paul</city><state>MN</state><postal>55155</postal></cntaddr><cntvoice>651-201-2467</cntvoice><cntfax>651-296-6398</cntfax><cntemail>gisinfo.mngeo@state.mn.us</cntemail></cntinfo></ptcontac></idinfo><dataqual><lineage><procstep>Criteria for Selecting the Imagery to Include in the Service

The Composite Image Service Workgroup evaluated candidate imagery on a number of factors including color, currency, resolution, coverage, season, leaf cover and image quality in order to determine which imagery to include at which scale. No quality is definitively more important than another, and different qualities may have different priorities at different scales.

The workgroup selected true-color Landsat scenes for small scales (state- and region-wide) and the most recent Farm Service Agency NAIP imagery for medium scales. The NAIP imagery also serves as the 'default' large-scale background in areas that do not have higher resolution imagery available. Beyond that, the workgroup discussed a long list of imagery concerns and agreed that decisions about large scale, high-resolution imagery choices would primarily come down to balancing three: currentness, resolution, and accuracy.

Some additional guidelines used:

- True color imagery is preferred.
- Recent imagery is preferred to older imagery.
- Imagery acquired during the winter months is not preferred.
- Leaf-off is acceptable at large scales.
- Lower resolution is preferred at smaller scales.
- Higher resolution is preferred at larger scales.
- Datasets with larger coverage areas are preferred to patchy coverages.
- Image quality is subjective; images may meet or exceed technical specifications of other imagery but still be rejected based on image quality.


Layers that are Displayed at Different Scales and Links to Source Imagery Documentation:

For each of these, the layers higher in the list will show through in areas not covered by layers further down. For example, Landsat will continue to be displayed across bordering states where the FSA 2010 data does not exist.

1:250,000-scale and above
- 1999-2002 Landsat: http://landsat.usgs.gov

1:250,000 - 1:10,000 scale
- 2010 Farm Service Agency NAIP for Minnesota: http://www.mngeo.state.mn.us/chouse/airphoto/naip10.html
- 2008 FSA NAIP for the following western Wisconsin counties: Douglas, Washburn, Polk, Barron, Dunn, St. Croix, Eau Claire, Pierce, Pepin, Jackson, Trempealeau, Buffalo, Monroe, La Crosse, Vernon, Richland, Crawford and Grant.

1:10,000 - 1:3,000 scale
- 2010 natural color leaf-off imagery for 11 counties in the Twin Cities metro area ( Anoka, Carver, Chisago, Dakota, Hennepin, Isanti, Ramsey, Scott, Sherburne, Washington and Wright): http://www.mngeo.state.mn.us/chouse/airphoto/ecmn10.html

&lt;1:3,000-scale
- 2006 NGA (National Geospatial-Intelligence Agency) over downtown St. Paul; this was used since there was excessive building lean in the 2010 leaf-off imagery:   http://extract.cr.usgs.gov/distmeta/servlet/gov.usgs.edc.MetaBuilder?TYPE=HTML&amp;DATASET=UA_292_03<procdesc>See the metadata for SECTIC-24K:  http://www.mngeo.state.mn.us/chouse/metadata/sectic.html

and the PLS API for Minnesota homepage:  http://www.mngeo.state.mn.us/chouse/pls/pls_api.html</procdesc></procstep></lineage><posacc><horizpa><horizpar>The database attempts to best fit the section corner locations shown on the published maps, even though better real world data for the locations of the section corners might be available elsewhere.</horizpar></horizpa></posacc><attracc><attraccr>See:  http://www.mngeo.state.mn.us/chouse/pls/pls_api.html</attraccr></attracc></dataqual><spdoinfo><indspref></indspref><direct>Raster</direct><mgmg3obj>Cell</mgmg3obj><mgmg3til></mgmg3til></spdoinfo><spref><vertdef><altsys><altdatum>not applicable</altdatum></altsys><depthsys><depthdn>not applicable</depthdn></depthsys></vertdef><horizsys><planar><gridsys><gridsysn>Universal Transverse Mercator</gridsysn><utm><utmzone>15</utmzone></utm></gridsys><planci><plandu>meters</plandu></planci></planar><geodetic><horizdn>NAD83</horizdn><ellips>GRS80</ellips></geodetic></horizsys></spref><eainfo><overview><eaover>utmx = NAD83 values of the x UTM coordinates
utmy = NAD83 values of the y UTM coordinates
latitude = latitude coordinates in degress
longitude = longitude coordinates in degrees

Public Land Survey descriptions of a location:
township = township number
range = range number
direction = direction number 1=E, 2=W (defaults to 2)
section = section number (1-36)
quarters = up to 6 quarterings identified by the letters A, B, C, D (A=NE, B=NW, C=SW, D=SE) (example: DCA)

county = county name
quad = 24K quad name
townname = township name (not all townships have names)

Additional optional parameters are described on the webpage:  http://www.mngeo.state.mn.us/chouse/pls/pls_api.html 


</eaover></overview></eainfo><distinfo><distliab>MnGeo's disclaimer is online:  http://www.mngeo.state.mn.us/chouse/disclaimer.html</distliab><stdorder><digform><digtinfo><formname></formname><formvern></formvern><transize></transize></digtinfo></digform><ordering>Click below after Online Linkage to get to the PLS API for Minnesota homepage which links to the interactive webpage and to a technical description of the API service.</ordering></stdorder><resdesc>PLS API for Minnesota</resdesc><distrib><cntinfo><cntperp><cntorg>Minnesota Geospatial Information Office (MnGeo)</cntorg><cntper>Nancy Rader</cntper></cntperp><cntpos>GIS Data Coordinator</cntpos><cntaddr><addrtype>mailing and physical</addrtype><address>658 Cedar Street, Room 300</address><city>St. Paul</city><state>MN</state><postal>55155</postal></cntaddr><cntvoice>651-201-2489</cntvoice><cntfax>651-296-6398</cntfax><cntemail>gisinfo.mngeo@state.mn.us</cntemail></cntinfo></distrib></distinfo><metainfo><metd>20141224</metd><metstdn>Minnesota Geographic Metadata Guidelines</metstdn><metstdv>1.2</metstdv><metextns><onlink>http://www.gis.state.mn.us/stds/metadata.htm</onlink></metextns><metc><cntinfo><cntperp><cntorg>Minnesota Geospatial Information Office (MnGeo)</cntorg><cntper>Nancy Rader</cntper></cntperp><cntpos>GIS Data Coordinator</cntpos><cntaddr><addrtype>mailing and physical</addrtype><address>658 Cedar Street, Room 300</address><city>St. Paul</city><state>MN</state><postal>55155</postal></cntaddr><cntvoice>651-201-2489</cntvoice><cntfax>651-296-6398</cntfax><cntemail>gisinfo.mngeo@state.mn.us</cntemail></cntinfo></metc></metainfo></metadata>