<?xml version="1.0"?><metadata><idinfo><citation><citeinfo><origin>Minnesota Department of Transportation, Office of Land Management</origin><title>Right of Way Plat and Commissioner's Graphic Order - Raster Image File Footprints, Minnesota</title><pubinfo><publish>Minnesota Department of Transportation, Office of Land Management</publish></pubinfo><pubdate>periodically revised</pubdate><onlink>https://gisdata.mn.gov/dataset/trans-georef-frwplat-footprints</onlink></citeinfo></citation><descript><abstract>The Right of Way Plat and Commissioner's Graphic Orders footprints layer is a statewide data set.  The footprints are constructed from the scanned right of way plat images (raster data) that were georeferenced using the Department of Natural Resource's Control Point Generated Public Land Survey Coverage (vector data), MnDOT's Statewide Basemap (vector data), and other reference data sets as necessary to support the positioning of the images.</abstract><purpose>The data set was created to enhance the accessibility to right of way plats by enabling the use of spatial indexing tools.  Georeferencing right of way plats is helping to assist the transition toward a more automated land information system.  Footprints are created to represent the extent of the Plats and have the advantage of shortening load time.</purpose><supplinf>Statewide</supplinf></descript><browse><browsen>None available</browsen></browse><crossref><citeinfo><title>Right of Way Map - Raster Image Files 
Right of Way Map - Raster Image File Footprints
Right of Way Map - Vector (CAD) Files
Right of Way Map - Vector (CAD) File Footprints
Original Highway Right of Way Plat Maps
Commissioner's Orders
Control Point Generated Public Land Survey 
</title></citeinfo></crossref><timeperd><current>The highway right of way plat and graphic commissioner's order documents are used as the basis for the footprints. The outer border of the document's electronic file image defines the footprint's shape. MnDOT's Office of Land Management LIS and Right of Way Mapping Unit intermittently geo-references and footprints batches of these documents and they become finalized by the Office's Platting Unit. This collection may not include recently completed plat or order footprints and is dependent upon work schedules and the available resources that are required to update the data set. For a current plat or graphic order listing see Contact Person Information in this document.</current><timeinfo><sngdate><caldate>Continuous</caldate></sngdate></timeinfo></timeperd><status><progress>In work</progress><update>As needed</update></status><spdom><bounding><westbc>-97.5</westbc><eastbc>-89.0</eastbc><northbc>49.5</northbc><southbc>43.0</southbc></bounding></spdom><keywords><place><placekey>County,
Section,
Township,
Range,
Minnesota,
Control Section,
Minnesota State Highway
</placekey></place><theme><themekey>transportation,
MnDOT Right of Way Plat,
Trunk Highway,
Parcel,
Minnesota State Highway,
Roads,
Commissioner orders,
Graphic orders,
Highway Right of Way,
State Highway,
US Highway,
Interstate Highway,
Statewide_PLAT_FP</themekey></theme></keywords><accconst>USE OF THIS DOCUMENT IS SUBJECT TO MNDOT'S DISCLAIMERS, LEGAL NOTICES AND POLICIES FOUND AT http://www.dot.state.mn.us/information/disclaimer.html</accconst><useconst>USE OF THIS DOCUMENT IS SUBJECT TO MNDOT'S DISCLAIMERS, LEGAL NOTICES AND POLICIES FOUND AT http://www.dot.state.mn.us/information/disclaimer.html</useconst><ptcontac><cntinfo><cntperp><cntorg>MN Department of Transportation, Office of Land Management</cntorg><cntper>Ralph Spude</cntper></cntperp><cntpos>Engineering Specialist</cntpos><cntaddr><addrtype>mailing and physical</addrtype><address>395 John Ireland Blvd., M.S. 643</address><city>St. Paul</city><state>MN</state><postal>55155</postal></cntaddr><cntvoice>651-366-3505</cntvoice><cntfax>651-366-3450</cntfax><cntemail>Ralph.Spude@state.mn.us</cntemail></cntinfo></ptcontac></idinfo><dataqual><attracc><attraccr>Attributes programmatically generated include: OBJECTID, ID, PERIMETER, FILE_NAME, SHEET_NUMBER, SHAPE, SHAPE_AREA, and SHAPE_FILE.  The following attributes are created by a combination of hand entry and copied by cut and paste from the existing database record for the map involved: ROLL_NUMBER, SHEET_NUMBER, COUNTY_NUM, SPLIT_SHEET, COUNTY_SRING, and IMAGE_PATH.</attraccr></attracc><logic>Polygons for footprint representations are created using a fully automated process to ensure 100% polygon closure.  The plat and graphic order images are geo-referenced using the Plat_Update_9.3.mxd program followed by the XX_RollShape.py script to automatically generate the polygon based on the physical extent of the map image file.  The Scan_ReadTFW_10.mxd program is used next to load the created polygon to ArcMap for appending to the Statewide_RW_FP data set.  Foot-print labeling is directly passed from the attribute table entries.  In rare instances due to unique properties of a particular map's content the geo-referencing may be handled in a manually where insufficient information was available to scale and place the map.  In such cases errors may exist but are corrected when discovered.  </logic><complete>A visual inspection for completeness of all placed items is performed using a standard checklist.</complete><posacc><horizpa><horizpar>The spatial placement of the footprint is based entirely on the geographic scale and coordinate reference system of the content of the map.  In rare cases where the scale and coordinate system are limited or unknown, hand placement of the plat or order representation is used based the location of roads and landmarks found in the MnDOT Base Map.</horizpar></horizpa><vertacc><vertaccr>N/A</vertaccr></vertacc></posacc><lineage><procstep><procdesc>The images that were used for this georeferencing process originated as a result of a photographic to scanning process made MnDOT's copy of the Right of Way Plat map mylar collection.

The georeferencing process was handled on a county-by-county basis. These plats were converted to single-sheet TIF files, one file per sheet. The images were georeferenced one at a time. There were two main pre-georeferencing processes. The following process consists of the georeferencing itself. 

Pre-Georeferencing

The pre-georeferencing starts by the identification of a target county and its surrounding counties.  This was followed by the creation of two shapefiles, xx_cent and xx_corn, which were used to provide quick access to X and Y coordinate information for both the centers and corners.  These files were created by two separate applications in ArcView 3.2 that did the spatial processing and stored it in the attribute table.  This was done in a separate application due to query time and debugging issues.

Building PLS section corners , quarter corners, and centers of section was the next step in the process.  To build centers of section, the quarter-quarter coverage from the 'Control Point Generated PLS' and the section polygons from the 'Section Level Public Land Survey' were used as acquired from the Minnesota DNR Data Deli website.  These layers were unzipped using Pkzip.  The Bld_cent.apr was used to calculate center of section nodes based on the quarter-quarter breakdowns by selecting the centroid of the polygon, and then looking for the breakdown that occurred closest.  Once the center of section was established, the section, township, and range were calculated to that point.  The application yielded a point shapefile that contained all the center of sections based on the Control Point Generated PLS.

To build corners, the corner building application, Bld_corn.apr, used both the section polygons and section arcs datasets from the 'Section Level Public Land Survey' at the Minnesota DNR Data Deli website.  From the section arcs, a point theme was generated (nodes) where two section lines intersected.  This process created the corners.  Using section polygons, each individual polygon was selected and spatially queried against the point theme so all the corners that intersected with that section were selected.  The section name, (e.g. T29, R22, Sec 22) was then calculated to those selected corners in the database.  The application repeated this process until all the sections in the county were processed.  The end result was a point shapefile containing the concatenated strings of all the sections that intersected each corner.  When the GeoImage Translator was run, it was able to select from those text strings the particular corner the user was querying.

A one-mile buffer around the target county was created so all the corners and centers near the county border could be built.  This, in turn, allowed for better georeferencing in those areas.  The buffered features of the surrounding counties were appended to the target county.

The final step in the pre-georeferencing process was to convert multi-sheet TIF files to single-sheet TIF files.

Georeferencing

In general, the georeferencing process consisted of taking raster TIF files and aligning them with the road centerline of the MnDOT Base Map.  The GeoImage Translator was developed to expedite this process.

Three different methods were used to align the two layers as closely as possible.  The preferred method consisted of the user identifying (clicking) two points on the raster, either a corner or center of section, and entering in the values.  The application then queried the support files to locate the corner or center and then retrieved their X and Y values.  A corner was defined by entering three out of four sections that intersect it, and a center was defined by entering the section, township, and range.

Using the two X and Y coordinates defined on the raster (user clicks), and the two x, y pairs retrieved from the database, the application computed the factors needed to scale, move, and rotate the image.  For example, if the distance of the raster x, y pairs was 10 feet and the distance of the x, y pairs from the database was 1,000 feet, the application knew to enlarge the image 100 times.  Once the image was scaled, the application moved the image from the first raster x, y (the first user click), to its corresponding x, y point that was retrieved from the database.  It set this point as an axis, computed the rotational angle based on the difference between the second x, y raster point and the second x, y point from the database and rotated the image.  The end result was a georeferenced image based on a two-point translation that scaled both the x and y proportionately.

Because over half of the Right of Way plat and Graphic order sheets didn't contain at least two corners or centers, a second method was used to georeference.  For those images that had at least one corner or center, calculating a quarter-quarter breakdown could derive the second coordinate pair.  The user would define one center or corner, and identify a quarter-quarter breakdown north, south, east, or west from that point.  The application would then compute the breakdown at 402 or 804 meters, depending on if the user selected one or two quarters for the calculation.  The coordinate was calculated straight along the x or y axis depending on the direction specified.

If no center or corner points existed on the raster images, the third method was used.  This procedure consisted of placing the image using the manual placement tools that were created for images with insufficient Public Land Survey information.  The manual placement tools consisted of the following:
     -  User Defined Translator - Performed translation based on two pairs of user-defined x, y coordinates.  The destination x, y pairs are provided by the user instead of being retrieved from the database.
     -  Move Raster Tool - Moved raster by user-defined placement (clicking and dragging).
     -  Rotate Raster Tool - Rotated raster around defined axis (single click) and by user-defined distance (clicking and dragging).
     -  Move to Layer - Moved un-georeferenced target image to extent of user-defined layer.
     -  Scale Manually - Scaled raster by a pre-defined scale.

The primary focus was to match the road centerlines between the plat or order and the basemap as closely as possible.  The Public Land Survey section lines were used as a secondary reference.  Due to the limits in their inherent accuracy.

Creating Footprints

Images were loaded into the Footprint tool one county at a time.  The tool found the extent of the image and drew a box around it, creating the footprint.  The FILE_NAME and CNTYFD_NU fields were automatically populated during this process.  The other fields (ROLL_NUM, SHEET_NUM, SPLIT_SHT, CNTYFD_STR and GEOR_PATH) were populated using data derived from these fields.  All county footprint shapefiles were then appended to each other to create a statewide footprint shapefile.
</procdesc></procstep></lineage></dataqual><eainfo><detailed><enttyp><enttypl>Statewide_PLAT_FP</enttypl><enttypd>Feature Class Name</enttypd></enttyp></detailed><overview><eaover>The Right of Way Plat Image data set contains the following attribute data fields:
   OBJECTID - data system file number, polygon identifier
   AREA - area of the footprint
   PERIMETER - perimeter of the footprint
   FILE_NAME - filename of the image
   ROLL_NUMBE - plat number or Commissioner's order number
   SHEET_NUMB - image sheet number
   COUNTY_NUM - Minnesota county number based on alphabetic order
   SPLIT_SHEE - split sheet, true or false
   COUNTY_STR - the MNDOT county number zero filled for single digits.
   IMAGE_PATH - full path name for image
   SHAPE_Leng - length value of the map image
   SHAPE_Area - area value of the map image</eaover></overview></eainfo><distinfo><resdesc>Right of Way Plat and Commissioner's Graphic Order Raster Image File Footprints</resdesc><distliab>USE OF THIS DOCUMENT IS SUBJECT TO MNDOT'S DISCLAIMERS, LEGAL NOTICES AND POLICIES FOUND AT http://www.dot.state.mn.us/information/disclaimer.html</distliab><stdorder><ordering>Download the footprint shapefile via the Minnesota Geospatial Commons (click "I AGREE" in the Online Linkage field below). The footprints shapefile transfer size is 2.66 MB. 

All plat and graphic order and raster image files can be downloaded directly from Right of WAY MAPPING AND MONITORING or ELECTRONIC DOCUMENT ACCESS. See this CHART for a comparison between these delivery sites. For other information or assistance complete the on-line request FORM by including your contact information and telephone number or send the same information to lisrwmap.dot@state.mn.us
              
                RIGHT OF WAY MAPPING &amp; MONITORING - http://www.dot.state.mn.us/maps/gisweb/row/
                ELECTRONIC DOCUMENT ACCESS - http://dotapp7.dot.state.mn.us/cyberdocs_guest/Libraries/Default_Library/Groups/GUESTS/frameset.asp
                CHART - http://gisservices.dot.state.mn.us/mndot-rwmm/Right%20of%20Way%20Mapping.docx
                FORM - http://olmwebservices.dot.state.mn.us/maprequest/requestmain.aspx</ordering></stdorder><distrib><cntinfo><cntperp><cntorg>MN Department of Transportation, Office of Land Management</cntorg><cntper>Jay Krafthefer</cntper></cntperp><cntpos>LIS and R/W Mapping Supervisor</cntpos><cntaddr><addrtype>mailing and physical</addrtype><address>395 John Ireland Blvd., M.S. 643</address><city>St. Paul</city><state>MN</state><postal>55155</postal></cntaddr><cntvoice>651-366-3463</cntvoice><cntfax>651-366-3450</cntfax><cntemail>jay.krafthefer@state.mn.us</cntemail></cntinfo></distrib></distinfo><metainfo><metstdn>Minnesota Geographic Metadata Guidelines</metstdn><metstdv>1.2</metstdv><metextns><onlink>http://www.mngeo.state.mn.us/committee/standards/mgmg/metadata.htm</onlink></metextns><metd>20150311</metd><metc><cntinfo><cntperp><cntorg>MN Department of Transportation, Office of Land Management</cntorg><cntper>Jay Krafthefer</cntper></cntperp><cntpos>LIS and R/W Mapping Supervisor</cntpos><cntaddr><addrtype>mailing and physical</addrtype><address>395 John Ireland Blvd., M.S. 643</address><city>St. Paul</city><state>MN</state><postal>55155</postal></cntaddr><cntvoice>651-366-3463</cntvoice><cntfax>651-366-3450</cntfax><cntemail>jay.krafthefer@state.mn.us</cntemail></cntinfo></metc></metainfo><spref><horizsys><planar><gridsys><gridsysn>Universal Transverse Mercator</gridsysn><utm><utmzone>15</utmzone></utm></gridsys><planci><plandu>meters</plandu></planci></planar><geodetic><horizdn>NAD83</horizdn><ellips>GRS80</ellips></geodetic></horizsys></spref></metadata>