<metadata>
  <idinfo>
    <citation>
      <citeinfo>
        <origin>U.S. Census Bureau</origin>
        <pubdate>unpublished material</pubdate>
        <title>Census 2000 Population Tables (by Block, Block Group and Tract)</title>
        <mgmg1cid>N/A</mgmg1cid>
        <pubinfo>
          <publish>Metropolitan Council</publish>
        </pubinfo>
        <onlink>https://gisdata.mn.gov/dataset/us-mn-state-metc-society-census2000pop-blkg-trc</onlink>
      </citeinfo>
    </citation>
    <descript>
      <abstract>This dataset includes three separate tables for census blocks, block groups and tracts.  The tables are a select subset of population data from the Census Bureau's P-94-171 redistricting data.  These tables can be linked to census block, block group and tract boundary files.

Notes:
- When linking population tables to the corresponding shape file, be aware that there are 3 block groups in the block group shape file that have 2 polygons each and 1 tract in the tract shape file that has 2 polygons. This impacts population summaries.

Bg00:  270030509012, 270530253011, 271230426023
Tract00:  27003050901</abstract>
      <purpose>This dataset was developed as a resource for GIS users interested in using population data with the census geography data.</purpose>
      <supplinf>Twin Cities 7 County Metropolitan Area.  This includes the counties of Anoka, Carver, Dakota, Hennepin, Ramsey, Scott and Washington in Minnesota.</supplinf>
    </descript>
    <timeperd>
      <timeinfo>
        <sngdate>
          <caldate>200004</caldate>
        </sngdate>
      </timeinfo>
      <current>The 2000 U.S. Census.</current>
    </timeperd>
    <status>
      <progress>Complete</progress>
      <update>None Planned</update>
    </status>
    <spdom>
      <bounding>
        <westbc>-94.012</westbc>
        <eastbc>-92.732</eastbc>
        <northbc>45.415</northbc>
        <southbc>44.471</southbc>
      </bounding>
    </spdom>
    <keywords>
      <theme>
        <themekt>None</themekt>
        <themekey>demographics, population, 2000 Census, census blocks, census block groups, census tracts</themekey>
      </theme>
      <place>
        <placekey>Twin Cities, Anoka County, Carver County, Dakota County, Hennepin County, Ramsey County, Scott County, Washington County</placekey>
      </place>
    </keywords>
    <accconst>None</accconst>
    <useconst>None</useconst>
    <browse>
      <browsen>None available</browsen>
    </browse>
    <native>SAS database file</native>
    <crossref>
      <citeinfo>
        <title>Census Geography 2000 -TIGER Tracts, Census Geography 2000 - TLG Aligned Tracts</title>
      </citeinfo>
    </crossref>
    <ptcontac>
      <cntinfo>
        <cntperp>
          <cntorg>Metropolitan Council</cntorg>
          <cntper>Tanya Mayer</cntper>
        </cntperp>
        <cntpos>GIS Coordinator</cntpos>
        <cntaddr>
          <addrtype> mailing and physical address </addrtype>
          <address>390 Robert Street North</address>
          <city>St. Paul</city>
          <state>Minnesota</state>
          <postal>55101-1805</postal>
        </cntaddr>
        <cntvoice>651-602-1604</cntvoice>
        <cntemail>tanya.mayer@metc.state.mn.us</cntemail>
      </cntinfo>
    </ptcontac>
  </idinfo>
  <dataqual>
    <complete>Entire seven county geographic area is covered.</complete>
    <lineage>
      <srcinfo>
        <srcscale/>
      </srcinfo>
      <procstep>
        <procdesc>Data were acquired from the U.S. Census Bureau.  More information about the PL-94-171 data can be found at http://www.census.gov/ .   The data reside in a SAS database and were exported out to Excel spreadsheets and then from Excel to dBase tables.</procdesc>
      </procstep>
    </lineage>
  </dataqual>
  <spdoinfo>
    <indspref>2000 census blocks, block groups and tracts</indspref>
    <direct/>
    <mgmg3obj/>
    <mgmg3til>One file for entire seven county region.</mgmg3til>
  </spdoinfo>
  <eainfo>
    <overview>
      <eaover>Block file only:
 
BLK00:      15 digit Census Block code (includes State &amp; County FIPS codes and 
            links to the Blk00 attribute in the block shape file)


Block Group file only:
 
BG00:       Long block group identifier code that includes state and county
            codes 

BLOCKGROUP: 7 digit Census block number (can be used to link to the block group 
            shape file)


Tract file only:
 
TRACT00:    Long tract identifier code that includes state and county codes

TRACT:      6 digit Census tract number (can be used to link to the tract shape 
            file)  
 
The following fields are found in each of the three files:
 
Total:      Total Population
 
1R:         Total One Race
 
WO:         Total White Only
 
TOMR:       Total 2 or More Races
 
H:          Total Hispanic or Latino
 
NH:         Total Not Hispanic or Latino
 
1R_NH:      One Race Not Hispanic or Latino
 
WO_NH:      White Only Not Hispanic or Latino
 
TOMRNH:     2 or More Races Not Hispanic or Latino
 
Total_18+:  Total Population
 
1R_18+:     Total One Race
 
WO_18+:     Total White Only
 
TOMR_18+:   Total 2 or More Races
 
H_18+:      Total Hispanic or Latino
 
NH_18+:     Total Not Hispanic or Latino
 
1R_NH_18+:  One Race Not Hispanic or Latino
 
WO_NH_18+:  White Only Not Hispanic or Latino
 
TOMRNH_18+: 2 or More Races Not Hispanic or Latino</eaover>
      <eadetcit>The Census Bureau web site at http://www.census.gov/ has more information about the PL-94-171 data.

The federal government considers race and Hispanic origin to be two separate and distinct concepts.  The question on race for the Census 2000 was different from the one for the 1990 census.  Because of these changes, the Census 2000 data on race are not directly comparable with data from the 1990 census or earlier censuses.  Please read the Overview of Race and Hispanic Origin from the Census Bureau at www.census.gov/prod/2001pubs/c2kbr01-1.pdf. 

For example, 
Total Population = Total 1 race + Total 2+ races
Total Population = Total Hispanic or Latino + Total Not Hispanic or Latino

Other Notes:
White Only is a subset of One Race
White Only Not Hispanic or Latino is a subset of 1 Race Not Hispanic or Latino.
1 Race Not Hispanic or Latino + Two or more Races Not Hispanic or Latino =  Total Not Hispanic or Latino</eadetcit>
    </overview>
  </eainfo>
  <distinfo>
    <resdesc>Census2000Population</resdesc>
    <distliab>NOTICE:  The Geographic Information System (GIS) Data to which this notice is attached are made available pursuant to the Minnesota Government Data Practices Act (Minnesota Statutes Chapter 13).  THE GIS DATA ARE PROVIDED TO YOU AS IS AND WITHOUT ANY WARRANTY AS TO THEIR PERFORMANCE, MERCHANTABILITY, OR FITNESS FOR ANY PARTICULAR PURPOSE.  The GIS Data were developed by the Metropolitan Council for its own internal business purposes.  The Metropolitan Council does not represent or warrant that the GIS Data or the data documentation are error-free, complete, current, or accurate.  You are responsible for any consequences resulting from your use of the GIS Data or your reliance on the GIS Data.  You should consult the data documentation for this particular GIS Data to determine the limitations of the GIS Data and the precision with which the GIS Data may depict distance, direction, location, or other geographic features.  If you transmit or provide the GIS Data (or any portion of it) to another user, it is recommended that the GIS Data include a copy of this disclaimer and this metadata.</distliab>
    <stdorder>
      <digform>
        <digtinfo>
          <formname>dBase</formname>
          <formvern>4.0</formvern>
          <transize>1.0 MB for zip file.</transize>
        </digtinfo>
      </digform>
      <ordering>See Online Linkage Below</ordering>
    </stdorder>
    <distrib>
      <cntinfo>
        <cntperp>
          <cntorg>Metropolitan Council</cntorg>
          <cntper>Jon Hoekenga</cntper>
        </cntperp>
        <cntpos>GIS System Administrator</cntpos>
        <cntaddr>
          <addrtype>mailing and physical</addrtype>
          <address>390 Robert Street North</address>
          <city>St. Paul</city>
          <state>Minnesota</state>
          <postal>55101-1805</postal>
        </cntaddr>
        <cntvoice>651-602-1561</cntvoice>
        <cntemail>jonathan.hoekenga@metc.state.mn.us</cntemail>
      </cntinfo>
    </distrib>
  </distinfo>
  <metainfo>
    <metd>20030815</metd>
    <metstdn>Minnesota Geographic Metadata Guidelines</metstdn>
    <metstdv>1.2</metstdv>
    <metextns>
      <onlink>http://www.gis.state.mn.us/stds/metadata.htm</onlink>
    </metextns>
    <metc>
      <cntinfo>
        <cntperp>
          <cntorg>Metropolitan Council</cntorg>
          <cntper>Tanya Mayer</cntper>
        </cntperp>
        <cntpos>GIS Coordinator</cntpos>
        <cntaddr>
          <addrtype>mailing and physical</addrtype>
          <address>390 Robert Street North</address>
          <city>St. Paul</city>
          <state>Minnesota</state>
          <postal>55101-1805</postal>
        </cntaddr>
        <cntvoice>651-602-1604</cntvoice>
        <cntemail>tanya.mayer@metc.state.mn.us</cntemail>
      </cntinfo>
    </metc>
  </metainfo>
  <Esri>
    <ModDate>20110729</ModDate>
    <ModTime>13281300</ModTime>
  </Esri>
  <mdDateSt Sync="TRUE">20110729</mdDateSt>
</metadata>
