<!--  <!DOCTYPE metadata SYSTEM "metadata.dtd">  -->
<metadata>
  <idinfo>
    <citation>
      <citeinfo>
        <origin>Minnesota Department of Revenue</origin>
        <pubdate>20100408</pubdate>
        <title>Income Tax, Minnesota, 2003-2008</title>
        <mgmg1cid/>
        <pubinfo>
          <publish>Minnesota Department of Revenue</publish>
        </pubinfo>
        <onlink>ftp://ftp.lmic.state.mn.us/pub/data/economy/income_tax.zip</onlink>
      </citeinfo>
    </citation>
    <descript>
      <abstract>This spreadsheet includes Minnesota Income Tax information for the years 2003-2008.  Data includes number of tax returns and the median, mean and sum of Minnesota Taxable Income (MTI).

Data are unduplicated and reported in one of four general categories:

1. Records outside of Minnesota are reported at the state level and include territories, APO's, foreign and unassigned.

Within Minnesota, records are assigned to one of three geographic levels (blockgroup, city or county):

2. Within the 7-county Twin Cities metro area, records are assigned to blockgroups.
3. Outside of the 7-county Twin Cities metro area, records are assigned to cities with populations greater than 2,000 residents.
4. All other unassigned Minnesota records are tabulated by county.

For additional information and statistical reports, please visit http://www.revenue.state.mn.us/research_stats/Pages/Whats-New.aspx</abstract>
      <purpose>This dataset details income information across the state.</purpose>
      <supplinf>Minnesota and other areas outside the state that pay Minnesota income tax</supplinf>
    </descript>
    <timeperd>
      <timeinfo>
        <sngdate>
          <caldate>2008</caldate>
        </sngdate>
      </timeinfo>
      <current>This data is current to the 2008 tax year, for taxes filed in 2009.</current>
    </timeperd>
    <status>
      <progress>Complete</progress>
      <update>None Planned</update>
    </status>
    <spdom>
      <bounding>
        <westbc>-97.5</westbc>
        <eastbc>-89</eastbc>
        <northbc>49.5</northbc>
        <southbc>43</southbc>
      </bounding>
    </spdom>
    <keywords>
      <theme>
        <themekt>ISO 19115 Topic Category</themekt>
        <themekey>economy, income tax, revenue</themekey>
      </theme>
      <place>
        <placekey>Minnesota, MN, Twin Cities, 7 County Metro</placekey>
      </place>
    </keywords>
    <accconst>None</accconst>
    <useconst>By acceptance of this data, the user agrees to include a copy of this metadata record, including the liability disclaimer, whenever the user transmits or provides the GIS Data (or any portion of it) to another user.

We recommend that other interested parties download this dataset from the Minnesota Geographic Data Clearinghouse to ensure that the most current data is obtained (see Ordering Instructions).</useconst>
    <browse>
      <browsen>None available</browsen>
      <browsed/>
    </browse>
    <native/>
    <crossref>
      <citeinfo>
        <title>Sales Tax, Minnesota: http://www.mngeo.state.mn.us/chouse/metadata/sales_tax.html</title>
      </citeinfo>
    </crossref>
    <ptcontac>
      <cntinfo>
        <cntperp>
          <cntorg>Minnesota Department of Revenue</cntorg>
          <cntper>Brian Udell</cntper>
        </cntperp>
        <cntpos>GIS Analyst - Tax Research</cntpos>
        <cntaddr>
          <addrtype> Mailing and Physical</addrtype>
          <address>600 North Robert St - MS 2230</address>
          <city>St. Paul</city>
          <state>MN</state>
          <postal>55146-2230</postal>
        </cntaddr>
        <cntvoice>651-556-4930</cntvoice>
        <cntfax>651-556-3103</cntfax>
        <cntemail>brian.udell@state.mn.us</cntemail>
      </cntinfo>
    </ptcontac>
  </idinfo>
  <dataqual>
    <attracc>
      <attraccr>Attributes are deemed accurate but not error free.

Records are assigned to the respective geographic area through geocoding of the listed address on the filed tax return, thus introducing an unknown, presumably small, level of error to the data through incorrect addressing.  Furthermore, income information is taken directly from tax return scanners, and those income figures are not verified as free of error.

It must also be noted that this dataset ONLY covers information gathered from filed, form M1 tax returns.  It does not include nor factor into the aggregated figures any information about people who did not file Minnesota income taxes.  Please visit the Income Tax page on the Minnesota Department of Revenue's website at http://www.revenue.state.mn.us/individuals/individ_income/Pages/File-and-Pay.aspx for additional information on filing requirements and guidelines.

IMPORTANT: The 7 records listed for the 7 Twin Cities metro counties are each the total of unmatched tax returns for those counties and are NOT the aggregate for each county. The counties are: Anoka, Carver, Dakota, Hennepin, Ramsey, Scott and Washington.

Geographic areas with fewer than 100 tax returns have been suppressed to ensure compliance with privacy laws.</attraccr>
    </attracc>
    <complete>The entire state of Minnesota is included.

Data are unduplicated and reported in one of four general categories:

1. Records outside of Minnesota are reported at the state level and include territories, APO's, foreign and unassigned.

Within Minnesota, records are assigned to one of three geographic levels (blockgroup, city or county):

2. Within the 7-county Twin Cities metro area, records are assigned to blockgroups.
3. Outside of the 7-county Twin Cities metro area, records are assigned to cities with populations greater than 2,000 residents.
4. All other unassigned Minnesota records are tabulated by county.

Geographic areas with fewer than 100 tax returns have been suppressed to ensure compliance with privacy laws.</complete>
    <posacc>
      <horizpa>
        <horizpar>Geographic boundaries are taken from U.S. Census Bureau TIGER files for 2008: http://www.census.gov/geo/maps-data/data/tiger-line.html</horizpar>
      </horizpa>
    </posacc>
    <lineage>
      <srcinfo>
        <srcscale/>
      </srcinfo>
      <procstep>
        <procdesc>Addresses, taken from the form M-1 Minnesota Individual Income Tax Return, are geocoded using a variety of software packages, including MapMarker (MapInfo), EDQ (FirstLogic), and ZP4 (Semaphore).  Problematic addresses, such as those on a boundary of two geographic areas, are manually assigned to a geographic area by Minnesota Department of Revenue staff.  

The total number of returns for each geographic area are then used to compute the mean, median and sum of the Minnesota Taxable Income (MTI).  For additional information on how MTI is computed, please visit http://www.house.leg.state.mn.us/hrd/pubs/taxterms.pdf

Data from geographic areas with fewer than 100 filed returns is then suppressed to comply with privacy laws.</procdesc>
      </procstep>
    </lineage>
  </dataqual>
  <spdoinfo>
    <indspref>FIPAREA - 2 to 12 digit FIPS code representing State, County, City, or Block Group</indspref>
    <direct/>
    <mgmg3obj/>
    <mgmg3til/>
  </spdoinfo>
  <eainfo>
    <overview>
      <eaover>RECNUM -- Record Number

FIPAREA -- Multi-jurisdictional FIPS code (text format) representing State, County, City, or Block Group

TYPEAREA -- FIPS level: State; Foreign; APO; Unknown; County; City; Block Group

AREANAME1 -- FIPS name for all area types except for block groups

FIPST -- FIPS code for each state (2-digit, text format)

FIPCTY -- FIPS code for each county (3-digit, text format)

FIPSTCTY -- Concatenated FIPS codes for state and county (5-digit, text format)

FIPMCD -- FIPS codes for minor civil divisions (cities); if a city is located in more than one county, the portion of the city located in each county is a separate record with a different code (5-digit, text format)

FIPTRT -- FIPS code for each Census tract (6-digit, text format)

FIPBGR -- Single-digit indicating the Census block group within a given Census tract. A block group is a cluster of census blocks having the same first digit of their four-digit identifying numbers within a census tract. For example, block group 3 within a census tract includes all blocks numbered from 3000 to 3999. (Single-digit, text format)

STABBR -- Two-letter state abbreviation in all caps.

[IMPORTANT: For the attributes below, the 7 records listed for the 7 Twin Cities metro counties are each the total of unmatched tax returns for those counties and are NOT the aggregate for each county. The counties are: Anoka, Carver, Dakota, Hennepin, Ramsey, Scott and Washington.]

Returns&lt;year&gt; -- Number of tax returns in that year, for example 'RETURNS2003' is the number of tax returns for 2003.

MTI Mean&lt;year&gt; -- Mean Minnesota Taxable Income in that year.

MTI Median&lt;year&gt; -- Median Minnesota Taxable Income in that year.

MTI Sum&lt;year&gt; -- Mean Minnesota Taxable Income in that year.

Note:  Totals for all the taxable income fields are in the last row of the spreadsheet.</eaover>
    </overview>
  </eainfo>
  <distinfo>
    <resdesc>MN Income Tax</resdesc>
    <distliab>NOTICE: The Data to which this notice is attached are made available pursuant to the Minnesota Government Data Practices Act (Minnesota Statutes Chapter 13). THE DATA ARE PROVIDED TO YOU AS IS AND WITHOUT ANY WARRANTY AS TO THEIR PERFORMANCE, MERCHANTABILITY, OR FITNESS FOR ANY PARTICULAR PURPOSE. The Data were developed by the Minnesota Department of Revenue for its own internal business purposes. The Minnesota Department of Revenue does not represent or warrant that the Data or the data documentation are error-free, complete, current, or accurate. You are responsible for any consequences resulting from your use of the Data or your reliance on the Data. You should consult the data documentation for this particular Data to determine the limitations of the Data and the precision with which the Data may depict location or other geographic features. If you transmit or provide the Data (or any portion of it) to another user, the Data must include a copy of this disclaimer.</distliab>
    <stdorder>
      <digform>
        <digtinfo>
          <formname>.xls</formname>
          <formvern/>
          <transize>.5 mb</transize>
        </digtinfo>
      </digform>
      <ordering>This dataset is distributed on the internet by clicking below after 'Online Linkage'. Doing so will tell your browser to download a 'ZIP' file which will contain the following:

- Excel spreadsheet (.xls) file
- Metadata for the dataset (.htm, .xml and .lgr formats)
- NOTICE.TXT, a disclaimer.

For help with unzipping (uncompressing) the file, see:  http://www.mngeo.state.mn.us/resource.html?Id=16253#compress</ordering>
    </stdorder>
    <distrib>
      <cntinfo>
        <cntperp>
          <cntorg>Minnesota Geospatial Information Office (MnGeo)</cntorg>
          <cntper>Nancy Rader</cntper>
        </cntperp>
        <cntpos>GIS Data Coordinator</cntpos>
        <cntaddr>
          <addrtype>Mailing and Physical</addrtype>
          <address>658 Cedar Street, Room 300</address>
          <city>St. Paul</city>
          <state>MN</state>
          <postal>55155</postal>
        </cntaddr>
        <cntvoice>651-201-2489</cntvoice>
        <cntemail>gisinfo.mngeo@state.mn.us</cntemail>
      </cntinfo>
    </distrib>
  </distinfo>
  <metainfo>
    <metd>20140610</metd>
    <metstdn>Minnesota Geographic Metadata Guidelines</metstdn>
    <metstdv>1.2</metstdv>
    <metextns>
      <onlink>http://www.mngeo.state.mn.us/committee/standards/mgmg/metadata.htm</onlink>
    </metextns>
    <metc>
      <cntinfo>
        <cntperp>
          <cntorg>Minnesota Geospatial Information Office (MnGeo)</cntorg>
          <cntper>Nancy Rader</cntper>
        </cntperp>
        <cntpos>GIS Data Coordinator</cntpos>
        <cntaddr>
          <addrtype>Mailing and Physical</addrtype>
          <address>658 Cedar Street, Room 300</address>
          <city>St. Paul</city>
          <state>MN</state>
          <postal>55155</postal>
        </cntaddr>
        <cntvoice>651-201-2489</cntvoice>
        <cntemail>gisinfo.mngeo@state.mn.us</cntemail>
      </cntinfo>
    </metc>
  </metainfo>
  <Esri>
    <ModDate>20110524</ModDate>
    <ModTime>16275700</ModTime>
  </Esri>
  <mdDateSt Sync="TRUE">20110524</mdDateSt>
</metadata>
