<metadata>
  <idinfo>
    <citation>
      <citeinfo>
        <origin>MN Board of Water and Soil Resources</origin>
        <title>One Watershed One Plan Planning Areas</title>
        <pubinfo>
          <publish>MN Board of Water and Soil Resources</publish>
        </pubinfo>
        <onlink>http://bwsr.state.mn.us/planning/1W1P/1W1P_Planning_Areas.zip</onlink>
      </citeinfo>
    </citation>
    <descript>
      <abstract>The State of Minnesota has a long history of water management by local government.  One Watershed, One Plan is rooted in this history and in work initiated in 2011 by the Local Government Water Roundtable (Association of Minnesota Counties, Minnesota Association of Watershed Districts, and Minnesota Association of Soil and Water Conservation Districts).  Roundtable members determined that it is in the public interest to manage groundwater and surface water resources from the perspective of watersheds to achieve protection, preservation, enhancement, and restoration of the state's valuable water resources. 

Supporting this determination, the Roundtable recommended that the local governments charged with water management should organize and develop focused implementation plans on a watershed scale. The recommendation was followed by the One Watershed, One Plan legislation (Minnesota Statutes &#167;103B.101 Subd. 14,)that permits the Minnesota Board of Water and Soil Resources (BWSR) to adopt methods to allow comprehensive plans, local water management plans, or watershed management plans to serve as substitutes for one another; or to be replaced with one comprehensive watershed management plan. The legislation also required BWSR to establish a suggested watershed boundary framework for these plans. This Framework consists of three parts: the suggested boundary map; procedures for establishing boundaries, requesting variances on boundaries, and appealing boundaries; and the criteria used to establish and consider requested variances from the suggested boundary map.</abstract>
      <purpose>As per Minnesota Statutes &#167;103B.101 Subd. 14, BWSR &#8220;shall, to the extent practicable, incorporate a watershed approach when adopting the resolutions, policies, or orders, and shall establish a suggested watershed boundary framework for development, approval, adoption, and coordination of plans.&#8221; The suggested boundary map adopted by the BWSR Board in April 2014 reflects suggested planning boundaries (not jurisdictional boundaries).  Criteria and procedures for making adjustments are outlined in the Operating Procedures for Pilots, adopted by the BWSR Board on June 25, 2014.</purpose>
      <supplinf>Statewide</supplinf>
    </descript>
    <timeperd>
      <current>April, 2015</current>
      <timeinfo>
        <sngdate>
          <caldate>20150415</caldate>
        </sngdate>
      </timeinfo>
    </timeperd>
    <status>
      <progress>In work</progress>
      <update>As needed</update>
    </status>
    <spdom>
      <bounding>
        <westbc>-97.23</westbc>
        <eastbc>-89.53</eastbc>
        <northbc>49.37</northbc>
        <southbc>43.5</southbc>
      </bounding>
    </spdom>
    <keywords>
      <place>
        <placekey>Minnesota, MN</placekey>
      </place>
      <theme>
        <themekey>One Watershed, One Plan</themekey>
      </theme>
    </keywords>
    <useconst>General planning purposes only.</useconst>
    <ptcontac>
      <cntinfo>
        <cntperp>
          <cntorg>Minnesota Board of Water and Soil Resources</cntorg>
          <cntper>Melissa Lewis</cntper>
        </cntperp>
        <cntpos>Water Plan and Policy Coordinator</cntpos>
        <cntaddr>
          <addrtype>mailing and physical</addrtype>
          <address>520 Lafayette Rd. N</address>
          <city>St. Paul</city>
          <state>MN</state>
          <postal>55155</postal>
        </cntaddr>
        <cntvoice>651-297-4735</cntvoice>
        <cntfax>651-297-5615</cntfax>
        <cntemail>melissa.k.lewis@state.mn.us</cntemail>
      </cntinfo>
    </ptcontac>
  </idinfo>
  <eainfo>
    <detailed>
      <enttyp>
        <enttypl>ID</enttypl>
      </enttyp>
    </detailed>
    <overview>
      <eaover>Note: Major watershed names have been removed from this data set. Since watersheds have been combined or split in some situations, the major watershed name can no longer be accurately applied to some planning areas.

In the future, names may be created for the planning areas, but in the meantime they will be referred to simply by a unique numeric identifier.

ID: The unique numeric identifier</eaover>
    </overview>
  </eainfo>
  <distinfo>
    <stdorder>
      <ordering>The layer may be downloaded from the BWSR website (see online linkage) or the MnGEO Geospatial Commons.</ordering>
    </stdorder>
    <distrib>
      <cntinfo>
        <cntperp>
          <cntorg>Minnesota Board of Water and Soil Resources</cntorg>
          <cntper>Aaron Spence</cntper>
        </cntperp>
        <cntpos>GIS Specialist</cntpos>
        <cntaddr>
          <addrtype>mailing and physical</addrtype>
          <address>520 Lafayette Rd. N</address>
          <city>St. Paul</city>
          <state>MN</state>
          <postal>55155</postal>
        </cntaddr>
        <cntvoice>651-296-0660</cntvoice>
        <cntfax>651-297-5615</cntfax>
        <cntemail>aaron.spence@bwsr.state.mn.us</cntemail>
      </cntinfo>
    </distrib>
  </distinfo>
  <metainfo>
    <metd>20150415</metd>
    <metstdn>Minnesota Geographic Metadata Guidelines</metstdn>
    <metstdv>1.2</metstdv>
    <metextns>
      <onlink>http://www.gis.state.mn.us/stds/metadata.htm</onlink>
    </metextns>
    <metc>
      <cntinfo>
        <cntperp>
          <cntorg>Minnesota Board of Water and Soil Resources</cntorg>
          <cntper>Aaron Spence</cntper>
        </cntperp>
        <cntpos>GIS Specialist</cntpos>
        <cntaddr>
          <addrtype>mailing and physical</addrtype>
          <address>520 Lafayette Rd. N</address>
          <city>St. Paul</city>
          <state>MN</state>
          <postal>55155</postal>
        </cntaddr>
        <cntvoice>651-296-0660</cntvoice>
        <cntfax>651-297-5615</cntfax>
        <cntemail>aaron.spence@bwsr.state.mn.us</cntemail>
      </cntinfo>
    </metc>
  </metainfo>
  <dataqual>
    <lineage>
      <procstep>
        <procdesc>The 1W1P planning boundaries are a modified boundaries from the DNR Level04 - HUC 08 - Major Watersheds. In some cases watersheds were combined or split based on subwatershed, or jurisdictional boundaries to accomodate better planning coordination between local governments and assure they are planning for their appropriate geographic area.</procdesc>
      </procstep>
    </lineage>
  </dataqual>
  <spref>
    <horizsys>
      <planar>
        <gridsys>
          <gridsysn>Universal Transverse Mercator</gridsysn>
          <utm>
            <utmzone>15</utmzone>
          </utm>
        </gridsys>
        <planci>
          <plandu>meters</plandu>
        </planci>
      </planar>
      <geodetic>
        <horizdn>NAD83</horizdn>
        <ellips>GRS80</ellips>
      </geodetic>
    </horizsys>
  </spref>
</metadata>
