<?xml version="1.0"?><metadata><eainfo><overview><eaover>SITEID: Unique identifier to link spatial easement data to database storing information about wetland banking accounts. Contact BWSR for more detailed information about wetland banking credits.</eaover></overview></eainfo><idinfo><citation><citeinfo><origin>Minnesota Board of Water and Soil Resources (BWSR)</origin><title>Minnesota Wetland Banking Program Easements</title><pubinfo><publish>Minnesota Board of Water and Soil Resources (BWSR)</publish></pubinfo><pubdate>20150511</pubdate></citeinfo></citation><descript><abstract>The State of Minnesota wetland banking program is authorized by State statutes and associated State rules (Chapter 8420). The program requires that all land being utilized for wetland banking purposes be protected by a State conservation easement, although other land protection mechanisms were used prior to 2000. These protected lands are primarily privately-owned and not accessible to the public without landowner permission. This spatial data layer shows the approximate boundaries of lands protected by State of Minnesota conservation easements and/or other land protection mechanisms associated with the State’s wetland banking program. Information on wetland banking and associated credits can be found at http://bwsr.state.mn.us/wetlands/wetlandbanking/credits.html.</abstract><purpose>The purpose of this spatial data layer is to depict the approximate boundaries of lands protected by State of Minnesota conservation easements and/or other land protection mechanisms associated with the State’s wetland banking program. Boundaries should be considered approximate and do not necessarily represent survey grade data. The data should be used for general planning purposes only. Those wishing to know the exact boundaries of any particular parcel of land that is protected due to its inclusion in the wetland banking program should contact the State’s Board of Water and Soil Resources (BWSR) to obtain the exact legal description of the easement (if available). Note that many, but not all easements include a legal description of the easement boundaries. Any calculations related to the size of protected land parcels based on this data should be considered approximate as there are varying degrees of mapping accuracy contained within. </purpose><supplinf>Statewide</supplinf></descript><timeperd><current>May, 2015</current><timeinfo><sngdate><caldate>20150511</caldate></sngdate></timeinfo></timeperd><status><progress>In work</progress><update>As needed</update></status><spdom><bounding><westbc>-97.23</westbc><eastbc>-89.53</eastbc><northbc>49.37</northbc><southbc>43.5</southbc></bounding></spdom><keywords><place><placekey>Minnesota</placekey></place><theme><themekey>Minnesota, Wetland, Wetlands, Banking, Conservation, Easements</themekey></theme></keywords><useconst>Boundaries should be considered approximate and do not necessarily represent survey grade data. The data should be used for general planning purposes only. Those wishing to know the exact boundaries of any particular parcel of land that is protected due to its inclusion in the wetland banking program should contact the State’s Board of Water and Soil Resources (BWSR) to obtain the exact legal description of the easement (if available). Note that many, but not all easements include a legal description of the easement boundaries. Any calculations related to the size of protected land parcels based on this data should be considered approximate as there are varying degrees of mapping accuracy contained within. </useconst><ptcontac><cntinfo><cntperp><cntorg>Minnesota Board of Water and Soil Resources</cntorg><cntper>Ken Powell</cntper></cntperp><cntpos>Wetland Banking Coordinator</cntpos><cntaddr><addrtype>mailing and physical</addrtype><address>520 Lafayette Rd. N</address><city>St. Paul</city><state>MN</state><postal>55155</postal></cntaddr><cntvoice>651-215-1703</cntvoice><cntfax>651-297-5615</cntfax><cntemail>ken.powell@bwsr.state.mn.us</cntemail></cntinfo></ptcontac></idinfo><dataqual><posacc><horizpa><horizpar>The horizontal accuracy of this data set is unknown. See lineage for more information.</horizpar></horizpa></posacc><lineage><procstep><procdesc>From the inception of the wetland banking program until May of 2015, wetland banking easements were digitized by BWSR staff using AutoCAD software and utlizing legal descriptions and reference GIS layers such as aerial imagery and PLS layers.  CAD files were converted to shapefiles and appended to a master geodatabase layer for all wetland banking easements. Due to the CAD to GIS conversion process, in some instances there may have been slight postional error introduced. Going forward from May 2015, CAD software is no longer being used for this process, and shapefiles for wetlang banking easements are being created from certified surveyors and sent directly to BWSR. Those shapefiles are then being added directly to the master geodatabase layer.</procdesc></procstep></lineage></dataqual><distinfo><stdorder><ordering>Check the BWSR website wetland page, or contact Aaron Spence at BWSR to obtain tabular information regarding wetland banking credits.</ordering></stdorder><distrib><cntinfo><cntperp><cntorg>Minnesota Board of Water and Soil Resources</cntorg><cntper>Aaron Spence</cntper></cntperp><cntpos>GIS Specialist</cntpos><cntaddr><addrtype>mailing and physical</addrtype><address>520 Lafayette Rd. N</address><city>St. Paul</city><state>MN</state><postal>55155</postal></cntaddr><cntvoice>651-296-0660</cntvoice><cntfax>651-297-5615</cntfax><cntemail>aaron.spence@bwsr.state.mn.us</cntemail></cntinfo></distrib></distinfo><metainfo><metd>20150511</metd><metstdn>Minnesota Geographic Metadata Guidelines</metstdn><metstdv>1.2</metstdv><metextns><onlink>http://www.gis.state.mn.us/stds/metadata.htm</onlink></metextns><metc><cntinfo><cntperp><cntorg>Minnesota Board of Water and Soil Resources</cntorg><cntper>Aaron Spence</cntper></cntperp><cntpos>GIS Specialist</cntpos><cntaddr><addrtype>mailing and physical</addrtype><address>520 Lafayette Rd. N</address><city>St. Paul</city><state>MN</state><postal>55155</postal></cntaddr><cntvoice>651-296-0660</cntvoice><cntfax>651-297-5615</cntfax><cntemail>aaron.spence@bwsr.state.mn.us</cntemail></cntinfo></metc></metainfo><spref><horizsys><planar><gridsys><gridsysn>Universal Transverse Mercator</gridsysn><utm><utmzone>15</utmzone></utm></gridsys><planci><plandu>meters</plandu></planci></planar><geodetic><horizdn>NAD83</horizdn><ellips>GRS80</ellips></geodetic></horizsys></spref></metadata>