<metadata>
  <idinfo>
    <citation>
      <citeinfo>
        <title>County CTU Lookup Table</title>
        <origin>Metropolitan Council</origin>
        <pubinfo>
          <publish>Metropolitan Council</publish>
        </pubinfo>
        <pubdate>periodically revised</pubdate>
        <onlink>https://gisdata.mn.gov/dataset/us-mn-state-metc-bdry-counties-and-ctus-lookup</onlink>
      </citeinfo>
    </citation>
    <descript>
      <abstract>This is a lookup table containing various data related to cities, townships, unorganized territories (CTUs) and any divisions created by county boundaries splitting them.  These are termed Minor Civil Division (MCDs) by the Census Bureau.  The table encompases the Twin Cities 7-county metropolitan area.  It is intended to be a Council wide master lookup table for these entites.  It contains official federal and state unique identifiers for CTUs and MCDs as well as identifiers created and used by other organizations.  The table also contains historical MCDs dating back to the 1990s and a few other non-MCD records that are of importance to Met. Council use of this table.

The County CTU Lookup Table relates to the Counties and Cities &amp; Townships, Twin Cities Metropolitan Area dataset here:  https://gisdata.mn.gov/dataset/us-mn-state-metc-bdry-metro-counties-and-ctus 

NOTES:

- On 5/28/2014 a new field was added to reflect the new community designations defined in the Council's Thrive MSP 2040 regional plan - COMDES2040

- On 3/17/2011 it was discovered that the CTU ID used for the City of Lake St. Croix Beach was incorrect.  It was changed from 2394379 to 2395599 to match GNIS.

- On 3/17/2011 it was discovered that the CTU ID used for the City of Lilydale was incorrect.  It was changed from 2394457 to 2395708 to match GNIS.

- On 11/9/2010 it was discovered that the CTU ID used for the City of Crystal was incorrect.  It was changed from 2393541 to 2393683 to match GNIS.

- Effective April 2008,  a change was made in GNIS to match the FIPS place codes to the "civil" feature for each city instead of the "populated place" feature.  Both cities and townships are now "civil" features within GNIS.  This means that the official GNIS unique ID for every city in Minnesota has changed.   

- As of January 1, 2006, the five digit FIPS 55-3 Place codes that were used as unique identifiers in this dataset (CTU_CODE and COCTU_CODE fields) were officially retired by the Federal governement.  They are replaced by a set of integer codes from the Geographic Names Information System (GNIS_CODE field).  Both codes will be kept in this database, but the GNIS_CODE is considered the official unique identifier from this point forward.  The GNIS codes are also slated to become official ANSI codes for these geographic features.  While GNIS treats these codes as 6 to 8 digit integer data types, the Census Bureau formats them as 8 digit text fields, right justified with leading zeros included.

- The Census Bureau will continue to create FIPS 55 Place codes for new cities and townships through the 2010 Census.  After that, no new FIPS 55 codes will be created.  Note that for townships that wholly incorporate into cities, the same FIPS 55 code will be used for the new city.  (GNIS creates a new ID for the new city.)

- Cities and townships have also been referred to as ''MCDs'' (a Census term), however this term technically refers to the part of each city or township within a single county.  Thus, a few cities in the metro area that are split by county boundaries are actually comprised of two different MCDs. This was part of the impetus for a proposed MN state data standard that uses the ''CTU'' terminology for clarity.

-  A variety of civil divisions of the land exist within the United States.  In Minnesota, only three types exist - cities, townships and unorganized territories.  All three of these exist within the Twin Cities seven county area.  The only unorganized territory is Fort Snelling (a large portion of which is occupied by the MSP International Airport).

-  Some cities are split between two counties.  Only those parts of cities within the 7-county area are included.

- Prior to the 2000 census, the FIPS Place code for the City of Greenwood in Hennepin County was changed from 25928 to 25918.  This dataset reflects that change.</abstract>
      <purpose>This dataset was developed to be used internally at the Metropolitan Council as a lookup and cross reference table for a variety of information related to cities, townships and unorganized territories.</purpose>
      <supplinf>Twin Cities 7 County Metropolitan Area.  This includes the counties of Anoka, Carver, Dakota, Hennepin, Ramsey, Scott and Washington in Minnesota.</supplinf>
    </descript>
    <timeperd>
      <timeinfo>
        <sngdate>
          <caldate>20150701</caldate>
        </sngdate>
      </timeinfo>
      <current>The table is up to date as of the time period of content date shown above.
</current>
    </timeperd>
    <status>
      <progress>Complete</progress>
      <update>As needed</update>
    </status>
    <spdom>
      <bounding>
        <westbc>-94.0</westbc>
        <eastbc>-92.7</eastbc>
        <northbc>45.4</northbc>
        <southbc>44.4</southbc>
      </bounding>
    </spdom>
    <keywords>
      <place>
        <placekey>Twin Cities, Anoka County, Carver County, Dakota County, Hennepin County, Ramsey County, Scott County, Washington County</placekey>
      </place>
      <theme>
        <themekey>counties, cities, townships, GNIS, FIPS place code, FIPS55, CTU, CTUs,  MCD, minor civil divisions, municipal codes</themekey>
        <themekt>None</themekt>
      </theme>
    </keywords>
    <accconst>None</accconst>
    <useconst>None</useconst>
    <browse>
      <browsen>ftp://ftp.gisdata.mn.gov/pub/gdrs/data/pub/us_mn_state_metc/bdry_counties_and_ctus_lookup/metadata/preview.jpg</browsen>
    </browse>
    <crossref>
      <citeinfo>
        <title>Counties and Cities &amp; Townships, Twin Cities Metropolitan Area</title>
      </citeinfo>
    </crossref>
    <native>Oracle</native>
    <ptcontac>
      <cntinfo>
        <cntperp>
          <cntorg>Metropolitan Council</cntorg>
          <cntper>Tanya Mayer</cntper>
        </cntperp>
        <cntpos>GIS Specialist</cntpos>
        <cntaddr>
          <addrtype>mailing and physical</addrtype>
          <address>390 Robert Street North</address>
          <city>St. Paul</city>
          <state>MN</state>
          <postal>55101-1805</postal>
        </cntaddr>
        <cntvoice>651.602.1604</cntvoice>
        <cntemail>tanya.mayer@metc.state.mn.us</cntemail>
      </cntinfo>
    </ptcontac>
  </idinfo>
  <dataqual>
    <attracc>
      <attraccr>CTU IDs were matched with a download of GNIS civil features for only the State of MN on 3/17/2011.  All citiy and township CTU IDs matched a GNIS civil feature within the state of MN.  An additional visual inspection was conducted to confirm the matching of feature names.</attraccr>
    </attracc>
    <complete>Entire seven county geographic area is covered.</complete>
    <lineage>
      <procstep>
        <procdesc>SOURCES USED:

GNIS identifiers are taken from the U.S. Board of Geographic Names GNIS database at http://geonames.usgs.gov/domestic/index.html . 

FIPS "Place" codes (CTU_CODE) are taken from the Federal Information Processing Standard (FIPS) Publication 55-3 database dated September, 2001.  Updated FIPS codes are obtained from the GNIS database or the Census Bureau.

Other codes are taken from various sources.  Population figures are from the Metropolitan Council Research Unit.</procdesc>
      </procstep>
      <srcinfo>
        <srcscale/>
      </srcinfo>
    </lineage>
  </dataqual>
  <spdoinfo>
    <indspref>CTU ID, County code, CTU code, county name, CTU name, COCTU ID, COCTU code</indspref>
    <direct/>
    <mgmg3obj/>
    <mgmg3til/>
  </spdoinfo>
  <eainfo>
    <overview>
      <eaover>Attributes for County CTU Lookup Table:
 
COCTU_ID:   11 digit identifier for the combination of county and CTU 
            (concatination of CO_CODE and CTU_ID_CEN).  This is the 
            official U.S. Census Bureau format.

COCTU_CODE: 8 digit code (concatenation of CO_CODE and CTU_CODE below).
            As of 2006 the FIPS55 codes upon which the CTU_CODEs based, 
            have been official retired by the federal governement.  They 
            are replaced by the GNIS codes used in the COCTU_ID field 
            described above.  The retired codes will continue to be 
            included in this dataset, but codes will not be created for 
            new cities after the 2010 Census.
 
CO_CODE:    3 digit ID for the county in which the MCD resides.  This is the 
            official state and federal county code and is to be treated as text 
            with leading zeros. e.g. 163, 003

CTU_ID:     The Geographic Names Information System (GNIS) official federal
            unique identifier for each city, township or unorganized territory.
            This field is an integer data type of 6 to 7 digits.

CTU_ID_CEN: This is a text representation of the CTU_ID above.  This format is 
            used by the Census Bureau (8 digits, right justified with leading
            zeros included).

CTU_CODE:   5 digit FIPS55 'Place' code for CTU.  As of 2006 these codes have 
            been official retired by the federal government.  They are replaced
            by the GNIS codes above. The Census Bureau will continue to create
            FIPS55 Place codes for new cities and townships through the 2010
            Census.  After that, no new FIPS55 codes will be created. Note that
            for townships that wholly incorporate into cities, the same FIPS55
            code for the former township will usually be used for the new city. 
            Conversely, GNIS creates a new ID for the new city.

CTU_NAME:   Name of the city, township or unorganized territory - format 1.  
            e.g. Burns Twp., Blaine

CTU_NAME2:  Name of the city, township or unorganized territory - format 2.
            e.g. Burns Township, Blaine

CTU_NAME3:  Name of the city, township or unorganized territory - format 3.
            e.g. Township of Burns, City of Blaine

CTU_NAME4:  Name of the city, township or unorganized territory - format 4
            e.g. Burns, Township of; Blaine, City of

CTU_NAME5:  Name of the city, township or unorganized territory - format 5
            e.g. Burns, Blaine

COCTU_DESC: Description of the COCTU, including portion of county and 
            historical designation if applicable; 
            e.g. Burns Township, Blaine (Anoka Co. part), Elko (historical)

CTU_PARTEX: Indicates that the whole city is part external
            T = Whole city has part that is external to seven county metro.
            F = Whole city is within seven county metro.

CO_NAME:    Name of the county (e.g. Carver)
 
CTU_ABBREV: 6 character unique abbreviation for the CTU developed by Met. 
            Council GIS staff for file naming purposes  e.g. ANDOVE, ANOKAX.

COMCD_CENS: The Census Bureau's old 6 digit county-MCD code 
            (concatenation of FIPS county code and old Census MCD code)
            This code was retired in the 1990s.
 
CTU_TYPE:   Type of CTU
            C = city
            T = township
            U = unorganized territory
            O = other (not a CTU, but useful as an entity in this table 
                e.g. MSP airport,)

CTU_STATUS: Indicates status of CTU
            A = Active CTU
            H = Historic CTU
            P = Pending CTU

DUP_CTYTWP: Identifies cities and townships with the same name (e.g. City of 
            Vermillion and Vermillion Township)
 
ABC_SORT:   3 digit integer that will sort alphabetically e.g. 'St.' is 
            sorted as 'Saint'
 
FIVE_COLOR: Numbers 1 to 5 for shading polygons so that adjacent CTUs have 
            different colors.

MCDIST2003: Metropolitan Council District number in which the MCD resides, as
            enacted in 2003.  Districts are numbered 1-16.  Six cities are 
            split into multiple districts.  Three of these (Hastings, Spring
            Lake Park and Chanhassen) are split along county boundaries.  Thus 
            each of the two record for each of those cities within this table
            have a distinct value in this field.  The other three cities are not
            split by county bundaries and thus have only one record each in this 
            table.  These cities have been given an alternate value in this field.
            Eagan = 97 (split into districts 15 and 16).  Minneapolis = 98 (split 
            into districts (6,7 and 8).  St. Paul = 99 (split into districts 14 
            and 15).  Cities exempt from Council jurisdiction are coded as 0.  
            Also see the MCDistByCTU field for a list of all 2013 Council Districts
            within each CTU.

MCDIST1993: Metropolitan Council District number in which the MCD resides, as 
            enacted in 1993.  Districts are numbered 1-16.  Three cities are 
            split into multiple districts and have been given an alternate 
            value in this dataset.  Maplewood = 96 (split into districts 11 and 
            12).  Minneapolis = 98 (split into districts 6,7 and 8).  St. Paul 
            = 99 (split into districts 13 and 14).  Cities exempt from Council 
            jurisdiction are coded as 0.

MCDistByCTU: The number(s) for the 2013 Metropolitan Council District(s) which 
            exist(s) within the city or township as a whole.  Thus six cities
            have multiple numbers separated by commas within this field. Historical
            CTUs and CTUs exempt from Council jurisdiction have no data.

MCFIN_CODE: The Metropolitan Council Finance Dept. accounting codes for those 
            cities and townships that are connected to Council owned waste 
            water treatment plants and are paying sewer access charges (SAC).  
            Not all cities and townships in the metro area will have a code.

MNREV_CODE: Minnesota Department of Revenue code for CTU; e.g. 1400, 500, 6 
            (unique within county only)

OLD_CO2D:   Old state 2 digit county code (Note 3 digit code is state standard)

CO2D_MNREV: MN Dept. of Revenue code for CTU preceded by 2 digit county code

MNDES_CODE: Minnesota Department of Economic Security 'community' code for 
            CTU, e.g. 0025, 0215  (unique within county only)
 
HENN_CODE:  'Municipal' code used by Hennepin County
 
POP_2000:   2000 population for county-CTU based on the 2000 census (does 
            not including any subsequent corrections of the data by the 
            Census Bureau, if any)

POP_1990:   1990 population for county-CTU based on the 1990 census 
            (including subsequent corrections of the data by the Census 
            Bureau)

ACRES_MCD:  The calculated acreage of the minor civil division based on the 
            quarterly MetroGIS county_ctu dataset.  Note that where cities fall 
            within two counties, each portion is a single MCD.  Both must be 
            summed to get the acreage for the entire city.  Where an MCD 
            contains multiple polygons (in the same county), this field 
            reflects the sum of those polygons.

ACRES_CTU:  The calculated acreage of the entire city, township or unorganized 
            territory based on the quarterly MetroGIS county_ctu dataset.  Note 
            that where a CTU resides within two counties, BOTH records in this 
            MCD table will contain the same total acreage for the entire CTU. 
            All polygons for a CTU are summed to create this acreage.  

MIN_X:      Minimum X Coordinate of CTU in UTM zone 15, meters, NAD83 coordinates

MAX_X:      Maximum X Coordinate of CTU in UTM zone 15, meters, NAD83 coordinates

MIN_Y:      Minimum Y Coordinate of CTU in UTM zone 15, meters, NAD83 coordinates

MAX_Y:      Maximum Y Coordinate of CTU in UTM zone 15, meters, NAD83 coordinates

MC_EXEMPT:  Exempt from Met. Council authority (Y/N) (e.g. Northfield)

BPPA_CODE : Metropolitan Council Blueprint 2030 planning area designations for 
            cities and townships.
             10 = central cities
             20 = developed communities
             30 = developing communities
             40 = rural growth centers
             51 = rural communities: diversified rural communities
             52 = rural communities: rural residential area
             53 = rural communities: ag preserve
             60 = 3 non-Council communities

RDF_AREA:   Metropolitan Council Regional Development Framework 2030 planning 
            area designations for cities and townships.
             21 = central cities (part of developed communities)
             22 = developed communities
             30 = developing communities
             40 = rural centers &amp; growth centers
             51 = rural communities: diversified rural communities
             52 = rural communities: rural residential areas
             53 = rural communities: ag preserve
             60 = 4 non-Council communities

RES_QUAD:   Metropolitan Council Research Dept. quadrants used for aggregating
            certain types of statistics (NE, NW, SE &amp; SW)

SECTOR_REP: Metropolitan Council planning sector representative for each 
            community

START_DATE: The date the CTU became active (status)

END_DATE:   The date the CTU became historical (status)

CHANGE_DAT: The date of the most recent change to a record in this table
            (e.g. new or historical CTU, corrections to table, etc.)

NOTES:      Notes or comments about this a record (e.g. date of incorporation)

TRANSIT:    Indicates if a community participated in the Transit Taxing District
            or the Transit Capital Levy.  
               TTD   = Transit Taxing District and Capital Levy. All TTD
                       communities are part of Capital Levy. 
               TCLYR = Only Transit Capital Levy.  'YR' indicates year that 
                       community was added to the levy, e.g. TCL09.
               null  = neither TTD nor TCL

TLG_COLOR:  Designated colors for communities by The Lawrence Group 
            used in Kings Atlas.
             1 = blue
             2 = gray
             3 = green
             4 = orange
             5 = pink
             6 = purple
             7 = white
             8 = yellow

MAC:        Metropolitan Airports Commission Affected Community  

RDF_2011:   Metropolitan Council Regional Development Framework 2030 planning
            area designations for cities and townships derived from the
            2008 comprehensive plan updates. 
             21 = central cities (part of developed communities) 
             22 = developed communities 
             30 = developing communities 
             41 = rural centers
             42 = rural growth centers 
             51 = diversified rural communities 
             52 = rural residential communities
             53 = agricultural communities
             60 = non-Council communities


CD_DESC: Generalized, single-designation planning area used by Metropolitan 
            Council's Community Development Research unit for reporting some 
            community level data. 
           RDF_2011 CD_DESC 
           21 = Central Cities (part of developed communities) 
           22 = Developed Communities 
           30 = Developing Communities 
           41 = Rural Centers &amp; Rural Growth Centers 
           42 = Rural Centers &amp; Rural Growth Centers 
           51 = Rural Communities 
           52 = Rural Communities 
           53 = Rural Communities 
           60 = Non-Council Communities 


MCDistByCT:   


COMDES2040:   Metropolitan Council Thrive
MSP 2040 community designations
            for cities and townships.
             21 = central cities (part of urban center) 
             23 = urban center
             24 = urban 
             25 = suburban 
             35 = suburban edge
             36 = emerging suburban edge
             41 = rural centers
             51 = diversified rural communities 
             52 = rural residential communities
             53 = agricultural communities
             60 = non-Council communities

METMO_SA: Metro Mobility ADA Service Provider Areas
      Metro East
      Metro South
      Metro West


-----------------------------------------------------------------------------
 
Field types and lengths
                            Decimal
Name        Type    Length  Places
----------  ------  ------  ------
COCTU_ID    string    11
COCTU_CODE  string     8
CO_CODE     string     3
CTU_ID      number     8
CTU_ID_CEN  string     8
CTU_CODE    string     5
CTU_NAME    string    24
CTU_NAME2   string    30
CTU_NAME3   string    40
CTU_NAME4   string    40
CTU_NAME5   string    24
COCTU_DESC  string    60
CTU_PARTEX  string     1
CO_NAME     string    10
CTU_ABBREV  string     6
COMCD_CENS  number    10
CTU_TYPE    string     1
CTU_STATUS  string     1
DUP_CTYTWP  string     1
ABC_SORT    numeric    4
FIVE_COLOR  numeric    1
MCDIST2003  numeric    2
MCDIST1993  numeric    2
MCFIN_CODE  string     4
COMCD_CENS  numeric    6
MNREV_CODE  numeric    4
OLD_CO2D    numeric    2
CO2D_MNREV  numeric    6
MNDES_CODE  string     7
HENN_CODE   numeric    4
POP_2000    numeric    9
POP_1990    numeric    9
ACRES_MCD   numeric    9
ACRES_CTU   numeric    9  
MIN_X       numeric    9 
MAX_X       numeric    9
MIN_Y       numeric    9
MAX_Y       numeric    9
MCEXEMPT    string     1
BPPA_CODE   numeric    2
RDF_AREA    numeric    2
RES_QUAD    string     2
SECTOR_REP  string    40
REV_FOLDER  string    40
START_DATE  date       8
END_DATE    date       8
CHANGE_DAT  date       8
NOTES       string   150
COCTU_ID_O  string    11
CTU_ID_OLD  number     8
CTU_ID_C_O  string     8
TRANSIT     string     5
TLG_COLOR   numeric    2
MAC         string     3
RDF_2011    numeric    2
MCDistByCTU string    10
COMDES2040    numeric    2
METMO_SA  string  12</eaover>
      <eadetcit>None</eadetcit>
    </overview>
  </eainfo>
  <distinfo>
    <resdesc>CountyCTULookupTable</resdesc>
    <distliab>NOTICE:  The Geographic Information System (GIS) Data to which this notice is attached are made available pursuant to the Minnesota Government Data Practices Act (Minnesota Statutes Chapter 13).  THE GIS DATA ARE PROVIDED TO YOU AS IS AND WITHOUT ANY WARRANTY AS TO THEIR PERFORMANCE, MERCHANTABILITY, OR FITNESS FOR ANY PARTICULAR PURPOSE.  The GIS Data were developed by the Metropolitan Council for its own internal business purposes.  The Metropolitan Council does not represent or warrant that the GIS Data or the data documentation are error-free, complete, current, or accurate.  You are responsible for any consequences resulting from your use of the GIS Data or your reliance on the GIS Data.  You should consult the data documentation for this particular GIS Data to determine the limitations of the GIS Data and the precision with which the GIS Data may depict distance, direction, location, or other geographic features.  If you transmit or provide the GIS Data (or any portion of it) to another user, it is recommended that the GIS Data include a copy of this disclaimer and this metadata.</distliab>
    <stdorder>
      <digform>
        <digtinfo>
          <formname/>
          <formvern/>
          <transize/>
        </digtinfo>
      </digform>
      <ordering>See Online Linkage Below</ordering>
    </stdorder>
    <distrib>
      <cntinfo>
        <cntperp>
          <cntorg>Metropolitan Council</cntorg>
          <cntper>Tanya Mayer</cntper>
        </cntperp>
        <cntpos>GIS Specialist</cntpos>
        <cntaddr>
          <addrtype>mailing and physical</addrtype>
          <address>390 Robert Street North</address>
          <city>St. Paul</city>
          <state>MN</state>
          <postal>55101-1805</postal>
        </cntaddr>
        <cntvoice>651.602.1604</cntvoice>
        <cntemail>tanya.mayer@metc.state.mn.us</cntemail>
      </cntinfo>
    </distrib>
  </distinfo>
  <metainfo>
    <metd>20150817</metd>
    <metstdn>Minnesota Geographic Metadata Guidelines</metstdn>
    <metstdv>1.2</metstdv>
    <metextns>
      <onlink>http://www.gis.state.mn.us/stds/metadata.htm</onlink>
    </metextns>
    <metc>
      <cntinfo>
        <cntperp>
          <cntorg>Metropolitan Council</cntorg>
          <cntper>Tanya Mayer</cntper>
        </cntperp>
        <cntpos>GIS Specialist</cntpos>
        <cntaddr>
          <addrtype>mailing and physical</addrtype>
          <address>390 Robert Street North</address>
          <city>St. Paul</city>
          <state>MN</state>
          <postal>55101-1805</postal>
        </cntaddr>
        <cntvoice>651.602.1604</cntvoice>
        <cntemail>tanya.mayer@metc.state.mn.us</cntemail>
      </cntinfo>
    </metc>
  </metainfo>
  <Esri>
    <ModDate>20110729</ModDate>
    <ModTime>13373500</ModTime>
  </Esri>
  <mdDateSt Sync="TRUE">20110729</mdDateSt>
</metadata>
