<metadata>
  <idinfo>
    <citation>
      <citeinfo>
        <origin>Metropolitan Council</origin>
        <title>Area of Concentrated Poverty</title>
        <pubinfo>
          <publish>Metropolitan Council</publish>
        </pubinfo>
        <pubdate>20150616</pubdate>
        <onlink>https://gisdata.mn.gov/dataset/us-mn-state-metc-society-areas-of-concntrtd-pvrty</onlink>
      </citeinfo>
    </citation>
    <descript>
      <abstract>In 2010, the Metropolitan Council was awarded a three-year $5 million dollar Sustainable Communities Regional Planning Grant by the U.S. Department of Housing and Urban Development (HUD). Because equity and access are critical underpinnings of the Sustainable Communities program, HUD required each grantee to complete a Fair Housing and Equity Assessment (FHEA). A Fair Housing and Equity Assessment involves analyses of a regions racial and ethnic diversity, identifying what HUD describes as Racially Concentrated Areas of Poverty and High Opportunity areas, describing public investments and policies as well as the jurisdictions fair housing landscape. This information, gathered through both community engagement and secondary data sources, provides a full picture of regional equity and access to opportunity. 

The Council released its FHEA, titled Choice, Place and Opportunity: An Equity Assessment of the Twin Cities Region, in 2014. Choice, Place and Opportunity: An Equity Assessment of the Twin Cities Region reported that limited opportunities for residents who live in Areas of Concentrated Poverty (40% or more of the households earn incomes that are less than 185% of the federal poverty level) contribute to racial and economic inequalities in the region. The report further states that race-specific barriers limits residential choices of people of color and hinders their ability to leave areas of concentrated poverty. 

The Metropolitan Council has defined Areas of Concentrated Poverty (ACP) as census tracts where 40% or more of the households earn incomes that are less than 185% of the federal poverty level (excluding tracts where a large percentage of the residents are post-secondary students).   The Council has also identified Areas of Concentrated Poverty where 50% or more of the residents are people of color (ACP50).  The original Choice, Place and Opportunity report used the terminology of Racially Concentrated Areas of Poverty, however, the Council is now using the term Areas of Concentrated Poverty where 50% or more of the residents are people of color to emphasize that concentrations of poverty are the problem, not concentrations of people of color living in close proximity. 

Note that HUD is now defining Racially / Ethnically Concentrated Areas of Poverty as census tracts where:
- at least half the population are people of color (that is, races or ethnicities other than white, non-Hispanic) AND
- at least 40% or more of the residents live at or below the federal poverty line OR the poverty rate exceeds three times the average tract poverty rate for the metropolitan area.

In June 2015, The Metropolitan Council has updated the Areas of Concentrated Poverty and Areas of Concentrated Poverty where 50% or more of the residents are people of color (ACP50) with more recent U.S. Census Bureau's American Community Survey, 5-Year Data, 2009-2013.

Downloading this data includes historic data for ACPs and ACP50s for the U.S. Census Bureau's Decennial Census, 1990 and 2000 and the U.S. Census Bureau's American Community Survey, 5-Year Data, 2007-2011.</abstract>
      <purpose>Identify and analize various social and demographic data within and outside the spatially defined areas.</purpose>
      <supplinf>Twin Cities 7 county metropolitan area.  This includes the counties of Anoka, Carver, Dakota, Hennepin, Ramsey, Scott and Washington.</supplinf>
    </descript>
    <timeperd>
      <current>Based on U.S. Census Bureau's American Community Survey 5-Year data, 2009-2013.</current>
      <timeinfo>
        <sngdate>
          <caldate>20131231</caldate>
        </sngdate>
      </timeinfo>
    </timeperd>
    <status>
      <progress>Complete</progress>
      <update>As needed</update>
    </status>
    <spdom>
      <bounding>
        <westbc>-94.012</westbc>
        <eastbc>-92.732</eastbc>
        <northbc>45.415</northbc>
        <southbc>44.471</southbc>
      </bounding>
    </spdom>
    <keywords>
      <place>
        <placekey>Twin Cities, Minneapolis, St. Paul, Brooklyn Park, Brooklyn Center, Ft. Snelling, Richfield</placekey>
      </place>
      <theme>
        <themekey>Race, Poverty, ACP, ACP50, Areas of Concentrated Poverty</themekey>
      </theme>
    </keywords>
    <ptcontac>
      <cntinfo>
        <cntperp>
          <cntorg>Metropolitan Council</cntorg>
          <cntper>Paul E. Hanson</cntper>
        </cntperp>
        <cntpos>GIS Specialist</cntpos>
        <cntaddr>
          <addrtype>mailing and physical</addrtype>
          <address>390 Robert Street North</address>
          <city>St. Paul</city>
          <state>MN</state>
          <postal>55101-1805</postal>
        </cntaddr>
        <cntvoice>651.602.1642</cntvoice>
        <cntemail>paul.hanson@metc.state.mn.us</cntemail>
      </cntinfo>
    </ptcontac>
  </idinfo>
  <distinfo>
    <distliab>NOTICE:  The Geographic Information System (GIS) Data to which this notice is attached are made available pursuant to the Minnesota Government Data Practices Act (Minnesota Statutes Chapter 13).  THE GIS DATA ARE PROVIDED TO YOU AS IS AND WITHOUT ANY WARRANTY AS TO THEIR PERFORMANCE, MERCHANTABILITY, OR FITNESS FOR ANY PARTICULAR PURPOSE.  The GIS Data were developed by the Metropolitan Council for its own internal business purposes.  The Metropolitan Council does not represent or warrant that the GIS Data or the data documentation are error-free, complete, current, or accurate.  You are responsible for any consequences resulting from your use of the GIS Data or your reliance on the GIS Data.  You should consult the data documentation for this particular GIS Data to determine the limitations of the GIS Data and the precision with which the GIS Data may depict distance, direction, location, or other geographic features.  If you transmit or provide the GIS Data (or any portion of it) to another user, it is recommended that the GIS Data include a copy of this disclaimer and this metadata.</distliab>
    <stdorder>
      <ordering>See Online Linkage Below</ordering>
    </stdorder>
    <distrib>
      <cntinfo>
        <cntperp>
          <cntorg>Metropolitan Council</cntorg>
          <cntper>Jon Hoekenga</cntper>
        </cntperp>
        <cntpos>GIS System Administrator</cntpos>
        <cntaddr>
          <addrtype>mailing and physical</addrtype>
          <address>390 Robert Street North</address>
          <city>St. Paul</city>
          <state>MN</state>
          <postal>55101-1805</postal>
        </cntaddr>
        <cntvoice>651.602.1561</cntvoice>
        <cntemail>jonathan.hoekenga@metc.state.mn.us</cntemail>
      </cntinfo>
    </distrib>
  </distinfo>
  <metainfo>
    <metd>20150616</metd>
    <metstdn>Minnesota Geographic Metadata Guidelines</metstdn>
    <metstdv>1.2</metstdv>
    <metextns>
      <onlink>http://www.mngeo.state.mn.us/committee/standards/mgmg/metadata.htm</onlink>
    </metextns>
    <metc>
      <cntinfo>
        <cntperp>
          <cntorg>Metropolitan Council</cntorg>
          <cntper>Paul E. Hanson</cntper>
        </cntperp>
        <cntpos>GIS Specialist</cntpos>
        <cntaddr>
          <addrtype>mailing and physical</addrtype>
          <address>390 Robert Street North</address>
          <city>St. Paul</city>
          <state>MN</state>
          <postal>55101-1805</postal>
        </cntaddr>
        <cntvoice>651.602.1642</cntvoice>
        <cntemail>paul.hanson@metc.state.mn.us</cntemail>
      </cntinfo>
    </metc>
  </metainfo>
  <eainfo>
    <overview>
      <eaover>FIELDS ASSOCIATED WITH: AreasOfConcentratedPoverty.shp:

STATEFP10 =  2 digit FIPS associated with the U.S. Census Bureau's Decennial Census 2010 (only valid with the AreasOfConcentratedPovertyTracts.shp)

COUNTYFP10 =  3 digit FIPS and state standard county ID code associated with the U.S. Census Bureau's Decennial Census 2010 (only valid with the AreasOfConcentratedPovertyTracts.shp)

TRACTCE10 =  6 digit Tract ID (Text) associated with the U.S. Census Bureau's Decennial Census 2010 (only valid with the AreasOfConcentratedPovertyTracts.shp)

GEOID10 = identifier for the combination of State, County, and Tract  associated with the U.S. Census Bureau's Decennial Census 2010 (only valid with the AreasOfConcentratedPovertyTracts.shp)

ALAND10 = Land area in Tract in square meters as defined by U.S. Census associated with the U.S. Census Bureau's Decennial Census 2010 (only valid with the AreasOfConcentratedPovertyTracts.shp)

AWATER10 = Area covered by water in Tract in square meters as defined by U.S. Census associated with the U.S. Census Bureau's Decennial Census 2010 (only valid with the AreasOfConcentratedPovertyTracts.shp)

GEOID2 = identifier for the combination of State, County, and Tract  assoicated with the specific Census dataset (see SOURCE)

SOURCE =  Identifies the Census dataset 

YEAR = Identifies the year. For American Community Survey data it identifies the terminal year of data collection. For example, 2013 represents 2009-2013 data. 

POPTOTAL = Total population for year. Population total for ACP2011 (American Community Survey, 5-Year Data, 2007-2011) is based on the more accurate Decennial Census, 2010

WHITENH = Population of White, Non-Hispanic for year. Population of White, Non-Hispanic for ACP2011 (American Community Survey, 5-Year Data, 2007-2011) is based on the more accurate Decennial Census, 2010

POC = Population of color for year. Population of color for ACP2011 (American Community Survey, 5-Year Data, 2007-2011) is based on the more accurate Decennial Census, 2010

PPOC = People of color as a percentage of total population 

POVDENOM = Population for whom poverty status is determined

POV185 = Number of people whose family or individual income is less than 185% of the federal poverty threshold

PPOV185 = People whose family or individual income is less than 185% of the federal poverty threshold, as a percentage of all  people for whom poverty status is determined

PSTUDENT = Percentage of population age 3+ who are enrolled in college or graduate school

POV_STUDENT = Percentage of people in poverty (family or individual income is less than 100% of federal poverty threshold) who are enrolled in college or graduate school  

POC50 = Are at least half of residents are people of color (PPOC_ACS&gt;=0.5)? &#8220;Y&#8221; = yes, &#8220;N&#8221; = no 

CONCPOV = Are at least 40% of residents with family or individual income below 185% of the federal poverty threshold (PPOV185 &gt;= 0.40)?  &#8220;Y&#8221; = yes, &#8220;N&#8221; = no

ACP = Area of Concentrated Poverty (CONCPOV=1 AND (PSTUDENT&gt;=0.5 OR PPOV_STUDENT&gt;=0.333)), &#8220;Y&#8221; = yes, &#8220;N&#8221; = no 

ACP50 = Area of Concentrate Poverty where at least half the residents are people of color (POC50=1 AND ACP=1), &#8220;Y&#8221; = yes, &#8220;N&#8221; = no

ACRES = Total area of Tract in Acres



FIELDS ASSOCIATED WITH:  AreasOfConcentratedPoverty.shp:

ACP = Area of Concentrated Poverty (CONCPOV=1 AND (PSTUDENT&gt;=0.5 OR PPOV_STUDENT&gt;=0.333)), &#8220;Y&#8221; = yes



FIELDS ASSOCIATED WITH:  AreasOfConcentratedPovertyACP50.shp:

ACP50 = Area of Concentrate Poverty where at least half the residents are people of color (POC50=1 AND ACP=1), &#8220;Y&#8221; = yes</eaover>
      <eadetcit>Zipfile contains three (3) related shapefiles and one related Excel workbook. The related Excel workbook contains four (4) data tables based on the U.S. Census Burueau's Decennial Census and the American Community Surveys for comparison and trend analysis: ACP1990; ACP2000; ACP2011; ACP2013 (the most current data). 

The three shapefiles include:

1) AreasOfConcentratedPovertyTracts - tracts where more than 40 percent of the residents have income less than or equal to 185 percent of the federal poverty line. Includes all associated information (i.e., total population, population of people of color, percent poverty, etc.)

2) AreasOfConcentratedPoverty - dissolved outline of Areas of Concentrated Poverty

3) AreasOfConcentratedPovertyACP50 - dissolve outline of Areas of Concentrated Poverty where 50 percent or more of residents are people of color

The related Excel workbook (AreasOf ConcentratedPoverty.xlsx) contains four data tables:

1) ACP1990 (based on U.S. Census Bureau's Decennial Census, 1990)

2) ACP2000 (based on U.S. Census Bureau's Decennial Census, 2000)

3) ACP2011 (data associated with CPO report, based on U.S. Census Bureau's American Community Survey, 5-Year data, 2007-2011)

4) ACP2013 (data associated with AreasOfConcentratedPovertyTracts, based on U.S. Census Bureau's American Community Survey, 5-Year data, 2009-2013)

The historic data tables need to be linked to historic U.S. Census Bureau geographies (i.e., U.S. Census Bureau's 2000 Decennial Census boundaries).</eadetcit>
    </overview>
  </eainfo>
  <Esri>
    <DataProperties>
      <itemProps>
        <itemLocation>
          <linkage Sync="TRUE">file://\\rafsshare.mc.local\shared\CommDev\Research\Research\GIS\BaseData\ACP\AreaOfConcentratedPoverty</linkage>
          <protocol Sync="TRUE">Local Area Network</protocol>
        </itemLocation>
      </itemProps>
      <copyHistory>
        <copy source="N:\CommDev\Research\Research\GIS\BaseData\AreaOfConcentratedPoverty" dest="\\rafsshare.mc.local\shared\CommDev\Research\Research\GIS\BaseData\ACP\AreaOfConcentratedPoverty" date="20150223" time="09253700"/>
      </copyHistory>
    </DataProperties>
  </Esri>
  <dataqual>
    <lineage>
      <procstep>In 2010, the Metropolitan Council was awarded a three-year $5 million dollar Sustainable Communities Regional Planning Grant by the U.S. Department of Housing and Urban Development (HUD). Because equity and access are critical underpinnings of the Sustainable Communities program, HUD required each grantee to complete a Fair Housing and Equity Assessment (FHEA). A Fair Housing and Equity Assessment involves analyses of a region&#8217;s racial and ethnic diversity, identifying what HUD describes as Racially Concentrated Areas of Poverty (RCAPs) and High Opportunity areas, describing public investments and policies as well as the jurisdiction&#8217;s fair housing landscape. This information, gathered through both community engagement and secondary data sources, provides a full picture of regional equity and access to opportunity. An FHEA also outlines how the resulting process and final product (i.e., the full report) will inform key public policies, such as regional planning.

The Council began work on its FHEA, titled Choice, Place and Opportunity: An Equity Assessment of the Twin Cities Region, in early 2012. Council staff consulted with external stakeholders (the FHEA Data and Mapping Team), engaged with community members (roundtable discussions in 2012 and 2013) and released two draft versions for public comment. In addition, the themes from the FHEA process infused the Thrive MSP 2040 policy development and engagement processes. This inclusive approach has allowed the Council to realize HUD&#8217;s goals for the Fair Housing and Equity Assessment. 

Choice, Place and Opportunity: An Equity Assessment of the Twin Cities Region reported that both economic and racial inequalities are limiting opportunities for residents who live in Areas of Concentrated Poverty (40% or more of the households earn incomes that are less than 185% of the federal poverty level). The report further states that race-specific barriers limits residential choices of people of color and hinders their ability to leave areas of concentrated poverty. Consequently, theses barriers feed existing racial disparities by creating and perpetuating Racially Concentrated Areas of Poverty (RCAPs), defined as census tracts where: 
&#8226;	50% or more of the residents are people of color and 
&#8226;	40% or more of the households earn incomes that are less than 185% of the federal poverty level.

Looking at the Twin Cities region as a whole, opportunities such as jobs, high-performing schools, and safe neighborhoods are unevenly distributed. Where people live influences their access to opportunities. Changing the uneven landscape of opportunity to enhance opportunity for all residents can help reduce both economic and racial inequities.
The report states that a region that shares both opportunities and challenges and seeks to improve the lives of its entire population is stronger and more vibrant. The Council hopes the report will raise awareness of the complex interdependencies of income, race, place, and opportunity and to challenge both itself and others to think regionally and act equitably for a better region for all. 

Upon completing the requirements of the Sustainable Communities Regional Planning Grant, local officials and advocacy groups have suggested that future dialog regarding opportunity and equity focus on Areas of Concentrated Poverty (40% or more of the households earn incomes that are less than 185% of the federal poverty level) or ACPs with additional awareness of Areas of Concentrated Poverty where 50% or more of the Residents are People of Color (a more accurate definition than the HUD defined RCAP term) or ACP50s.

It should also be noted that Areas of Concentrated Poverty where a large percentage of the residents were post-secondary students living in poverty were excluded from the defined areas.
</procstep>
    </lineage>
  </dataqual>
  <spref>
    <horizsys>
      <planar>
        <gridsys>
          <gridsysn>Universal Transverse Mercator</gridsysn>
          <utm>
            <utmzone>15</utmzone>
          </utm>
        </gridsys>
        <planci>
          <plandu>meters</plandu>
        </planci>
      </planar>
      <geodetic>
        <horizdn>NAD83</horizdn>
        <ellips>GRS80</ellips>
      </geodetic>
    </horizsys>
  </spref>
</metadata>
