<!DOCTYPE metadata SYSTEM "http://www.fgdc.gov/metadata/fgdc-std-001-1998.dtd">
<metadata>
  <idinfo>
    <citation>
      <citeinfo>
        <title>Top of Bedrock Units - Twin Cities Metropolitan Area, Minnesota</title>
        <origin>Barr Engineering Company</origin>
        <pubinfo>
          <publish>Metropolitan Council</publish>
        </pubinfo>
        <pubdate>20091201</pubdate>
        <onlink>https://gisdata.mn.gov/dataset/us-mn-state-metc-geos-metro-top-elev-bedrock</onlink>
      </citeinfo>
    </citation>
    <descript>
      <abstract>This raster dataset represents the tops of the St. Peter Sandstone, Prairie du Chien Group, Jordan Sandstone, St. Lawrence Formation, Franconia Formation, Ironton and Galesville Sandstones, Eau Claire Formation, and Mt. Simon Sandstone in the Twin Cities metropolitan area of Minnesota.This dataset was developed by Barr Engineering Company for the Metropolitan Council to support the development of Metro Model 2.

More information about this process is provided in the 2009 Metropolitan Council report 'Twin Cities Metropolitan Area Regional Groundwater Flow Model Version 2.00 - Technical Report in Support of the Metropolitan Area Master Water Supply Plan', which is available online at www.metrocouncil.org/environment/WaterSupply/metrogroundwatermodeldatasets.htm</abstract>
      <purpose>The 2005 Minnesota Legislature directed the Metropolitan Council to "carry out planning activities addressing the water supply needs of the metropolitan area" (Minnesota Statutes, Section 473.1565). Specifically the Council is charged with developing a base of technical information for water supply planning decisions and to prepare a metropolitan area master water supply plan. This dataset supports this charge.</purpose>
      <supplinf>Twin Cities metropolitan area and parts of surrounding counties</supplinf>
    </descript>
    <timeperd>
      <timeinfo>
        <sngdate>
          <caldate>20090326</caldate>
        </sngdate>
      </timeinfo>
      <current>Datasets developed by Barr Engineering Company in 2008</current>
    </timeperd>
    <status>
      <progress>Complete</progress>
      <update>As needed</update>
    </status>
    <spdom>
      <bounding>
        <westbc>-406649.37482366</westbc>
        <eastbc>-535147.93345905</eastbc>
        <northbc>5046789.6321115</northbc>
        <southbc>4910785.3165465</southbc>
      </bounding>
    </spdom>
    <keywords>
      <place>
        <placekey>Anoka County, Carver County, Chisago County, Dakota County, Goodhue County, Hennepin County, Isanti County, LeSueur County, McLeod County, Ramsey County, Rice County, Scott County, Sherburne County, Sibley County, Washington County, Wright County, in Minnesota</placekey>
      </place>
      <theme>
        <themekey>St. Peter Sandstone, Prairie du Chien Group, Jordan Sandstone, St. Lawrence Formation, Franconia Formation, Ironton and Galesville Sandstones, Eau Claire Formation, Mt. Simon Sandstone, Geology</themekey>
      </theme>
    </keywords>
    <accconst>None</accconst>
    <useconst>By acceptance of this data, the user agrees to include a copy of the metadata record, including the liability disclaimer, whenever the user transmits or provides the GIS data (or any portion of it) to another user.</useconst>
    <browse>
      <browsen>None available</browsen>
    </browse>
    <crossref>
      <citeinfo>
        <title>Supporting datasets:
1) digital elevation models for the tops of the St. Peter Sandstone, Prairie du Chien Group, Jordan Sandstone, and St. Lawrence Formation within the seven county metropolitan area (Tipping and Mossler, 1996); 
2) digital elevation models for top of the St. Peter Sandstone, Prairie Du Chein Group, Jordan Sandstone, St. Lawrence Formation, Franconia Formation, Ironton-Galesville Sandstone, Eau Claire Formation, and the Mt. Simon Sandstone in Scott County (Runkel and Tipping, 2006); 
3) digital elevation models for the top of the Eau Claire Formation, Ironton-Galesville Sandstone, Mt. Simon Sandstone, and Precambrian crystaline bedrock in the northwest metro area (Runkel et al., 2003); and 
4) County Well Index (CWI) stratigraphic information (MGS, 2006).

Datasets described by this metadata:
TOPELEVATIONEAUCLAIREFORMATION
TOPELEVATIONFRANCONIAFORMATION
TOPELEVATIONIRONTONGALESVILLESANDSTONE
TOPELEVATIONJORDANSANDSTONE
TOPELEVATIONMTSIMONHINCKLEYSANDSTONE
TOPELEVATIONPRAIRIEDUCHIENGROUP
TOPELEVATIONSTLAWRENCEFORMATION
TOPELEVATIONSTPETERSANDSTONE</title>
      </citeinfo>
    </crossref>
    <native>Microsoft Windows XP Version 5.1 (Build 2600) Service Pack 2; ESRI ArcCatalog 9.2.5.1450</native>
    <ptcontac>
      <cntinfo>
        <cntperp>
          <cntorg>Metropolitan Council</cntorg>
          <cntper>Lanya Ross</cntper>
        </cntperp>
        <cntpos>Sr. Environmental Scientist</cntpos>
        <cntaddr>
          <addrtype>mailing and physical</addrtype>
          <address>390 Robert Street North</address>
          <city>St. Paul</city>
          <state>MN</state>
          <postal>55102</postal>
        </cntaddr>
        <cntvoice>651-602-1803</cntvoice>
        <cntemail>lanya.ross@metc.state.mn.us</cntemail>
      </cntinfo>
    </ptcontac>
  </idinfo>
  <dataqual>
    <attracc>
      <attraccr>Not assessed</attraccr>
    </attracc>
    <logic>Not assessed</logic>
    <complete>Dataset is complete</complete>
    <posacc>
      <horizpa>
        <horizpar>Unknown</horizpar>
      </horizpa>
      <vertacc>
        <vertaccr>Not Assessed</vertaccr>
      </vertacc>
    </posacc>
    <lineage>
      <procstep>
        <procdesc>DATA SOURCES:
1) digital elevation models for the tops of the St. Peter Sandstone, Prairie du Chien Group, Jordan Sandstone, and St. Lawrence Formation within the seven county metropolitan area (Tipping and Mossler, 1996); 2) digital elevation models for top of the St. Peter Sandstone, Prairie Du Chein Group, Jordan Sandstone, St. Lawrence Formation, Franconia Formation, Ironton-Galesville Sandstone, Eau Claire Formation, and the Mt. Simon Sandstone in Scott County (Runkel and Tipping, 2006); 3) digital elevation models for the top of the Eau Claire Formation, Ironton-Galesville Sandstone, Mt. Simon Sandstone, and Precambrian crystaline bedrock in the northwest metro area (Runkel et al., 2003); and 4) County Well Index (CWI) stratigraphic information (MGS, 2006).

PROCESS:
In areas where digital elevation models had previously been developed by the MGS, it was assumed they are correct and no further work necessary.  In areas outside that covered by the MGS digital elevation models, and for the deeper layers, the CWI was used to determine the elevation of the lithologic contacts.  Data from MGS digital elevation models and CWI lithologic contacts were then combined to form continuous grids for the entire model domain.</procdesc>
      </procstep>
      <srcinfo>
        <srcscale/>
      </srcinfo>
      <procstep>
        <procdesc Sync="TRUE">Dataset copied.</procdesc>
        <srcused Sync="TRUE">N:\EQA\WaterSupply\MAPS_Make_A_Map\MAM_WaterSupply_2Mar09\MAM_WatSUp_Metadata_23Apr09\GeologyDEMs</srcused>
        <procdate Sync="TRUE">20091208</procdate>
        <proctime Sync="TRUE">10043000</proctime>
      </procstep>
    </lineage>
  </dataqual>
  <spdoinfo>
    <indspref/>
    <direct>Raster</direct>
    <mgmg3obj/>
    <mgmg3til/>
  </spdoinfo>
  <spref>
    <vertdef>
      <altsys>
        <altdatum>NGVD29</altdatum>
        <altunits>meters</altunits>
      </altsys>
      <depthsys>
        <depthdn>mean sea level</depthdn>
        <depthdu>meters</depthdu>
      </depthsys>
    </vertdef>
    <horizsys>
      <planar>
        <gridsys>
          <gridsysn>Universal Transverse Mercator</gridsysn>
          <utm>
            <utmzone>15</utmzone>
          </utm>
        </gridsys>
        <planci>
          <plandu>meters</plandu>
          <coordrep>
            <absres>300.2953848</absres>
            <ordres>300.2953848</ordres>
          </coordrep>
        </planci>
      </planar>
      <geodetic>
        <horizdn>NAD83</horizdn>
        <ellips>GRS80</ellips>
      </geodetic>
    </horizsys>
  </spref>
  <distinfo>
    <distliab>NOTICE:  The Geographic Information System (GIS) Data to which this notice is attached are made available pursuant to the Minnesota Government Data Practices Act (Minnesota Statutes Chapter 13).  THE GIS DATA ARE PROVIDED TO YOU AS IS AND WITHOUT ANY WARRANTY AS TO THEIR PERFORMANCE, MERCHANTABILITY, OR FITNESS FOR ANY PARTICULAR PURPOSE.  The GIS Data were developed by the Metropolitan Council for its own internal business purposes.  The Metropolitan Council does not represent or warrant that the GIS Data or the data documentation are error-free, complete, current, or accurate.  You are responsible for any consequences resulting from your use of the GIS Data or your reliance on the GIS Data.  You should consult the data documentation for this particular GIS Data to determine the limitations of the GIS Data and the precision with which the GIS Data may depict distance, direction, location, or other geographic features.  If you transmit or provide the GIS Data (or any portion of it) to another user, it is recommended that the GIS Data include a copy of this disclaimer and this metadata.</distliab>
    <stdorder>
      <digform>
        <digtinfo>
          <formname/>
          <formvern/>
          <transize/>
        </digtinfo>
      </digform>
      <ordering>See Online Linkage Below</ordering>
    </stdorder>
    <distrib>
      <cntinfo>
        <cntperp>
          <cntorg>Metropolitan Council</cntorg>
          <cntper>Lanya Ross</cntper>
        </cntperp>
        <cntpos>Senior Enviromental Scientist</cntpos>
        <cntaddr>
          <addrtype>mailing and physical</addrtype>
          <address>390 Robert Street North</address>
          <city>St. Paul</city>
          <state>MN</state>
          <postal>55101</postal>
        </cntaddr>
        <cntvoice>651-602-1803</cntvoice>
        <cntemail>lanya.ross@metc.state.mn.us</cntemail>
      </cntinfo>
    </distrib>
  </distinfo>
  <metainfo>
    <metd>20090326</metd>
    <metstdn>Minnesota Geographic Metadata Guidelines</metstdn>
    <metstdv>1.2</metstdv>
    <metextns>
      <onlink>http://www.gis.state.mn.us/stds/metadata.htm</onlink>
    </metextns>
    <metc>
      <cntinfo>
        <cntperp>
          <cntorg>Metropolitan Council</cntorg>
          <cntper>Lanya Ross</cntper>
        </cntperp>
        <cntpos>Sr. Environmental Scientist</cntpos>
        <cntaddr>
          <addrtype>mailing and physical</addrtype>
          <address>390 Robert Street North</address>
          <city>St. Paul</city>
          <state>MN</state>
          <postal>55102</postal>
        </cntaddr>
        <cntvoice>651-602-1803</cntvoice>
        <cntemail>lanya.ross@metc.state.mn.us</cntemail>
      </cntinfo>
    </metc>
  </metainfo>
  <Esri>
    <ModDate>20091208</ModDate>
    <ModTime>14120800</ModTime>
    <MetaID>{D29BCB44-2877-4D2D-8E93-5E46D38EE88F}</MetaID>
    <CreaDate>20091208</CreaDate>
    <CreaTime>10043000</CreaTime>
    <SyncOnce>TRUE</SyncOnce>
  </Esri>
  <mdDateSt Sync="TRUE">20091208</mdDateSt>
  <distInfo>
    <distributor>
      <distorTran>
        <onLineSrc>
          <linkage Sync="TRUE">file://\\rafs\shared\EQA\WaterSupply\MAPS_Make_A_Map\Metadata\GeologyDEMs</linkage>
          <protocol Sync="TRUE">Local Area Network</protocol>
        </onLineSrc>
      </distorTran>
    </distributor>
  </distInfo>
</metadata>
