<?xml version="1.0"?><!--  <!DOCTYPE metadata SYSTEM "metadata.dtd">  --><metadata><idinfo><citation><citeinfo><origin>Minnesota Department of Revenue</origin><pubdate>20111107</pubdate><title>Sales Tax, Minnesota, 2003-2009</title><mgmg1cid></mgmg1cid><pubinfo><publish>Minnesota Department of Revenue</publish></pubinfo><onlink>ftp://ftp.lmic.state.mn.us/pub/data/economy/sales_tax.zip</onlink></citeinfo></citation><descript><abstract>This spreadsheet includes Minnesota sales tax information for the years 2003-2009.  Data includes total amount of sales tax collected (state, county, city, and special purpose levies) and the number of businesses in the geographic area.  

Data are unduplicated and reported in one of four general categories:

1. Records outside of Minnesota are reported at the state level and include territories, APO's, foreign and unassigned.

Within Minnesota, records are assigned to one of three geographic levels (blockgroup, city or county):

2. Within the 7-county Twin Cities metro area, records are assigned to blockgroups.
3. Outside of the 7-county Twin Cities metro area, records are assigned to cities with populations greater than 2,000 residents.
4. All other unassigned Minnesota records are tabulated by county.

For additional information and statistical reports, please visit 
http://taxes.state.mn.us/legal_policy/pages/research_reports_research_reports.aspx

Note:  The positional accuracy of many locations for years 2003-08 has been improved in this version, therefore, anyone using this data should download and replace any previous version.</abstract><purpose>This dataset details sales tax information and the number of businesses in each geographic area across the state.</purpose><supplinf>Minnesota, and other areas outside the state that pay Minnesota sales tax</supplinf></descript><timeperd><timeinfo><sngdate><caldate>2009</caldate></sngdate></timeinfo><current>This data begins in the 2003 tax year, for taxes filed in 2004, and is current to the 2009 tax year, for taxes filed in 2010.</current></timeperd><status><progress>Complete</progress><update>Irregular</update></status><spdom><bounding><westbc>-97.5</westbc><eastbc>-89</eastbc><northbc>49.5</northbc><southbc>43</southbc></bounding></spdom><keywords><theme><themekt>ISO 19115 Topic Category</themekt><themekey>economy, sales tax, revenue</themekey></theme><place><placekey>Minnesota, MN, Twin Cities, 7 County Metro</placekey></place></keywords><accconst>None</accconst><useconst>By acceptance of this data, the user agrees to include a copy of this metadata record, including the liability disclaimer, whenever the user transmits or provides the GIS Data (or any portion of it) to another user.

We recommend that other interested parties download this dataset from the Minnesota Geographic Data Clearinghouse to ensure that the most current data is obtained (see Ordering Instructions).</useconst><browse><browsen>None available</browsen><browsed></browsed></browse><native></native><crossref><citeinfo><title>Income Tax, Minnesota: http://www.mngeo.state.mn.us/chouse/metadata/income_tax.html</title></citeinfo></crossref><ptcontac><cntinfo><cntperp><cntorg>Minnesota Department of Revenue</cntorg><cntper>Brian Udell</cntper></cntperp><cntpos>GIS Analyst - Tax Research</cntpos><cntaddr><addrtype> Mailing and Physical</addrtype><address>600 North Robert St  - MS 2230</address><city>St. Paul</city><state>MN</state><postal>55146-2230</postal></cntaddr><cntvoice>651-556-4930</cntvoice><cntfax>651-556-3103</cntfax><cntemail>brian.udell@state.mn.us</cntemail></cntinfo></ptcontac></idinfo><dataqual><attracc><attraccr>Attributes are deemed accurate but not error free. This data is administrative in nature and may be misrepresentative due to changing filing requirements or other administrative functions.

Records are assigned to the respective geographic area through geocoding of the listed address on the filed tax return, thus introducing an unknown, presumably small, level of error to the data through incorrect addressing.  

It must also be noted that this dataset ONLY covers sales tax, and does not include the use tax or other forms of taxation. These figures do include total sales tax, which includes the state portion along with any county, city, and special purpose levies.  It does not include nor factor into the aggregated figures any information about businesses who failed to pay Minnesota sales tax.    Please visit the Sales Tax page on the Minnesota Department of Revenue's website at http://www.taxes.state.mn.us/taxes/sales/index.shtml for additional information on filing requirements and guidelines.

IMPORTANT: The 7 records listed for the 7 metro counties are each the total of unmatched tax returns for those counties and are NOT the aggregate for each county. The 7 counties are: Anoka, Carver, Dakota, Hennepin, Ramsey, Scott and Washington.

Geographic areas with fewer than 10 businesses have been suppressed to ensure compliance with privacy laws.</attraccr></attracc><complete>The entire state of Minnesota is included.

Data are unduplicated and reported in one of four general categories:

1. Records outside of Minnesota are reported at the state level and include territories, APO's, foreign and unassigned.

Within Minnesota, records are assigned to one of three geographic levels (blockgroup, city or county):

2. Within the 7-county Twin Cities metro area, records are assigned to blockgroups.
3. Outside of the 7-county Twin Cities metro area, records are assigned to cities with populations greater than 2,000 residents.
4. All other unassigned Minnesota records are tabulated by county.

Geographic areas with fewer than 10 businesses have been suppressed to ensure compliance with privacy laws.</complete><posacc><horizpa><horizpar>Geographic boundaries are taken from U.S. Census Bureau TIGER files for 2008: http://www.census.gov/geo/maps-data/data/tiger-line.html

Individual records are linked back through previous years in order to provide better positional precision.  For example, if a point for 2008 is a rooftop match, and the address hasn't changed since 2003, the same blockgroup is assigned to all intervening years, even though the 2003 match only provided the city.</horizpar></horizpa></posacc><lineage><srcinfo><srcscale></srcscale></srcinfo><procstep><procdesc>Addresses, taken from the Minnesota Sales Tax forms, are geocoded using a variety of software packages, including MapMarker (MapInfo), EDQ (FirstLogic), and ZP4 (Semaphore).  Problematic addresses, such as those on a boundary of two geographic areas, are manually assigned to a geographic area by Minnesota Department of Revenue staff.

The total number of returns for each geographic area are then used to compute the total amount of collected sales tax and the total number of businesses.

Data from geographic areas with fewer than 10 businesses is then suppressed to comply with privacy laws.

Additional processing step added in 2010:  Individual records are linked back through previous years in order to provide better precision.  For example, if a point for 2008 is a rooftop match, and the address hasn't changed since 2003, the same blockgroup is assigned to all intervening years, even though the 2003 match only provided the city.  Therefore, anyone using the data should download and replace any previous version.</procdesc></procstep></lineage></dataqual><spdoinfo><indspref>FIPAREA - 2 to 12 digit FIPS code representing State, County, City, or Block Group</indspref><direct></direct><mgmg3obj></mgmg3obj><mgmg3til></mgmg3til></spdoinfo><eainfo><overview><eaover>FIPAREA -- Multi-jurisdictional FIPS code (text format) representing State, County, City, or Block Group

TYPEAREA --  FIPS level: State; Foreign; Unknown; County; City; Block Group

AREANAME1 -- FIPS name for all area types except for block groups

FIPST -- FIPS code for each state (2-digit, text format) 

FIPCTY -- FIPS code for each county (3-digit, text format)

FIPSTCTY -- Concatenated FIPS codes for state and county (5-digit, text format)

FIPMCD -- FIPS codes for minor civil divisions (cities); if a city is located in more than one county, the portion of the city located in each county is a separate record with a different code (5-digit, text format)

FIPTRT -- FIPS code for each Census tract (6-digit, text format)

FIPBGR -- Single-digit indicating the Census block group within a given Census tract. A block group is a cluster of census blocks having the same first digit of their four-digit identifying numbers within a census tract. For example, block group 3 within a census tract includes all blocks numbered from 3000 to 3999. (Single-digit, text format)

STABBR -- Two-letter state abbreviation in all caps. 

POP2000 -- Population from 2000 census

[IMPORTANT: For the attributes below, the 7 records listed for the 7 metro counties are each the total of unmatched tax returns for those counties and are NOT the aggregate for each county. The 7 counties are: Anoka, Carver, Dakota, Hennepin, Ramsey, Scott and Washington.]

SALESTAX3 -- Collected sales tax from 2003

SALESTAX4 -- Collected sales tax from 2004

SALESTAX5 -- Collected sales tax from 2005

SALESTAX6 -- Collected sales tax from 2006

SALESTAX7 -- Collected sales tax from 2007

SALESTAX8 -- Collected sales tax from 2008

SALESTAX9 -- Collected sales tax from 2009

BUSINESS3 -- Number of Businesses in 2003

BUSINESS4 -- Number of Businesses in 2004

BUSINESS5 -- Number of Businesses in 2005

BUSINESS6 -- Number of Businesses in 2006

BUSINESS7 -- Number of Businesses in 2007

BUSINESS8 -- Number of Businesses in 2008

BUSINESS9 -- Number of Businesses in 2009

NOTE -- Additional Information

Also note:  Totals for all the sales tax fields are in the last row of the spreadsheet.</eaover></overview></eainfo><distinfo><resdesc>MN Sales Tax</resdesc><distliab>NOTICE: The Data to which this notice is attached are made available pursuant to the Minnesota Government Data Practices Act (Minnesota Statutes Chapter 13). THE DATA ARE PROVIDED TO YOU AS IS AND WITHOUT ANY WARRANTY AS TO THEIR PERFORMANCE, MERCHANTABILITY, OR FITNESS FOR ANY PARTICULAR PURPOSE. The Data were developed by the Minnesota Department of Revenue for its own internal business purposes. The Minnesota Department of Revenue does not represent or warrant that the Data or the data documentation are error-free, complete, current, or accurate. You are responsible for any consequences resulting from your use of the Data or your reliance on the Data. You should consult the data documentation for this particular Data to determine the limitations of the Data and the precision with which the Data may depict location or other geographic features. If you transmit or provide the Data (or any portion of it) to another user, the Data must include a copy of this disclaimer.</distliab><stdorder><digform><digtinfo><formname>.xls</formname><formvern></formvern><transize>.5 mb</transize></digtinfo></digform><ordering>This dataset is distributed on the internet by clicking below after 'Online Linkage'. Doing so will tell your browser to download a 'ZIP' file which will contain the following:

- Excel spreadsheet (.xls format) file
- Metadata for the dataset (.htm, .xml and .lgr formats)
- NOTICE.TXT, a disclaimer.

For help with unzipping (uncompressing) the file, see:  http://www.gda.state.mn.us/resource.html?Id=16253#compress</ordering></stdorder><distrib><cntinfo><cntperp><cntorg>Minnesota Geospatial Information Office (MnGeo)</cntorg><cntper>Nancy Rader</cntper></cntperp><cntpos>GIS Data Coordinator</cntpos><cntaddr><addrtype>Mailing and Physical</addrtype><address>658 Cedar Street</address><address>Room 300</address><city>St. Paul</city><state>MN</state><postal>55155</postal></cntaddr><cntvoice>651-201-2489</cntvoice><cntemail>gisinfo.mngeo@state.mn.us</cntemail></cntinfo></distrib></distinfo><metainfo><metd>20140116</metd><metstdn>Minnesota Geographic Metadata Guidelines</metstdn><metstdv>1.2</metstdv><metextns><onlink>http://www.mngeo.state.mn.us/committee/standards/mgmg/metadata.htm</onlink></metextns><metc><cntinfo><cntperp><cntorg>Minnesota Geospatial Information Office (MnGeo)</cntorg><cntper>Nancy Rader</cntper></cntperp><cntpos>GIS Data Coordinator</cntpos><cntaddr><addrtype>Mailing and Physical</addrtype><address>658 Cedar Street</address><address>Room 300</address><city>St. Paul</city><state>MN</state><postal>55155</postal></cntaddr><cntvoice>651-201-2489</cntvoice><cntemail>gisinfo.mngeo@state.mn.us</cntemail></cntinfo></metc></metainfo></metadata>