<metadata xml:lang="en">
  <idinfo>
    <citation>
      <citeinfo>
        <origin>Minnesota Pollution Control Agency</origin>
        <pubdate>Revised weekly</pubdate>
        <title>MPCA Feedlots with Animal Counts and Animal Units</title>
        <geoform>vector digital data</geoform>
        <pubinfo>
          <publish>Minnesota Pollution Control Agency</publish>
        </pubinfo>
      </citeinfo>
    </citation>
    <descript>
      <abstract>This dataset contains point representations of the locations of animal feedlot facilities in Minnesota.  The attribute table includes information about the number of animals for each location.</abstract>
      <purpose>The locations of animal feedlots provide information and context to support decisions on animal health, land use, and maintaining environmental quality.  </purpose>
      <supplinf>Minnesota</supplinf>
    </descript>
    <timeperd>
      <current>Generated from the MPCA Delta database on the 'created' date for the shapefile files.</current>
      <timeinfo>
        <sngdate>
          <caldate>20150415</caldate>
        </sngdate>
      </timeinfo>
    </timeperd>
    <status>
      <update>Weekly</update>
    </status>
    <spdom>
      <bounding>
        <westbc>-97.069700</westbc>
        <eastbc>-90.511807</eastbc>
        <northbc>48.968607</northbc>
        <southbc>43.442165</southbc>
      </bounding>
    </spdom>
    <browse>
      <browsen>None available</browsen>
      <browsed/>
    </browse>
    <native>Microsoft Windows XP Version 5.1 (Build 2600) Service Pack 3; ESRI ArcCatalog 9.3.1.1850</native>
    <accconst>None</accconst>
    <useconst>Redistribution Conditions: If you obtain data from the MPCA, it is understood that you and/or your organization have the right to use them for any internal purpose. If you modify them, you should document those changes in a metadata record that should accompany all redistributed data. If you transmit or provide these data in any form to another user, the data should be accompanied by all documentation provided with the original data set including the full metadata record.</useconst>
    <keywords>
      <place>
        <placekey>Minnesota</placekey>
      </place>
      <theme>
        <themekey>farming, environment, feedlot, animal, cafo, livestock, animal units</themekey>
      </theme>
    </keywords>
    <ptcontac>
      <cntinfo>
        <cntperp>
          <cntorg>Minnesota Pollution Control Agency</cntorg>
          <cntper>David Fawcett</cntper>
        </cntperp>
        <cntpos>GIS Database Administrator</cntpos>
        <cntaddr>
          <address>520 Lafayette Rd N</address>
          <city>Saint Paul</city>
          <state>MN</state>
          <postal>55155</postal>
        </cntaddr>
        <cntvoice>651.757.2350</cntvoice>
        <cntemail>david.fawcett@pca.state.mn.us</cntemail>
      </cntinfo>
    </ptcontac>
  </idinfo>
  <dataqual>
    <complete>This dataset contains approximately 35,000 features.  There are approximately 3000 additional feedlots in the Delta database for which we have not generated spatial features.</complete>
    <posacc>
      <horizpa>
        <horizpar>Horizontal Accuracy is variable by feature.  The accuracy of an individual feature can be determined by the value of the 'CONFIDENCE' column.  

The current and detailed descriptions of the confidence codes can be found at:  http://www.mda.state.mn.us/efdp/
(login required)</horizpar>
      </horizpa>
    </posacc>
    <lineage>
      <srcinfo>
        <srcscale/>
      </srcinfo>
      <procstep>
        <srcused>Server=globe; Service=5152; User=DELTA; Version=SDE.DEFAULT</srcused>
        <time>14161000</time>
        <procdesc>Metadata imported.</procdesc>
      </procstep>
      <procstep>
        <procdesc>Metadata imported.</procdesc>
        <srcused>H:\sqlScriptsLive\AgData\mpca_feedlots_au_old2.shp.xml</srcused>
        <time>15474900</time>
      </procstep>
      <procstep>
        <procdesc>Metadata imported.</procdesc>
        <srcused>H:\sqlScriptsLive\AgData\mpca_feedlots_au_old.shp.xml</srcused>
        <time>10182500</time>
      </procstep>
      <procstep>
        <procdesc>Metadata imported.</procdesc>
        <srcused>D:\TestGisData\feedlotsForAg\LastVersion\mpca_feedlots_au.shp.xml</srcused>
        <time>11101700</time>
      </procstep>
      <procstep>
        <procdesc>Metadata imported.</procdesc>
        <srcused>C:\DOCUME~1\dfawcett\LOCALS~1\Temp\xml8A.tmp</srcused>
        <procdate>20081211</procdate>
        <proctime>11310900</proctime>
      </procstep>
      <procstep>
        <procdesc>Metadata imported.</procdesc>
        <srcused>V:\feedlots\mpca_feedlots_au.shp.xml</srcused>
        <date>20090123</date>
        <time>13435300</time>
      </procstep>
      <procstep>
        <procdesc>Metadata imported.</procdesc>
        <srcused>V:\feedlots\mpca_feedlots_ac_old.shp.xml</srcused>
        <date>20090123</date>
        <time>15180600</time>
      </procstep>
      <procstep>
        <procdesc>Metadata imported.</procdesc>
        <srcused>V:\feedlots\mpca_feedlots_ac_old2.shp.xml</srcused>
        <procdate>20090128</procdate>
        <proctime>13523000</proctime>
      </procstep>
      <procstep>
        <procdesc>Metadata imported.</procdesc>
        <srcused>V:\feedlots\mpca_feedlots_ac_old.shp.xml</srcused>
        <procdate>20090304</procdate>
        <proctime>14205100</proctime>
      </procstep>
      <procstep>
        <procdesc>Metadata imported.</procdesc>
        <srcused>V:\feedlots\mpca_feedlots_ac.shp.xml</srcused>
        <procdate>20090416</procdate>
        <proctime>13281800</proctime>
      </procstep>
    </lineage>
  </dataqual>
  <spdoinfo>
    <direct>Vector</direct>
    <ptvctinf>
      <sdtsterm>
        <sdtstype>Entity point</sdtstype>
        <ptvctcnt>24433</ptvctcnt>
      </sdtsterm>
    </ptvctinf>
    <indspref/>
    <mgmg3obj/>
    <mgmg3til/>
  </spdoinfo>
  <spref>
    <vertdef>
      <altsys>
        <altenc>Explicit elevation coordinate included with horizontal coordinates</altenc>
        <altres>1.000000</altres>
      </altsys>
    </vertdef>
    <horizsys>
      <planar>
        <gridsys>
          <gridsysn>Universal Transverse Mercator</gridsysn>
          <utm>
            <utmzone>15</utmzone>
          </utm>
        </gridsys>
        <planci>
          <plandu>meters</plandu>
        </planci>
      </planar>
      <geodetic>
        <horizdn>NAD83</horizdn>
        <ellips>GRS80</ellips>
      </geodetic>
    </horizsys>
  </spref>
  <eainfo>
    <detailed>
      <enttyp>
        <enttypl>mpca_feedlots_ac</enttypl>
      </enttyp>
      <attr>
        <attrlabl>ACTIVE</attrlabl>
        <attrdef>Is the facility active?</attrdef>
        <attrdomv>
          <edom>
            <edomv>Y</edomv>
            <edomvd>Yes</edomvd>
          </edom>
        </attrdomv>
        <attrdomv>
          <edom>
            <edomv>N</edomv>
            <edomvd>No</edomvd>
          </edom>
        </attrdomv>
      </attr>
      <attr>
        <attrlabl>OPEN_LOT</attrlabl>
        <attrdef>A 'Y' or 'N' value to identify whether this facility is considered an open lot.  An uncovered lot intended for the confined feeding, breeding, raising, or holding of animals and specifically designed as a confinement area in which manure may accumulate, or where the concentration of animals is such that a vegetative cover cannot be maintained within the enclosure.</attrdef>
        <attrdomv>
          <edom>
            <edomv>Y</edomv>
            <edomvd>Yes</edomvd>
          </edom>
        </attrdomv>
        <attrdomv>
          <edom>
            <edomv>N</edomv>
            <edomvd>No</edomvd>
          </edom>
        </attrdomv>
      </attr>
      <attr>
        <attrlabl>CAFO</attrlabl>
        <attrdef>Is this facility considered a Confined Animal Feedlot Operation?</attrdef>
        <attrdomv>
          <edom>
            <edomv>Y</edomv>
            <edomvd>Yes</edomvd>
          </edom>
        </attrdomv>
        <attrdomv>
          <edom>
            <edomv>N</edomv>
            <edomvd>No</edomvd>
          </edom>
        </attrdomv>
      </attr>
      <attr>
        <attrlabl>CONFIDENCE</attrlabl>
        <attrdef>Relative confidence in the accuracy of the horizontal positional accuracy based on collection method.</attrdef>
        <attrdomv>
          <edom>
            <edomv>1</edomv>
            <edomvd>Very High - Location GPS'd or identified using heads-up digitizing by a knowledgeable party over high-resolution aerial photography</edomvd>
          </edom>
        </attrdomv>
        <attrdomv>
          <edom>
            <edomv>2</edomv>
            <edomvd>High - Location address matched with a high degree of confidence using multiple levels of complete street, city, and zip code information</edomvd>
          </edom>
        </attrdomv>
        <attrdomv>
          <edom>
            <edomv>3</edomv>
            <edomvd>Medium - Location matched to a Public Land Survey (PLS) description to the section level or beyond</edomvd>
          </edom>
        </attrdomv>
        <attrdomv>
          <edom>
            <edomv>4</edomv>
            <edomvd>Low - Location matched to a Public Land Survey (PLS) description at the township level, or address matched to zip code, city or county</edomvd>
          </edom>
        </attrdomv>
        <attrdomv>
          <edom>
            <edomv>5</edomv>
            <edomvd>Unknown - Unknown methods were used to create the location</edomvd>
          </edom>
        </attrdomv>
      </attr>
    </detailed>
    <overview>
      <eadetcit>Name: ID
Type: Text
Length: 40
Description: Unique MPCA ID for the facility. 

Name: CONFIDENCE
Type: Text
Length: 1
Description: A rating of the confidence the agency has in the location. See CONFIDENCE Codes table for valid codes and meanings. 

Name: NAME
Type: Text
Length: 64
Description: Facility Name for the Feedlot or Livestock operation

Name: CONTNAME
Type: Text
Length: 64
Description: Contact Name (Lastname, Firstname) for the operation

Name: CONTPHONE
Type: Text
Length: 16
Description: 10 digit phone number for the above person; nnn-nnn-nnnn

Name: PRIMSTOCK
Type: Text
Length: 10
Description: Code for the primary type of livestock at the facility.  See PRIMSTOCK codes table. 

Name: TOTALAN
Type: Integer
Size: 8
Description: Number of total animals on the premise/feedlot

Name: TOTALAU
Type: Double
Size: 12,3
Description: Number of total animals units on the premise/feedlot.  An animal unit is a measure used to compare differences in the production of manure for an animal feedlot or manure storage area.  Different animal unit calculation factors are applied based on the species and size of an animal.


Name: BIRDS
Type: Integer
Size: 8
Description: Number of animals;  any fowl, domesticated or game bird, of the Galliformes Order.   Absence of a type of livestock at a feedlot should be denoted with a '0' in the appropriate field.  

Name: BOVINES
Type: Integer
Size: 8
Description: Number of animals;  Cattle, Bison, or other animals in the Bovinae SubFamily.  Absence of a type of livestock at a feedlot should be denoted with a '0' in the appropriate field.  

Name: DEERELK
Type: Integer
Size:: 8
Description: Number of animals;  Deer, Elk, or other animals in the Cervidae Family.   Absence of a type of livestock at a feedlot should be denoted with a '0' in the appropriate field.  

Name: GOATSHEEP
Type: Integer
Size: 8
Description: Number of animals; Goats, Sheep or other animals of the Caprinae SubFamily.  Absence of a type of livestock at a feedlot should be denoted with a '0' in the appropriate field.  

Name: HORSES
Type: Integer
Size:: 8
Description: Number of animals; Horse, Donkey, Mule, or other animal of the Equidae Family. Absence of a type of livestock at a feedlot should be denoted with a '0' in the appropriate field.  

Name: LLAMALPAC
Type: Integer
Size: 8
Description: Number of animals; Llamas, Alpacas, or other animals in the Camelidae Family. Absence of a type of livestock at a feedlot should be denoted with a '0' in the appropriate field.  

Name: PIGS
Type: Integer
Size: 8
Description: Number of animals; Pigs, Hogs, Swine, or other animals in the Suidae Family. Absence of a type of livestock at a feedlot should be denoted with a '0' in the appropriate field.  

Name: OTHER
Type: Integer
Size: 8
Description: Number of animals; Foxes, Rabbits, Mink, &amp; other unknown or unspecified species. Absence of a type of livestock at a feedlot should be denoted with a '0' in the appropriate field.  

Name: ACTIVE
Type: Text
Size: 1
Description: A 'Y' or 'N' value to identify whether this facility is currently active.

Name: OPEN_LOT
Type: Text
Size: 1
Description: A 'Y' or 'N' value to identify whether this facility is considered an open lot.  An uncovered lot intended for the confined feeding, breeding, raising, or holding of animals and specifically designed as a confinement area in which manure may accumulate, or where the concentration of animals is such that a vegetative cover cannot be maintained within the enclosure. 

Valid Codes for CONFIDENCE Field

Code: 1
Confidence Level:  Very High
Description:  Location GPS'd or identified using heads-up digitizing by a knowledgeable party over high-resolution aerial photography

Code: 2
Confidence Level:  High
Description:  Location address matched with a high degree of confidence using multiple levels of complete street, city, and zip code information

Code: 3
Confidence Level:  Medium
Description:  Location matched to a Public Land Survey (PLS) description to the section level or beyond

Code: 4
Confidence Level:  Low
Description:  Location matched to a Public Land Survey (PLS) description at the township level, or address matched to zip code, city or county

Code: 5
Confidence Level:  Unknown
Description:  Unknown methods were used to create the location</eadetcit>
    </overview>
  </eainfo>
  <distinfo>
    <resdesc>mpca_feedlots_ac</resdesc>
    <stdorder>
      <digform>
        <digtinfo>
          <formname>Shapefile</formname>
          <transize>1.2</transize>
          <formvern/>
        </digtinfo>
      </digform>
    </stdorder>
    <distliab>Limitations: Although extensive effort has been made to produce error-free and complete data, all geographic information has limitations due to the scale, resolution, date and interpretation of the original source materials. Users should consult available data documentation (metadata) for this particular data to determine limitations and the precision to which the data depict distance, direction, location or other geographic characteristics. Data may be subject to change without prior notification.

No warranty: Data is provided "as is," without any warranty whatsoever, including but not limited to any warranty as to performance, merchantability or fitness for any particular purpose.

Liability: The entire risk as to the results of the use of this data is assumed by the user. The MPCA is not responsible for any interpretation or conclusions made by those who acquire or use it. The MPCA shall not be liable for any direct, indirect, special, incidental, compensatory or consequential damages or third-party claims resulting from the use of this data, even if the MPCA has been advised of the possibility of such potential loss or damage. In states that do not allow the exclusion or limitation of incidental or consequential damages, this data may not be used.

Redistribution conditions: In obtaining this data from the MPCA, it is understood that individuals or organizations have the right to use it for any internal purpose. If data is modified, changes should be documented in a metadata record that should accompany all redistributed data. If data is transmitted or provided in any form to another user, the data should be accompanied by a copy of this disclaimer and all documentation provided with the original data set, including the full metadata record.

Data delivered on electronic media: If data has been requested from the MPCA on magnetic media, CD or any other physical media, the MPCA will deliver it in the computer-readable format agreed upon with the requestor. The MPCA will reissue data if it is unreadable by correctly adjusted computer input devices or when the media is delivered in a damaged condition. Requests for reissue of this digital data product must be made within 30 days of the date shipped from the MPCA.</distliab>
    <distrib>
      <cntinfo>
        <cntperp>
          <cntorg>Minnesota Pollution Control Agency</cntorg>
          <cntper>David Fawcett</cntper>
        </cntperp>
        <cntpos>GIS Database Administrator</cntpos>
        <cntaddr>
          <address>520 Lafayette Rd N</address>
          <city>St. Paul</city>
          <state>MN</state>
          <postal>55155</postal>
        </cntaddr>
        <cntvoice>651.757.2350</cntvoice>
        <cntemail>david.fawcett@pca.state.mn.us</cntemail>
      </cntinfo>
    </distrib>
  </distinfo>
  <metainfo>
    <metd>20150415</metd>
    <metstdn>Minnesota Geographic Metadata Guidelines</metstdn>
    <metstdv>1.2</metstdv>
    <mettc>local time</mettc>
    <metextns>
      <onlink>http://www.gis.state.mn.us/stds/metadata.htm</onlink>
      <metprof>ESRI Metadata Profile</metprof>
    </metextns>
    <metc>
      <cntinfo>
        <cntperp>
          <cntorg>Minnesota Pollution Control Agency</cntorg>
          <cntper>David J. Fawcett</cntper>
        </cntperp>
        <cntpos>GIS Database Administrator</cntpos>
        <cntaddr>
          <addrtype>mailing and physical address</addrtype>
          <address>520 Lafayette Rd N</address>
          <city>St. Paul</city>
          <state>MN</state>
          <postal>55155</postal>
        </cntaddr>
        <cntvoice>651.757.2350</cntvoice>
        <cntemail>david.fawcett@pca.state.mn.us</cntemail>
      </cntinfo>
    </metc>
  </metainfo>
  <lineage/>
  <dataIdInfo>
    <envirDesc>Microsoft Windows XP Version 5.1 (Build 2600) Service Pack 3; ESRI ArcCatalog 9.3.1.1850</envirDesc>
    <dataLang>
      <languageCode value="en"/>
    </dataLang>
    <idCitation>
      <resTitle>mpca_feedlots_ac</resTitle>
      <presForm>
        <PresFormCd value="005"/>
      </presForm>
    </idCitation>
    <spatRpType>
      <SpatRepTypCd value="001"/>
    </spatRpType>
    <dataExt>
      <geoEle>
        <GeoBndBox esriExtentType="native">
          <westBL>201751</westBL>
          <eastBL>682197</eastBL>
          <northBL>5423966</northBL>
          <southBL>4816519</southBL>
          <exTypeCode>1</exTypeCode>
        </GeoBndBox>
      </geoEle>
    </dataExt>
    <geoBox esriExtentType="decdegrees">
      <westBL>-97.0697</westBL>
      <eastBL>-90.511807</eastBL>
      <northBL>48.968607</northBL>
      <southBL>43.442165</southBL>
      <exTypeCode>1</exTypeCode>
    </geoBox>
  </dataIdInfo>
  <mdLang>
    <languageCode value="en"/>
  </mdLang>
  <mdStanName>ISO 19115 Geographic Information - Metadata</mdStanName>
  <mdStanVer>DIS_ESRI1.0</mdStanVer>
  <mdChar>
    <CharSetCd value="004"/>
  </mdChar>
  <mdHrLv>
    <ScopeCd value="005"/>
  </mdHrLv>
  <mdHrLvName>dataset</mdHrLvName>
  <distInfo>
    <distributor>
      <distorTran>
        <onLineSrc>
          <orDesc>002</orDesc>
          <linkage>file://\\XP-1497249\D$\TestGisData\feedlotsForAg\mpca_feedlots_ac.shp</linkage>
          <protocol>Local Area Network</protocol>
        </onLineSrc>
        <transSize>0.653</transSize>
      </distorTran>
      <distorFormat>
        <formatName>Shapefile</formatName>
      </distorFormat>
    </distributor>
  </distInfo>
  <refSysInfo>
    <RefSystem>
      <refSysID>
        <identCode>NAD_1983_UTM_Zone_15N</identCode>
      </refSysID>
    </RefSystem>
  </refSysInfo>
  <spatRepInfo>
    <VectSpatRep>
      <topLvl>
        <TopoLevCd value="001"/>
      </topLvl>
      <geometObjs>
        <geoObjTyp>
          <GeoObjTypCd value="004"/>
        </geoObjTyp>
        <geoObjCnt>24433</geoObjCnt>
      </geometObjs>
    </VectSpatRep>
  </spatRepInfo>
  <mdDateSt>20091030</mdDateSt>
</metadata>
