<metadata>
	<idinfo>
		<citation>
			<citeinfo>
				<origin>U.S. Dept. of Transportation - Pipeline and Hazardous Materials Safety Administration (PHMSA)</origin>
				<pubdate>20040128</pubdate>
				<title catid="96001024-0c6e-4426-9af4-6d8c9a81625b">National Pipeline Mapping System</title>
				<onlink>http://gisdata.mn.gov/dataset/util-npms</onlink>
				<mgmg1cid />
				<pubinfo>
					<publish>U.S. Dept. of Transportation - Pipeline and Hazardous Materials Safety Administration (PHMSA)</publish>
				</pubinfo>
			</citeinfo>
		</citation>
		<descript>
			<abstract>The National Pipeline Mapping System (NPMS) is a geographic information system (GIS) created by the U.S. Department of Transportation, Pipeline and Hazardous Materials Safety Administration (PHMSA), Office of Pipeline Safety (OPS) in cooperation with other federal and state governmental agencies and the pipeline industry.  The NPMS consists of geospatial data, attribute data, public contact information, and metadata pertaining to the interstate and intrastate hazardous liquid trunklines and hazardous liquid low-stress lines as well as gas transmission pipelines, liquefied natural gas (LNG) plants, and hazardous liquid breakout tanks jurisdictional to PHMSA.
			</abstract>
			<purpose>The Pipeline and Hazardous Materials Safety Administration uses the NPMS as a tool to support various regulatory programs, pipeline inspections, and authorized external customers.</purpose>
			<supplinf>United States</supplinf>
		</descript>
		<timeperd>
			<current>See the NPMS website for the most recent version of pipeline data.</current>
		</timeperd>
		<status>
			<progress>In work</progress>
			<update>As needed</update>
		</status>
		<spdom>
			<bounding>
				<westbc>-179.00</westbc>
				<eastbc>-66.00</eastbc>
				<northbc>73.00</northbc>
				<southbc>18.00</southbc>
			</bounding>
		</spdom>
		<keywords>
			<theme>
				<themekt>ISO 19115 Topic Category</themekt>
				<themekey>utilitiesCommunication, LNG Facility, Pipeline, Oil, Gas, Natural Gas</themekey>
			</theme>
			<place>
				<placekey>U.S., USA, United States, Minnesota, MN</placekey>
			</place>
		</keywords>
		<accconst>The Pipeline and Hazardous Materials Safety Administration restricts access to the NPMS to federal, state, and local government agencies (including emergency responders).  Pipeline operators are allowed access to their own pipeline data only.</accconst>
		<useconst>Neither the United States Government nor any party involved in the creation and compilation of NPMS data and maps guarantees the accuracy or completeness of the products. NPMS data should be considered no more accurate than plus or minus 500 feet and must never be used as a substitute for contacting the appropriate local one-call center prior to digging.</useconst>
		<native />
		<crossref>
			<citeinfo>
				<title>The data set, 'Gas and Liquid Pipelines, Minnesota Statewide Overview, 1996: Department of Public Safety, Office of Pipeline Safety', previously available from the State of Minnesota, is no longer available.  Emergency officials and pipeline operators should instead request the National Pipeline Mapping System described in this metadata record.</title>
			</citeinfo>
		</crossref>
		<ptcontac>
			<cntinfo>
				<cntperp>
					<cntorg>U.S. Dept. of Transportation - Pipeline and Hazardous Materials Safety Administration (PHMSA)</cntorg>
					<cntper>Amy Nelson</cntper>
				</cntperp>
				<cntpos>GIS Manager</cntpos>
				<cntaddr>
					<addrtype>Mailing and Physical</addrtype>
					<address>1200 New Jersey Avenue SE</address>
					<city>Washington</city>
					<state>DC</state>
					<postal>20590</postal>
				</cntaddr>
				<cntvoice>202-493-0591</cntvoice>
				<cntfax>202-366-4566</cntfax>
				<cntemail>amy.nelson@dot.gov</cntemail>
			</cntinfo>
		</ptcontac>
	</idinfo>
	<dataqual>
		<attracc>
			<attraccr>The NPMS National Repository checks all entities and their attribute data for compliance with NPMS data standards. These checks do not ensure that NPMS data accurately reflects conditions in the field, only that the attributes meet database design specifications.</attraccr>
		</attracc>
		<logic>The National Repository is responsible for ensuring 1) that all geospatial data are complete and correctly projected to the proper geodetic datum, 2) that the attribute data are compliant with the NPMS data standards. However, NPMS is built from contributions of data from pipeline operators. Operator contributions vary in many respects. Logical consistency of NPMS data cannot be guaranteed.</logic>
		<complete>The NPMS represents hazardous liquid and gas transmission pipelines and LNG facilities under PHMSA jurisdiction. Distribution lines and gathering lines are not represented. The repository verifies each submitted dataset for completeness according to NPMS standards. The repository checks to ensure that all submissions include the required geospatial data, attribute data, and metadata. PHMSA makes every effort to ensure that the NPMS is complete and that pipeline and LNG facility operators comply with the NPMS Congressional mandate.</complete>
		<posacc>
			<horizpa>
				<horizpar>Positional accuracy of plus or minus 500 feet has been attempted for all pipelines and LNG facilities. Actual positional accuracy depends on the spatial accuracy of the pipeline operators' submission. Thus, actual positional accuracy of NPMS data varies. Positional accuracy is indicated in the QUALITY_CD field found in both the pipeline and LNG facility attribute tables. Positional accuracy is designated as E, V, G, P, or U where E = Excellent: within 50 feet, V = Very Good: 50-300 feet, G = Good: 301-500 feet, P = Poor: 501-1000 feet, and U = Unknown.</horizpar>
			</horizpa>
			<vertacc>
				<vertaccr>N/A</vertaccr>
			</vertacc>
		</posacc>
		<lineage>
			<srcinfo>
				<srcscale />
			</srcinfo>
			<procstep>
				<procdesc>Source materials:

Various pipeline operators.  All pipeline and LNG facility datasets submitted to NPMS by pipeline operators for processing are required to originate from scale sources less than or equal to 1:24000. Metadata for individual pipeline systems indicate Source Scale.

Processing steps:

The NPMS data compilation process begins when a pipeline or LNG facility operator submits data to the National Repository. In total there are seven major steps in the NPMS process:

1. Operator Submission. The process starts when an operator sends information (termed submission) to the NPMS repository.
2. Repository Check-in. The repository logs the submission, scans digital submissions for viruses, inventories the submission, notifies operator of submission receipt, and initiates tracking procedures. 
3. Metadata Review and Repair. The repository will review the metadata file that is supposed to accompany each NPMS submission. If problems exist with the metadata, the National Repository will work with the operator to complete the submission.
4. Data Conversion. Submissions with hard-copy geospatial data are separated from submissions with digital geospatial data. Hard-copy submissions are digitized, and digital submissions are translated. Attribute data is matched to the appropriate line features and reviewed for compliance with the standards. At the end of this step, the data will be in ARC/INFO format and ready for final processing. 
5. Quality Assurance and Quality Control. Harvard Design and Mapping Inc. (HDM) performs an independent quality control review and reports findings back to the National Repository. HDM does not make repairs to the data. The repository must make repairs and resend the data to HDM. The process continues until HDM approves the submission.
6. Check Plot Review by Operators . The repository prepares a random selection of check plots for review by the submitting operator. Operators are asked to review and comment on the check plots. 
7. Data Incorporation. The repository incorporates the data into the master database.</procdesc>
			</procstep>
		</lineage>
	</dataqual>
	<spdoinfo>
		<indspref />
		<direct>Vector</direct>
		<mgmg3obj>line</mgmg3obj>
		<mgmg3til />
	</spdoinfo>
	<spref>
		<vertdef>
			<altsys>
				<altdatum />
				<altunits />
			</altsys>
			<depthsys>
				<depthdn />
				<depthdu />
			</depthsys>
		</vertdef>
		<horizsys>
			<geograph>
				<latres>0.000001</latres>
				<longres>0.000001</longres>
				<geogunit>Decimal degrees</geogunit>
			</geograph>
			<geodetic>
				<horizdn>NAD83</horizdn>
				<ellips>GRS80</ellips>
			</geodetic>
		</horizsys>
	</spref>
	<eainfo>
		<overview>
			<eaover>Attributes in the NPMS pipeline data layer include:

    PHMSA-assigned operator identification number
    Operator name
    System name
    Subsystem name
    Diameter (voluntary data element)
    General commodities transported
    Interstate/intrastate designation
    Operating status (in service, abandoned, retired)
    Geospatial accuracy estimate
			</eaover>
			<eadetcit>See:
   https://www.npms.phmsa.dot.gov/
for more entity and attribute information.</eadetcit>
		</overview>
	</eainfo>
	<distinfo>
		<resdesc>npms</resdesc>
		<distliab>Check with the US Department of Transportation, Pipeline and Hazardous Materials Safety Administration (PHMSA) for their distribution liability policy.</distliab>
		<stdorder>
			<digform>
				<digtinfo>
					<formname>Contact the Pipeline and Hazardous Materials Safety Administration for available formats and media.</formname>
					<formvern />
					<transize />
				</digtinfo>
			</digform>
			<ordering>Viewers:

1. Public Viewer:  
https://www.npms.phmsa.dot.gov/PublicViewer/

2. Restricted Viewer:  
PIMMA (Pipeline Integrity Mapping and Management Application) is an online viewer that allows users to view the pipeline data directly on the NPMS website. This viewer is available to government officials for areas in which they provide data or have jurisdiction over. To apply for PIMMA, submit your state application here: https://www.npms.phmsa.dot.gov/StateApplication/StateApplication.aspx 

Data:
Due to security issues, pipeline data can only be released to pipeline operators and certified local, state, and federal government officials.

1. To apply to obtain raw GIS pipeline data (transmission pipeline data only) visit the following website for more details on the data available to you:
https://www.npms.phmsa.dot.gov/application.asp?tact=Data&amp;page=subapp.asp?app=data&amp;act=data_req 

2. To submit a request for pipeline data, use the following application: 
https://www.npms.phmsa.dot.gov/PipelineDataRequest/DataRequestForm.aspx

3. Also see the Frequently Asked Questions document:  
https://www.npms.phmsa.dot.gov/application.asp?tact=npms&amp;page=subapp.asp?app=aboutnpms&amp;act=about</ordering>
		</stdorder>
		<distrib>
			<cntinfo>
				<cntperp>
					<cntorg>NPMS National Repository; Michael Baker Jr., Inc.</cntorg>
					<cntper>Katie Field </cntper>
				</cntperp>
				<cntpos>Project Manager</cntpos>
				<cntaddr>
					<addrtype>Mailing and Physical</addrtype>
					<address>3601 Eisenhower Avenue, Suite 600</address>
					<city>Alexandria</city>
					<state>VA</state>
					<postal>22304</postal>
				</cntaddr>
				<cntvoice>703-317-6294</cntvoice>
				<cntfax>703-960-9125</cntfax>
				<cntemail>npms-nr@mbakercorp.com</cntemail>
			</cntinfo>
		</distrib>
	</distinfo>
	<metainfo>
		<metd>20140214</metd>
		<metstdn>Minnesota Geographic Metadata Guidelines</metstdn>
		<metstdv>1.2</metstdv>
		<metextns>
			<onlink>http://www.mngeo.state.mn.us/committee/standards/mgmg/metadata.htm</onlink>
		</metextns>
		<metc>
			<cntinfo>
				<cntperp>
					<cntorg>Minnesota Geospatial Information Office (MnGeo)</cntorg>
					<cntper>Nancy Rader</cntper>
				</cntperp>
				<cntpos>GIS Data Coordinator</cntpos>
				<cntaddr>
					<addrtype>Mailing and Physical</addrtype>
					<address>658 Cedar Street</address>
					<address>Room 300</address>
					<city>St. Paul</city>
					<state>MN</state>
					<postal>55155</postal>
				</cntaddr>
				<cntvoice>651-201-2489</cntvoice>
				<cntemail>gisinfo.mngeo@state.mn.us</cntemail>
			</cntinfo>
		</metc>
	</metainfo>
</metadata>