<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><metadata><idinfo><citation><citeinfo><origin>Minnesota Department of Natural Resources, Ducks Unlimited, Inc.</origin><pubdate>5/23/2013</pubdate><title>NWI Update for the East-Central region of Minnesota</title><geoform>vector digital data</geoform><pubinfo><publish>Minnesota Department of Natural Resources (DNR)</publish></pubinfo><onlink>http://gisdata.mn.gov/dataset/water-nat-wetlands-inv-2009-2014</onlink></citeinfo></citation><descript><abstract>The National Wetland Inventory (NWI) for east-central Minnesota were updated through multi-agency collaborative effort under leadership from the Minnesota DNR. Operational support for wetland mapping and classification was provided by Ducks Unlimited and support for methods development and field validation were provided by the Remote Sensing and Geospatial Analysis Laboratory at the University of Minnesota. Major funding was provided by the Environmental and Natural Resources Trust Fund.The project area consists of 13 counties in east-central Minnesota including: Anoka, Carver, Chisago, Dakota, Goodhue, Hennepin, Isanti, Ramsey, Rice, Scott, Sherburne, Washington, and Wright Counties. The updated wetland inventory area included complete coverage for all USGS quarter quadrangles that intersect any of these counties (about 7,150 square mile).The NWI classification process for east-central Minnesota consisted of three basic steps: 1) creation of image segments (polygons), 2) RandomForest classification of the segments, and 3) photo-interpretation of the classified image segments. The updated NWI also contains a Simplified Plant Community Classification and a Simplified Hydrogemorphic Classification. Quality assurance of the data included a 100% visual inspection, automated checks for attribute validity and topologic consistency, as well as a formal accuracy assessment based on an independent field verified data set. Further details on the methods employed can be found in the technical procedures document for this project (provide URL).The updated NWI data are primarily based on aerial imagery acquired in 2010 and 2011 as well as other modern ancillary data. This data is intended to replace the original NWI data which was based on imagery acquired in the early 1980s. NWI data support effective wetland management, protection, and restoration. The data provide a baseline for assessing the effectiveness of wetland policies and management actions. These data are used at all levels of government, as well as by private industry and non-profit organizations for wetland regulation and management, land use and conservation planning, environmental impact assessment, and natural resource inventories.</abstract><purpose>The updated NWI data are based on recent aerial imagery (2010 and 2011) as well as other recent ancillary data. These data are intended to replace the original NWI data which was based on imagery acquired in the early 1980s. NWI data support effective wetland management, protection, and restoration. The data provide a baseline for assessing the effectiveness of wetland policies and management actions. These data are used at all levels of government, as well as by private industry and non-profit organizations for wetland regulation and management, land use and conservation planning, environmental impact assessment, and natural resource inventories.</purpose><supplinf>The project area consists of 13 counties in east-central Minnesota including: Anoka, Carver, Chisago, Dakota, Goodhue, Hennepin, Isanti, Ramsey, Rice, Scott, Sherburne, Washington, and Wright Counties. The updated wetland inventory area included complete coverage for all USGS quarter quadrangles that intersect any of these counties (about 7,150 square mile).</supplinf></descript><timeperd><timeinfo><sngdate><caldate>20140808</caldate></sngdate></timeinfo><current>Based on 2010-2011 digital aerial photos, minor revisions last made in August 2014. Time Period of Content Date indicates when dataset was last updated.</current></timeperd><status><progress>Complete</progress><update>None Planned</update></status><spdom><bounding><westbc>-93.254375</westbc><eastbc>-93.183651</eastbc><northbc>45.690290</northbc><southbc>45.622132</southbc></bounding></spdom><keywords><place><placekey>Minnesota</placekey><placekey>East-Central Minnesota</placekey></place><theme><themekey>Surface Water, Wetlands, Swamp, Marsh, Bog, Fen</themekey><themekt>ISO 19115 Category</themekt></theme></keywords><accconst>None</accconst><useconst>None</useconst><datacred>Funding for this project was provided by the Minnesota Environment and Natural Resources Trust Fund as recommended by the Legislative-Citizen Commission on Minnesota Resources (LCCMR). The Trust Fund is a permanent fund constitutionally established by the citizens of Minnesota to assist in the protection, conservation, preservation, and enhancement of the state's air, water, land, fish, wildlife, and other natural resources. Currently 40% of net Minnesota State Lottery proceeds are dedicated to building the Trust Fund and ensuring future benefits for Minnesota's environment and natural resources. Additional funding and support was supplied by the U.S. Fish and Wildlife Service. Ducks Unlimited (DU) and the Minnesota Department of Natural Resources partnered to perform the NWI update for the east-central project area. DU had primary responsibility for developing the final updated NWI and DNR had primary responsibility overall project management and quality assurance oversight as well as providing support for data processing and field data collection. The Remote Sensing and Geospatial Analysis Laboratory at the University of Minnesota provided support for methods development and acquisition of independent field validation data.</datacred><secinfo><secclass>Unclassified</secclass></secinfo><native>Microsoft Windows XP Version 5.1 (Build 2600) Service Pack 3; ESRI ArcCatalog 9.3.1.3000</native><browse><browsen>ftp://gdrs.dnr.state.mn.us/gdrs/data/pub/us_mn_state_dnr/water_nat_wetlands_inv_2009_2014/preview/preview.jpg</browsen></browse><ptcontac><cntinfo><cntperp><cntorg>Minnesota Department of Natural Resources</cntorg><cntper>Steve Kloiber</cntper></cntperp><cntpos>Wetlands Monitoring Coordinator</cntpos><cntaddr><addrtype>mailing address</addrtype><address>Minnesota Department of Natural Resources</address><address>500 Lafayette Road, Box25</address><city>St. Paul</city><state>MN</state><postal>55155-4025</postal></cntaddr><cntvoice>651-259-5164</cntvoice><cntemail>steve.kloiber@state.mn.us</cntemail></cntinfo></ptcontac></idinfo><dataqual><attracc><attraccr>The source data was checked using standard review procedures. Attributes were checked by using visual inspection as well as automated verification routines.

PHOTOINTERPRETATION ACCURACY

To assess the performance of the final deliverable provided by Ducks Unlimited with respect to the FGDC accuracy goals, the data were compared to an independently developed set of 901 photo-interpreted points (PI points). The points were selected by a stratified-random sampling process and classified using high-resolution stereo imagery (mostly 1-foot resolution), 3-meter LiDAR derived digital elevation models, and other ancillary data. The mapped wetland class (polygons) was associated with the validation class (points) using a spatial join process in ArcGIS. The distance to the nearest wetland-upland boundary was calculated for each point. Points inside of the 95% confidence interval of the positional uncertainty of the imagery were excluded from analysis (1.53 meters).

The data were compared at two classification levels: level one compares the level of agreement between the two data sets for a two-class system of wetland versus upland, and level two compares the agreement between the data sets for the Cowardin wetland class-level. The producer's accuracy, the user's accuracy, and the overall accuracy were calculated along with the Kappa value for the level one (wetland-upland) classification. The level-two assessment calculated the overall accuracy for wetland class.

Wetland-Upland Accuracy
Wetland Producer's Accuracy = 93.0%
Wetland User's Accuracy = 98.1%
Overall Wetland-Upland Accuracy = 93.4%
Kappa = 83.1%

Wetland Class Accuracy
Overall Class Accuracy = 77.8%

Many of the classification differences between the two datasets were associated with confusion between the L1 system (limnetic) and L2 system (littoral) as well as confusion between aquatic bed (AB) and unconsolidated bottom (UB) classes. The limnetic-littoral boundary is generally defined by the 2-meter depth contour by the Cowardin system; however, data on water body depth is not universally available, so differentiating between these systems is difficult to do with precision. The difference between AB and UB systems is based on the presence macrophytic aquatic vegetation. Differentiation between these two classes is confounded by the dynamic nature of vegetation patterns. If these two classes of error are excluded from the analysis, the overall photo-interpreted wetland classification accuracy for the updated NWI would be 85.9%.

FIELD-LEVEL ACCURACY

The NWI is a map product derived from remote sensing. While remote sensing methods are the only practical means of wide-area mapping, these methods are somewhat limited in their ability to detect and classify certain feature types compared to a field-level assessment. To provide additional information regarding the reliability of the NWI for field-level use, the data were also compared to a set of validation data points mostly derived from field efforts. The Remote Sensing and Geospatial Analysis Laboratory at the University of Minnesota collected 915 field-based validation points in the summer of 2010. Sample points were located using a stratified-random sampling process. All field data were reviewed by the DNR wetland monitoring coordinator to check for obvious data errors. A ground-level assessment was made of wetland class and GPS coordinates were acquired using a Trimble Juno field computer. The geographic coordinate data were differentially corrected to improve accuracy. An additional 168 points were added by photo-interpreting high-resolution stereo imagery and other ancillary data to compliment the field data and ensure complete spatial distribution across the project area. 

The mapped wetland class (polygons) was associated with the validation class (points) using a spatial join process in ArcGIS. The distance to the nearest wetland class boundary was calculated for each point. Points inside of the combined 95% confidence interval of the positional uncertainty of the imagery and the GPS were excluded (5.64 meters). The data were compared at two classification levels: level one compares the level of agreement between the two data sets for a two-class system of wetland versus upland, and level two compares the agreement between the data sets for the Cowardin wetland class-level. The producer's accuracy, the user's accuracy, and the overall accuracy were calculated along with the Kappa value for the level one (wetland-upland) classification. The level-two assessment calculated the overall accuracy for wetland class.

Wetland-Upland Accuracy
Wetland Producer's Accuracy = 88.5%
Wetland User's Accuracy = 96.9%
Overall Wetland-Upland Accuracy = 89.3%
Kappa = 74.1%

Wetland Class Accuracy
Overall Wetland Class Accuracy = 72.1%

As with the comparison to the PI points, many of the difference between the field classification and the mapped classification are related to the L1/L2 system and AB/UB classes. If these two classes of error are excluded from the analysis, the overall field wetland classification accuracy for the updated NWI would be 83.8%.</attraccr><qattracc><attraccv>All polygons are attributed</attraccv></qattracc></attracc><logic>Polygon and chain-node topology are present. Every polygon has a label.</logic><complete>This data set represents the extent of wetlands and deepwater habitats that can be determined with the use of remotely sensed data and within the timeframe for which the layer was produced. The accuracy of image interpretation depends on the quality of the imagery, the experience of the image analysts, the amount and quality of the collateral data, and the amount of ground truth verification work conducted.</complete><posacc><horizpa><horizpar>The base imagery used to develop the NWI data has a horizontal RMSE of 1.53 meters. Wetland boundaries typically exist along a gradient of hydrology, soils, and vegetation and determining precise locations can be difficult even in the field. </horizpar></horizpa><vertacc><vertaccr>Not Applicable</vertaccr></vertacc></posacc><lineage><procstep><procdesc>Input Data
MN DNR Spring Aerial Imagery 2010 - 0.5 meter
MN DNR Spring Aerial Imagery 2010/11 - 0.3 meter
Farm Service Agency NAIP Imagery 2008, 2009, 2010 - 1 meter
MN DNR Lidar Data - 3 meter
USGS National Elevation Data - 10 meter
Alaska Satellite Facility - 10 meter
USDA SSURGO Soils
Metropolitan Mosquito Control District Wetland Data
MN DNR Minnesota County Biological Survey Native Plant Communities
USFWS National Wetland Inventory
USGS National Hydrography Data
MN DNR Public Water Inventory
MN DNR Streams
FEMA Floodplains

Step 1 - Field Data Acquisition
Field training data for photo interpretation projects is extremely important in order to guide the interpretation.  The field training data for the east-central project area served three purposes: 1) provided experience for the staff members updating the Minnesota NWI in the local wetland identification and classification, 2) gathered images for use in a guidebook for wetland photo interpretation, and 3) collected training data for the creation of a potential wetlands layer using a Random Forest? classification.   Within the project area, 12 quads with wetlands representative of those found in the project area were selected for field verification.  These quads included urban, residential, and rural areas.

Step 2 - Image Segmentation
The input to the eCognition segmentation process is a tiff layer stack and the raw spring 2010 aerial imagery.  The NED 10 meter DEM was resampled to 3 meter resolution after the derived products were created.  The SSURGO soils derived products were converted to raster format and added in the stack.  All layers were clipped to the spring 2010 aerial image boundary.  The final tiff layer stack consisted of the following layers:
1) Combined Curvature
2) Planimetric Curvature
3) Profile Curvature
4) TPI 15
5) TPI 20
6) CTI
7) Palsar
8) SSURGO Hydric Percentage
9) SSURGO Water Regime
10) DEM

Step 3 - Random Forest Classification
The output of the segmentation process consists of two shapefiles; a polygon shapefile of the segments and a point shapefile of the centroids of the polygons.  The polygons and points were related using a unique identification number (ID).  The point file contains all of the descriptive information from the polygon segments and was used as the input into the random forest classification.  Topology was built for the image segments and any issues are corrected.  Additional fields (attribute, comments, field verified) were added to the image segments for the photo interpretation process. A random forest classification was run using the point file and training data (described in section 6 above).  The random forest classification classified each point based on the training data and assigned a confidence value to each classification.  The resulting classification was then joined to the polygons using the unique ID.

Step 4 - Photointerpretation
The classified segments were then used to enhance a more traditional photo interpretation of the imagery.  Each of the segments was viewed, edited (merged with neighboring segments of the same class or cut to exclude an area), and assigned a final NWI classification using a variety of imagery and data.  A custom object inspector was created to incorporate the information from the random forest classification as well as the soils and Radar classifications.  Once a quarter quad was completed, the segments were dissolved based on NWI attribute and run through a quality control process that checks for overlaps, gaps and approved NWI codes.

Step 5 - Draft Data Review
The draft version of the NWI classification for the quarter quad was sent to the MN DNR for review.  Once the review was completed, the quarter quad was merged into a seamless state-wide layer.  The final NWI layer for the east-central project area was projected to Albers equal area projection for delivery to the U.S. Fish and Wildlife Service.

For more detailed information on the process, please see the Technical Documentation.

These data underwent a minor revision between July 25, 2014 and August 8, 2014. Requested edits since the initial release of the data were compiled into a geodatabase. The data steward reviewed 81 requested edits. Most of the edit requests were submitted by the USFWS National Standards and Support Team through a post-project review. Seventy-three (73) edit requests were accepted and eight (8) edit requests were rejected. Of the accepted edit requests, 53 of these involved adding small wetlands or parts of wetlands (min = 0.03 acres, max = 10.5 acres, mean = 0.89 acres) that were missed in the initial release, four edits involved a change of wetland class, and 16 edits involved a deletion of some portion of a wetland (min = 3.5 acre, max = 10.6 acres, mean = 0.66 acres).
The geometry of the updated data were checked using the Check Geometry tool from ArcGIS and any errors found were fixed using the Repair Geometry tool. A topology was created and the data were checked for gaps and overlaps. All gaps and overlaps were resolved. Finally, the USFWS QAQC tool was run on the data.</procdesc></procstep></lineage></dataqual><spdoinfo><direct>Vector</direct><ptvctinf><sdtsterm><sdtstype>G-polygon</sdtstype><ptvctcnt>1444</ptvctcnt></sdtsterm></ptvctinf></spdoinfo><spref><vertdef><altsys><altres>0.000100</altres><altenc>Explicit elevation coordinate included with horizontal coordinates</altenc></altsys></vertdef><horizsys><planar><gridsys><gridsysn>Universal Transverse Mercator</gridsysn><utm><utmzone>15</utmzone></utm></gridsys><planci><plandu>meters</plandu><coordrep><absres>0.000100</absres><ordres>0.000100</ordres></coordrep></planci></planar><geodetic><horizdn>NAD83</horizdn><ellips>GRS80</ellips></geodetic></horizsys></spref><eainfo><detailed><enttyp><enttypl>MN NWI Update 2010</enttypl><enttypd>Reference:  Cowardin et al. 1979</enttypd><enttypds>U.S. Fish and Wildlife Service</enttypds></enttyp><attr><attrlabl>OBJECTID</attrlabl><attrdef>Internal feature number.</attrdef><attrdefs>ESRI</attrdefs><attrdomv><udom>Sequential unique whole numbers that are automatically generated.</udom></attrdomv></attr><attr><attrlabl>Shape</attrlabl><attrdef>Feature geometry.</attrdef><attrdefs>ESRI</attrdefs><attrdomv><udom>Coordinates defining the features.</udom></attrdomv></attr><attr><attrlabl>Acres</attrlabl><attrdef>Area of the polygon in acres.</attrdef><attrdefs>Calculated in an UTM zone 15 projection using ESRI's geometry calculator.</attrdefs></attr><attr><attrlabl>HGM_CODE</attrlabl><attrdef>Hydrogeomorphic classification code</attrdef><attrdefs>ftp://ftp.dnr.state.mn.us/pub/eco/nwi/MappingGuidance/NWI_ecmn_Technical_Documentation_051713.pdf</attrdefs></attr><attr><attrlabl>QAQC_CODE</attrlabl><attrdef>Results of a test for data quality</attrdef></attr><attr><attrlabl>WETLAND_TYPE</attrlabl><attrdef>General description of the wetland classification.</attrdef><attrdefs>http://www.fws.gov/wetlands/Data/MapperTips.html</attrdefs></attr><attr><attrlabl>ATTRIBUTE</attrlabl><attrdef>Alphanumeric code identifying the wetland classification of the polygon</attrdef><attrdefs>http://www.fws.gov/wetlands/Data/wetlandcodes.html</attrdefs></attr><attr><attrlabl>DECODE</attrlabl></attr><attr><attrlabl>SPCC</attrlabl><attrdef>Simplified Plant Community Classification</attrdef><attrdefs>ftp://ftp.dnr.state.mn.us/pub/eco/nwi/MappingGuidance/NWI_ecmn_Technical_Documentation_051713.pdf</attrdefs><attrdomv><edom><edomv>Seasonally Flooded Basin</edomv></edom></attrdomv><attrdomv><edom><edomv>Wet Meadow</edomv></edom></attrdomv><attrdomv><edom><edomv>Shallow Marsh</edomv></edom></attrdomv><attrdomv><edom><edomv>Deep Marsh</edomv></edom></attrdomv><attrdomv><edom><edomv>Shallow Open Water Community</edomv></edom></attrdomv><attrdomv><edom><edomv>Peatland</edomv></edom></attrdomv><attrdomv><edom><edomv>Shrub Wetland</edomv></edom></attrdomv><attrdomv><edom><edomv>Hardwood Wetland</edomv></edom></attrdomv><attrdomv><edom><edomv>Coniferous Swamp</edomv></edom></attrdomv><attrdomv><edom><edomv>Non-Vegetated Aquatic Community</edomv></edom></attrdomv></attr><attr><attrlabl>Landscape</attrlabl><attrdef>HGM Landscape Attribute</attrdef><attrdefs>ftp://ftp.dnr.state.mn.us/pub/eco/nwi/MappingGuidance/NWI_ecmn_Technical_Documentation_051713.pdf</attrdefs><attrdomv><edom><edomv>Lentic</edomv><edomvd>Associated with a lake</edomvd></edom></attrdomv><attrdomv><edom><edomv>Lotic River</edomv><edomvd>Associated with a wide river</edomvd></edom></attrdomv><attrdomv><edom><edomv>Lotic Stream</edomv><edomvd>Associated with a narrow stream</edomvd></edom></attrdomv><attrdomv><edom><edomv>Terrene</edomv><edomvd>Not associated with a lake, river, or stream</edomvd></edom></attrdomv></attr><attr><attrlabl>Landform</attrlabl><attrdef>HGM Landform Attribute</attrdef><attrdefs>ftp://ftp.dnr.state.mn.us/pub/eco/nwi/MappingGuidance/NWI_ecmn_Technical_Documentation_051713.pdf</attrdefs><attrdomv><edom><edomv>Slope</edomv><edomvd>Occurs on land with slope &gt;2%</edomvd></edom></attrdomv><attrdomv><edom><edomv>Island</edomv><edomvd>Completely surrounded by open water</edomvd></edom></attrdomv><attrdomv><edom><edomv>Fringe</edomv><edomvd>Adjacent to, and frequently inundated by open water</edomvd></edom></attrdomv><attrdomv><edom><edomv>Floodplain</edomv><edomvd>Periodically inundated by high water from adjacent open water feature</edomvd></edom></attrdomv><attrdomv><edom><edomv>Basin</edomv><edomvd>Occurs in a distinct topographic depression</edomvd></edom></attrdomv><attrdomv><edom><edomv>Flat</edomv><edomvd>Occurs on nearly level land</edomvd></edom></attrdomv></attr><attr><attrlabl>WaterFlow</attrlabl><attrdef>HGM Water flow path attribute</attrdef><attrdefs>ftp://ftp.dnr.state.mn.us/pub/eco/nwi/MappingGuidance/NWI_ecmn_Technical_Documentation_051713.pdf</attrdefs><attrdomv><edom><edomv>Inflow</edomv><edomvd>Water flows in from an identifiable surface channel</edomvd></edom></attrdomv><attrdomv><edom><edomv>Outflow</edomv><edomvd>Water flows out from an identifiable surface channel</edomvd></edom></attrdomv><attrdomv><edom><edomv>Throughflow</edomv><edomvd>Water flows both in and out through identifiable surface channels</edomvd></edom></attrdomv><attrdomv><edom><edomv>Bidirectional-Nontidal</edomv><edomvd>Water flows back and forth from an adjacent open water feature depending upon water levels</edomvd></edom></attrdomv><attrdomv><edom><edomv>Isolated</edomv><edomvd>Wetland has no identifiable surface connections</edomvd></edom></attrdomv></attr><attr><attrlabl>HGM_NAME</attrlabl><attrdef>Full HGM name</attrdef><attrdefs>ftp://ftp.dnr.state.mn.us/pub/eco/nwi/MappingGuidance/NWI_ecmn_Technical_Documentation_051713.pdf</attrdefs></attr><attr><attrlabl>Shape_Length</attrlabl><attrdef>Length of feature in internal units.</attrdef><attrdefs>ESRI</attrdefs><attrdomv><udom>Positive real numbers that are automatically generated.</udom></attrdomv></attr><attr><attrlabl>Shape_Area</attrlabl><attrdef>Area of feature in internal units squared.</attrdef><attrdefs>ESRI</attrdefs><attrdomv><udom>Positive real numbers that are automatically generated.</udom></attrdomv></attr></detailed></eainfo><distinfo><resdesc>water_nat_wetlands_inv_2009_2014</resdesc><stdorder><digform><digtinfo><transize>0.000</transize></digtinfo></digform><ordering>Visit the web site noted in the online linkage section, or send an email to the Distribution Contact listed in this metadata record</ordering></stdorder><distliab>The Minnesota Department of Natural Resources General Geographic Data License Agreement is online: http://www.dnr.state.mn.us/sitetools/data_software_license.html</distliab><distrib><cntinfo><cntperp><cntorg>Minnesota Department of Natural Resources</cntorg><cntper>Steve Kloiber</cntper></cntperp><cntpos>Wetland Monitoring Coordinator</cntpos><cntaddr><address>500 Lafayette Road</address><city>St. Paul</city><state>MN</state><postal>55155</postal></cntaddr><cntvoice>651-259-5164</cntvoice><cntemail>steve.kloiber@state.mn.us</cntemail></cntinfo></distrib></distinfo><metainfo><metd>20140818</metd><metstdn>Minnesota Geographic Metadata Guidelines</metstdn><metstdv>1.2</metstdv><mettc>local time</mettc><metextns><onlink>http://www.mngeo.state.mn.us/committee/standards/mgmg/metadata.htm</onlink></metextns><metc><cntinfo><cntperp><cntorg>Minnesota Department of Natural Resources</cntorg><cntper>Steve Kloiber</cntper></cntperp><cntpos>Wetland Monitoring Coordinator</cntpos><cntaddr><address>500 Lafayette Road</address><city>St. Paul</city><state>MN</state><postal>55155</postal></cntaddr><cntvoice>651-259-5164</cntvoice><cntemail>steve.kloiber@state.mn.us</cntemail></cntinfo></metc></metainfo><mdLang><languageCode value="eng"></languageCode></mdLang><mdHrLv><ScopeCd value="005"></ScopeCd></mdHrLv><mdContact><rpIndName>Steve Kloiber</rpIndName><rpOrgName>Minnesota DNR</rpOrgName><rpPosName>Wetland Monitoring Coordinator</rpPosName><rpCntInfo><cntPhone><voiceNum tddtty="">651-259-5164</voiceNum></cntPhone><cntAddress addressType=""><eMailAdd>steve.kloiber@state.mn.us</eMailAdd></cntAddress></rpCntInfo><role><RoleCd value="007"></RoleCd></role></mdContact><mdDateSt>20130326</mdDateSt><mdStanName>Minnesota Geographic Metadata</mdStanName><mdStanVer>1.0</mdStanVer><distInfo><distributor><distorCont><rpIndName>Steve Kloiber</rpIndName><rpOrgName>MN DNR</rpOrgName><rpPosName>Wetland Monitoring Coordinator</rpPosName><rpCntInfo><cntPhone><voiceNum>651-259-5164</voiceNum></cntPhone><cntAddress><eMailAdd>steve.kloiber@state.mn.us</eMailAdd></cntAddress></rpCntInfo><role><RoleCd value="005"></RoleCd></role></distorCont><distorTran><onLineSrc><orDesc>002</orDesc><linkage></linkage><protocol>Local Area Network</protocol></onLineSrc></distorTran><distorFormat><formatName>File Geodatabase Feature Class</formatName></distorFormat></distributor><distTranOps><onLineSrc><linkage>none</linkage></onLineSrc></distTranOps></distInfo><mdChar><CharSetCd value="004"></CharSetCd></mdChar><mdMaint><maintFreq><MaintFreqCd value="011"></MaintFreqCd></maintFreq></mdMaint><mdHrLvName>dataset</mdHrLvName><refSysInfo><RefSystem><refSysID><identCode>NAD_1983_UTM_Zone_15N</identCode></refSysID></RefSystem></refSysInfo></metadata>