<?xml version="1.0"?><metadata><idinfo><citation><citeinfo><title>Transitways: 2040 Increased Revenue Scenario </title><origin>Metropolitan Transportation Services - Metropolitan Council</origin><pubinfo><publish>Metropolitan Council</publish></pubinfo><pubdate>20160127</pubdate><onlink>ftp://ftp.gisdata.mn.gov/pub/gdrs/data/pub/us_mn_state_metc/trans_transitway_inc_rev_sch2040/metadata/preview.jpg</onlink></citeinfo></citation><descript><abstract>The Increased Revenue Scenario Transitways data set was developed as part of the 2040 Transportation Policy Plan, published in Jan 2015. (see http://metrocouncil.org/tpp-update)

This data can be seen on maps in the plan – Figure 8 and Figure 6-9 

More info about how this data were developed can be found in Chapter 6: Transit Investment Direction and Plan. (http://metrocouncil.org/Transportation/Planning-2/Key-Transportation-Planning-Documents/Transportation-Policy-Plan-(1)/The-Adopted-2040-TPP-(1)/Final-2040-Transportation-Policy-Plan/2040-TPP-Chapter-6-Transit-Investment-Direction-an.aspx)

This data are for planning purposes and should be used at a regional level. Actual corridor alignment is still being developed. Data subject to any amendments of the TPP. 

Please use the layer file provided to symbolize this data. 

The data determinations were made on a subjective basis by managers at Metropolitan Transportation Services and Metro Transit. 

</abstract><purpose>Overview of the Increased Revenue Scenario Transitways 2040</purpose><supplinf>Twin Cities 7 County Area (Anoka, Carver, Dakota, Hennepin, Ramsey, Scott and Washington) and the urbanized portions of urbanized portions of Wright and Sherburne Counties</supplinf></descript><timeperd><timeinfo><sngdate><caldate>20160127</caldate></sngdate></timeinfo></timeperd><status><progress>Complete</progress><update>As needed</update></status><spdom><bounding><westbc>-94.012</westbc><eastbc>-92.732</eastbc><northbc>45.415</northbc><southbc>44.471</southbc></bounding></spdom><keywords><place><placekey>Twin Cities, Anoka County, Carver County, Dakota County, Hennepin County, Ramsey County, Scott County, Washington County</placekey></place><theme><themekey>Transit, transportation, transitways, transit planning, transportation policy plan, BRT, LRT, Commuter Rail, Express Bus Corridors, Arterial Street Corridors, TPP</themekey><themekt>None</themekt></theme></keywords><accconst>None</accconst><useconst>None</useconst><browse><browsed>Sample Map showing the transitways </browsed></browse><native>ArcView 9x</native><ptcontac><cntinfo><cntperp><cntorg>Metropolitan Council</cntorg><cntper>Rachel Wiken</cntper></cntperp><cntpos>GIS Specialist</cntpos><cntaddr><addrtype>mailing and physical</addrtype><address>390 Robert Street North</address><city>St. Paul</city><state>MN</state><postal>55101-1805</postal></cntaddr><cntvoice>651.602.1572</cntvoice><cntemail>rachel.wiken@metc.state.mn.us</cntemail></cntinfo></ptcontac></idinfo><dataqual><attracc><attraccr>This is regional planning level data and is not intended to be used for anything but regional planning.  Some alignments may have been shifted for cartographic display purposes.</attraccr></attracc><logic>The dataset is topologically 'clean'.</logic><complete>Entire seven county geographic area is covered.</complete><posacc><horizpa><horizpar>Unknown - This is regional planning level data and is not intended for site specific purposes.</horizpar></horizpa></posacc><lineage><procstep><procdesc>This data was digitized at approximately 1:100,000 scale using TLG streets, regional highways, and Minnesota railroads as "snap-to" base files. It is to be used at a regional scale for planning purposes only and is not intended for site specific uses. The data determinations were made on a subjective basis by managers at Metropolitan Transportation Services and Metro Transit.</procdesc></procstep><srcinfo><srcscale></srcscale></srcinfo></lineage></dataqual><spdoinfo><indspref>None</indspref><direct>Vector</direct><mgmg3obj>line shapes</mgmg3obj><mgmg3til>One layer for entire seven county region.</mgmg3til></spdoinfo><eainfo><overview><eaover>Name: Common name used for corridor 

Transitway: 
        Red, Green, Blue, Gold, Orange - The official METRO color for lines with assigned color
       ABRT - Arterial BRT Corridors. When built, these lines will be assigned letter designations. 
       TW Under Study - Accelerated Transitways under study, mode and alignment not yet specified. </eaover></overview></eainfo><distinfo><distliab>NOTICE:  The Geographic Information System (GIS) Data to which this notice is attached are made available pursuant to the Minnesota Government Data Practices Act (Minnesota Statutes Chapter 13).  THE GIS DATA ARE PROVIDED TO YOU AS IS AND WITHOUT ANY WARRANTY AS TO THEIR PERFORMANCE, MERCHANTABILITY, OR FITNESS FOR ANY PARTICULAR PURPOSE.  The GIS Data were developed by the Metropolitan Council for its own internal business purposes.  The Metropolitan Council does not represent or warrant that the GIS Data or the data documentation are error-free, complete, current, or accurate.  You are responsible for any consequences resulting from your use of the GIS Data or your reliance on the GIS Data.  You should consult the data documentation for this particular GIS Data to determine the limitations of the GIS Data and the precision with which the GIS Data may depict distance, direction, location, or other geographic features.  If you transmit or provide the GIS Data (or any portion of it) to another user, it is recommended that the GIS Data include a copy of this disclaimer and this metadata.</distliab><stdorder><digform><digtinfo><formname>ArcView Shape file</formname><formvern>ArcView: 9x</formvern><transize>0.1 MB for Zip file.</transize></digtinfo></digform><ordering>See Online Linkage Below</ordering></stdorder><distrib><cntinfo><cntperp><cntorg>Metropolitan Council</cntorg><cntper>Jon Hoekenga</cntper></cntperp><cntpos>GIS System Administrator</cntpos><cntaddr><addrtype>mailing and physical</addrtype><address>390 Robert Street North</address><city>St. Paul</city><state>MN</state><postal>55101-1805</postal></cntaddr><cntvoice>651.602.1561</cntvoice><cntemail>jonathan.hoekenga@metc.state.mn.us</cntemail></cntinfo></distrib></distinfo><metainfo><metd>20160127</metd><metstdn>Minnesota Geographic Metadata Guidelines</metstdn><metstdv>1.2</metstdv><metextns><onlink>http://www.mngeo.state.mn.us/committee/standards/mgmg/metadata.htm</onlink></metextns><metc><cntinfo><cntperp><cntorg>Metropolitan Council</cntorg><cntper>Rachel Wiken</cntper></cntperp><cntpos>GIS Specialist</cntpos><cntaddr><addrtype>mailing and physical</addrtype><address>390 Robert Street North</address><city>St. Paul</city><state>MN</state><postal>55101-1805</postal></cntaddr><cntvoice>651.602.1572</cntvoice><cntemail>rachel.wiken@metc.state.mn.us</cntemail></cntinfo></metc></metainfo><Esri><ModDate>20110721</ModDate><ModTime>16044100</ModTime><CreaDate>20130717</CreaDate><CreaTime>14085700</CreaTime><SyncOnce>TRUE</SyncOnce><DataProperties><itemProps><itemLocation><linkage Sync="TRUE">file://\\rafs2a.mc.local\Wikenrl\2030 transit\data\Transitways2030</linkage><protocol Sync="TRUE">Local Area Network</protocol></itemLocation></itemProps><copyHistory><copy source="L:\Metadata\Layers\Transitways2030" dest="\\rafs2a.mc.local\Wikenrl\2030 transit\data\Transitways2030" date="20130717" time="14085700"></copy></copyHistory></DataProperties></Esri><mdDateSt Sync="TRUE">20110721</mdDateSt><spref><horizsys><planar><gridsys><gridsysn>Universal Transverse Mercator</gridsysn><utm><utmzone>15</utmzone></utm></gridsys><planci><plandu>meters</plandu></planci></planar><geodetic><horizdn>NAD83</horizdn><ellips>GRS80</ellips></geodetic></horizsys></spref></metadata>