<metadata>
  <idinfo>
    <citation>
      <citeinfo>
        <pubdate>1980-06-01 00:00:00.0</pubdate>
        <title>Soils and Land Surfaces of Minnesota (Cummins and Grigal)</title>
        <mgmg1cid/>
        <pubinfo>
          <publish>University of Minnesota - Department of Soil, Water and Climate</publish>
        </pubinfo>
        <onlink>ftp://gdrs.dnr.state.mn.us/gdrs/data/pub/edu_umn_swac/geos_soils_cummins_grigal.zip</onlink>
      </citeinfo>
    </citation>
    <descript>
      <abstract>Soils lay in a complex mosaic across Minnesota. This mosaic is not random, but is the result of the blending of the effects of five major environmental elements. The five elements that lead to the pattern of soils that we observe are the geologic material from which the soils originally formed (the parent material); the climate in the area in which the material is found; properties of the landscape upon which that material lay, such as its slope and aspect (relief); the plans and animals (organisms) that can potentially live on or in the material; and the length of time during which the previous four elements have interacted.

This generalized view of the Minnesota landscape results in this data set. The polygons were delineated based on the above five characteristics and originally produced on a map commonly referred to as the Cummings/Grigal Soils Map.</abstract>
      <supplinf>Statewide</supplinf>
    </descript>
    <spdom>
      <bounding>
        <westbc>-96.832790</westbc>
        <eastbc>-89.393121</eastbc>
        <northbc>49.346077</northbc>
        <southbc>43.433784</southbc>
      </bounding>
    </spdom>
    <keywords>
      <theme>
        <themekey>geoscientificInformation</themekey>
      </theme>
      <place>
        <placekey>Minnesota</placekey>
      </place>
    </keywords>
    <browse>
      <browsen>http://jmaps.dnr.state.mn.us/gis/dp_datasample.jsp?mpid=28000001&amp;ptid=2&amp;fcid=1&amp;lname=Soils and Land Surfaces of Minnesota (Cummins and Grigal)</browsen>
      <browsed/>
    </browse>
    <native/>
    <ptcontac>
      <cntinfo>
        <cntperp>
          <cntorg>DNR-MIS</cntorg>
          <cntper>Tim Loesch</cntper>
        </cntperp>
        <cntpos>GIS Manager</cntpos>
        <cntaddr>
          <addrtype>Mailing and Physical</addrtype>
          <address>500 Lafayette Road, Box 11</address>
          <city>St. Paul</city>
          <state>MN</state>
          <postal>55155-4011</postal>
        </cntaddr>
        <cntvoice> 651-259-5475</cntvoice>
        <cntfax>(651) 297-4946</cntfax>
        <cntemail>tim.loesch@state.mn.us</cntemail>
      </cntinfo>
    </ptcontac>
  </idinfo>
  <spdoinfo>
    <indspref/>
    <direct>vector</direct>
    <mgmg3obj>polygon</mgmg3obj>
    <mgmg3til>state</mgmg3til>
  </spdoinfo>
  <spref>
    <vertdef>
      <altsys>
        <altdatum>Not Applicable</altdatum>
        <altunits>Not Applicable</altunits>
      </altsys>
      <depthsys>
        <depthdn>Not Applicable</depthdn>
        <depthdu>Not Applicable</depthdu>
      </depthsys>
    </vertdef>
    <horizsys>
      <planar>
        <gridsys>
          <gridsysn>Universal Transverse Mercator</gridsysn>
          <utm>
            <utmzone>15</utmzone>
          </utm>
        </gridsys>
        <planci>
          <plandu>meters</plandu>
        </planci>
      </planar>
      <geodetic>
        <horizdn>NAD83</horizdn>
        <ellips>GRS80</ellips>
      </geodetic>
    </horizsys>
  </spref>
  <eainfo>
    <detailed>
      <enttyp>
        <enttypl>soil_cumgrpy1.dbf</enttypl>
        <enttypd>Soils lay in a complex mosaic across Minnesota. This mosaic is not random, but is the result of the blending of the effects of five major environmental elements. The five elements that lead to the pattern of soils that we observe are the geologic material from which the soils originally formed (the parent material); the climate in the area in which the material is found; properties of the landscape upon which that material lay, such as its slope and aspect (relief); the plans and animals (organisms) that can potentially live on or in the material; and the length of time during which the previous four elements have interacted. This generalized view of the Minnesota landscape results in this data set. The polygons were delineated based on the above five characteristics and originally produced on a map commonly referred to as the Cummings/Grigal Soils Map.</enttypd>
      </enttyp>
      <attr>
        <attrlabl>GEISSOIL_C</attrlabl>
        <attrdef>The GEISSOIL_C is the same value number as the suborder number.</attrdef>
      </attr>
      <attr>
        <attrlabl>GEISSOIL_K</attrlabl>
        <attrdef>The titles for each legend soil type. The value shown in the most dominate within the group and therefore is the only on displayed.</attrdef>
      </attr>
      <attr>
        <attrlabl>SUBORDER</attrlabl>
        <attrdef>is the same as the GEISSOIL_C number value and also corresponds to the GEISSOIL_K title.</attrdef>
      </attr>
      <attr>
        <attrlabl>GG1</attrlabl>
        <attrdef>Great Group 1 soil great groups that dominate in a unit are identified in the legend. Soils at the great group level are separated into broad climatic zones; which in turn are more narrowly divided, often based on moisture conditions;
and then subdivided based on the kinds and sequences of soil horizons. Great Group 1 corresponds with Text_1, MAT1, SS1, and DESC.</attrdef>
      </attr>
      <attr>
        <attrlabl>GG2</attrlabl>
        <attrdef>Great Group 2 soil great groups that dominate in a unit are identified in the legend. Soils at the great group level are separated into broad climatic zones; which in turn are more narrowly divided, often based on moisture conditions;
and then subdivided based on the kinds and sequences of soil horizons. Great Group 2 corresponds with Text_2, MAT2, SS2, and DESC.</attrdef>
      </attr>
      <attr>
        <attrlabl>GG3</attrlabl>
        <attrdef>Great Group 3 soil great groups that dominate in a unit are identified in the legend. Soils at the great group level are separated into broad climatic zones; which in turn are more narrowly divided, often based on moisture conditions;
and then subdivided based on the kinds and sequences of soil horizons. Great Group 3 corresponds with Text_3, MAT3, SS3, and DESC.</attrdef>
      </attr>
      <attr>
        <attrlabl>GG4</attrlabl>
        <attrdef>Great Group 4 soil great groups that dominate in a unit are identified in the legend. Soils at the great group level are separated into broad climatic zones; which in turn are more narrowly divided, often based on moisture conditions;
and then subdivided based on the kinds and sequences of soil horizons. Great Group 4 corresponds with Text_4, MAT4, SS4, and DESC.</attrdef>
      </attr>
      <attr>
        <attrlabl>TEXT_1</attrlabl>
        <attrdef>Texture column provides information about soil textures within a delineation The sequence of soil textures in approximate order of increasing fineness or clay are: sandy, coarse-loamy, fine-loamy, coarse-silty, fine-silty, fine (clayey), and very- fine (also clayey). In some mineral soils, materials of two widely different textures occur, usually as a result of geologic deposition. In those cases, the textural family name is also stratified, such as sandy over loamy
(sandy/loamy).</attrdef>
      </attr>
      <attr>
        <attrlabl>TEXT_2</attrlabl>
        <attrdef>Texture column provides information about soil textures within a delineation The sequence of soil textures in approximate order of increasing fineness or clay are: sandy, coarse-loamy, fine-loamy, coarse-silty, fine-silty, fine (clayey), and very- fine (also clayey). In some mineral soils, materials of two widely different textures occur, usually as a result of geologic deposition. In those cases, the textural family name is also stratified, such as sandy over loamy
(sandy/loamy).</attrdef>
      </attr>
      <attr>
        <attrlabl>TEXT_3</attrlabl>
        <attrdef>Texture column provides information about soil textures within a delineation The sequence of soil textures in approximate order of increasing fineness or clay are: sandy, coarse-loamy, fine-loamy, coarse-silty, fine-silty, fine (clayey), and very- fine (also clayey). In some mineral soils, materials of two widely different textures occur, usually as a result of geologic deposition. In those cases, the textural family name is also stratified, such as sandy over loamy
(sandy/loamy).</attrdef>
      </attr>
      <attr>
        <attrlabl>TEXT_4</attrlabl>
        <attrdef>Texture column provides information about soil textures within a delineation The sequence of soil textures in approximate order of increasing fineness or clay are: sandy, coarse-loamy, fine-loamy, coarse-silty, fine-silty, fine (clayey), and very- fine (also clayey). In some mineral soils, materials of two widely different textures occur, usually as a result of geologic deposition. In those cases, the textural family name is also stratified, such as sandy over loamy
(sandy/loamy).</attrdef>
      </attr>
      <attr>
        <attrlabl>MAT1</attrlabl>
        <attrdef>The parent material is that from which the soil has formed. It varies both in texture and in color as it relates to
the glacial lobe from which it originated, and the mode of deposition. Deposition by the ice itself, by standing water,
or by running water all produced differing kinds of parent material.</attrdef>
      </attr>
      <attr>
        <attrlabl>MAT2</attrlabl>
        <attrdef>The parent material is that from which the soil has formed. It varies both in texture and in color as it relates to
the glacial lobe from which it originated, and the mode of deposition. Deposition by the ice itself, by standing water,
or by running water all produced differing kinds of parent material.</attrdef>
      </attr>
      <attr>
        <attrlabl>MAT3</attrlabl>
        <attrdef>The parent material is that from which the soil has formed. It varies both in texture and in color as it relates to
the glacial lobe from which it originated, and the mode of deposition. Deposition by the ice itself, by standing water,
or by running water all produced differing kinds of parent material.</attrdef>
      </attr>
      <attr>
        <attrlabl>SS1</attrlabl>
        <attrdef>Soil series are the lowest level in the classification system. The range of properties within any given soil series is rather small, and quite specific statements can be made about uses of such soils.</attrdef>
      </attr>
      <attr>
        <attrlabl>SS2</attrlabl>
        <attrdef>Soil series are the lowest level in the classification system. The range of properties within any given soil series is rather small, and quite specific statements can be made about uses of such soils.</attrdef>
      </attr>
      <attr>
        <attrlabl>SS3</attrlabl>
        <attrdef>Soil series are the lowest level in the classification system. The range of properties within any given soil series is rather small, and quite specific statements can be made about uses of such soils.</attrdef>
      </attr>
      <attr>
        <attrlabl>SS4</attrlabl>
        <attrdef>Soil series are the lowest level in the classification system. The range of properties within any given soil series is rather small, and quite specific statements can be made about uses of such soils.</attrdef>
      </attr>
      <attr>
        <attrlabl>DESC</attrlabl>
        <attrdef>is a combination of all the different landscape types found in each of the columns associated with that row and is read from left to right.</attrdef>
      </attr>
    </detailed>
  </eainfo>
  <distinfo>
    <resdesc>soils_and_land_surfaces_mn_cummins_grigal</resdesc>
    <distliab>The Minnesota Department of Natural Resources makes no representation or warranties, express or implied, with respect to the reuse of data provided herewith, regardless of its format or the means of its transmission. There is no guarantee or representation to the user as to the accuracy, currency, suitability, or reliability of this data for any purpose. The user accepts the data 'as is', and assumes all risks associated with its use. By accepting this data, the user agrees not to transmit this data or provide access to it or any part of it to another party unless the user shall include with the data a copy of this disclaimer. The Minnesota Department of Natural Resources assumes no responsibility for actual or consequential damage incurred as a result of any user's reliance on this data.</distliab>
    <stdorder>
      <digform>
        <digtinfo>
          <formname>Shapefile</formname>
          <formvern>Not Applicable</formvern>
          <transize/>
        </digtinfo>
      </digform>
      <ordering>See Online Linkage or Distribution Contact</ordering>
    </stdorder>
    <distrib>
      <cntinfo>
        <cntperp>
          <cntorg>DNR-MIS</cntorg>
          <cntper>Hal Watson</cntper>
        </cntperp>
        <cntpos>GIS Database Coordinator</cntpos>
        <cntaddr>
          <addrtype>Mailing and Physical</addrtype>
          <address>500 Lafayette Road, Box 11</address>
          <city>St. Paul</city>
          <state>MN</state>
          <postal>55155-4011</postal>
        </cntaddr>
        <cntvoice>(651) 259-5508</cntvoice>
        <cntfax>(651) 297-4946</cntfax>
        <cntemail>hal.watson@state.mn.us</cntemail>
      </cntinfo>
    </distrib>
  </distinfo>
  <metainfo>
    <metd>2007-05-11 09:39:13.0</metd>
    <metstdn>Minnesota Geographic Metadata Guidelines</metstdn>
    <metstdv>1.2</metstdv>
    <metextns>
      <onlink>http://www.mngeo.state.mn.us/committee/standards/mgmg/metadata.htm</onlink>
    </metextns>
    <metc>
      <cntinfo>
        <cntperp>
          <cntorg>DNR-MIS</cntorg>
          <cntper>Tim Loesch</cntper>
        </cntperp>
        <cntpos>GIS Manager</cntpos>
        <cntaddr>
          <addrtype>Mailing and Physical</addrtype>
          <address>500 Lafayette Road, Box 11</address>
          <city>St. Paul</city>
          <state>MN</state>
          <postal>55155-4011</postal>
        </cntaddr>
        <cntvoice> 651-259-5475</cntvoice>
        <cntfax>(651) 297-4946</cntfax>
        <cntemail>tim.loesch@state.mn.us</cntemail>
      </cntinfo>
    </metc>
  </metainfo>
</metadata>
