<metadata>
  <idinfo>
    <citation>
      <citeinfo>
        <origin>Metropolitan Council</origin>
        <title>Travel Behavior Inventory (TBI) 2010 Household Interview Survey</title>
        <pubinfo>
          <publish>Metropolitan Council</publish>
        </pubinfo>
        <pubdate>20130430</pubdate>
        <onlink>https://gisdata.mn.gov/dataset/us-mn-state-metc-society-tbi-home-interview2010</onlink>
      </citeinfo>
    </citation>
    <spdom>
      <bounding>
        <westbc>-95.846</westbc>
        <eastbc>-91.533</eastbc>
        <northbc>46.776</northbc>
        <southbc>41.284</southbc>
      </bounding>
    </spdom>
    <useconst>None</useconst>
    <status>
      <progress>Complete</progress>
      <update>As needed</update>
    </status>
    <timeperd>
      <timeinfo>
        <sngdate>
          <caldate>November 2010 - March 2012</caldate>
        </sngdate>
      </timeinfo>
      <current>Time period of the survey</current>
    </timeperd>
    <descript>
      <abstract>Household travel survey conducted from fall 2010 to spring 2012 as part of the 2010 Travel Behavior Inventory (TBI).  

The TBI is a battery of surveys conducted 2010-2012 to support transportation planning and transportation forecast model development.

Dataset includes record surveyed in 2010, as well as some records from 2005 for routes that were not surveyed in 2010.  Four expansion factors were developed, all matching systemwide totals:
Allsys- All records, at route level
ODsys-All records with O/D information, at route level
ODTPsys- All records with O/D and purpose information, at route level
ODTP_Geosys- All records with O/D and purpose information, at segment level

Please refer to documentation for information about sample plan, survey instruments, field implementation, and data expansion.</abstract>
      <purpose>To assist the Twin Cities Metropolitan Planning Organization with transportation planning and project programming in the Twin Cities region.</purpose>
      <supplinf>Origins and Destinations of surveyed users in the 7 Country Metropolitan area and surrounding counties</supplinf>
    </descript>
    <keywords>
      <place>
        <placekey>Twin Cities, Anoka County, Carver County, Dakota County, Hennepin County, Ramsey County, Scott County, Washington County, Sherburne County, Wright County, Isanti County, Chisago County, Polk County, Pierce County, St. Croix County, Goodhue County, Rice County, Le Sueur County, McLeod County, Sibley County, Minnesota, Wisconsin, Minneapolis, St. Paul</placekey>
      </place>
      <theme>
        <themekey>Travel Behavior Inventory, TBI, transit, household interview survey, household ravel survey, home interview survey, HIS</themekey>
      </theme>
    </keywords>
    <accconst>None</accconst>
    <ptcontac>
      <cntinfo>
        <cntperp>
          <cntorg>Metropolitan Council</cntorg>
          <cntper>Jonathan Ehrlich</cntper>
        </cntperp>
        <cntpos>Senior Planner</cntpos>
        <cntaddr>
          <addrtype>mailing and physical</addrtype>
          <address>390 Robert Street North</address>
          <city>St. Paul</city>
          <state>MN</state>
          <postal>55101-1805</postal>
        </cntaddr>
        <cntvoice>651.602.1408</cntvoice>
        <cntemail>jonathan.ehrlich@metc.state.mn.us</cntemail>
      </cntinfo>
    </ptcontac>
  </idinfo>
  <distinfo>
    <distliab>NOTICE:  The Geographic Information System (GIS) Data to which this notice is attached are made available pursuant to the Minnesota Government Data Practices Act (Minnesota Statutes Chapter 13).  THE GIS DATA ARE PROVIDED TO YOU AS IS AND WITHOUT ANY WARRANTY AS TO THEIR PERFORMANCE, MERCHANTABILITY, OR FITNESS FOR ANY PARTICULAR PURPOSE.  The GIS Data were developed by the Metropolitan Council for its own internal business purposes.  The Metropolitan Council does not represent or warrant that the GIS Data or the data documentation are error-free, complete, current, or accurate.  You are responsible for any consequences resulting from your use of the GIS Data or your reliance on the GIS Data.  You should consult the data documentation for this particular GIS Data to determine the limitations of the GIS Data and the precision with which the GIS Data may depict distance, direction, location, or other geographic features.  If you transmit or provide the GIS Data (or any portion of it) to another user, it is recommended that the GIS Data include a copy of this disclaimer and this metadata.</distliab>
    <stdorder>
      <ordering>See Online Linkage Below</ordering>
    </stdorder>
    <distrib>
      <cntinfo>
        <cntperp>
          <cntorg>Metropolitan Council</cntorg>
          <cntper>Jonathan Ehrlich</cntper>
        </cntperp>
        <cntpos>Senior Planner</cntpos>
        <cntaddr>
          <addrtype>mailing and physical</addrtype>
          <address>390 Robert Street North</address>
          <city>St. Paul</city>
          <state>MN</state>
          <postal>55101-1805</postal>
        </cntaddr>
        <cntvoice>651.602.1408</cntvoice>
        <cntemail>jonathan.ehrlich@metc.state.mn.us</cntemail>
      </cntinfo>
    </distrib>
  </distinfo>
  <eainfo>
    <overview>
      <eaover>Data Dictionary is availability internally to the file</eaover>
    </overview>
  </eainfo>
  <dataqual>
    <posacc>
      <horizpa>
        <horizpar>TAZ
Thousandth of a degree
One hundred meters</horizpar>
      </horizpa>
      <vertacc>
        <vertaccr>TAZ
Thousandth of a degree
One hundred meters</vertaccr>
      </vertacc>
    </posacc>
    <lineage>
      <procstep>
        <procdesc>Data was entered by three modes: mailback, web, and phone interview.  The mode is indicated in the household table.</procdesc>
      </procstep>
    </lineage>
  </dataqual>
  <metainfo>
    <metd>20130430</metd>
    <metstdn>Minnesota Geographic Metadata Guidelines</metstdn>
    <metstdv>1.2</metstdv>
    <metextns>
      <onlink>http://www.mngeo.state.mn.us/committee/standards/mgmg/metadata.htm</onlink>
    </metextns>
    <metc>
      <cntinfo>
        <cntperp>
          <cntorg>Metropolitan Council</cntorg>
          <cntper>Jonathan Ehrlich</cntper>
        </cntperp>
        <cntpos>Senior Planner</cntpos>
        <cntaddr>
          <addrtype>mailing and physical</addrtype>
          <address>390 Robert Street North</address>
          <city>St. Paul</city>
          <state>MN</state>
          <postal>55101-1805</postal>
        </cntaddr>
        <cntvoice>651.602.1408</cntvoice>
        <cntemail>jonathan.ehrlich@metc.state.mn.us</cntemail>
      </cntinfo>
    </metc>
  </metainfo>
  <spref>
    <horizsys>
      <planar>
        <gridsys>
          <gridsysn>Universal Transverse Mercator</gridsysn>
          <utm>
            <utmzone>15</utmzone>
          </utm>
        </gridsys>
        <planci>
          <plandu>meters</plandu>
        </planci>
      </planar>
      <geodetic>
        <horizdn>NAD83</horizdn>
        <ellips>GRS80</ellips>
      </geodetic>
    </horizsys>
  </spref>
</metadata>
