<?xml version="1.0"?><!--  <!DOCTYPE metadata SYSTEM "metadata.dtd">  --><metadata><idinfo><citation><citeinfo><origin>Minnesota Geological Survey (MGS)</origin><pubdate>1995</pubdate><title>Geologic Atlas of Fillmore County, Minnesota (Part A)</title><mgmg1cid></mgmg1cid><pubinfo><publish>Minnesota Geological Survey</publish></pubinfo><onlink>http://conservancy.umn.edu/handle/11299/58513</onlink></citeinfo></citation><descript><abstract>A County Geologic Atlas is a systematic study of a county's geologic and ground water resources. Geologic studies include both near-surface deposits and bedrock. Ground water studies include flow systems, aquifer capacity, and ground water chemistry. In some areas sand and gravel deposits, sinkholes, or other features are studied. Interpretation of sensitivity to pollution is also part of an atlas. The information is organized, analyzed, and displayed using geographic information technology.

Most Geologic Atlas and Regional Hydrogeologic Assessment projects are done in two parts. The Minnesota Geological Survey covers basic geology and creates databases of information such as wells and soil borings in part A. The Minnesota Department of Natural Resources (DNR) handles hydrogeology and ground water sensitivity layers in Part B. Completion of a project's two parts is staggered: Part A is completed about two years before Part B, compiling information used to create part B. Parts A and B are published and distributed as two separate products.</abstract><purpose>County Geologic Atlas and Regional Hydrogeologic Assessment information is used in planning and environmental protection efforts at all levels of government. Wellhead protection and well-sealing programs are examples of local programs that need geologic and ground water information. The information is also used by businesses and the general public.</purpose><supplinf>Fillmore County, Minnesota</supplinf></descript><timeperd><timeinfo><sngdate><caldate>1995</caldate></sngdate></timeinfo><current>Geologic maps were compiled based on information available during the compilation period 1993-1995.</current></timeperd><status><progress>Complete</progress><update>None Planned</update></status><spdom><bounding><westbc>-92.45</westbc><eastbc>-91.72</eastbc><northbc>43.85</northbc><southbc>43.50</southbc></bounding></spdom><keywords><theme><themekt>ISO 19115 Topic Category</themekt><themekey>geoscientificInformation, Bedrock Geology, Surficial Geology, Bedrock Topography, Sinkhole Probability, Sinkholes,  Wells, Geologic Resources</themekey></theme><place><placekey>Minnesota, MN, Fillmore County</placekey></place></keywords><accconst>None</accconst><useconst>Credit given to the Minnesota Geological Survey and Fillmore County for use of data in map products.</useconst><native>Arc/INFO Unix environment</native><crossref><citeinfo><title>C-8, Part A. Geologic atlas of Fillmore County, Minnesota. J.H. Mossler, project manager. 1995. 5 plates. Scale  1:100,000. Plates: 1, Data-base map; 2, Bedrock geology; 3, Surficial geology; 4, Depth to bedrock and bedrock topography; 5, Geologic resources. $12.00. Digital files in unix format, no metadata.  Paper map and report available from MGS Map Sales Office (2609 Territorial Road, St. Paul, Minnesota, 55114, 612-626-2969.)

C-8, Part B. Geologic atlas of Fillmore County, Minnesota. J. Falteisek, Minnesota Dept. of Natural Resources, Division of  Waters, project supervisor. 1996. 4 pls. Scale 1:100,000. Plates: 6, Bedrock hydrogeology; 7, Sensitivity of the St. Peter-Prairie du Chien-Jordan aquifer to pollution; 8, Sinkholes and sinkhole probability; 9, Springsheds. $12.00. Note: Numbering continues from Part A. 

C-8, Part C. Text supplement to the Geologic Atlas of Fillmore County, Minnesota. R.S. Lively and N.H. Balaban, eds. 1995. 41 p. $2.00. 

For a listing of all geologic maps go to the Minnesota Geological Survey website at: http://www.mngs.umn.edu/mgsdocs.html

For a complete listing of MGS State Map Series Maps, Reports, and GIS Data, see http://conservancy.umn.edu/handle/11299/708

For other County Atlas and Regional Hydrogeologic Assessment data see: http://www.mngs.umn.edu/county_atlas/countyatlas.htm 

For a listing of the status of the DNR Ground Water Mapping Program (Part B), go to: http://www.dnr.state.mn.us/waters/groundwater_section/mapping/index.html</title></citeinfo></crossref><ptcontac><cntinfo><cntperp><cntorg>Minnesota Geological Survey</cntorg><cntper>General Information</cntper></cntperp><cntpos>Administrative Staff</cntpos><cntaddr><addrtype>Mailing and Physical</addrtype><address>2609 Territorial Road</address><city>St. Paul</city><state>MN</state><postal>55114</postal></cntaddr><cntvoice>612-626-2969</cntvoice><cntemail>mgs@umn.edu</cntemail></cntinfo></ptcontac></idinfo><dataqual><lineage><srcinfo><srcscale>100000</srcscale></srcinfo><procstep><procdesc>Investigations begin with a review of existing information, such as earlier geologic maps, soil maps, and hydrologic reports. Drillers send water well logs to the Minnesota Geological Survey, where they are reviewed, interpreted, and entered into the County Well Index (CWI), an interactive data base of water-well information. Building on the previous data, field studies are conducted to improve the understanding of local geologic and hydrologic conditions. Linework is created based upon the field studies and base data, and digitized. Background GIS data layers such as roads, surface hydrography, township grids, etc., are obtained from various sources.

The projection for the covers is:  UTM NAD27 with a y-shift of -4700000
This projection was commonly used by other agencies such as LMIC at the time of creation.

* Oct. 2001 update note *
The following covers were created in 1995.  They do not have all the current  attributes contained in recent MGS digital products.  Go to the  documents folder on the MGS ftp site and there is a master "look up table" that will give character descriptions of the MGSCODE attribute given in these covers. 3 of the most commonly used covers; bgpg, sgpg, and btpg have been updated  and contain an expanded attribute table in the .pat.  No metadata is currently available for this data.

** June 2003 update **
Most of the primary coverages have been re-projected to UTM zone 15, unshifted, NAD83.</procdesc></procstep></lineage><logic>Not available</logic><complete>Not available</complete><posacc><horizpa><horizpar>Not available</horizpar></horizpa></posacc><attracc><attraccr>Not available</attraccr></attracc></dataqual><spdoinfo><indspref></indspref><direct>Vector</direct><mgmg3obj>Point, Vector, Polygon</mgmg3obj><mgmg3til>Fillmore County</mgmg3til></spdoinfo><eainfo><overview><eaover>Index of coverages for Fillmore County Geologic Atlas

** Bedrock Geology plate **
 bgpg      =  polygon cover of bedrock geology,  scale 1:100,000
 bgpgk     =  polygon cover of Cretaceous unit 
 bgln      =  line cover of structure lines

** Bedrock Topography plate **
 btpg      =  polygon cover of bedrock topography
 dtln      =  line cover of depth to bedrock elevations (elev in feet)

** Surficial Geology **
 sgpg      =  polygon cover of surficial geology
 sgpge     =  polygon cover of eolian deposits
 sgan      =  annotation cover of surf. geol. units

**  Watershed plate **
 pmpgws    =  polygon cover of water shed areas (subsurface &amp; surface)
 pmpgbv    =  polygon cover of blind valleys (Calvin Alexander)
 dyln      =  line cover of dye trace paths
 dypt      =  point cover of springs, water wells, sink holes or stream sinks
              as beginning or end points of dye traces
 p1ptws    =  point cover containing numbers for water shed identification calls the hydro.aml which has the following covers:

 l1lngal   =  line cover of contact line for galena bedrock unit
 hylnmod   =  line cover of streams with identification as to type of 
              stream, i.e., surface, sinking, intermittent surface
 
** Sinkhole Probability plate **
pmpgsh    =  polygon cover of sink hole probability areas based on density
 p1ptsh    =  point cover of sinkhole locations

** Geological Resources plate **
 rspg      =  polygon cover of surficial and bedrock msp units
 rspt      =  point cover of quarries, gravel pits, geochemistry, Pb-Zn
              mineralization
 rspgm1    =  polygon cover of selected mineral property leases

** Database plate **
wwptcwi   =  water well coverage (including CWI index attributes)
 wwpt      =  water well point coverage (contains a few SB points)

** Base layers **
county    =  county boundary [TIGER]
 mcd       =  civil divisions [TIGER]
 hydro     =  rivers/lake boundaries [TIGER]
 lakes     =  lakes (polygons) [TIGER]
 bsanblk   =  base annotation - black
 llpt      =  lat/lon tics
 p1pt      =  road labels (uses ../rrv/rrvmark.mrk )
 r1lnmod   =  major roads (modified from TIGER)
 r1lnmod   =  minor roads (modified from TIGER)
 scbsblk   =  section lines (black)</eaover><eadetcit>No layer-level metadata is available for this dataset.</eadetcit></overview></eainfo><distinfo><stdorder><digform><digtinfo><formname>Arc/Info Export (uncompressed) in unix format.</formname><formvern></formvern><transize>8.4 MB as compressed tarfile (unix)</transize></digtinfo></digform><ordering>Data download is from the U of M Libraries Digital Conservancy. All GIS data and metadata for the Fillmore County Geologic Atlas is provided in the zip file C8 Part A Extras.zip. (Supplementary Files). GIS distribution format for most data in this dataset is Esri .e00 (arc interchange format). The direct Digital Conservancy link to PDF map products and GIS data projects (Supplementary Files) for this data set is: http://conservancy.umn.edu/handle/11299/58513

If you would prefer to have the digital data on DVD, or paper copies of the geologic plates, contact the MGS Map Sales office at 612-626-2969 and specify publication County Atlas Series C-08, part A, or County Geologic Atlas of Fillmore County.</ordering></stdorder><resdesc>c8  (http://conservancy.umn.edu/handle/11299/58513)</resdesc><distrib><cntinfo><cntperp><cntorg>Minnesota Geological Survey</cntorg><cntper>Timothy E. Wahl</cntper></cntperp><cntpos>Geologic Information Systems</cntpos><cntaddr><addrtype>mailing and physical</addrtype><address>2609 Territorial Road</address><city>St. Paul</city><state>MN</state><postal>55114</postal></cntaddr><cntvoice>612-626-0992</cntvoice><cntemail>tewahl@umn.edu</cntemail></cntinfo></distrib></distinfo><metainfo><metd>20150416</metd><metstdn>Minnesota Geographic Metadata Guidelines</metstdn><metstdv>1.2</metstdv><metextns><onlink>http://www.mngeo.state.mn.us/committee/standards/mgmg/metadata.htm</onlink></metextns><metc><cntinfo><cntperp><cntorg>Minnesota Geospatial Information Office (MnGeo)</cntorg><cntper>Nancy Rader</cntper></cntperp><cntpos>GIS Data Coordinator</cntpos><cntaddr><addrtype>mailing and physical</addrtype><address>658 Cedar Street</address><city>St. Paul</city><state>MN</state><postal>55155</postal></cntaddr><cntvoice>651-201-2489</cntvoice><cntemail>gisinfo.mngeo@state.mn.us</cntemail></cntinfo></metc></metainfo><spref><horizsys><planar><gridsys><gridsysn>Universal Transverse Mercator</gridsysn><utm><utmzone>15E</utmzone></utm></gridsys><planci><plandu>meters</plandu></planci></planar><geodetic><horizdn>NAD83</horizdn><ellips>GRS80</ellips></geodetic></horizsys></spref></metadata>