<metadata>
  <idinfo>
    <citation>
      <citeinfo>
        <origin>Minnesota Department of Natural Resources (MNDNR)</origin>
        <pubdate>19950601</pubdate>
        <title>Control Point Generated Public Land Survey (PLS)</title>
        <mgmg1cid/>
        <pubinfo>
          <publish>MNDNR - Division of  Lands and Minerals</publish>
        </pubinfo>
        <onlink>http://gisdata.mn.gov/dataset/plan-mndnr-public-land-survey</onlink>
      </citeinfo>
    </citation>
    <descript>
      <abstract>The Control Point Generated PLS layer contains line and polygon features to the 1/4 of 1/4 PLS section (approximately 40 acres) and government lot level.  The layer was created using the most accurate information available at the time, including Government Land Office plat drawings and survey notes, official resurveys, and PLS control points from MNDNR's Control Point Inventory database.

For the details about the creation of the PLS layer to the forty/government lot, refer to the documentation that comes with the downloaded data:
&lt;a href="pls40glotpyMetadata.pdf"&gt;pls40glotpyMetadata.pdf&lt;/a&gt; for the polygons, and
&lt;a href="pls40glotlnMetadata.pdf"&gt;pls40glotlnMetadata.pdf&lt;/a&gt; for the lines.</abstract>
      <purpose>Detailed PLS forty level mapping at a 1:24,000 scale of any information georeferenced to the Public Land Survey System, especially land ownership and management.  It can also be used as a general PLS reference map for any other data projected into UTM  - meters, extended zone 15, NAD83.</purpose>
      <supplinf>Minnesota</supplinf>
    </descript>
    <timeperd>
      <current>Time Period of Content date indicates the date which the user can be confident of accuracy and completeness of the dataset.  This data should be considered up-to-date. Data is derived from sources dating continuously from mid-nineteenth century survey notes to results from current modern surveys.</current>
      <timeinfo>
        <sngdate>
          <caldate>20130222</caldate>
        </sngdate>
      </timeinfo>
    </timeperd>
    <status>
      <progress>In work</progress>
      <update>Irregular</update>
    </status>
    <spdom>
      <bounding>
        <westbc>-96.832273</westbc>
        <eastbc>-89.394358</eastbc>
        <northbc>49.345099</northbc>
        <southbc>43.435410</southbc>
      </bounding>
    </spdom>
    <keywords>
      <theme>
        <themekey>planningCadastre, PLS, Public Land Survey, Townships, Sections, Forties, Government Lots</themekey>
        <themekt>ISO 19115 Category</themekt>
      </theme>
      <place>
        <placekey>Minnesota, MN</placekey>
      </place>
    </keywords>
    <accconst>None</accconst>
    <useconst>Use of the data are constrained only by the DNR GIS Data License Agreement. See the Distribution Liability section below for a link.</useconst>
    <native>ARC/INFO 7.0.3</native>
    <browse>
      <browsen>ftp://ftp.gisdata.mn.gov/pub/gdrs/data/pub/us_mn_state_dnr/plan_mndnr_public_land_survey/preview/preview.jpg</browsen>
    </browse>
    <ptcontac>
      <cntinfo>
        <cntperp>
          <cntorg>DNR-Lands and Minerals</cntorg>
          <cntper>Renee Johnson</cntper>
        </cntperp>
        <cntpos>ITS 3</cntpos>
        <cntaddr>
          <addrtype>Mailing and Physical</addrtype>
          <address>500 Lafayette Road - Box 45</address>
          <city>St. Paul</city>
          <state>MN</state>
          <postal>55155</postal>
        </cntaddr>
        <cntvoice>(651) 259-5396</cntvoice>
        <cntfax>(651) 296-5939</cntfax>
        <cntemail>renee.johnson@state.mn.us</cntemail>
      </cntinfo>
    </ptcontac>
  </idinfo>
  <dataqual>
    <logic>Polygons and lines are coincident, verified closed, and intersect where intended.</logic>
    <complete>All available Government Land Office Land Survey notes, plats and resurvey information was used in the creation of this data set.  Since the meander line data is being derived from the Government Land Office PLS survey notes, margins around meandered water bodies tend to have a coarse representation and may not accurately reflect the current shape of these features on the ground.  Meander lines are NOT land ownership boundaries.  The Public Land Survey process was conducted, in part, to inventory the rough acreage of land for the purposes of selling it for agriculture, timber, railroads, etc.  Meander lines were used to determine how many acres of land were available for sale at the time, whereas the beds of navigable water bodies are held in ownership by the state.  Depending upon when the survey was conducted, surveyors followed different guidelines for what was to be meandered.  'In subdividing any one township, you are to meander as hereinafter directed, any lake or lakes, pond or ponds, lying entirely within the boundaries thereof, of the area of [twenty five to] forty acres and upwards, and which cannot be drained and are not likely to fill up, or from any cause to become dry.'  (A Collection of Original Instructions to Surveyors of the Public Lands, 1815 - 1881, Roy Minnick, Landmark Enterprises)</complete>
    <posacc>
      <horizpa>
        <horizpar>Variable. At its least accurate, the data is based upon points derived from manual digitizing of PLS section corners from 1:24,000 scale paper media (GISMO and SECTIC-24K points).  At its most accurate, the data is based upon points collected using GPS units operating at a sub-meter level of accuracy.  Refer to the ACCURACY and METHOD fields in the related PLS Control Point layer (cornrpt3), for specific information.</horizpar>
      </horizpa>
      <vertacc>
        <vertaccr>Not Applicable
</vertaccr>
      </vertacc>
    </posacc>
    <lineage>
      <srcinfo>
        <srcscale>Source layer pls40ne3:  24000
</srcscale>
      </srcinfo>
      <procstep>
        <procdesc>For the details about the creation of the PLS layer to the forty/government lot, refer to &lt;a href="pls40glotpyMetadata.pdf"&gt;pls40glotpyMetadata.pdf&lt;/a&gt; for the polygons and &lt;a href="pls40glotlnMetadata.pdf"&gt;pls40glotlnMetadata.pdf&lt;/a&gt; for the lines. These documents can be found in the download for the data.

The following layers are included in this geodatabase:
pls_fortypy3 - statewide PLS layer to the forty/government lot (also referred to as quarter&#8208;quarter sections)
pls_fortyln3 - statewide PLS layer to the forty/government lot differentiating the type of line
pls_fortypt3 - statewide PLS layer to the forty/government lot - the centroid of each polygon
pls4own_fortypy3 - statewide PLS layer to the forty/government lot, modified to better match the MNDNR Land Records
for mapping purposes
pls4own_fortyln3 - statewide PLS layer to the forty/government lot differentiating the type of line
pls4own_fortypt3 - statewide PLS layer to the forty/government lot - the centroid of each polygon
pls_sectpy3 - statewide PLS layer of PLS sections, created by dissolving the Pls4own_fortypy3 layer on the COUN,
TOWN, RDIR, RANG, SECT fields
pls_sectpt3 - statewide PLS layer of PLS sections - the centroid of each polygon
pls_twpspy3 - statewide PLS layer of PLS townships, created by dissolving the Pls4own_fortypy3 layer on the COUN,
TOWN, RDIR, RANG fields
pls_twpspt3 - statewide PLS layer of PLS townships - the centroid of each polygon
twprng - statewide PLS layer of PLS townships, created by dissolving the pls4own_fortypy3 layer on TOWN, RDIR, RANG
fields
twplabpts - layer of points to label the townships and ranges around the outer edge of the state and through the middle
of the state where the 4th and 5th Principal Meridians come together
twplabptsAnno - annotation layer of the twplabpts layer</procdesc>
      </procstep>
    </lineage>
  </dataqual>
  <spdoinfo>
    <indspref>Not Applicable</indspref>
    <direct>vector</direct>
    <mgmg3obj>line</mgmg3obj>
    <mgmg3til>county</mgmg3til>
  </spdoinfo>
  <spref>
    <vertdef>
      <altsys>
        <altdatum>Not Applicable</altdatum>
        <altunits>Not Applicable</altunits>
      </altsys>
      <depthsys>
        <depthdn>Not Applicable</depthdn>
        <depthdu>Not Applicable</depthdu>
      </depthsys>
    </vertdef>
    <horizsys>
      <planar>
        <gridsys>
          <gridsysn>Universal Transverse Mercator</gridsysn>
          <utm>
            <utmzone>15</utmzone>
          </utm>
        </gridsys>
        <planci>
          <plandu>meters</plandu>
        </planci>
      </planar>
      <geodetic>
        <horizdn>NAD83</horizdn>
        <ellips>GRS80</ellips>
      </geodetic>
    </horizsys>
  </spref>
  <eainfo>
    <detailed>
      <enttyp>
        <enttypl>PLS_FORTYLN3</enttypl>
        <enttypd>Feature Class Attribute Table</enttypd>
      </enttyp>
      <attr>
        <attrlabl>PLSLINETYP</attrlabl>
        <attrdef>This field contains the corresponding text for the numeric values in the PLSLINE field.  See the 'Description' column of the PLSLINE field</attrdef>
      </attr>
      <attr>
        <attrlabl>ANGLE</attrlabl>
        <attrdef>The direction of the line in degrees from true north.  This field is not consistently populated, since in some instances it has been necessary to restructure the data during  processing in such a manner that this information is eliminated.  The field itself is retained since it is mandatory for use within the ARC/INFO COGO package</attrdef>
      </attr>
      <attr>
        <attrlabl>FLAG</attrlabl>
        <attrdef>A flagging field used in edgematching township to township and county to county</attrdef>
      </attr>
      <attr>
        <attrlabl>PLSLINE</attrlabl>
        <attrdef>The type of boundary that the line feature represents. The PLSLINETYP field contains the corresponding text for the numeric values in the PLSLINE field, as seen in the description column below</attrdef>
        <attrdomv>
          <edom>
            <edomv>0</edomv>
            <edomvd>Neatline</edomvd>
          </edom>
        </attrdomv>
        <attrdomv>
          <edom>
            <edomv>01</edomv>
            <edomvd>State line that is also a township or range line (all PLS state lines are county and forty/governmen</edomvd>
          </edom>
        </attrdomv>
        <attrdomv>
          <edom>
            <edomv>02</edomv>
            <edomvd>State line that is not a township line but is a section line</edomvd>
          </edom>
        </attrdomv>
        <attrdomv>
          <edom>
            <edomv>03</edomv>
            <edomvd>State line that is a PLS line but is neither a township line nor a section line (e.g. east side of s</edomvd>
          </edom>
        </attrdomv>
        <attrdomv>
          <edom>
            <edomv>11</edomv>
            <edomvd>County line that is also a township or range line (all county lines are forty/government lot lines)</edomvd>
          </edom>
        </attrdomv>
        <attrdomv>
          <edom>
            <edomv>12</edomv>
            <edomvd>County line that is not a township or range line but is a section line</edomvd>
          </edom>
        </attrdomv>
        <attrdomv>
          <edom>
            <edomv>13</edomv>
            <edomvd>County line that is a PLS line, but is neither a township line nor a section line (e.g., south side</edomvd>
          </edom>
        </attrdomv>
        <attrdomv>
          <edom>
            <edomv>14</edomv>
            <edomvd>County statutory boundary that is not a PLS line (e.g., center lines of rivers)</edomvd>
          </edom>
        </attrdomv>
        <attrdomv>
          <edom>
            <edomv>21</edomv>
            <edomvd>Township or range line (all township and range lines are also section lines and forty/government lot</edomvd>
          </edom>
        </attrdomv>
        <attrdomv>
          <edom>
            <edomv>21</edomv>
            <edomvd>Township lines</edomvd>
          </edom>
        </attrdomv>
        <attrdomv>
          <edom>
            <edomv>22</edomv>
            <edomvd>Pseudo township or range line (line extending across meandered water body to complete the polygons).</edomvd>
          </edom>
        </attrdomv>
        <attrdomv>
          <edom>
            <edomv>23</edomv>
            <edomvd>Type 2 pseudo township line.  Same as above except that at least one point defining the line was not</edomvd>
          </edom>
        </attrdomv>
        <attrdomv>
          <edom>
            <edomv>31</edomv>
            <edomvd>Section line (all section lines are also forty/government lot lines)</edomvd>
          </edom>
        </attrdomv>
        <attrdomv>
          <edom>
            <edomv>31</edomv>
            <edomvd>Section lines</edomvd>
          </edom>
        </attrdomv>
        <attrdomv>
          <edom>
            <edomv>32</edomv>
            <edomvd>Pseudo section line (line extending across meandered water body to complete the polygons).  Both poi</edomvd>
          </edom>
        </attrdomv>
        <attrdomv>
          <edom>
            <edomv>33</edomv>
            <edomvd>Type 2 pseudo section line.  Same as above except that at least one point defining the line was not</edomvd>
          </edom>
        </attrdomv>
        <attrdomv>
          <edom>
            <edomv>41</edomv>
            <edomvd>Quarter section line</edomvd>
          </edom>
        </attrdomv>
        <attrdomv>
          <edom>
            <edomv>42</edomv>
            <edomvd>Sixteenth section line</edomvd>
          </edom>
        </attrdomv>
        <attrdomv>
          <edom>
            <edomv>43</edomv>
            <edomvd>Meander line (Note:  Meander lines are rough approximations of water body outlines at the time of th</edomvd>
          </edom>
        </attrdomv>
        <attrdomv>
          <edom>
            <edomv>44</edomv>
            <edomvd>Pseudo government lot lines (e.g., lines extending from meander line to current water boundary)</edomvd>
          </edom>
        </attrdomv>
        <attrdomv>
          <edom>
            <edomv>45</edomv>
            <edomvd>Reservation line dividing forties and forming government lot boundaries.  (e.g., Red Lake Reservatio</edomvd>
          </edom>
        </attrdomv>
        <attrdomv>
          <edom>
            <edomv>46</edomv>
            <edomvd>Miscellaneous government lot line. (e.g., previous meander line; originally a meander line but now</edomvd>
          </edom>
        </attrdomv>
      </attr>
      <attr>
        <attrlabl>DISTANCE</attrlabl>
        <attrdef>The length of a line in map units. This field is not consistently populated since it has been necessary to restructure the data during processing in such a manner that this information is eliminated. The field itself is retained since it is mandatory for use within the ARC/INFO COGO package.</attrdef>
      </attr>
    </detailed>
  </eainfo>
  <distinfo>
    <resdesc>plan_mndnr_public_land_survey, pls_fortypy3</resdesc>
    <distliab>The Minnesota Department of Natural Resources General Geographic Data License Agreement is online: http://www.dnr.state.mn.us/sitetools/data_software_license.html
</distliab>
    <stdorder>
      <digform>
        <digtinfo>
          <formname>Shapefile</formname>
          <formvern>Not Applicable</formvern>
          <transize>900</transize>
        </digtinfo>
      </digform>
      <ordering>Please visit the download page for this dataset on the Minnesota Geospatial Commons website using the web link below (Online Linkage).</ordering>
    </stdorder>
    <distrib>
      <cntinfo>
        <cntperp>
          <cntorg>Minnesota Department of Natural Resources</cntorg>
          <cntper>Zeb Thomas</cntper>
        </cntperp>
        <cntpos>GIS Data Systems Coordinator</cntpos>
        <cntaddr>
          <addrtype>Mailing and Physical</addrtype>
          <address>500 Lafayette Rd</address>
          <city>St. Paul</city>
          <state>MN</state>
          <postal>55155-4011</postal>
        </cntaddr>
        <cntvoice>651-259-5637</cntvoice>
        <cntemail>zeb.thomas@state.mn.us</cntemail>
      </cntinfo>
    </distrib>
  </distinfo>
  <metainfo>
    <metd>20140924</metd>
    <metstdn>Minnesota Geographic Metadata Guidelines</metstdn>
    <metstdv>1.2</metstdv>
    <metextns>
      <onlink>http://www.mngeo.state.mn.us/committee/standards/mgmg/metadata.htm</onlink>
    </metextns>
    <metc>
      <cntinfo>
        <cntperp>
          <cntorg>Minnesota Department of Natural Resources</cntorg>
          <cntper>Zeb Thomas</cntper>
        </cntperp>
        <cntpos>GIS Data Systems Coordinator</cntpos>
        <cntaddr>
          <addrtype>Mailing and Physical</addrtype>
          <address>500 Lafayette Rd</address>
          <city>St. Paul</city>
          <state>MN</state>
          <postal>55155-4011</postal>
        </cntaddr>
        <cntvoice>651-259-5637</cntvoice>
        <cntemail>zeb.thomas@state.mn.us</cntemail>
      </cntinfo>
    </metc>
  </metainfo>
</metadata>
