<metadata>
  <eainfo>
    <overview>
      <eaover>GIS data are available for each completed project.</eaover>
    </overview>
  </eainfo>
  <idinfo>
    <citation>
      <citeinfo>
        <origin>Minnesota Department of Natural Resources</origin>
        <title>County Geologic Atlas, Part B</title>
        <pubinfo>
          <publish>Minnesota Department of Natural Resources, Ecological and Water Resources Division</publish>
        </pubinfo>
        <pubdate>20150722</pubdate>
        <onlink>http://www.dnr.state.mn.us/waters/groundwater_section/mapping/status.html</onlink>
      </citeinfo>
    </citation>
    <descript>
      <abstract>GIS files depicting characteristics of the groundwater system of Minnesota. A County Geologic Atlas is a systematic study of a county's geologic and groundwater resources. Geologic studies include both Quaternary deposits and bedrock. Groundwater studies include flow systems, aquifer capacity, groundwater chemistry, and sensitivity to pollution. In some areas sand and gravel deposits, sinkholes, or other features are studied.</abstract>
      <purpose>GIS layers convey geologic and hydrogeologic information and interpretations to governmental units, businesses, and the general public. The information is used in planning and environmental protection efforts and to provide information for permit applications and plans and emergency response to contaminant releases.</purpose>
      <supplinf>Benton, Carver, Carlton, Chisago, Crow Wing, Fillmore, Goodhue, McLeod, Mower, Pine, Pope, Rice, Stearns, Todd, and Wabasha counties, Minnesota</supplinf>
    </descript>
    <crossref>
      <citeinfo>
        <title>County Geologic Atlas, Part A, published by the Minnesota Geological Survey (MGS). More information and downloadable data for Part A available on the MGS site: http://www.mngs.umn.edu/county_atlas/countyatlas.htm.</title>
      </citeinfo>
    </crossref>
    <timeperd>
      <current>publication dates range from 1996 to 2014 with the time period of the content ranging from 1995 to 2012</current>
    </timeperd>
    <status>
      <progress>Complete</progress>
      <update>Additional counties will be added as completed</update>
    </status>
    <spdom>
      <bounding>
        <westbc>-95.8</westbc>
        <eastbc>-91.7</eastbc>
        <northbc>46.8</northbc>
        <southbc>43.5</southbc>
      </bounding>
    </spdom>
    <keywords>
      <place>
        <placekey>Benton, Carver, Carlton, Chisago, Crow Wing, Fillmore, Goodhue, McLeod, Mower, Pine, Pope, Rice, Stearns, Todd, Wabasha, Minnesota</placekey>
      </place>
      <theme>
        <themekt>--</themekt>
        <themekey>buried sand and gravel aquifer, groundwater, water chemistry, residence time, wells, water table, pollution sensitivity, surficial sand aquifer, County Geologic Atlas</themekey>
      </theme>
    </keywords>
    <accconst>None</accconst>
    <useconst>Users may wish to verify critical information; sources include both the references here and information on file in the offices of the Minnesota Geological Survey and the Minnesota Department of Natural Resources. Every effort has been made to ensure the interpretation shown conforms to sound geologic and cartographic principles. This map should not be used to establish legal title, boundaries, or locations of improvements.</useconst>
    <browse>
      <browsen>http://www.dnr.state.mn.us/waters/groundwater_section/mapping/status.html</browsen>
      <browsed>Counties completed or in progress</browsed>
    </browse>
    <ptcontac>
      <cntinfo>
        <cntperp>
          <cntorg>Minnesota Department of Natural Resources</cntorg>
          <cntper>Holly Johnson</cntper>
        </cntperp>
        <cntpos>GIS Specialist</cntpos>
        <cntaddr>
          <addrtype>mailing and physical</addrtype>
          <address>500 Lafayette Rd</address>
          <city>St. Paul</city>
          <state>MN</state>
          <postal>55155-4025</postal>
        </cntaddr>
        <cntvoice>651-259-5693</cntvoice>
        <cntemail>holly.je.johnson@state.mn.us</cntemail>
      </cntinfo>
    </ptcontac>
  </idinfo>
  <dataqual>
    <complete>Complete</complete>
    <posacc>
      <horizpa>
        <horizpar>NA</horizpar>
      </horizpa>
      <vertacc>
        <vertaccr>NA</vertaccr>
      </vertacc>
    </posacc>
    <logic>Data are topologically correct</logic>
    <attracc>
      <attraccr>--</attraccr>
    </attracc>
    <lineage>
      <procstep>
        <procdesc>Review of available data:
Investigations begin with a review of existing information, such as earlier geologic maps, soil maps, hydrologic reports, and information provided by well drillers. Minnesota Geological Survey staff review and interpret driller's logs, and enter the data into the County Well Index (CWI), an interactive data base of water-well information.

Collection of data from the field:
Field studies are conducted to measure static water level elevations and chemistry of selected wells. These studies, combined with pre-existing data, are used to create models of water-table and bedrock hydrogeology (elevation, potentiometric surface, flow direction, aquifer parameters), and sensitivity of groundwater system to pollution.

Creation of GIS layers:
Using a variety of techniques, data are converted into ArcGIS shapefiles, grids, or feature classes for cartographic display and spatial analysis. Metadata for individual projects and layers contain more detailed lineage information.</procdesc>
      </procstep>
    </lineage>
  </dataqual>
  <metainfo>
    <metstdn>Minnesota Geographic Metadata Guidelines</metstdn>
    <metstdv>1.2</metstdv>
    <metextns>
      <onlink>http://www.mngeo.state.mn.us/committee/standards/mgmg/metadata.htm</onlink>
    </metextns>
    <metd>20150722</metd>
    <metc>
      <cntinfo>
        <cntperp>
          <cntorg>Minnesota Department of Natural Resources</cntorg>
          <cntper>Holly Johnson</cntper>
        </cntperp>
        <cntpos>GIS Specialist</cntpos>
        <cntaddr>
          <addrtype>mailing and physical</addrtype>
          <address>500 Lafayette Rd</address>
          <city>St. Paul</city>
          <state>MN</state>
          <postal>55155-4025</postal>
        </cntaddr>
        <cntvoice>651-259-5693</cntvoice>
        <cntemail>holly.je.johnson@state.mn.us</cntemail>
      </cntinfo>
    </metc>
  </metainfo>
  <distinfo>
    <distliab>The maps were prepared from publicly available information only. Every reasonable effort has been made to ensure the accuracy of the factual data on which the maps are based. However, the Department of Natural Resources does not warrant the accuracy, completeness, or any implied uses of these data.

Users may wish to verify critical information; sources include both the references here and information on file in the offices of the Minnesota Geological Survey and the Department of Natural Resources. Every effort has been made to ensure the interpretation shown conforms to sound geologic and cartographic principles. These maps should not be used to establish legal title, boundaries, or locations of improvements.</distliab>
    <stdorder>
      <ordering>Click on county or area of interest to access GIS data for that project. Each completed project contains a zip file of the GIS data.</ordering>
    </stdorder>
    <resdesc>geos_geologic_atlas_part_b</resdesc>
    <distrib>
      <cntinfo>
        <cntperp>
          <cntorg>Minnesota Department of Natural Resources</cntorg>
          <cntper>Holly Johnson</cntper>
        </cntperp>
        <cntpos>GIS Specialist</cntpos>
        <cntaddr>
          <addrtype>mailing and physical</addrtype>
          <address>500 Lafayette Rd</address>
          <city>St. Paul</city>
          <state>MN</state>
          <postal>55155-4025</postal>
        </cntaddr>
        <cntvoice>651-259-5693</cntvoice>
        <cntemail>holly.je.johnson@state.mn.us</cntemail>
      </cntinfo>
    </distrib>
  </distinfo>
  <spref>
    <horizsys>
      <planar>
        <gridsys>
          <gridsysn>Universal Transverse Mercator</gridsysn>
          <utm>
            <utmzone>15</utmzone>
          </utm>
        </gridsys>
        <planci>
          <plandu>meters</plandu>
        </planci>
      </planar>
      <geodetic>
        <horizdn>NAD83</horizdn>
        <ellips>GRS80</ellips>
      </geodetic>
    </horizsys>
  </spref>
</metadata>
