<metadata>
  <idinfo>
    <citation>
      <citeinfo>
        <origin>Minnesota Department of Natural Resouces (DNR) - Division of Waters</origin>
        <pubdate>2009-01-23 00:00:00.0</pubdate>
        <title>National Wetlands Inventory, Minnesota, 1980-1986</title>
        <mgmg1cid/>
        <pubinfo>
          <publish>Minnesota DNR - Division of Waters</publish>
        </pubinfo>
        <onlink>http://gisdata.mn.gov/dataset/water-nat-wetlands-inventory</onlink>
      </citeinfo>
    </citation>
    <descript>
      <abstract>Wetland area features mapped as part of the National Wetlands Inventory (NWI). The National Wetlands Inventory is a national program sponsored by the US Fish and Wildlife Service (USFWS). The NWI database was funded jointly between the USFWS and the State. The base data was developed through interpretation of National Aerial Photography Program (NAPP) imagery (approx. 1:50,000 scale, typically color-infrared) in conjunction with limited field verification studies. Ancillary data sources, particularly USGS Quadrangle Maps and soil surveys, were also used in the interpretation process. After interpreting the aerial photographs, delineations were transferred to a 1:24,000 scale orthogonal base, digitized, and coded in conformance to the USFWS classification scheme and structured into a DLG format. The original interpretation/automation effort was performed under contract by GEONIX-MARTEL of St. Petersburg, FL. The data were delivered to LMIC, who converted it into an ARC/INFO format, and performed some additional processing to prepare it for distribution.  Librarian data were then appended adn converted to ArcGIS File Geodatabase feature classes by DNR Staff (2009)</abstract>
      <purpose>Wetlands permitting support, Environmental Review, Watershed Management, Wildlife Management, Timber Inventories, Rare Natural Feature Inventory</purpose>
    </descript>
    <timeperd>
      <timeinfo>
        <sngdate>
          <caldate>Prior to 1989</caldate>
        </sngdate>
      </timeinfo>
      <current>Source aerial photography was from 1979-1988. Ancillary data sources had variable dates. The interpretation\automation effort began in 1991 and was completed in early 1994.</current>
    </timeperd>
    <status>
      <progress>Complete</progress>
      <update>None Planned</update>
    </status>
    <spdom>
      <bounding>
        <westbc>-96.916176</westbc>
        <eastbc>-89.401375</eastbc>
        <northbc>49.338081</northbc>
        <southbc>43.432557</southbc>
      </bounding>
    </spdom>
    <keywords>
      <theme>
        <themekey>Wetland, Lake, Bog, Swamp, inlandWaters, Hydrography</themekey>
        <themekt>ISO 19115 Category</themekt>
      </theme>
      <place>
        <placekey>Minnesota</placekey>
      </place>
    </keywords>
    <accconst>None</accconst>
    <useconst>Federal, State, and local regulatory agencies with jurisdiction over wetlands may define and describe wetlands in a different manner than that used in this inventory. There is no attempt, in either the design or products of this inventory, to define the limits of proprietary jurisdiction of any Federal, State, or local government or to establish the geographical scope of the regulatory programs of government agencies. Persons intending to engage in activities involving modifications within or adjacent to wetland areas should seek the advice of appropriate Federal, State, or local agencies concerning specified agency regulatory programs and proprietary jurisdictions that may affect such activities. NWI information is not intended to be used as a precise locator of wetland boundaries, for site specific planning or management, or for regulatory purposes.</useconst>
    <native>Unknown</native>
    <browse>
      <browsen>ftp://ftp.gisdata.mn.gov/pub/gdrs/data/pub/us_mn_state_dnr/water_nat_wetlands_inventory/preview/preview.jpg</browsen>
    </browse>
    <ptcontac>
      <cntinfo>
        <cntperp>
          <cntorg>DNR-Waters</cntorg>
          <cntper>Glenn Radde</cntper>
        </cntperp>
        <cntpos>Wetlands GIS Manager</cntpos>
        <cntaddr>
          <addrtype>Mailing and Physical</addrtype>
          <address>500 Lafayette Road
Central Office - Box 32</address>
          <city>St. Paul</city>
          <state>MN</state>
          <postal>55155</postal>
        </cntaddr>
        <cntvoice>651-259-5690</cntvoice>
        <cntfax>(651) 296-0445</cntfax>
        <cntemail>glenn.radde@state.mn.us</cntemail>
      </cntinfo>
    </ptcontac>
  </idinfo>
  <dataqual>
    <logic>Data are topolocially correct using ARC/INFO 7.0.3. All polygons are closed and lines intersect where intended. Data were post processed in ArcGIS 9.3 to append tiles. </logic>
    <complete>Statewide</complete>
    <posacc>
      <horizpa>
        <horizpar>Source layer wetl_nwi:  Horizontal positional accuracy for the digital data is tested by visual comparison of the source with hard copy plots. Enhanced digital data is also snapped to existing quadrangle boundaries and is compared to adjacent files.
</horizpar>
      </horizpa>
      <vertacc>
        <vertaccr>Source layer wetl_nwi:  Not Applicable
</vertaccr>
      </vertacc>
    </posacc>
    <lineage>
      <srcinfo>
        <srcscale>Source layer wetl_nwi:  24000
</srcscale>
      </srcinfo>
    </lineage>
  </dataqual>
  <spdoinfo>
    <indspref>Not Applicable</indspref>
    <direct>vector</direct>
    <mgmg3obj>multiple</mgmg3obj>
    <mgmg3til>state</mgmg3til>
  </spdoinfo>
  <spref>
    <vertdef>
      <altsys>
        <altdatum>Not Applicable</altdatum>
        <altunits>Not Applicable</altunits>
      </altsys>
      <depthsys>
        <depthdn>Not Applicable</depthdn>
        <depthdu>Not Applicable</depthdu>
      </depthsys>
    </vertdef>
    <horizsys>
      <planar>
        <gridsys>
          <gridsysn>Universal Transverse Mercator</gridsysn>
          <utm>
            <utmzone>15</utmzone>
          </utm>
        </gridsys>
        <planci>
          <plandu>meters</plandu>
        </planci>
      </planar>
      <geodetic>
        <horizdn>NAD83</horizdn>
        <ellips>GRS80</ellips>
      </geodetic>
    </horizsys>
  </spref>
  <distinfo>
    <resdesc>water_nat_wetlands_inventory</resdesc>
    <distliab>The Minnesota Department of Natural Resources General Geographic Data License Agreement is online: http://www.dnr.state.mn.us/sitetools/data_software_license.html</distliab>
    <stdorder>
      <digform>
        <digtinfo>
          <formname>ArcGIS File Geodatabase</formname>
          <formvern>9.3</formvern>
          <transize>2048000</transize>
        </digtinfo>
      </digform>
      <ordering>See Online Linkage or Distribution Contact</ordering>
    </stdorder>
    <distrib>
      <cntinfo>
        <cntperp>
          <cntorg>Minnesota Department of Natural Resources</cntorg>
          <cntper>Zeb Thomas</cntper>
        </cntperp>
        <cntpos>GIS Data Systems Coordinator</cntpos>
        <cntaddr>
          <address>500 Lafayette Rd</address>
          <city>Saint Paul</city>
          <state>MN</state>
          <postal>55155</postal>
        </cntaddr>
        <cntvoice>651-259-5637</cntvoice>
        <cntemail>zeb.thomas@state.mn.us</cntemail>
      </cntinfo>
    </distrib>
  </distinfo>
  <metainfo>
    <metd>20140716</metd>
    <metstdn>Minnesota Geographic Metadata Guidelines</metstdn>
    <metstdv>1.2</metstdv>
    <metextns>
      <onlink>http://www.mngeo.state.mn.us/committee/standards/mgmg/metadata.htm</onlink>
    </metextns>
    <metc>
      <cntinfo>
        <cntperp>
          <cntorg>Minnesota Department of Natural Resources</cntorg>
          <cntper>Zeb Thomas</cntper>
        </cntperp>
        <cntpos>GIS Data Systems Coordinator</cntpos>
        <cntaddr>
          <address>500 Lafayette Rd</address>
          <city>Saint Paul</city>
          <state>MN</state>
          <postal>55155</postal>
        </cntaddr>
        <cntvoice>651-259-5637</cntvoice>
        <cntemail>zeb.thomas@state.mn.us</cntemail>
      </cntinfo>
    </metc>
  </metainfo>
</metadata>
