<metadata>
  <idinfo>
    <citation>
      <citeinfo>
        <origin>Metropolitan Council</origin>
        <title>Potential Water Supply Issues By Watershed</title>
        <pubinfo>
          <publish>Metropolitan Council</publish>
        </pubinfo>
        <pubdate>20150916</pubdate>
        <onlink>https://gisdata.mn.gov/dataset/us-mn-state-metc-water-potential-sply-issue</onlink>
      </citeinfo>
    </citation>
    <descript>
      <purpose>To provide water supply related planning information at the parcel, community, county, and watershed scale. This data does not indicate availability of water supplies, but it does highlight some potential issues may need to be addressed as part of plan and permit development in the area.</purpose>
      <supplinf>7-County Twin Cities Metropolitan Area</supplinf>
      <abstract>The Potential Water Supply Issues dataset encompasses the seven county Twin Cities (Minneapolis and St. Paul) Metropolitan Area in Minnesota.  The dataset was developed by the Metropolitan Council, a regional governmental organization that deals, in part, with regional issues and long range planning for the Twin Cities area.  The data were interpreted from several existing state agencies datasets.

This dataset is composed of one feature class and three standalone tables. 
- PotentialWaterSupplyIssues = Detailed potential water supply issue polygons
- PotentialWaterSupplyIssuesByCTU = Standalone table with summary of potential water supply issues by CTU
- PotentialWaterSupplyIssuesByCounty = Standalone table with summary of potential water supply issues by county
- PotentialWaterSupplyIssuesByWatershed = Standalone table with summary of potential water supply issues by Watershed Management District or Organization

See "Attributes" section of the metadata for a detailed description of each of these water supply issue categories.</abstract>
    </descript>
    <crossref>
      <citeinfo>
        <title>Community and township information (Metropolitan Council)
Watershed information (Metropolitan Council)
Watershed Management Districts and Organizations (BWSR)
Drinking Water Supply Management Area boundaries (MDH)
Drinking Water Supply Management Area vulnerability (MDH)
Special Well Boring and Construction Areas (Metropolitan Council)
Trends in groundwater level observation wells (DNR)
Calcareous fen locations (DNR)
Vertical travel time from land surface to uppermost bedrock aquifers (MGS)
County information (Metropolitan Council)
Karst Feature Inventory (DNR)
Trout stream locations (DNR)
Supplier status information (Metropolitan Council)
Regional groundwater flow model scenarios for 2040 (Metropolitan Council)
Surface water feature vulnerability (Metropolitan Council)
Aquifer tests (MDH)
Groundwater level observation wells (DNR)
Groundwater Management Area (DNR)
Shakopee Mdewakanton Sioux Community infomration (SMSC)</title>
      </citeinfo>
    </crossref>
    <timeperd>
      <current>This dataset contains information that was updated at different times. This dataset contains the most recent data available as of August 2015.</current>
      <timeinfo>
        <sngdate>
          <caldate>20150916</caldate>
        </sngdate>
      </timeinfo>
    </timeperd>
    <status>
      <progress>Complete</progress>
      <update>Irregular</update>
    </status>
    <keywords>
      <place>
        <placekey>Twin Cities Metropolitan Area, Minnesota, Anoka, Carver, Dakota, Hennepin, Ramsey, Scott, Washington</placekey>
      </place>
      <theme>
        <themekt>Metropolitan Council</themekt>
        <themekey>Metropolitan Council, Water Supply, Planning</themekey>
      </theme>
    </keywords>
    <accconst>None</accconst>
    <useconst>None</useconst>
    <spdom>
      <bounding>
        <westbc>-94.012</westbc>
        <eastbc>-92.732</eastbc>
        <northbc>45.415</northbc>
        <southbc>44.471</southbc>
      </bounding>
    </spdom>
    <ptcontac>
      <cntinfo>
        <cntperp>
          <cntorg>Metropolitan Council</cntorg>
          <cntper>Lanya Ross</cntper>
        </cntperp>
        <cntpos>Sr. Environmental Specialist</cntpos>
        <cntaddr>
          <addrtype>mailing and physical</addrtype>
          <address>390 Robert Street North</address>
          <city>St. Paul</city>
          <state>MN</state>
          <postal>55101-1805</postal>
        </cntaddr>
        <cntvoice>651.602.1803</cntvoice>
        <cntemail>lanya.ross@metc.state.mn.us</cntemail>
      </cntinfo>
    </ptcontac>
  </idinfo>
  <metainfo>
    <metstdn>Minnesota Geographic Metadata Guidelines</metstdn>
    <metstdv>1.2</metstdv>
    <metextns>
      <onlink>http://www.mngeo.state.mn.us/committee/standards/mgmg/metadata.htm</onlink>
    </metextns>
    <metd>20151012</metd>
    <metc>
      <cntinfo>
        <cntperp>
          <cntorg>Metropolitan Council</cntorg>
          <cntper>Lanya Ross</cntper>
        </cntperp>
        <cntpos>Sr. Environmental Specialist</cntpos>
        <cntaddr>
          <addrtype>mailing and physical</addrtype>
          <address>390 Robert Street North</address>
          <city>St. Paul</city>
          <state>MN</state>
          <postal>55101-1805</postal>
        </cntaddr>
        <cntvoice>651.602.1803</cntvoice>
        <cntemail>lanya.ross@metc.state.mn.us</cntemail>
      </cntinfo>
    </metc>
  </metainfo>
  <eainfo>
    <detailed>
      <enttyp>
        <enttypl>PotentialWaterSupplyIssues</enttypl>
        <enttypd>Set of combined water supply data, clipped to 7-county metro area</enttypd>
      </enttyp>
      <attr>
        <attrlabl>OBJECTID</attrlabl>
      </attr>
      <attr>
        <attrlabl>popup</attrlabl>
        <attrdef>Used for the customized popup in the internal web application.</attrdef>
      </attr>
      <attr>
        <attrlabl>Shape</attrlabl>
        <attrdef>Polygon</attrdef>
      </attr>
      <attr>
        <attrlabl>V_DWSMA</attrlabl>
        <attrdef>Is a Drinking Water Supply Management Area (DWSMA) vulnerable? 1=Yes, 0=No</attrdef>
      </attr>
      <attr>
        <attrlabl>Trend</attrlabl>
        <attrdef>Is an area lcoated within 1.5 miles of a DNR well with downward trend ? 1=Yes, 0=No</attrdef>
      </attr>
      <attr>
        <attrlabl>Aquifer</attrlabl>
        <attrdef>Aquifer name where groundwater level observation well is located</attrdef>
      </attr>
      <attr>
        <attrlabl>CO_NAME</attrlabl>
        <attrdef>County Name</attrdef>
      </attr>
      <attr>
        <attrlabl>CTU_NAME</attrlabl>
        <attrdef>Community Name</attrdef>
      </attr>
      <attr>
        <attrlabl>SupplierSt</attrlabl>
        <attrdef>Descriptor of the community public water supplier if there is one.</attrdef>
      </attr>
      <attr>
        <attrlabl>CTU_ID</attrlabl>
        <attrdef>Community Code</attrdef>
      </attr>
      <attr>
        <attrlabl>TYPE</attrlabl>
        <attrdef>Descriptor of whether watershed is watershed management organization (WMO), watershed district (WD), or county (COU)</attrdef>
      </attr>
      <attr>
        <attrlabl>Watershed</attrlabl>
        <attrdef>Watershed organization name. If blank, then the area isn't located within a watershed organization.</attrdef>
      </attr>
      <attr>
        <attrlabl>DNRObs</attrlabl>
        <attrdef>Is an area located within 1.5 miles of a DNR observation well? 1=Yes, 0=No</attrdef>
      </attr>
      <attr>
        <attrlabl>Fen_</attrlabl>
        <attrdef>Is an area located within 5 miles of a fen? 1=Yes, 0=No</attrdef>
      </attr>
      <attr>
        <attrlabl>Sinkhole</attrlabl>
        <attrdef>Is an area located within 1.5 miles of a sinkhole? 1=Yes, 0=No</attrdef>
      </attr>
      <attr>
        <attrlabl>Spring</attrlabl>
        <attrdef>Is an area located within 1.5 miles of a spring? 1=Yes, 0=No</attrdef>
      </attr>
      <attr>
        <attrlabl>AqTest</attrlabl>
        <attrdef>Is an area located within 1.5 miles of an aquifer test area? 1=Yes, 0=No</attrdef>
      </attr>
      <attr>
        <attrlabl>Atlas</attrlabl>
        <attrdef>Is an area located within a County Geological Atlas over 20 years old? 1=Yes, 0=No</attrdef>
      </attr>
      <attr>
        <attrlabl>F50PerAvg</attrlabl>
        <attrdef>Is an area flagged for greater than 50% aquifer drawdown under average 2040 conditions? 1=Yes, 0=No</attrdef>
      </attr>
      <attr>
        <attrlabl>F50PerL</attrlabl>
        <attrdef>Is an area flagged for greater than 50% aquifer drawdown under 20% below  average 2040 conditions? 1=Yes, 0=No</attrdef>
      </attr>
      <attr>
        <attrlabl>F50PerH</attrlabl>
        <attrdef>Is an area flagged for greater than 50% aquifer drawdown under 20% above average 2040 conditions? 1=Yes, 0=No</attrdef>
      </attr>
      <attr>
        <attrlabl>OtherGov</attrlabl>
        <attrdef>Other governement jurisdication name. If blank, then the area isn't located within another governement jurisdication.</attrdef>
      </attr>
      <attr>
        <attrlabl>SWBCA_</attrlabl>
        <attrdef>Is Special Well Boring Construction Area (SWBCA) present? 1=Yes, 0=No</attrdef>
      </attr>
      <attr>
        <attrlabl>TT50Yr</attrlabl>
        <attrdef>Is the time of travel less than 50 years? 1=Yes, 0=No</attrdef>
      </attr>
      <attr>
        <attrlabl>Trout</attrlabl>
        <attrdef>Is an area located within 5 miles of a trout stream? 1=Yes, 0=No</attrdef>
      </attr>
      <attr>
        <attrlabl>SWGW</attrlabl>
        <attrdef>Is an area located within 0.25 miles of a vulnerable surface-water feature? 1=Yes, 0=No</attrdef>
      </attr>
      <attr>
        <attrlabl>DWSMA</attrlabl>
        <attrdef>Is a Drinking Water Supply Management Area (DWSMA) present? 1=Yes, 0=No</attrdef>
      </attr>
      <attr>
        <attrlabl>DWS_NAME</attrlabl>
        <attrdef>Drinking Water Supply Management Area Name, as designated by the MN Department of Health</attrdef>
      </attr>
      <attr>
        <attrlabl>Shape_Length</attrlabl>
        <attrdef>Perimeter of polygon in meters.</attrdef>
      </attr>
      <attr>
        <attrlabl>Shape_Area</attrlabl>
        <attrdef>Area of polygon in square meters.</attrdef>
      </attr>
      <attr>
        <attrlabl>GWMA_</attrlabl>
        <attrdef>Is a Ground Water Management Area (GWMA) present? 1=Yes, 0=No</attrdef>
      </attr>
      <attr>
        <attrlabl>Name</attrlabl>
        <attrdef>Sub-region name</attrdef>
      </attr>
      <attr>
        <attrlabl>CO_CODE</attrlabl>
        <attrdef>County Code</attrdef>
      </attr>
      <attr>
        <attrlabl>AqDecline</attrlabl>
        <attrdef>Is an area flagged for aquifer decline? 3= Yes in all 3 scenarios; 2= Yes in Average and High scenarios; 1= Yes in High scenario; and 0= No</attrdef>
      </attr>
    </detailed>
    <overview>
      <eaover>See detailed information below.</eaover>
    </overview>
  </eainfo>
  <distinfo>
    <resdesc>WaterSupplyIssues_September2015</resdesc>
    <distliab>NOTICE:  The Geographic Information System (GIS) Data to which this notice is attached are made available pursuant to the Minnesota Government Data Practices Act (Minnesota Statutes Chapter 13).  THE GIS DATA ARE PROVIDED TO YOU AS IS AND WITHOUT ANY WARRANTY AS TO THEIR PERFORMANCE, MERCHANTABILITY, OR FITNESS FOR ANY PARTICULAR PURPOSE.  The GIS Data were developed by the Metropolitan Council for its own internal business purposes.  The Metropolitan Council does not represent or warrant that the GIS Data or the data documentation are error-free, complete, current, or accurate.  You are responsible for any consequences resulting from your use of the GIS Data or your reliance on the GIS Data.  You should consult the data documentation for this particular GIS Data to determine the limitations of the GIS Data and the precision with which the GIS Data may depict distance, direction, location, or other geographic features.  If you transmit or provide the GIS Data (or any portion of it) to another user, it is recommended that the GIS Data include a copy of this disclaimer and this metadata.</distliab>
    <stdorder>
      <ordering>See Online Linkage Below</ordering>
    </stdorder>
    <distrib>
      <cntinfo>
        <cntperp>
          <cntorg>Metropolitan Council</cntorg>
          <cntper>Lanya Ross</cntper>
        </cntperp>
        <cntpos>Sr. Environmental Specialist</cntpos>
        <cntaddr>
          <addrtype>mailing and physical</addrtype>
          <address>390 Robert Street North</address>
          <city>St. Paul</city>
          <state>MN</state>
          <postal>55101-1805</postal>
        </cntaddr>
        <cntvoice>651.602.1803</cntvoice>
        <cntemail>lanya.ross@metc.state.mn.us</cntemail>
      </cntinfo>
    </distrib>
  </distinfo>
  <dataqual>
    <complete>Entire seven county geographic area is covered.</complete>
    <lineage>
      <procstep>
        <procdesc>DATA SOURCES:
- Metropolitan Council maps of community and township, county, and watershed management organization boundaries
- Metropolitan Council Master Water Supply Plan information about hydrogeologic sub-regions, public water supply system status, and regional groundwater flow model results
- MN Department of Health Drinking Water Supply Management Area delineations and vulnerability assessments
- MN Department of Health Special Well and Boring Construction Area delineations and names
- MN Department of Natural Resources groundwater level observation well locations, aquifers, and trend analysis
- MN Department of Natural Resources calcareous fen location map
- MN Geological Survey evaluation of aveage vertical travel time from land surface to uppermost bedrock
- MN Departmen of Natural Resources geologic atlas information
- MN Departmen of Natural Resources karst database
- MN Department of Natural Resources trout stream location map
- Metropolitan Council and Barr Engineering Company evaluation of potential groundwater and surface water interaction
- MN Department of Health records of aquifer testing
- MN Department of Natural Resources Groundwater Management Area delineation
- Shakopee Mdewakanton Sioux (Dakotah) Community boundary


PROCESSING STEPS FOR THE WATER SUPPLY ISSUES LAYER
Point files were buffered to create polygons. A calculated field was added to each polygon file, to allow a value of 1 or 0 to be assigned as needed. Polygon datasets were merged, and extraneous fields were deleted from each source dataset.</procdesc>
      </procstep>
    </lineage>
  </dataqual>
  <spref>
    <horizsys>
      <planar>
        <gridsys>
          <gridsysn>Universal Transverse Mercator</gridsysn>
          <utm>
            <utmzone>15</utmzone>
          </utm>
        </gridsys>
        <planci>
          <plandu>meters</plandu>
        </planci>
      </planar>
      <geodetic>
        <horizdn>NAD83</horizdn>
        <ellips>GRS80</ellips>
      </geodetic>
    </horizsys>
  </spref>
</metadata>
