<?xml version="1.0"?><metadata><idinfo><citation><citeinfo><origin>Federal Communications Commission (FCC) Media Bureau and Wireless Telecommunications Bureau</origin><title>Federal Communications Commission (FCC) Geospatial Data, United States</title><pubinfo><publish>Federal Communications Commission (FCC)</publish></pubinfo><pubdate>20120614</pubdate><onlink>http://wireless.fcc.gov/geographic/index.htm?job=licensing_database_extracts</onlink></citeinfo></citation><descript><abstract>Various telecommunication datasets such as cellphone towers and service areas, land mobile station locations, AM, FM, and TV communication can be downloaded on an FCC page. Additionally, data files can be individually downloaded from the FCC Universal Licensing System data site.

Individual metadata pages can be seen here:

&lt;b&gt;Antenna Structure Registration: &lt;/b&gt; &lt;a href="antenna_structure_registration_mn.html"&gt;antenna_structure_registration_mn.html&lt;/a&gt;</abstract><purpose>With these datasets, users are able to determine the locations and limited technical details of existing towers, stations and areas the FCC licenses (i.e. Cellular, Paging, Microwave, AM, FM, etc.). This information can be extremely helpful in conducting analysis such as: current service deployment, need/feasibility determinations of new services, co-location of antenna structures, inventorying of structures, network planning, etc.</purpose><supplinf>United States and Territories</supplinf></descript><crossref><citeinfo><title>FCC Universal Licensing System homepage:
http://wireless.fcc.gov/uls/about/</title></citeinfo></crossref><timeperd><current>FCC website contains the most recent downloadable version of these datasets.</current><timeinfo><sngdate><caldate>20120614</caldate></sngdate></timeinfo></timeperd><spdom><bounding><westbc>-170.764583</westbc><eastbc>145.793611</eastbc><northbc>71.318472</northbc><southbc>-14.333194</southbc></bounding></spdom><status><progress>Complete</progress><update>Unknown</update></status><keywords><place><placekey>United States, US Territories, Minnesota, MN</placekey></place><theme><themekt>ISO 19115 Topic Category</themekt><themekey>utilitiesCommunication, FCC, Federal Communications Commission, Transmission, Towers, Licensing, Infrastructure, Utilities, Communication, AM Towers, AM Radio, Antennas, Antenna Structure Registration, ASR, BRS, Cellular, Cellular Service Area Boundaries, Cellular Towers, EBS, FM Towers, FM Radio, Land Mobile, Land Mobile Stations, Land Mobile Communications, Microwave, Microwave Towers, Pager, Paging, Pager Towers, TV Towers, TV Transmission, Television</themekey></theme></keywords><accconst>None</accconst><useconst>Data provided is to serve as base information for use in GIS systems for general planning, analytical, and research purposes. It is not intended for engineering work or to legally define reservation boundaries, FCC licensee data or FCC market boundaries.</useconst><browse><browsen>http://wireless.fcc.gov/geographic/images/image1.gif</browsen><browsed>Cellular, Antenna Structure Registration, AM and FM databases on one map (example from FCC website)</browsed></browse><ptcontac><cntinfo><cntperp><cntorg>Federal Communications Commission</cntorg><cntper>Melvin C. Del Rosario</cntper></cntperp><cntaddr><addrtype>Mailing and Physical</addrtype><address>445 12th Street SW</address><city>Washington</city><state>DC</state><postal>20554</postal></cntaddr><cntvoice>202-418-0615</cntvoice><cntemail>mdelrosa@fcc.gov</cntemail></cntinfo></ptcontac></idinfo><spref><horizsys><geograph><latres>0.000001</latres><longres>0.000001</longres><geogunit>Decimal degrees</geogunit></geograph><geodetic><horizdn>NAD27</horizdn><ellips>Clarke 1866</ellips></geodetic></horizsys></spref><eainfo><overview><eaover>Datasets available include the following: 

AM Towers
Antenna Structure Registration (ASR)
BRS/EBS
Cellular Towers
Cellular Service Area Boundaries (aggregated by callsign)
FM Towers
Land Mobile - Commercial
Land Mobile - Private
Land Mobile - Broadcast
Microwave
Paging
TV - NTSC
TV - Digital
TV Contours - NTSC and Digital

Each dataset has its own set of attributes. Map extents are U.S. and Territories.  Contact Distributor for more information.

A demonstration data set for Antenna Structure Registration is provided here: &lt;/b&gt; &lt;a href="antenna_structure_registration_mn.html"&gt;antenna_structure_registration_mn.html&lt;/a&gt;</eaover></overview></eainfo><distinfo><resdesc>FCC Geospatial Data - Licensing Database Extracts</resdesc><distliab>Any use of trade, product, or firm names is for descriptive purposes only and does not imply endorsement by the U.S. Government or the Federal Communications Commission (FCC). No warranty expressed or implied is made by the FCC as to the accuracy of the data and related materials. The act of distribution shall not constitute any such warranty, and no responsibility is assumed by the FCC in the use of this data, or related materials.</distliab><stdorder><ordering>These datasets are distributed on the internet by clicking 'Online Linkage'. Doing so will direct your browser to the Federal Communications Commission GIS site where several different ZIP files are available to download. Each ZIP file is composed of a given dataset's shapefiles.</ordering></stdorder><distrib><cntinfo><cntperp><cntorg>Federal Communications Commission</cntorg><cntper>Melvin C. Del Rosario</cntper></cntperp><cntaddr><addrtype>mailing and physical</addrtype><address>445 12th Street SW</address><city>Washington</city><state>DC</state><postal>20554</postal></cntaddr><cntvoice>202-418-0615</cntvoice><cntemail>mdelrosa@fcc.gov</cntemail></cntinfo></distrib></distinfo><metainfo><metd>20141209</metd><metstdn>Minnesota Geographic Metadata Guidelines</metstdn><metstdv>1.2</metstdv><metextns><onlink>http://www.mngeo.state.mn.us/committee/standards/mgmg/metadata.htm</onlink></metextns><metc><cntinfo><cntperp><cntorg>MN Geospatial Information Office</cntorg><cntper>Mike Dolbow</cntper></cntperp><cntpos>GIS Supervisor</cntpos><cntaddr><addrtype>mailing and physical</addrtype><address>658 Cedar Street</address><city>St. Paul</city><state>MN</state><postal>55155</postal></cntaddr><cntvoice>651-201-3944</cntvoice><cntemail>mike.dolbow@state.mn.us</cntemail></cntinfo></metc></metainfo><dataqual><lineage><procstep><procdesc>FCC staff extract these datasets periodically from their Licensing Database.</procdesc></procstep></lineage><logic>Not available</logic><complete>Not available</complete><posacc><horizpa><horizpar>Not available. Projection is "Geographic". Some files list Horizontal Datum as NAD27, and others as NAD83. See .prj files associated with individual shapefiles for Projection and Datum information.</horizpar></horizpa><vertacc><vertaccr>Not available</vertaccr></vertacc></posacc><attracc><attraccr>Not available</attraccr></attracc></dataqual></metadata>