<?xml version="1.0"?><metadata><eainfo><overview><eaover>Attributes 
 
SHELTER_NB: A unique identifier assigned to shelters to distinguish ownership and number.  The letter represents the first letter of the shelter owner. 
 
SHELTER_ID: An object identification number assigned by MetroTransit, originating in the bus stop database. 
 
SITE_ID:    An idenfication number assigned by MetroTransit originating from the bus stop database. More than one shelter can be associated. 
 
SITE_ON:  The street or address where the shelter is found. 
 
SITE_AT:  The cross street or address nearest the shelter 
 
CORN_DESC:  The description of the corner location. 
 
CITY: The city the shelter is located in  
 
OWNER: Owner and caretaker of the shelter.  'METRO' are shelters owned and maintained by Metro Transit.  
 
SHEL_TYPE: I don’t know what this field is.  We should follow-up with the shelter group
 
RT_CD:      The route code assigned to the shelter for maintenance. 
 
item_id:  Code identifying bus shelters with that have lights (lighthps) or lights &amp; heat (heat) 

 


</eaover></overview></eainfo><idinfo><citation><citeinfo><origin>Metropolitan Council - Metro Transit</origin><title>Transit Shelters</title><pubinfo><publish>Metropolitan Council - Metro Transit</publish></pubinfo><pubdate>20120216</pubdate><onlink>https://gisdata.mn.gov/dataset/us-mn-state-metc-trans-bus-shelters</onlink></citeinfo></citation><descript><abstract>The Transit Shelters layer includes around 1200 bus shelters in the Metro Transit service area.  It includes shelters owned by Metro Transit and third party entities. 

Attributes include Site_id, Shelter_id, Shelter_nb, Site_loc, Shelter_ow, Rt_cd, Shel_elec, X, Y and corn_desc. All shelters identified in this database correspond to a bus stop, and can be linked to the bus_stops shapefile using the Siteid field. This dataset does not reflect situations where shelters may be designed to serve more than one bus stop number or where  multiple shelters may also serve one stop. 
</abstract><purpose>To identify all bus shelter locations associated with bus stops in the Twin Cities metropolitan area. </purpose><supplinf>Twin Cities 7 county metropolitan area.  This includes the counties of Anoka, Carver, Dakota, Hennepin, Ramsey, Scott and Washington.</supplinf></descript><crossref><citeinfo><title>Transit Stops, Transit Routes, transit segments, Park and Ride Lots</title></citeinfo></crossref><timeperd><current>This dataset is update weekly</current><timeinfo><sngdate><caldate>Updated Weekly</caldate></sngdate></timeinfo></timeperd><status><progress>Complete</progress><update>As needed</update></status><spdom><bounding><westbc>-94.012</westbc><eastbc>-92.732</eastbc><northbc>45.415</northbc><southbc>44.471</southbc></bounding></spdom><accconst>None</accconst><useconst>By acceptance of this data, the user agrees to include a copy of this metadata record, including the liability disclaimer, whenever the user transmits or provides the GIS Data (or any portion of it) to another user.</useconst><keywords><place><placekey>Twin Cities, Anoka County, Carver County, Dakota County, Hennepin County, Ramsey County, Scott County, Washington County</placekey></place><theme><themekey>bus shelter, shelters, transit, buses, patterns, streets, roads, transportation</themekey></theme></keywords><ptcontac><cntinfo><cntperp><cntorg>Metropolitan Council - Metro Transit</cntorg><cntper>Steve Baisden</cntper></cntperp><cntpos>Associate Planner</cntpos><cntaddr><addrtype>mailing and physical</addrtype><address>560 6th Ave N</address><city>Minneapolis</city><state>MN</state><postal>55411</postal></cntaddr><cntvoice>612.349.7361</cntvoice><cntemail>stephen.baisden@metrotransit.org</cntemail></cntinfo></ptcontac></idinfo><dataqual><posacc><horizpa><horizpar>Positional accuracy is accurate to the location of the bus stop GPS coordinates.</horizpar></horizpa></posacc></dataqual><distinfo><distliab>NOTICE:  The Geographic Information System (GIS) Data to which this notice is attached are made available pursuant to the Minnesota Government Data Practices Act (Minnesota Statutes Chapter 13).  THE GIS DATA ARE PROVIDED TO YOU AS IS AND WITHOUT ANY WARRANTY AS TO THEIR PERFORMANCE, MERCHANTABILITY, OR FITNESS FOR ANY PARTICULAR PURPOSE.  The GIS Data were developed by the Metropolitan Council for its own internal business purposes.  The Metropolitan Council does not represent or warrant that the GIS Data or the data documentation are error-free, complete, current, or accurate.  You are responsible for any consequences resulting from your use of the GIS Data or your reliance on the GIS Data.  You should consult the data documentation for this particular GIS Data to determine the limitations of the GIS Data and the precision with which the GIS Data may depict distance, direction, location, or other geographic features.  If you transmit or provide the GIS Data (or any portion of it) to another user, it is recommended that the GIS Data include a copy of this disclaimer and this metadata.</distliab><stdorder><ordering>See Online Linkage Below</ordering></stdorder><resdesc>TransitShelters</resdesc><distrib><cntinfo><cntperp><cntorg>Metropolitan Council</cntorg><cntper>Jon Hoekenga</cntper></cntperp><cntpos>GIS System Administrator</cntpos><cntaddr><addrtype>mailing and physical</addrtype><address>390 Robert Street North</address><city>St. Paul</city><state>MN</state><postal>55101-1805</postal></cntaddr><cntvoice>651.602.1561</cntvoice><cntemail>jonathan.hoekenga@metc.state.mn.us</cntemail></cntinfo></distrib></distinfo><metainfo><metd>20120228</metd><metstdn>Minnesota Geographic Metadata Guidelines</metstdn><metstdv>1.2</metstdv><metextns><onlink>http://www.mngeo.state.mn.us/committee/standards/mgmg/metadata.htm</onlink></metextns><metc><cntinfo><cntperp><cntorg>Metropolitan Council - Metro Transit</cntorg><cntper>Steve Baisden</cntper></cntperp><cntpos>Associate Planner</cntpos><cntaddr><addrtype>mailing and physical</addrtype><address>560 6th Ave N</address><city>Minneapolis</city><state>MN</state><postal>55411</postal></cntaddr><cntvoice>612.349.7361</cntvoice><cntemail>stephen.baisden@metrotransit.org</cntemail></cntinfo></metc></metainfo><spref><horizsys><planar><gridsys><gridsysn>Universal Transverse Mercator</gridsysn><utm><utmzone>15</utmzone></utm></gridsys><planci><plandu>meters</plandu></planci></planar><geodetic><horizdn>NAD83</horizdn><ellips>GRS80</ellips></geodetic></horizsys></spref></metadata>