<metadata>
  <idinfo>
    <citation>
      <citeinfo>
        <title>Park and Ride Lots</title>
        <origin>Metro Transit</origin>
        <pubinfo>
          <publish>Metropolitan Council</publish>
        </pubinfo>
        <pubdate>periodically revised</pubdate>
        <onlink>https://gisdata.mn.gov/dataset/us-mn-state-metc-trans-park-and-ride-lots</onlink>
      </citeinfo>
    </citation>
    <descript>
      <abstract>The Park-and-Ride layer contains the 196 existing and future park-and-ride lots in the Twin Cities Metropolitan area. 

The dataset was geocoded using TLG centerline streets. When specific site details were available, the geography was moved off the street lines to the actual lot locations using 2005 Markhurd orthophotography as a base layer. All attempts were made to correctly reflect the real lot locations; however, the positional accuracy of this data cannot be guaranteed. 

Attribute information is considered current to the metadata date and will be updated as needed.</abstract>
      <purpose>To identify all park-and-ride locations in the Twin Cities metropolitan area.</purpose>
      <supplinf>Twin Cities Metropolitan Area - including Minnesota Counties: Anoka, Carver, Chisago, Dakota, Goodhue, Hennepin, Isanti, Le Sueur, Mille Lacs, Ramsey, Rice, Scott, Sherburne, Stearns, Washington, Wright; Wisconsin Counties: Dunn, St. Croix</supplinf>
    </descript>
    <timeperd>
      <timeinfo>
        <sngdate>
          <caldate>20150915</caldate>
        </sngdate>
      </timeinfo>
      <current>Park-and-ride locations are accurate as of the Time Period of Content date for the Twin Cities Metropolitan Area.</current>
    </timeperd>
    <status>
      <progress>Complete</progress>
      <update>As needed</update>
    </status>
    <spdom>
      <bounding>
        <westbc>-94.581</westbc>
        <eastbc>-91.719</eastbc>
        <northbc>45.628</northbc>
        <southbc>44.385</southbc>
      </bounding>
    </spdom>
    <keywords>
      <place>
        <placekey>Twin Cities, Minnesota, Anoka County, Carver County, Chisago County, Dakota County, Goodhue County, Hennepin County, Isanti County, Le Sueur County, Mille Lacs County, Ramsey County, Rice County, Scott County, Sherburne County, Stearns County, Washington County, Wright County, Dunn County, St. Croix County</placekey>
      </place>
      <theme>
        <themekey>Transit Centers, Transit Stops, Transit Routes, Transit Patterns by Node Segments, transit, buses, nodes, stops, transportation</themekey>
        <themekt>None</themekt>
      </theme>
    </keywords>
    <accconst>None</accconst>
    <useconst>None</useconst>
    <browse>
      <browsen>ftp://ftp.gisdata.mn.gov/pub/gdrs/data/pub/us_mn_state_metc/trans_park_and_ride_lots/metadata/preview.jpg</browsen>
      <browsed>Sample map showing the Park and Ride Lots layer.</browsed>
    </browse>
    <crossref>
      <citeinfo>
        <title>Transit Centers, Transit Stops, Transit Routes</title>
      </citeinfo>
    </crossref>
    <native>ArcGIS 9x</native>
    <ptcontac>
      <cntinfo>
        <cntperp>
          <cntorg>Metropolitan Council - Metro Transit</cntorg>
          <cntper>Julie Quinn</cntper>
        </cntperp>
        <cntpos>Associate Planner, Engineering and Facilities</cntpos>
        <cntaddr>
          <addrtype>mailing and physical</addrtype>
          <address>560 6th Ave N</address>
          <city>Minneapolis</city>
          <state>MN</state>
          <postal>55411</postal>
        </cntaddr>
        <cntvoice>612.349.7333</cntvoice>
        <cntemail>julie.quinn@metc.state.mn.us</cntemail>
      </cntinfo>
    </ptcontac>
  </idinfo>
  <dataqual>
    <attracc>
      <attraccr>Attributes are considered accurate. See the Entity and Attribute Overview for more details.</attraccr>
    </attracc>
    <logic>The dataset is topologically 'clean'.</logic>
    <complete>All active park-and-rides in the metropolitan area are covered.</complete>
    <posacc>
      <horizpa>
        <horizpar>Orthophotos were used in referencing the park-and-ride lot locations. Positional accuracy varies throughout the dataset. In some cases, locations outside the seven county metro area were located using NCompass Technologies Street Centerline and Address Ranges dataset where available and not have been referenced to aerial photos.</horizpar>
      </horizpa>
    </posacc>
  </dataqual>
  <spdoinfo>
    <indspref>None</indspref>
    <direct>Point</direct>
    <mgmg3obj>Point</mgmg3obj>
    <mgmg3til>One file for entire metro area.</mgmg3til>
  </spdoinfo>
  <eainfo>
    <overview>
      <eaover>PR_NUM:   Unique P&amp;R facility ID number

NAME:  Park-and-ride name

DESCRIPT:  Description of general P&amp;R location

CITY: City in which P&amp;R is located

ACTIVE:  1 = Active park-and-ride; 0 = Inactive park-and-ride (e.g., not open for service)

YEAR_EST: Year P&amp;R opened

PR_PP: Park-and-pool or Park-and-Ride type (based on 2030 P&amp;R Plan)

MPLSCORR: Minneapolis travel corridor served by P&amp;R

STPCORR: St. Paul travel corridor served by P&amp;R

CLOSURE: 
            Blank = P&amp;R not planned for closure;
            Non-blank = P&amp;R planned or potentially planned for closure pending construction of listed facility

SIZECATG:
          0 = Park-and-pool or park-and-ride closing
          1 = P&amp;R's with 2030 capacity less than 150 spaces
          2 = P&amp;R's with 2030 capacity of 151-400 spaces
          3 = P&amp;R's with 2030 capacity of 400-800 spaces
          4 = P&amp;R's with 2030 capacity of greater than 800 spaces

CAPCT08: Actual P&amp;R capacity in 2008

CAPCT10: Actual P&amp;R capacity in 2010

FUNDEXP: Number of funded, new parking spaces

PLNEXP:  Number of planned, new parking spaces

TWAYEXPN: Number of planned, new parking spaces in facility along Transitway corridor

TOTEXPN: Total number of new parking spaces (FundExp+PlnExp+TwayExpn = TotExpn)

CLOSESPC: Number of parking spaces to be closed pending construction of new facility (negative value)

CAPCT30:  2030 Capacity (Capct10 + TotExpn + CloseSpc = Capct30)

PROVIDER: Transit provider serving P&amp;R facility

USE2008:  P&amp;R usage observed in September/October 2008 (# of vehicles parked)

USE2009:  P&amp;R usage observed in September/October 2009 (# of vehicles parked)

USE2010:  P&amp;R usage observed in September/October 2010 (# of vehicles parked)</eaover>
      <eadetcit>PR_PP: Park-and-pool or Park-and-Ride type (based on 2030 P&amp;R Plan):
          -Park-and-POOL = park-and-pool lot (no transit service at facility)
          -Park-and-Ride = Existing P&amp;R facility with no planned capacity expansion or closure.
          -Park-and-Ride- Expand = Existing P&amp;R facility with planned capacity expansion (and no
identified funding source)
          -Park-and-Ride Funded Expn = Existing P&amp;R facility with planned capacity expansion and
an identified funding source (e.g., CMAQ or other grant)
          -Park-and-Ride- Future = New P&amp;R facility with no identified funding source
          -Park-and-Ride New Funded = New P&amp;R facility with an identified funding source (e.g.,
CMAQ or other grant)
          -Park-and-Ride- To Close = Existing P&amp;R facility planned for closure pending construction
of new facility
          -Park-and-Ride- Tway = New P&amp;R facility along a Transitway corridor identified in 2030
TPP
          - Park-and-Ride- Tway Exp = Existing P&amp;R facility with planned capacity expansion along a
Transitway corridor identified in the 2030 TPP</eadetcit>
    </overview>
  </eainfo>
  <distinfo>
    <resdesc>ParkAndRideLots</resdesc>
    <distliab>NOTICE: The Geographic Information System (GIS) Data to which this notice is attached are made available pursuant to the Minnesota Government Data Practices Act (Minnesota Statutes Chapter 13). THE GIS DATA ARE PROVIDED TO YOU AS IS AND WITHOUT ANY WARRANTY AS TO THEIR PERFORMANCE, MERCHANTABILITY, OR FITNESS FOR ANY PARTICULAR PURPOSE. The GIS Data were developed by the Metropolitan Council for its own internal business purposes. The Metropolitan Council does not represent or warrant that the GIS Data or the data documentation are error-free, complete, current, or accurate. You are responsible for any consequences resulting from your use of the GIS Data or your reliance on the GIS Data. You should consult the data documentation for this particular GIS Data to determine the limitations of the GIS Data and the precision with which the GIS Data may depict distance, direction, location, or other geographic features. If you transmit or provide the GIS Data (or any portion of it) to another user, it is recommended that the GIS Data include a copy of this disclaimer and this metadata.</distliab>
    <stdorder>
      <digform>
        <digtinfo>
          <formname>ArcView Shape File</formname>
          <formvern>ArcGIS 9x</formvern>
          <transize>0.1 Meg. for zip file.</transize>
        </digtinfo>
      </digform>
      <ordering>See Online Linkage Below</ordering>
    </stdorder>
    <distrib>
      <cntinfo>
        <cntperp>
          <cntorg>Metropolitan Council</cntorg>
          <cntper>Jon Hoekenga</cntper>
        </cntperp>
        <cntpos>GIS System Administrator</cntpos>
        <cntaddr>
          <addrtype>mailing and physical</addrtype>
          <address>390 Robert Street North</address>
          <city>St. Paul</city>
          <state>MN</state>
          <postal>55101-1805</postal>
        </cntaddr>
        <cntvoice>651-602-1561</cntvoice>
        <cntemail>jonathan.hoekenga@metc.state.mn.us</cntemail>
      </cntinfo>
    </distrib>
  </distinfo>
  <metainfo>
    <metd>20150915</metd>
    <metstdn>Minnesota Geographic Metadata Guidelines</metstdn>
    <metstdv>1.2</metstdv>
    <metextns>
      <onlink>http://www.gis.state.mn.us/stds/metadata.htm</onlink>
    </metextns>
    <metc>
      <cntinfo>
        <cntperp>
          <cntorg>Metro Transit</cntorg>
          <cntper>Julie Quinn</cntper>
        </cntperp>
        <cntpos>Associate Planner</cntpos>
        <cntaddr>
          <addrtype>mailing and physical</addrtype>
          <address>560 6th Ave N</address>
          <city>Minneapolis</city>
          <state>MN</state>
          <postal>55411</postal>
        </cntaddr>
        <cntvoice>612-349-7333</cntvoice>
        <cntemail>julie.quinn@metc.state.mn.us</cntemail>
      </cntinfo>
    </metc>
  </metainfo>
  <Esri>
    <ModDate>20110721</ModDate>
    <ModTime>14581600</ModTime>
  </Esri>
  <mdDateSt Sync="TRUE">20110721</mdDateSt>
  <spref>
    <horizsys>
      <planar>
        <gridsys>
          <gridsysn>Universal Transverse Mercator</gridsysn>
          <utm>
            <utmzone>15</utmzone>
          </utm>
        </gridsys>
        <planci>
          <plandu>meters</plandu>
        </planci>
      </planar>
      <geodetic>
        <horizdn>NAD83</horizdn>
        <ellips>GRS80</ellips>
      </geodetic>
    </horizsys>
  </spref>
</metadata>
