<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><metadata><idinfo><citation><citeinfo><title>Park and Ride Lots</title><origin>Metro Transit</origin><pubinfo><publish>Metropolitan Council</publish></pubinfo><pubdate>periodically revised</pubdate><onlink>https://gisdata.mn.gov/dataset/us-mn-state-metc-trans-park-and-ride-lots</onlink></citeinfo></citation><descript><abstract>The Park-and-Ride layer contains the 196 existing and future park-and-ride lots in the Twin Cities Metropolitan area. 

The dataset was geocoded using TLG centerline streets. When specific site details were available, the geography was moved off the street lines to the actual lot locations using 2005 Markhurd orthophotography as a base layer. All attempts were made to correctly reflect the real lot locations; however, the positional accuracy of this data cannot be guaranteed. 

Attribute information is considered current to the metadata date and will be updated as needed.</abstract><purpose>To identify all park-and-ride locations in the Twin Cities metropolitan area.</purpose><supplinf>Twin Cities Metropolitan Area - including Minnesota Counties: Anoka, Carver, Chisago, Dakota, Goodhue, Hennepin, Isanti, Le Sueur, Mille Lacs, Ramsey, Rice, Scott, Sherburne, Stearns, Washington, Wright; Wisconsin Counties: Dunn, St. Croix</supplinf></descript><timeperd><timeinfo><sngdate><caldate>20160114</caldate></sngdate></timeinfo><current>Park-and-ride locations are accurate as of the Time Period of Content date for the Twin Cities Metropolitan Area.</current></timeperd><status><progress>Complete</progress><update>As needed</update></status><spdom><bounding><westbc>-94.581</westbc><eastbc>-91.719</eastbc><northbc>45.628</northbc><southbc>44.385</southbc></bounding></spdom><keywords><place><placekey>Twin Cities, Minnesota, Anoka County, Carver County, Chisago County, Dakota County, Goodhue County, Hennepin County, Isanti County, Le Sueur County, Mille Lacs County, Ramsey County, Rice County, Scott County, Sherburne County, Stearns County, Washington County, Wright County, Dunn County, St. Croix County</placekey></place><theme><themekey>Transit Centers, Transit Stops, Transit Routes, Transit Patterns by Node Segments, transit, buses, nodes, stops, transportation</themekey><themekt>None</themekt></theme></keywords><accconst>None</accconst><useconst>None</useconst><browse><browsen>ftp://ftp.gisdata.mn.gov/pub/gdrs/data/pub/us_mn_state_metc/trans_park_and_ride_lots/metadata/preview.jpg</browsen><browsed>Sample map showing the Park and Ride Lots layer.</browsed></browse><crossref><citeinfo><title>Transit Centers, Transit Stops, Transit Routes</title></citeinfo></crossref><native>ArcGIS 9x</native><ptcontac><cntinfo><cntperp><cntorg>Metropolitan Council - Metro Transit</cntorg><cntper>Pierce Canser</cntper></cntperp><cntpos>Planner</cntpos><cntaddr><address>560 6th Ave N</address><city>Minneapolis</city><state>MN</state><postal>55411</postal><addrtype>mailing and physical</addrtype></cntaddr><cntvoice>612.349.7404</cntvoice><cntemail>pierce.canser@metc.state.mn.us</cntemail></cntinfo></ptcontac></idinfo><dataqual><attracc><attraccr>Attributes are considered accurate. See the Entity and Attribute Overview for more details.</attraccr></attracc><logic>The dataset is topologically 'clean'.</logic><complete>All active park-and-rides in the metropolitan area are covered.</complete><posacc><horizpa><horizpar>Orthophotos were used in referencing the park-and-ride lot locations. Positional accuracy varies throughout the dataset. In some cases, locations outside the seven county metro area were located using NCompass Technologies Street Centerline and Address Ranges dataset where available and not have been referenced to aerial photos.</horizpar></horizpa></posacc></dataqual><spdoinfo><indspref>None</indspref><direct>Point</direct><mgmg3obj>Point</mgmg3obj><mgmg3til>One file for entire metro area.</mgmg3til></spdoinfo><eainfo><overview><eaover>PnRNum:   P&amp;R ID #. Same as "T Code" without the "T"

Old_PnRNum:  Former P&amp;R ID #, if applicable

TCode:  T Code (P&amp;R ID # with a "T" as the first character)

NAME:  Park-and-ride name

LocDetails:  Park-and-Ride location details (e.g., intersection, quadrant, portion of parking lot)

Address:  Park-and-Ride Address, if available
(Some park-and-rides are located within road right-of-way and do not have an address)

City:  City in which facility is located

Provider: Transit service provider at facility

Type:     PR = Park-and-Ride
PP = Park-and-Pool

ACTIVE:  1 = Active; 0 = Inactive

Status:  Current Facility Status  
Open = Facility is open for use
Closed = Facility is closed
Occasional = Facility is used seasonally or for special events only
Future = Possible future facility

OccasUse:  Description of occasional facility use

OverflwLot:  Facility is an overflow lot for another park-and-ride
 N = Not an overflow lot
 Y, &lt;Facility Name&gt; = Yes, an overflow lot for &lt;specified&gt; facility
 
CurrntTway:  Name of existing transitway serving facility

FutureTway:  Name of future transitway serving facility

Year_Est:  Year facility was established. May not be available for "historic" facilities

Year_Close:  Year facility was closed

CurrntCpct:  Current Capacity (field is updated as facility capacity increases or decreases)

PrkngType:  Parking Lot Type 
Surface = Surface parking lot 
Structured = Structured parking ramp
Surface &amp; Structured = Combination of parking in a structured ramp and surface lot

SharedUse:  Y = Parking is shared use with another use; N = Parking is not shared with another use

ShrUseDesc:  Description of shared or complementary use

BikePrkng: Bike Parking Present
Y = Yes
N = No
Blank = Future Facility, Historic Facility, or Unknown

EVChrgeStn:  Electric Vehicle Charging Station(s) Present
Y = Yes
N = No
Blank = Future Facility, Historic Facility, or Unknown

ShelterSA:  Standalone Transit Shelter Present
Y = Yes
N = No
Blank = Future Facility, Historic Facility, or Unknown

IndoorWt:  Indoor Waiting Area Present
Y = Yes
N = No
Blank = Future Facility, Historic Facility, or Unknown

LghtPrkng:  Lights in the Parking Area Present
Y = Yes 
N = No
Blank = Future Facility, Historic Facility, or Unknown

DropOff:  Designated Drop-Off Area ("Kiss &amp; Ride") Present
Y = Yes
N = No
Blank = Future Facility, Historic Facility, or Unknown

Bench_SA:  Stand Alone Bench Present
Y = Yes
N = No 
Blank = Future Facility, Historic Facility, or Unknown

TrashRec:  Trash Receptacle Bench Present
Y = Yes
N = No
Blank = Future Facility, Historic Facility, or Unknown

PblicRest:  Public Restroom Present
Y = Yes
N = No
Blank = Future Facility, Historic Facility, or Unknown

OpRestrm:  Operator Restroom Present
Y = Yes
N = No
Blank = Future Facility, Historic Facility, or Unknown

Elevator:  Elevator Present
Y = Yes
N = No
Blank = Future Facility, Historic Facility, or Unknown

Escalator:  Escalator Present
Y = Yes
N = No
Blank = Future Facility, Historic Facility, or Unknown

Mpls_Corr:   Downtown Minneapolis express bus corridor served by park-and-ride

Stp_Corr:  Downtown St. Paul express bus corridor served by park-and-ride

LandOwn:  Owner of land on which facility is located (facility owner may be different)

FcltyOwn:  Owner of transit facility (may be different from land owner)

Leased: Y = Facility is leased from another owner; N = facility is not leased

PrPlCapc08:  2030 Park-and-Ride Plan - park-and-ride 2008 "base year" capacity

PrPlCapc30:  2030 Park-and-Ride Plan - park-and-ride 2030 planned capacity

PrPlRec:  2030 Park-and-Ride Plan Facility Status in Chapter 3 :
Existing Facility - Park-and-Ride = Existing park-and-rides at the time the Plan was developed
Existing Facility - Park-and-POOL =  Existing park-and-pools at the time the Plan was developed
Park-and-Ride - Expand =  Existing facilities planned for expansion with no funding identified
Park-and-Ride - Funded Expn = Existing facilities planned for expansion with funding identified
Park-and-Ride - Future =  Planned future facility with no funding identified
Park-and-Ride - New Funded = Planned future facility with funding identified
Park-and-Ride - To Close =  Facility will close upon construction or expansion of a different facility
Park-and-Ride - Tway = Park-and-Ride = Planned future facility to be constructed as part of a transitway project
Park-and-Ride - Tway Exp = Existing facilities planned for expansion as part of a transitway project

Notes:  Facility notes about capacity corrections, expansion, closure notes and other miscellaneous information




</eaover><eadetcit>PR_PP: Park-and-pool or Park-and-Ride type (based on 2030 P&amp;R Plan): 
-Park-and-POOL = park-and-pool lot (no transit service at facility) 
-Park-and-Ride = Existing P&amp;R facility with no planned capacity expansion or closure. 
-Park-and-Ride- Expand = Existing P&amp;R facility with planned capacity expansion (and no 
identified funding source) 
-Park-and-Ride Funded Expn = Existing P&amp;R facility with planned capacity expansion and 
an identified funding source (e.g., CMAQ or other grant) 
-Park-and-Ride- Future = New P&amp;R facility with no identified funding source 
-Park-and-Ride New Funded = New P&amp;R facility with an identified funding source (e.g., 
CMAQ or other grant) 
-Park-and-Ride- To Close = Existing P&amp;R facility planned for closure pending construction 
of new facility 
-Park-and-Ride- Tway = New P&amp;R facility along a Transitway corridor identified in 2030 
TPP 
- Park-and-Ride- Tway Exp = Existing P&amp;R facility with planned capacity expansion along a 
Transitway corridor identified in the 2030 TPP
</eadetcit></overview></eainfo><distinfo><resdesc>ParkAndRideLots</resdesc><distliab>NOTICE: The Geographic Information System (GIS) Data to which this notice is attached are made available pursuant to the Minnesota Government Data Practices Act (Minnesota Statutes Chapter 13). THE GIS DATA ARE PROVIDED TO YOU AS IS AND WITHOUT ANY WARRANTY AS TO THEIR PERFORMANCE, MERCHANTABILITY, OR FITNESS FOR ANY PARTICULAR PURPOSE. The GIS Data were developed by the Metropolitan Council for its own internal business purposes. The Metropolitan Council does not represent or warrant that the GIS Data or the data documentation are error-free, complete, current, or accurate. You are responsible for any consequences resulting from your use of the GIS Data or your reliance on the GIS Data. You should consult the data documentation for this particular GIS Data to determine the limitations of the GIS Data and the precision with which the GIS Data may depict distance, direction, location, or other geographic features. If you transmit or provide the GIS Data (or any portion of it) to another user, it is recommended that the GIS Data include a copy of this disclaimer and this metadata.</distliab><stdorder><digform><digtinfo><formname>ArcView Shape File</formname><formvern>ArcGIS 9x</formvern><transize>0.1 Meg. for zip file.</transize></digtinfo></digform><ordering>See Online Linkage Below</ordering></stdorder><distrib><cntinfo><cntperp><cntorg>Metropolitan Council - Metro Transit</cntorg><cntper>Pierce Canser</cntper></cntperp><cntpos>Planner</cntpos><cntaddr><address>560 6th Ave N</address><city>Minneapolis</city><state>MN</state><postal>55411</postal><addrtype>mailing and physical</addrtype></cntaddr><cntvoice>612.349.7404</cntvoice><cntemail>pierce.canser@metc.state.mn.us</cntemail></cntinfo></distrib></distinfo><metainfo><metd>20160114</metd><metstdn>Minnesota Geographic Metadata Guidelines</metstdn><metstdv>1.2</metstdv><metextns><onlink>http://www.gis.state.mn.us/stds/metadata.htm</onlink></metextns><metc><cntinfo><cntperp><cntorg>Metropolitan Council - Metro Transit</cntorg><cntper>Pierce Canser</cntper></cntperp><cntpos>Planner</cntpos><cntaddr><address>560 6th Ave N</address><city>Minneapolis</city><state>MN</state><postal>55411</postal><addrtype>mailing and physical</addrtype></cntaddr><cntvoice>612.349.7404</cntvoice><cntemail>pierce.canser@metc.state.mn.us</cntemail></cntinfo></metc></metainfo><Esri><ModDate>20110721</ModDate><ModTime>14581600</ModTime></Esri><mdDateSt Sync="TRUE">20110721</mdDateSt><spref><horizsys><planar><gridsys><gridsysn>Universal Transverse Mercator</gridsysn><utm><utmzone>15</utmzone></utm></gridsys><planci><plandu>meters</plandu></planci></planar><geodetic><horizdn>NAD83</horizdn><ellips>GRS80</ellips></geodetic></horizsys></spref></metadata>