<metadata>
  <idinfo>
    <citation>
      <citeinfo>
        <origin>Metropolitan Council and NCompass Technologies (NCT) </origin>
        <title>Census Geography 2010 - Realigned; Block, BlockGroup &amp; Tract</title>
        <pubinfo>
          <publish>Metropolitan Council</publish>
        </pubinfo>
        <pubdate>20130415</pubdate>
        <onlink>https://gisdata.mn.gov/dataset/us-mn-state-metc-society-census2010realign</onlink>
      </citeinfo>
    </citation>
    <descript>
      <abstract>NCompass Technologies, under contract with Metropolitan Council, created a 2010 Census Bureau block polygon dataset for the Twin Cities Metropolitan Area (Anoka, Carver, Dakota, Hennepin, Ramsey, Scott and Washington Counties). This dataset is coincident with and developed using the NCT Street Centerline and Landmarks databases where 2010 block boundaries fall on those features. For those block boundaries that are defined by features not included in NCT databases, NCT used other digital resources to generate these boundaries, such as orthophotography or additional features from city and county GIS databases. NCT used it's best judgement to digitize block boundaries when the block boundaries followed nonvisible features or street extensions.  Polygon centroid points were also generated by the Metropolitan Council for blocks, block groups and tracts (Census2010RealignBlockGroupPoints, Census2010RealignBlockPoints, Census2010RealignTractPoints). </abstract>
      <purpose>The dataset was developed to have a 2010 census block database that is aligned to the NCT street centerlines and landmarks files, for use in analysis which utilizes both the census data and NCT street centerlines/landmarks. Blockgroup and tract datasets have been dissolved from the block dataset. Additionally, since NCT's street centerline dataset is aligned within county rights-of-way for these counties, this dataset allows for improved parcel based analysis as it may pertain to census blocks, block groups and tracts.

This dataset was developed for use in a variety of GIS applications like census data analysis.</purpose>
      <supplinf>Twin Cities 7 county metropolitan area.  This includes the counties of Anoka, Carver, Dakota, Hennepin, Ramsey, Scott and Washington.</supplinf>
    </descript>
    <crossref>
      <citeinfo>
        <title>NCompass Street Centerlines, NCompass Landmarks, Census2010RealignBlockGroupPoints, Census2010RealignBlockPoints, Census2010RealignTractPoints</title>
      </citeinfo>
    </crossref>
    <timeperd>
      <current>2010 Census. Adjustment 3/20/2013. </current>
      <timeinfo>
        <sngdate>
          <caldate>20100401</caldate>
        </sngdate>
      </timeinfo>
    </timeperd>
    <status>
      <progress>Complete</progress>
      <update>None Planned</update>
    </status>
    <spdom>
      <bounding>
        <westbc>-94.012</westbc>
        <eastbc>-92.732</eastbc>
        <northbc>45.415</northbc>
        <southbc>44.471</southbc>
      </bounding>
    </spdom>
    <keywords>
      <place>
        <placekey>Twin Cities, Anoka County, Carver County, Dakota County, Hennepin County, Ramsey County, Scott County, Washington County</placekey>
      </place>
      <theme>
        <themekey>census, demographics, TIGER, blocks, block, block groups, block group, tracts, tract </themekey>
      </theme>
    </keywords>
    <accconst>None</accconst>
    <useconst>None</useconst>
    <ptcontac>
      <cntinfo>
        <cntperp>
          <cntorg>Metropolitan Council</cntorg>
          <cntper>Tanya Mayer</cntper>
        </cntperp>
        <cntpos>GIS Specialist</cntpos>
        <cntaddr>
          <addrtype>mailing and physical</addrtype>
          <address>390 Robert Street North</address>
          <city>St. Paul</city>
          <state>MN</state>
          <postal>55101-1805</postal>
        </cntaddr>
        <cntvoice>651.602.1604</cntvoice>
        <cntemail>tanya.mayer@metc.state.mn.us</cntemail>
      </cntinfo>
    </ptcontac>
  </idinfo>
  <dataqual>
    <logic>The dataset is topologically 'clean'. </logic>
    <complete>Entire seven county geographic area is covered. </complete>
    <posacc>
      <horizpa>
        <horizpar>The positional accuracy of the dataset has not been tested under the National Standards for Spatial Data Accuracy.</horizpar>
      </horizpa>
      <vertacc>
        <vertaccr>Not applicable </vertaccr>
      </vertacc>
    </posacc>
    <lineage>
      <procstep>
        <procdesc>Sources used in the development of the data include NCT GBF street centerlines, NCT lines of interest, NCT Areas of interest; and Metropolitan Council provided municipal boundaries and parcel based school district boundaries. 

Datasets used as reference include 2010 Census TIGER/Line files, 2010 NCT Census blocks, licensed Metropolitan Council 2010 Digital Orthophotography for the seven county metro area, and licensed county parcel data. 

NCompass Technologies aligned Census Blocks to their street centerline file. When Census block boundaries were not streets but MCD boundaries, they aligned them to our MCD file (available on Data Finder) and if they were school district boundaries they followed the SD boundaries we dissolved from the county parcel data. If the Census geography was so completely different that it affected the Census block boundary topology to follow our MCD or SD boundaries, they used the TIGER alignment. They used the parcel boundaries as a guide when needed, and used the aerial photography for other visible physical features for Census block boundaries (like water features, railroads, etc.). There were also times when the TIGER Census geography was not reality at all, and if a block did not really exist and had no population assigned to it, it was not included in the file. Sometimes there were multiple polygons that create a block in reality, so there is a list of Census blocks with multiple polygons. This is important if you plan to sum up any census data based on the geography file (it would count those blocks more than once). 

***The positional accuracy of TIGER features that follow non-visible features, such as municipal boundaries, school district boundaries or other political boundaries is, in some locations, significantly off or just wrong; especially in relationship to visible features, such as roads. This posed difficult challenges to improve the block boundaries to more accurate sources while maintaining the block topology created by the TIGER features. NCT and MC staff used their best judgment to decide the best solution for those block boundaries representing those situations. At times this resulted in 1) eliminating a block completely, 2) causing multiple polygon blocks, 3) the need for following a non-visible parcel boundary that best represented the TIGER feature location, or 4) simply using the TIGER feature alignment as the best solution.

LINEAGE FROM NCompass Technologies 

TIGER/Line 2010 Census Files using NCT based features - 
Processing Documentation 

Several macros and menus have been created to automate repetitive tasks and expedite manual processing. 

&lt;coun&gt; is used to specify the first 4 letters of the county name 

Step 1- Import TIGER files 
Move all files from county directory on CD (Tiger 2010 data, 7/1/2012, Met Council) to local directory 
import covers and info files 
separate feature classes so we know what line types delineate the blocks 
Specific block boundary arc files: 
- counblkarcs (all boundary arcs) 
- counblkext (nonvisable extensions of an existing feature) 
- counblkfence (fence lines) 
- counblkinvis (invisible features) 
- counblkmun (munics boundaries) 
- counblkprop (property lines) 
- counblkrds (roads) 
- counblkprr (railroads) 
- counblkschdis (schooldist) 
- counblkwater (water- rivers, streams, ponds, lakes) 

clip .tiff parcels into quads to allow quick drawing in AE 

Step 2- Alignment of features 
Edit UTM projected coverages 

*To expedite the process, only adjust features that delineate a block boundary. 
-speeds process and ensures that our features are geographically correct 

1. Data sources 
a. DOQ in both Tiff world and Mr. SID format 
b. County supplied parcels 
c. MCD Boundaries 2010 from Met Council 
d. School district boundaries 2010, same as provided to create census boundaries 
2. Covers to adjust, and source 
a. Individual road centerline files to county parcels and DOQs 
b. Geoareas to county parcels and DOQs 
c. Linear to county parcels and DOQs 
d. Munics to MCD boundaries 
e. County to MCD boundaries 

Step 3- Assemble NCT and Other Supplied Lines 
- Project roads, linear, and Geoareas, clip these with the county boundary 
- Use separated feature covers (from Step1) to select the appropriate linear, geoareas, munics and school district boundaries that make up block boundaries. 
- display DOQs 
- display different TIGER line types and parcels (colors pre set) 
- put selected geoareas and linear arcs to individual files. 

Step 4- Create block relationship files, and Calculate 2010 Block and Tract Values through a Relate 
Create of block relationship files: 
1. Copy and paste 2010 data table from Census web page to a new .txt file. 
2. Convert to .dbf file, data in columns 3, 4, 5, 10 is text, the rest is number format 
3. In Excel add the following headings: ST90, CO90, CT90, BLK90, PART90, ST00, CO00, CT00, BLK00, PART00 
4. Convert to info file into the COUN_census/COUN_tgr/ directory called COUN90_00 

Relate created, relate called RELATE is saved in relate info file called censusrelates 
Selects features through relate, calculate ALL00 = to ALL00 from 9_0relate1to1 info file 
Puts features to new cover in coun_tgr directory 
Projects and builds cover from SPTCMA83 to UTM 

Step 5- Combining Points and Placing Them into Linear Features 
(Continuation of above step) 
Macro continues to assembles linear features and places them into same coverage as points, so when built polygons with label points will be created. 

Step 6- Moving Points to Create Proper Polygons 
Bring up edit cover, backcovers, and menus for editing. 
Select and copy points to make sure attributes are in each poly once it is built. Utilize back covers unique symbology for each feature type to determine TIGER's intended boundary, or to see the 2010 block if available. 

Step 7- Building Polygons and Checking for Errors 
Make 4 separate checks before converting covers to shapefiles for final visual checks. 
- The first step checks for blocks that do not contain a point. 
- Second checks for block polys present in the TIGER file, but not in the dissolved %.coun%work file. 
- Third checks for tract polys present in the TIGER file, but not in the dissolved %.coun%work file 
- Fourth is a check for polygons present in the dissolved %.coun%work file, but not in the TIGER file. 
Finally the macro outputs nine shapefiles (see next step for names) for visual checks. 

Step 8- Setup ArcView Project to Begin Visual Checks 
In Arc View, bring up new project and view. Add the first 5 of the following themes and classify as follows: 
- NCT block lines - single symbol, 1pt solid line 
- TIGER block group lines - single symbol, 3pt dashed line 
- TIGER block lines - single symbol, thin (.1) solid line, contrasting color 
- Intersected polygons - unique value, classify field SAME, red fill, no outline 
- NCT block group polygons - unique value, classify field blockgroup, your choice of color schemes 
- TIGER block polygons (reference if necessary) 
- TIGER Tract lines (reference if necessary) 
- NCT block polygons (reference if necessary) 
- NCT tracts as polygons (reference if necessary) 

With the intrsct theme, classify the N (different blk00) blocks to RED with NO OUTLINE and the Y blocks to NO FILL and NO OUTLINE. 

Step 9- Append 7 Counties using ArcTools. Fixed any fixable overlap/gaps using Topology Editor. 

Step 10- Packaging and Sending Out 
Drop and calculate items and export cover to geodatabase 

LINEAGE FROM THE METROPOLITAN COUNCIL 
NCT delivered one county tile at a time. Metropolitan Council staff ran independent checks to account for all blocks, block groups and tracts. Then developed with NCT a list of any missing blocks, verifying zero population, and added to the list any blocks, block groups or tracts of more than one polygon, verifying that there were no errors in the block geography causing the multiple polygons. Council staff then visually checked each tile for block boundary errors. NCT fixed errors as needed and resent final county tiles.

After the final seven edgematched tiles were received and accepted from NCT, NCT created a final region wide geodatabase of blocks, block groups and tracts.  MC staff added and modified attribute fields with in each tile layer to match other Census files.

******** IMPORTANT ***********
CHALLENGES/PROBLEMS and SOLUTIONS 

1) Census feature alignment to DOQs/Parcel data - Although technically outside the scope of work for this contract this phase took us much longer than expected. In most cases our roads were within the right of way, but we took this opportunity to do some fine tuning that we otherwise might not have done. Alignment of Area and Linear features to the DOQs was very helpful in making our features much closer to how they actually are; unfortunately this process was also time consuming and at times created difficulties in replicating the TIGER census blocks since there are differing levels of accuracy in the TIGER data. 

2) Process of determining proper block geography - Correlating TIGER Geography with ours sometimes caused big headaches. Often times TIGER creates blocks using features that are either nonexistent, or whose locations are just incorrect. Initially these problems were very aggravating, but we were able to work through many of them with The Council and come up with solutions that would work on a systematic basis with these recurring issues. 

Met Council Note: ***The positional accuracy of TIGER features that follow non-visible features, such as municipal boundaries, school district boundaries or other political boundaries is, in some locations, significantly off or just wrong; especially in relationship to visible features, such as roads.   This posed difficult challenges to improve the block boundaries to more accurate sources while maintaining the block topology created by the TIGER features.   NCT and MC staff used their best judgment to decide the best solution for those block boundaries representing those situations.  At times this resulted in 1) eliminating a block completely, 2) causing multiple polygon blocks, 3) the need for following a non-visible parcel boundary that best represented the TIGER feature location, or 4) simply using the TIGER feature alignment as the best solution.  

3) Timing - We had difficulty completing the first few tiles on the specified dates due to a variety of problems including extra time spent aligning features, and an underestimation of the time it would take to complete the manual processing. A revised time schedule was worked out. 


</procdesc>
      </procstep>
    </lineage>
  </dataqual>
  <distinfo>
    <distliab>NOTICE:  The Geographic Information System (GIS) Data to which this notice is attached are made available pursuant to the Minnesota Government Data Practices Act (Minnesota Statutes Chapter 13).  THE GIS DATA ARE PROVIDED TO YOU AS IS AND WITHOUT ANY WARRANTY AS TO THEIR PERFORMANCE, MERCHANTABILITY, OR FITNESS FOR ANY PARTICULAR PURPOSE.  The GIS Data were developed by the Metropolitan Council for its own internal business purposes.  The Metropolitan Council does not represent or warrant that the GIS Data or the data documentation are error-free, complete, current, or accurate.  You are responsible for any consequences resulting from your use of the GIS Data or your reliance on the GIS Data.  You should consult the data documentation for this particular GIS Data to determine the limitations of the GIS Data and the precision with which the GIS Data may depict distance, direction, location, or other geographic features.  If you transmit or provide the GIS Data (or any portion of it) to another user, it is recommended that the GIS Data include a copy of this disclaimer and this metadata.</distliab>
    <stdorder>
      <ordering>See Online Linkage Below</ordering>
    </stdorder>
    <distrib>
      <cntinfo>
        <cntperp>
          <cntorg>Metropolitan Council</cntorg>
          <cntper>Tanya Mayer</cntper>
        </cntperp>
        <cntpos>GIS Specialist</cntpos>
        <cntaddr>
          <addrtype>mailing and physical</addrtype>
          <address>390 Robert Street North</address>
          <city>St. Paul</city>
          <state>MN</state>
          <postal>55101-1805</postal>
        </cntaddr>
        <cntvoice>651.602.1604</cntvoice>
        <cntemail>tanya.mayer@metc.state.mn.us</cntemail>
      </cntinfo>
    </distrib>
  </distinfo>
  <metainfo>
    <metd>20130415</metd>
    <metstdn>Minnesota Geographic Metadata Guidelines</metstdn>
    <metstdv>1.2</metstdv>
    <metextns>
      <onlink>http://www.mngeo.state.mn.us/committee/standards/mgmg/metadata.htm</onlink>
    </metextns>
    <metc>
      <cntinfo>
        <cntperp>
          <cntorg>Metropolitan Council</cntorg>
          <cntper>Tanya Mayer</cntper>
        </cntperp>
        <cntpos>GIS Specialist</cntpos>
        <cntaddr>
          <addrtype>mailing and physical</addrtype>
          <address>390 Robert Street North</address>
          <city>St. Paul</city>
          <state>MN</state>
          <postal>55101-1805</postal>
        </cntaddr>
        <cntvoice>651.602.1604</cntvoice>
        <cntemail>tanya.mayer@metc.state.mn.us</cntemail>
      </cntinfo>
    </metc>
  </metainfo>
  <eainfo>
    <overview>
      <eaover>Polygon and Point attributes for the all delivered Geodatabases: 
[Metro Area Published]
- Census2010RealignTract
- Census2010RealignBlockGroup
- Census2010RealignBlock
- Census2010RealignBlockGroupPoints
- Census2010RealignBlockPoints
- Census2010RealignTractPoints

****IMPORTANT NOTE*****
MISSING CENSUS BLOCKS; BLOCKS, BLOCK GROUPS, TRACTS WITH MULTIPLE POLYGONS are listed in this &lt;a href="Census2010RealignNotes.xlsx" target=_blank&gt;Excel Spreadsheet &lt;/a&gt;
************************
  
Census2010RealignTract 
********************  
TRACT:      Census Tract; Number; e.g. 50109  
  
STATE:      2 digit FIPS standard state code; String; e.g. 27

CO:         3 digit FIPS and state standard county code; String; e.g. 163, 003 
  
TRACTCE10:  6 digit Census Tract code with leading 0s; String; e.g. 050109

GEOID: 	11 digit Census Tract string preceded with State, County codes; String; e.g. 27003050109

ALAND10:    Census 2010 Provided Land Area for geographic unit in square meters - use this for consistency with TIGER

AWATER10:   Census 2010 Provided Water Area for geographic unit in square meters - use this for consistency with TIGER

SHAPE_AREA: Area of the polygon in square meters 

  
Census2010RealignBlockGroup
*************************
BLOCKGROUP: 7 digit Census Block Group (Tract + 1st number of the block  
            code); Number; e.g. 501092
  
STATE:      2 digit FIPS standard state code; String; e.g. 27

CO:         3 digit FIPS and state standard county code; String; e.g. 163, 003 
  
TRACT:	6 digit Census Tract code with leading 0s; String; e.g. 050109

BLKGRPCE10: 7 digit Census Block Group code with leading 0s; String; e.g. 0501092

GEOID: 	12 digit Census Block Group string preceded with State, County codes; String; e.g. 270030501092

ALAND10:    Census 2010 Provided Land Area for geographic unit in square meters - use this for consistency with TIGER

AWATER10:   Census 2010 Provided Water Area for geographic unit in square meters - use this for consistency with TIGER

SHAPE_AREA: Area of the polygon in square meters 
  
Census2010RealignBlock
********************  
BLK00:      15 digit block code includes STATE, CO, TRACT &amp; BLOCK; String; e.g. 270030501092011 
  
STATE:      2 digit FIPS standard state code; Integer; e.g. 27 
  
CO:         3 digit FIPS and state standard county code; String; e.g. 163, 003 
  
TRACT:      6 digit Census Tract with leading 0s; String; e.g. 050109   
  
BLOCK:      4 digit Census Block code; String; e.g. 2011  
  
BLOCKGROUP: 7 digit Census Block Group (Tract + 1st number of the block code); Number; e.g. 501092  

ALAND10:    Census 2010 Provided Land Area for geographic unit in square meters - use this for consistency with TIGER

AWATER10:   Census 2010 Provided Water Area for geographic unit in square meters - use this for consistency with TIGER

SHAPE_AREA:       Area of the polygon in square meters 
</eaover>
      <eadetcit>https://www.census.gov/geo/maps-data/data/tiger-line.html

Census 2010 TIGER/Line Technical Documentation and Metadata </eadetcit>
    </overview>
  </eainfo>
  <spref>
    <horizsys>
      <planar>
        <gridsys>
          <gridsysn>Universal Transverse Mercator</gridsysn>
          <utm>
            <utmzone>15</utmzone>
          </utm>
        </gridsys>
        <planci>
          <plandu>meters</plandu>
        </planci>
      </planar>
      <geodetic>
        <horizdn>NAD83</horizdn>
        <ellips>GRS80</ellips>
      </geodetic>
    </horizsys>
  </spref>
</metadata>
