<?xml version="1.0"?><!--  <!DOCTYPE metadata SYSTEM "metadata.dtd">  --><metadata><idinfo><citation><citeinfo><origin>Minnesota Geological Survey </origin><pubdate>1995</pubdate><title>Quaternary Geology - Southwestern Minnesota (Part A)</title><mgmg1cid></mgmg1cid><pubinfo><publish>Minnesota Geological Survey</publish></pubinfo><onlink>http://conservancy.umn.edu/handle/11299/59763</onlink></citeinfo></citation><descript><abstract>A County Geologic Atlas is a systematic study of a county's geologic and ground water resources. Geologic studies include both near-surface deposits and bedrock.  Ground water studies include flow systems, aquifer capacity, and ground water chemistry.  In some areas sand and gravel deposits, sinkholes, or other features are studied.  Interpretation of sensitivity to pollution is also part of an atlas.  The information is organized, analyzed, and displayed using geographic information technology.

A Regional Hydrogeologic Assessment (RHA) is similar to a County Geologic Atlas in that both geology and ground water are studied.  However, a Regional Hydrogeologic Assessment covers a larger area, typically four to nine counties, in less detail.  The  RHA emphasizes near-surface geologic, ground water, and pollution sensitivity mapping.</abstract><purpose>County Geologic Atlas and Regional Hydrogeologic Assessment information is used in planning and environmental protection efforts at all levels of government.  Wellhead protection and well-sealing programs are examples of local programs that need geologic and ground water information. The information is also used by businesses and the general public.</purpose><supplinf>Southwestern Minnesota.  Murray, Nobles, Pipestone, Rock Counties.  Portions of Cottonwood, Jackson, Lincoln, Lyon, Redwood Counties.</supplinf></descript><timeperd><timeinfo><sngdate><caldate>21995</caldate></sngdate></timeinfo><current>Duration of Study, approx. two years; published in 1995. Content reflects the geologic information available at the time of study (1993-1995).</current></timeperd><status><progress>Complete</progress><update>None Planned</update></status><keywords><theme><themekt>ISO 19115 Topic Category</themekt><themekey>geoscientificInformation, Geology, Surficial Geology, Quaternary Stratigraphy,  Regional Hydrogeologic Assessment</themekey></theme><place><placekey>Minnesota, MN, Southwestern Minnesota. Counties of Cottonwood, Jackson, Lincoln, Lyon, Murray, Nobles, Pipestone, Redwood, Rock.</placekey></place></keywords><accconst>None</accconst><useconst>Credit to Minnesota Geological Survey for use of data in map products.</useconst><browse><browsen>None available</browsen></browse><native>ArcGIS</native><crossref><citeinfo><title>Paper Report: RHA-2, Part. A. Setterholm, D.R., project manager, Quaternary geology--Southwestern Minnesota: 1995: Scale: 1:200,000. 2 plates. Plate 1: Surficial geology; Plate 2: Quaternary stratigraphy. $30.00. Paper map and report are available from MGS Map Sales Office (2609 Territorial Road, St. Paul, Minnesota, 55114, 612-626-2969.)  

RHA-2, Part B, Hydrogeology, is available from the MGS Map Sales Office (paper report). Digital data is available from the Minnesota Department of Natural Resources Ground Water Mapping Unit:
http://www.dnr.state.mn.us/waters/groundwater_section/mapping/index.html

For the U of M Libraries Digital Conservancy listing of map products see: http://conservancy.umn.edu/handle/11299/708</title></citeinfo></crossref><spdom><bounding><westbc>-96.5</westbc><eastbc>-95.4</eastbc><northbc>44.4</northbc><southbc>43.5</southbc></bounding></spdom><ptcontac><cntinfo><cntperp><cntorg>Minnesota Geological Survey</cntorg><cntper>Dale R. Setterholm</cntper></cntperp><cntpos>Associate Director</cntpos><cntaddr><addrtype>Mailing and Physical</addrtype><address>2609 Territorial Road</address><city>St. Paul</city><state>MN</state><postal>55114</postal></cntaddr><cntvoice>612-626-5119</cntvoice><cntemail>sette001@umn.edu</cntemail></cntinfo></ptcontac></idinfo><dataqual><lineage><srcinfo><srcscale>200000</srcscale></srcinfo><procstep><procdesc>Investigations begin with a review of existing information, such as earlier geologic maps, soil maps, and hydrologic reports. Drillers send water well logs to the Minnesota Geological Survey, where they are reviewed, interpreted, and entered into the County Well Index (CWI), an interactive data base of water-well information.  Building on the previous data, field studies are conducted to improve the understanding of local geologic and hydrologic conditions. Linework is created based upon the field studies and base data, and digitized.  Background GIS data layers such as roads, surface hydrography, township grids, etc., are obtained from various sources. 

All coverages were converted from single precision, UTM zone 15 - shifted, NAD27 to double precision, UTM zone 15, unshifted NAD83 in February of 2008.</procdesc></procstep></lineage><posacc><horizpa><horizpar>Not available</horizpar></horizpa></posacc><attracc><attraccr>Not available</attraccr></attracc><logic>Not available</logic><complete>Not available</complete></dataqual><spdoinfo><indspref></indspref><direct>Vector</direct><mgmg3obj>Point, Vector</mgmg3obj><mgmg3til>Traverse-Grant Study Area</mgmg3til></spdoinfo><eainfo><overview><eadetcit>Not available</eadetcit><eaover>Minnesota Geological Survey - Southwestern Minnesota Regional Assessment; RHA-2 - GIS data base. 1996

This index lists the significant covers used in the generatation of the plates for the Southwestern Minnesota Regional Assessment. Digital work was performed from summer of 1993 - winter 1995.

The cover names include an identifing prefix of sw.

Base layers (except township) modified from TIGER census data.  Surficial geology linework by Carrie Patterson &amp; other MGS staff with digital editing &amp; cleanup by MGS GIS staff.

All coverages were converted from single precision, UTM zone 15 - shifted, NAD27 to double precision, UTM zone 15, unshifted NAD83 in February of 2008.


Base layers:
 
swpgpa	 =  polygon cover of the project area
swpglk 	 =  modified polygon cover of lakes
swlnhy 	 =  line cover of rivers
swlnrd 	 =  line cover of major highways, also points for hiway symbols
swpgco 	 =  polygon cover of county outlines
swpgmcd  =  polygon cover of township-range grid
swptll	 =  point cover for latitude-longitude tics


Surficial Geology:

swpgsg   =  polygon cover of surficial geology units
swlnsg   =  line cover of surficial geology linear features
swptrs   =  point cover of sand and gravel pits and quarries
swptp1   =  point cover of Giddings, outcrop, cuttings and bucket auger sites 
swlngp   =  line/point cover of seismic lines and because they are so small
                  at map scale a point to identify as a marker symbol on map 


Bedrock topography and Drift Thickness:

swptbt  =  point cover of bedrock control locations from drilling logs
swlnbt  =  line cover of bedrock topographic contours
           (derived from generating a grid (POINTGRID) from the bedrock control 
           points, converting those grid points to an arc cover (GRIDARC). 
           Dale Setterholm then interpreted the contours and edited them by hand
           to create the final bedrock topography linework, which was then digitized
           for this coverage.
</eaover></overview></eainfo><distinfo><resdesc>RHA-2A (http://conservancy.umn.edu/handle/11299/59763)</resdesc><stdorder><digform><digtinfo><formname>Arc Export, shapefiles</formname><formvern></formvern><transize>14.0 MB</transize></digtinfo></digform><ordering>Digital data and PDF files representing map plates are available for download from the University of Minnesota Libraries Digital Conservancy. All digital data for RHA-2A is provided in the "Supplementary Files" download. The direct Digital Conservancy Link to this product is http://conservancy.umn.edu/handle/11299/59763

To obtain the digital data on DVD, or to obtain paper copies of the geologic map plates, contact the MGS Map Sales Office at 612-626-2969.</ordering></stdorder><distrib><cntinfo><cntperp><cntorg>Minnesota Geological Survey</cntorg><cntper>Timothy E. Wahl</cntper></cntperp><cntpos>Geologic Information Systems</cntpos><cntaddr><addrtype>mailing and physical</addrtype><address>2609 Territorial Road</address><city>St. Paul</city><state>MN</state><postal>55114</postal></cntaddr><cntvoice>612-626-0992</cntvoice><cntemail>tewahl@umn.edu</cntemail></cntinfo></distrib></distinfo><metainfo><metd>20150418</metd><metstdn>Minnesota Geographic Metadata Guidelines</metstdn><metstdv>1.2</metstdv><metextns><onlink>http://www.mngeo.state.mn.us/committee/standards/mgmg/metadata.htm
</onlink></metextns><metc><cntinfo><cntperp><cntorg>Minnesota Geospatial Information Office (MnGeo)</cntorg><cntper>Nancy Rader</cntper></cntperp><cntpos>GIS Data Coordinator</cntpos><cntaddr><addrtype>mailing and physical</addrtype><address>658 Cedar Street</address><city>St. Paul</city><state>MN</state><postal>55155</postal></cntaddr><cntvoice>651-201-2489</cntvoice><cntemail>gisinfo.mngeo@state.mn.us</cntemail></cntinfo></metc></metainfo><spref><horizsys><planar><gridsys><gridsysn>Universal Transverse Mercator</gridsysn><utm><utmzone>15E</utmzone></utm></gridsys><planci><plandu>meters</plandu></planci></planar><geodetic><horizdn>NAD83</horizdn><ellips>GRS80</ellips></geodetic></horizsys></spref></metadata>