<?xml version="1.0"?><metadata><idinfo><citation><citeinfo><origin>Counties of Anoka, Carver, Dakota, Hennepin, Ramsey, Scott and Washington</origin><pubdate>200401</pubdate><title>MetroGIS Regional Parcel Dataset (Year End 2003) </title><mgmg1cid>N/A</mgmg1cid><pubinfo><publish>The Metropolitan Council and the Counties of Anoka, Carver, Dakota, Hennepin, Ramsey, Scott and Washington</publish></pubinfo><onlink>https://gisdata.mn.gov/dataset/us-mn-state-metrogis-plan-regonal-parcels-2003</onlink></citeinfo></citation><descript><abstract>This dataset is a compilation of tax parcel polygon layers from the seven Twin Cities, Minnesota metropolitan area counties of Anoka, Carver, Dakota, Hennepin, Ramsey, Scott and Washington.  The seven counties were assembled into a common coordinate system.  No attempt has been made to edgematch or rubbersheet between counties.  A standard set of attribute fields is included for each county.  Not all attributes are populated for all counties.

This is an annual version of the MetroGIS Regional Parcel Dataset that can be used with other annual versions to do change analysis and time series investigations. This dataset is intended to contain all updates to each county's parcel data through the end of 2003.  It was originally published as the 'January 1, 2004' version of the dataset. See the Currentness Reference below and the Entity and Attribute information in Section 5 for more information about the dates for specific aspects of the dataset. 

This dataset contains one record for each real estate/tax parcel polygon.  In many places a one-to-one relationship does not exist between these parcel polygons and the actual buildings or occupancy units that lie within them.  There may be many buildings on one parcel and there may be many occupancy units (e.g. apartments, stores or offices) within each building.  Additionally, no information exists within this dataset about residents of parcels.  Parcel owner and taxpayer information exists for many, but not all counties.

Some counties have also made available a parcel points dataset that includes the same attribute fields as the polygon dataset.  The point are intended to provide information in situations where multiple tax parcels are represented by a single polygon.  The primary example of this is the condominium.  Condominiums, by definition, are legally owned as individual, taxed real estate units.  Records for condominiums may not show up in the polygon dataset.

This is a MetroGIS Regionally Endorsed dataset.  
</abstract><purpose>To view, analyze and display parcel data anywhere in the seven county metro area.  This is an annual version of the MetroGIS Regional Parcel Dataset that can be used with other annual versions to do change analysis and time series investigations.</purpose><supplinf>Twin Cities 7 County Metropolitan Area.  This includes the counties of Anoka, Carver, Dakota, Hennepin, Ramsey, Scott and Washington in Minnesota.</supplinf></descript><timeperd><timeinfo><sngdate><caldate>20031231</caldate></sngdate></timeinfo><current>This dataset reflects the status of each county's parcel polygon and attribute data as of the following dates:

Anoka = 12/16/2003 for polygons and 12/16/2003 for attributes
Carver = 01/21/2004 for polygons and 01/21/2004 for attributes
Dakota = 12/31/2003 for polygons and 12/31/2003 for attributes
Hennepin = 01/12/2004 for polygons and 01/05/2004 for attributes
Ramsey = 01/05/2004 for polygons, attribute dates vary
Scott = 01/08/2004 for polygons and 01/10/2004 for attributes
Washington = 12/26/2003 for polygons and 12/26/2003 for attributes</current></timeperd><status><progress>Complete</progress><update>Annually</update></status><spdom><bounding><westbc>-94.012</westbc><eastbc>-92.732</eastbc><northbc>45.415</northbc><southbc>44.471</southbc></bounding></spdom><keywords><theme><themekt>None</themekt><themekey>parcels, regional parcel data, cadastre, land ownership</themekey></theme><place><placekey>Twin Cities, Anoka County, Carver County, Dakota County, Hennepin County, Ramsey County, Scott County, Washington County</placekey></place></keywords><accconst>None</accconst><useconst>None</useconst><browse><browsen>ftp://ftp.gisdata.mn.gov/pub/gdrs/data/pub/us_mn_state_metrogis/plan_regonal_parcels_2003/metadata/preview.jpg</browsen><browsed>Sample map showing the MetroGIS Regional Parcel Data.</browsed></browse><native>See metadata for individual counties.</native><crossref><citeinfo><title>Regional Parcel Dataset - Seven County Twin Cities Metropolitan Area
2002 - current</title></citeinfo></crossref><ptcontac><cntinfo><cntperp><cntorg>Metropolitan Council</cntorg><cntper>Tanya Mayer</cntper></cntperp><cntpos>GIS Specialist</cntpos><cntaddr><addrtype>mailing and physical</addrtype><address>390 Robert Street North</address><city>St. Paul</city><state>MN</state><postal>55101-1805</postal></cntaddr><cntvoice>651.602.1604</cntvoice><cntemail>tanya.mayer@metc.state.mn.us</cntemail></cntinfo></ptcontac></idinfo><dataqual><attracc><attraccr>A standard set of attribute fields is included for each county.  However, not all attributes are available for all counties.  No attempt has been made by MetroGIS to assess the accuracy of the attribute data.

Any questions or comments about suspected errors or omissions in this dataset can be addressed to the contact person listed in the individual county metadata.   Links to that metadata can be found in the Horizontal Positional Accuracy element below.</attraccr></attracc><logic>No attempt was made to edgematch or rubbersheet the seven counties, thus overlaps and gaps will exist between counties.  Not all tax parcels are represented by a unique polygon.   For example, a county might have one polygon representing a condominium complex.  Some counties have provided an additional parcel points shape file that will include points to represent such tax parcels (e.g. a point for each individual condominium).</logic><complete>For parcel attributes, see Section 5 of this metadata.
For parcel geography, see metadata for individual counties.

Any questions or comments about suspected errors or omissions in this dataset can be addressed to the contact person listed in the individual county metadata.   Links to that metadata can be found in the Horizontal Positional Accuracy element below.</complete><posacc><horizpa><horizpar>ANOKA:   No information provided.

CARVER:  The Horizontal Accuracy of the counties parcel dataset is, for the most part, UNDER 1' accuracy. This is possible because the County's Surveyor used COGO (Coordinate Geometry) which is a highly accurate way of plotting parcel lines. 

DAKOTA:  90% less than 2.0 feet 

HENNEPIN:  Estimated to be +or- 2 to 4 feet at section corners. Positional accuracy decreases with distance from section corners.

RAMSEY:  Digitized information is generally +or- 7 feet; some areas have been found to be +or- 30 feet. Cogo (coordinate geometry) accuracy generally is +or- 1.0 foot. 

SCOTT:  No information provided.

WASHINGTON:  Digitized features outside areas of high vertical relief (e.g. major river valleys) tested 23 feet horizontal accuracy at the 95 % confidence level using National Standard Spatial Data Accuracy (NSSDA).

Digitized features within areas of high vertical relief tested 120 feet horizontal accuracy by other testing procedures. 

All other features are generated by coordinate geometry and based on a framework of accurately located PLSS corner positions used with public information of record. Computed positions of parcel boundaries are not based on individual field surveys. Although tests of randomly selected points may show high accuracy between field and parcel map content, variations between boundary monumentation and legal description of record can and do exist. Caution is necessary in use of land boundary data shown. Contact the Land Management/Land Survey Division for more information.</horizpar></horizpa></posacc><lineage><srcinfo><srcscale></srcscale></srcinfo><procstep><procdesc>Each county provided parcel polygons and attributes in shape file format with UTM coordinates, to the Metropolitan Council.  The Metropolitan Council checked each shape file to insure it had all desired attribute fields, field names, types and lengths.  

No attempt was made to edgematch or rubber sheet the parcel geography between counties.</procdesc></procstep></lineage></dataqual><spdoinfo><indspref>None</indspref><direct>Vector</direct><mgmg3obj>polygon shapes</mgmg3obj><mgmg3til>One shape file for each of the seven counties.</mgmg3til></spdoinfo><eainfo><overview><eaover>A standard set of attribute fields is included for each county; however, not
all attributes fields are populated by each county.  Some qualifying comments
have been provided by counties and are included after the description of
the attributes.
 
 
COUNTY_ID:  Three digit FIPS and state standard county code.
            003 = Anoka
            019 = Carver
            037 = Dakota
            053 = Hennepin
            123 = Ramsey
            139 = Scott
            163 = Washington
 
 
PIN:        Unique regional parcel ID comprised of the county PIN with 
            the county code and dash appended to the front.
 
  
OWN_NAME:   The full (first and last) name of the owner. The format 
            (e.g. last name first or last name last) and inclusion of 
            multiple owners is up to each county.
 
            Anoka:      No data.
            Dakota:     Owner name or Contract Purchaser name. Not all owner 
                        names will appear on joint or multiple ownership
                        parcels.
            Ramsey:     Uses PRIMARY. This is not guaranteed to be the owner.
 
 
OWN_ADD_L1: Owner address line 1.
OWN_ADD_L2: Owner address line 2.
OWN_ADD_L3: Owner address line 3.
            These three fields are for the mailing address of the owner. 
            Typically line 1 is street address and line 2 is city, state 
            &amp; zip, but other variations exist.
 
            Hennepin:   No data.
            Ramsey:     Uses PRIMARY address.  This is not guaranteed 
                        to be the owner's address.
 
 
TAX_NAME:   The full (first and last) name of the taxpayer. The format 
            (e.g. last name first or last name last) and inclusion of 
            multiple taxpayers is up to each county.
 
            Anoka:      No data.
            Dakota:     No data.
            Ramsey:     Uses ALTERNATE name.  When available, this is
                        often the person who pays taxes.  This field is 
                        usually blank.
            Washington: Some data provided.
 
 
TAX_ADD_L1: Taxpayer address line 1.
TAX_ADD_L2: Taxpayer address line 2.
TAX_ADD_L3: Taxpayer address line 3.
            Mailing address of the taxpayer. Typically line 1 is street 
            address and line 2 is city, state &amp; zip, but other variations
            exist.
 
            Dakota:     No data.
            Ramsey:     Uses ALTERNATE address.  The fields are 
                        usually blank.
            Washington: No data.
 
 
HOMESTEAD:  Homesteaded (Y/N).
 
            Anoka:      Used EXPT_CODE1 = HST.  Some additional homesteads 
                        may exist.  Does not distinguish between agricultural 
                        and residential homesteads.
            Dakota:     Payable 2004 Homestead Status. Y includes fractional 
                        and disabled homesteads.
            Hennepin:   2003 Assessment for Taxes Payable in 2004.
            Ramsey:     Uses numeric codes.  There are issues with converting
                        partial and disabled homesteads to a direct Y/N.
 
 
BLDG_NUM:   The building or house number of the parcel.
            Note that in some cases in Dakota and Hennepin Counties, leading 
            and following blank spaces exist in this field which may cause 
            problems when performing a search (e.g. search for "12345" may not 
            find " 12345").
 
            Dakota:     Field is unverified.
 
 
STREET:     The street name (with street type and direction). This is the 
            actual location of the parcel, which may not be the mailing 
            address.
 
            Dakota:     Field is unverified.
 
 
CITY:       Name of city or township in which the parcel resides (not the 
            mailing address city or township).


            Note that for Carver, Ramsey, Scott and Washington Counties, this 
            field is not populated according to the definition above
 
 
ZIP:        Zip code in which the parcel resides
 
            Dakota:     Field is unverified.
 
 
EMV_LAND:   Land estimated market value.
EMV_BLDG:   Building estimated market value.
EMV_TOTAL:  Total estimated market value.  This may include more than
            the land and building values.
 
            Anoka:      2003 estimated values for taxes payable in 2004.
            Carver:     2003 estimated values for taxes payable in 2004.
            Dakota:     2003 estimated values for taxes payable in 2004.
            Hennepin:   2003 estimated values for taxes payable in 2004.
                        EMV_TOTAL includes sum of Land, Building &amp; Machinery
                        Estimated Market Values.
            Ramsey:     2002 estimated values for taxes payable in 2003.
            Scott:      2003 estimated values for taxes payable in 2004.
            Washington: 2003 estimated values for taxes payable in 2004.
 
 
TAX_CAPAC:  Tax capacity of the parcel.
 
            Anoka:      For taxes payable in 2003.
            Carver:     For taxes payable in 2003.
            Dakota:     Total tax capacity, year payable 2003.
            Hennepin:   For taxes payable in 2003.
            Ramsey:     No data.
            Scott:      No data.
            Washington: For taxes payable in 2003
 
 
TOTAL_TAX:  Total tax of the parcel.
 
            Anoka:      For taxes payable in 2003.
            Carver:     For taxes payable in 2003.
            Dakota:     Total real estate tax, including special assessments, 
                        due and payable in 2003.
            Hennepin:   For Taxes Payable in 2003 (includes special
                        assessments).
            Ramsey:     For taxes payable in 2003.
            Scott:      No data.
            Washington: No data.
 
 
TAX_EXEMPT: Tax exempt (Y/N).
 
            Anoka:      Used EXPT_CODE1 = EXM.
            Hennepin:   2002 Assessment for Taxes Payable in 2003.
            Ramsey:     Uses CAMA numeric codes for land use codes.  Numeric
                        codes in the six hundred range were assumed to be
                        exempt and converted to Y. All others were coded N.
            Scott:      No data.
 
 
YEAR_BUILT: The year the primary structure was initially built.

            Hennepin:   This field is populated by individual city assessors
                        and cannot be guaranteed by Hennepin County.
            Ramsey:     Dwelling data and Commercial data were combined.
            Washington: No values newer than 1999.  No values for Woodbury.
 
 
SCHOOL_DST: Unique school district number.
 
 
WSHD_DIST:  Watershed district name.
 
            Hennepin:   Data for approximately  63% of properties.  Properties
                        that do not have a watershed name are located in a
                        watershed district that does not levy a watershed
                        district tax rate.
            Ramsey:     The last character of the district code was used with a
                        lookup table to produce a descriptive watershed
                        district.
            Scott:      No data.
 
 
NUM_UNITS:  Number of residential units.
 
            Anoka:      Some data provided.
            Carver:     No data.
            Dakota:     Data provided.
            Hennepin:   No data.
            Ramsey:     Data provided.
            Scott:      No data.
            Washington: No data.
 
 
STRUC_TYPE: Information pertaining to the type of structure on the parcel.
 
            Carver:     No data.
            Dakota:     Describes the main use for which this building was 
                        designed, such as single family residence, duplex, 
                        tri-plex, restaurant, etc.
            Hennepin:   No data.
            Ramsey:     Uses CAMA codes.  Dwelling and commercial tables 
                        were aggregated and a lookup table was developed to 
                        produce structure descriptions.


SALE_DATE:  Date of last sale.  In general this includes all "arm's length" 
            transactions and would not, for example, include a sale to a family 
            member for $1.  This may vary by county.
              
            Carver:     Includes all sales.
            Dakota:     Month and year of last QUALIFIED SALE (day not part of
                        attributes available). Day of the month is fictitious 
                        (set to the 1st of the month to conform to date field
                        FORMAT).
            Ramsey:     The CAMA valid sales were used.  Data exist for 39% of
                        parcels.
            Washington: No values newer than 8/14/2000 and no data for 
                        Woodbury.

 
SALE_VALUE: Value of last sale.
 
            Anoka:      Field is partially populated.
            Ramsey:     The CAMA valid sales were used.  Data exist for 39% 
                        of parcels.


PARC_CODE:  Parcel Polygon to Parcel Point and PIN Relationship Code. This 
            field is used to provide information about the relationship between 
            parcel polygons, parcel points and unique tax parcel identifiers 
            (PINs). At this time, most counties do not populate this field. 
            Values are: 

            0 = Information not available or not provided
            1 = Valid Parcel with a single tax PIN
            2 = In polygon dataset: Parcel polygon representing multiple tax
                PINs In point dataset: One of multiple parcel points that 
                together are represented by a single polygon

            The values below are likely only to be found in the polygon 
            dataset.  The polygons for which they are assigned are unlikely to 
            have a tax PIN or other parcel attributes. The parcel points 
            datasets, where available, are unlikely to include these feature 
            types.

            10 = Condominium Common Area
            11 = Right-of-way
            12 = Easement
            13 = Ownership Unknown 
            14 = Gap between parcel boundary descriptions
            15 = Water Body
            16 = Ditch
            17 = Walkway
            98 = Other non-parcel feature
            99 = Unspecified non-parcel feature

            Anoka:    No data. 
            Hennepin: No data. 
            Scott:    No data.</eaover></overview></eainfo><distinfo><resdesc>MetroGIS Regional Parcels 2003</resdesc><distliab>NOTICE: The Geographic Information System (GIS) Data to which this notice is attached are made available pursuant to the Minnesota Government Data Practices Act (Minnesota Statutes Chapter 13). THE GIS DATA ARE PROVIDED TO YOU AS IS AND WITHOUT ANY WARRANTY AS TO THEIR PERFORMANCE, MERCHANTABILITY, OR FITNESS FOR ANY PARTICULAR PURPOSE. The GIS Data were developed by the counties of Anoka, Carver, Dakota, Hennepin, Ramsey, Scott, and Washington (Counties) for their own internal business purposes. The Counties do not represent or warrant that the GIS Data or the data documentation are error-free, complete, current, or accurate. You are responsible for any consequences resulting from your use of the GIS Data or your reliance on the GIS Data. You should consult the data documentation for this particular GIS Data to determine the limitations of the GIS Data and the precision with which the GIS Data may depict distance, direction, location, or other geographic features.  If you transmit or provide the GIS Data (or any portion of it) to another user, you must provide a copy of this disclaimer and the accompanying metadata for this dataset to the user.</distliab><stdorder><digform><digtinfo><formname>Shapefile</formname><formvern>ArcGIS: 10x</formvern><transize>Less than 350 MB</transize></digtinfo></digform><ordering>See Online Linkage Below</ordering></stdorder><distrib><cntinfo><cntperp><cntorg>Metropolitan Council</cntorg><cntper>Tanya Mayer</cntper></cntperp><cntpos>GIS Specialist</cntpos><cntaddr><addrtype>mailing and physical</addrtype><address>390 Robert Street North</address><city>St. Paul</city><state>MN</state><postal>55101-1805</postal></cntaddr><cntvoice>651.602.1604</cntvoice><cntemail>tanya.mayer@metc.state.mn.us</cntemail></cntinfo></distrib></distinfo><metainfo><metd>20120719</metd><metstdn>Minnesota Geographic Metadata Guidelines</metstdn><metstdv>1.2</metstdv><metextns><onlink>http://www.gis.state.mn.us/stds/metadata.htm</onlink></metextns><metc><cntinfo><cntperp><cntorg>Metropolitan Council</cntorg><cntper>Tanya Mayer</cntper></cntperp><cntpos>GIS Specialist</cntpos><cntaddr><addrtype>mailing and physical</addrtype><address>390 Robert Street North</address><city>St. Paul</city><state>MN</state><postal>55101-1805</postal></cntaddr><cntvoice>651.602.1604</cntvoice><cntemail>tanya.mayer@metc.state.mn.us</cntemail></cntinfo></metc></metainfo><Esri><ModDate>20120224</ModDate><ModTime>15420700</ModTime></Esri><mdDateSt Sync="TRUE">20120224</mdDateSt><spref><horizsys><planar><gridsys><gridsysn>Universal Transverse Mercator</gridsysn><utm><utmzone>15</utmzone></utm></gridsys><planci><plandu>meters</plandu></planci></planar><geodetic><horizdn>NAD83</horizdn><ellips>GRS80</ellips></geodetic></horizsys></spref></metadata>