<?xml version="1.0"?><metadata><eainfo><overview><eaover>Attributes 
 
TAZ:  TAZ number
 
CO_NAME:  Name of the county
 
CO_NUM:  Unique number for the county
 
TAD:  TAD name (sequential in 7 county, census in ring)
 
CensusTAZ:  2010 US census TAZ number most closely matching this TAZ (census TAZs are larger, and boundaries do not always exactly match)
 
POPTOTAL:  2010 US Census population
 
HHTOTAL:  2010 US Census households
 
HUTOTAL:  2010 US Census housing units
 
POPINHH:  2010 US Census households
 
POPINGQ:  2010 US Census population in group quarters
 
MARKIDS:  2010 US Census married with children

UNMARRKIDS:  2010 US Census unmarried with children

FAMNOKIDS:  2010 US Census familes without children

NONFAMILY:  2010 US Census non-family households  

WHITENH:  2010 US Census white non-hispanic

BLACKNH:  2010 US Census black non-hispanic

AMINDNH:  2010 US Census American Indian non-hispanic

ASIANNH:2010 US Census Asian non-hispanic

PACIFICNH:  2010 US Census Pacific Islander non-hispanic

OTHERNH:  2010 US Census Other non-hispanic

MULTRACNH:  2010 US Census multi-racial non-hispanic

HISPOP:  2010 US Census Hispanic population

OWNEROCC:  2010 US Census occupied housing

RENTEROCC:  2010 US Census occupied housing

VACANT:  2010 US Census vacant housing 

POPOVER5:  2010 US Census population over 5

POPOVER16:  2010 US Census population over 16

POPOVER18:  2010 US Census population over 18

POPOVER65:  2010 US Census population over 65

HH_UNDER18:  2010 US Census households with members under 18

HH_65OVER:  2010 US Census households with members over 65

HHTYPE1:  Family households with children, householder under 65

HHTYPE2:  Family households with no children, householder under 65

HHTYPE3:  Other householders that are not families and with more than one person

HHTYPE4:  Householders with one person alone, householder under 65

HHTYPE5:  Householders more than one person, 65 and older

HHTYPE6:  Householders with one person alone, 65 and older

TOTAL_EMP:  Total Employment (QCEW 2010, augmented with 2009 LED where nondiscloseable)

RETAIL_EMP:  Retail Employment (QCEW 2010, augmented with 2009 LED where nondiscloseable)

NONRETAIL_:  non-Retail Employment (QCEW 2010, augmented with 2009 LED where nondiscloseable)

  
  
 


</eaover></overview></eainfo><idinfo><citation><citeinfo><origin>Metropolitan Council</origin><title>Transportation Analysis Zones (TAZ) 2010</title><pubinfo><publish>Metropolitan Council</publish></pubinfo><pubdate>20120305</pubdate><onlink>https://gisdata.mn.gov/dataset/us-mn-state-metc-trans-anlys-zones2010</onlink></citeinfo></citation><descript><abstract>This file depicts the Transportation Analysis Zone (TAZ) system developed as part of the 2010 Travel Behavior Inventory.  It will be used for the Council's next generation of travel forecast models</abstract><purpose>To show the boundaries of 2010 TAZs, aggregations, and household/employment data</purpose><supplinf>Travel Model Area (19 counties)</supplinf></descript><timeperd><current>Data considered current through the date of this metadata.  Household/population data from 2010 US decennial Census.  Employment data from QCEW/LED data.</current><timeinfo><sngdate><caldate>20120305</caldate></sngdate></timeinfo></timeperd><status><progress>Complete</progress><update>As needed</update></status><spdom><bounding><westbc>-94.012</westbc><eastbc>-92.732</eastbc><northbc>45.415</northbc><southbc>44.471</southbc></bounding></spdom><accconst>None</accconst><useconst>By acceptance of this data, the user agrees to include a copy of this metadata record, including the liability disclaimer, whenever the user transmits or provides the GIS Data (or any portion of it) to another user.</useconst><keywords><place><placekey>Twin Cities, Anoka County, Carver County, Dakota County, Hennepin County, Ramsey County, Scott County, Washington County</placekey></place><theme><themekey>Transportation Analysis Zones, Traffic Assignment Zones, Traffic Analysis Zones, transportation</themekey></theme></keywords><ptcontac><cntinfo><cntperp><cntorg>Metropolitan Council</cntorg><cntper>Jonathan Ehrlich</cntper></cntperp><cntpos>Senior Planner</cntpos><cntaddr><addrtype>mailing and physical</addrtype><address>390 Robert Street North</address><city>St. Paul</city><state>MN</state><postal>55101-1805</postal></cntaddr><cntvoice>651.602.1408</cntvoice><cntemail>jonathan.ehrlich@metc.state.mn.us</cntemail></cntinfo></ptcontac></idinfo><distinfo><distliab>NOTICE:  The Geographic Information System (GIS) Data to which this notice is attached are made available pursuant to the Minnesota Government Data Practices Act (Minnesota Statutes Chapter 13).  THE GIS DATA ARE PROVIDED TO YOU AS IS AND WITHOUT ANY WARRANTY AS TO THEIR PERFORMANCE, MERCHANTABILITY, OR FITNESS FOR ANY PARTICULAR PURPOSE.  The GIS Data were developed by the Metropolitan Council for its own internal business purposes.  The Metropolitan Council does not represent or warrant that the GIS Data or the data documentation are error-free, complete, current, or accurate.  You are responsible for any consequences resulting from your use of the GIS Data or your reliance on the GIS Data.  You should consult the data documentation for this particular GIS Data to determine the limitations of the GIS Data and the precision with which the GIS Data may depict distance, direction, location, or other geographic features.  If you transmit or provide the GIS Data (or any portion of it) to another user, it is recommended that the GIS Data include a copy of this disclaimer and this metadata.</distliab><stdorder><ordering>See Online Linkage Below</ordering></stdorder><resdesc>TAZ2010</resdesc><distrib><cntinfo><cntperp><cntorg>Metropolitan Council</cntorg><cntper>Jon Hoekenga</cntper></cntperp><cntpos>GIS Specialist</cntpos><cntaddr><addrtype>mailing and physical</addrtype><address>390 Robert Street North</address><city>St. Paul</city><state>MN</state><postal>55101-1805</postal></cntaddr><cntvoice>651.602.1561</cntvoice><cntemail>jonathan.hoekenga@metc.state.mn.us</cntemail></cntinfo></distrib></distinfo><metainfo><metd>20120305</metd><metstdn>Minnesota Geographic Metadata Guidelines</metstdn><metstdv>1.2</metstdv><metextns><onlink>http://www.mngeo.state.mn.us/committee/standards/mgmg/metadata.htm</onlink></metextns><metc><cntinfo><cntperp><cntorg>Metropolitan Council</cntorg><cntper>Jonathan Ehrlich</cntper></cntperp><cntpos>Senior Planner</cntpos><cntaddr><addrtype>mailing and physical</addrtype><address>390 Robert Street North</address><city>St. Paul</city><state>MN</state><postal>55101-1805</postal></cntaddr><cntvoice>651.602.1408</cntvoice><cntemail>jonathan.ehrlich@metc.state.mn.us</cntemail></cntinfo></metc></metainfo><dataqual><lineage><procstep><procdesc>Polygons were drawn based on transportation analysis needs, following natural and transportation boundaries, following FHWA TMIP guidance on TAZ boundary definition.  In Minnesota, TAZs were created from scratch (Census TAZs were later created for submittal to the census based on these boundaries).  In Wisconsin, definitions were initially based on submitted census TAZs and MnDOT Collar County TAZ files, but were extensively modified to serve transportation analysis needs</procdesc></procstep></lineage></dataqual><spref><horizsys><planar><gridsys><gridsysn>Universal Transverse Mercator</gridsysn><utm><utmzone>15</utmzone></utm></gridsys><planci><plandu>meters</plandu></planci></planar><geodetic><horizdn>NAD83</horizdn><ellips>GRS80</ellips></geodetic></horizsys></spref></metadata>