<?xml version="1.0"?><metadata><idinfo><citation><citeinfo><origin>Minnesota Geospatial Information Office (MnGeo)</origin><title>Minnesota Cities, Townships, and Counties  Reference Map</title><pubinfo><publish>Minnesota Geospatial Information Office</publish></pubinfo><pubdate>2013</pubdate><onlink>https://gisdata.mn.gov/dataset/bdry-cities-counties-twps-map</onlink></citeinfo></citation><descript><supplinf>Minnesota, Statewide, with inset for Twin Cities Metropolitan Area</supplinf><abstract>This map of Minnesota cities, townships, and counties was published by MnGeo in November 2013.  The primary data set for the map is the "Cities, Townships, and Unorganized Territories" (MnCTU) data maintained by the Minnesota Department of Transportation. Other reference data on the map include County Seats and Other Cities, County Boundaries, Interstate, US Trunk, and State Trunk Highways, Major Rivers, Lakes,  County and State Boundaries. The download is a PDF file with embedded layers that can be printed at E-scale (36" x 48").  </abstract><purpose>This map, produced by MnGeo for the Office of Administrative Hearings (OAH) in 2013, was intended to serve as a reference map of state administrative boundaries.  </purpose></descript><timeperd><current>Map published in November 2013 reflects "Cities, Townships, and Unorganized Territories" data current as of 6/19/2012. </current><timeinfo><sngdate><caldate>2012</caldate></sngdate></timeinfo></timeperd><status><progress>Complete</progress><update>None Planned</update></status><spdom><bounding><westbc>-97.23</westbc><eastbc>-89.53</eastbc><northbc>49.37</northbc><southbc>43.5</southbc></bounding></spdom><keywords><place><placekey>Minnesota, MN</placekey></place><theme><themekt>ISO 19115 Topic Categories</themekt><themekey>boundaries, county, city, township, county seat, map</themekey></theme></keywords><accconst>None</accconst><useconst>None</useconst><crossref><citeinfo><title>https://gisdata.mn.gov/dataset/bdry-mn-city-township-unorg  (MnCTU data)

https://gisdata.mn.gov/dataset/trans-roads-mndot-tis (MnDOT Road Centerlines)</title></citeinfo></crossref><ptcontac><cntinfo><cntperp><cntorg>Minnesota Geospatial Information Office (MnGeo)</cntorg><cntper>Nancy Rader</cntper></cntperp><cntpos>GIS Data Coordinator</cntpos><cntaddr><addrtype>Mailing and Physical</addrtype><address>658 Cedar Street, Room 300</address><city>St. Paul</city><state>MN</state><postal>55155</postal></cntaddr><cntvoice>651-201-2489</cntvoice><cntemail>gisinfo.mngeo@state.mn.us</cntemail></cntinfo></ptcontac></idinfo><distinfo><distliab>Map disclaimer: This map is provided 'as is', without express or implied warranties, including warranties of merchantability and fitness. In no event will MN.IT Services be liable for any consequential, incidental or special damages, including any lost profits or lost savings, even if an MN.IT Services representative has been advised of the possibility of such damages or any other claim by a third party.

Standard MnGeo disclaimer: MnGeo's data disclaimer is online: http://www.mngeo.state.mn.us/chouse/disclaimer.html </distliab><stdorder><ordering>Available for download through the Minnesota Geospatial Commons via the online linkage below. </ordering></stdorder><resdesc>MNCitiesTownshipsCounties_MNIT2013  (bdry_cities_counties_twps_map)</resdesc><distrib><cntinfo><cntperp><cntorg>Minnesota Geospatial Information Office (MnGeo)</cntorg><cntper>Nancy Rader</cntper></cntperp><cntpos>GIS Data Coordinator</cntpos><cntaddr><addrtype>mailing and physical</addrtype><address>658 Cedar Street, Room 300</address><city>St. Paul</city><state>MN</state><postal>55155</postal></cntaddr><cntvoice>651-201-2489</cntvoice><cntemail>gisinfo.mngeo@state.mn.us</cntemail></cntinfo></distrib></distinfo><metainfo><metd>20150902</metd><metstdn>Minnesota Geographic Metadata Guidelines</metstdn><metstdv>1.2</metstdv><metextns><onlink>http://www.mngeo.state.mn.us/committee/standards/mgmg/metadata.htm</onlink></metextns><metc><cntinfo><cntperp><cntorg>Minnesota Geospatial Information Office (MnGeo)</cntorg><cntper>Nancy Rader</cntper></cntperp><cntpos>GIS Data Coordinator</cntpos><cntaddr><addrtype>mailing and physical</addrtype><address>658 Cedar Street, Room 300</address><city>St. Paul</city><state>MN</state><postal>55155</postal></cntaddr><cntvoice>651-201-2489</cntvoice><cntemail>gisinfo.mngeo@state.mn.us</cntemail></cntinfo></metc></metainfo><eainfo><overview><eaover>Layers used to produce the map are described under Lineage. </eaover></overview></eainfo><dataqual><complete>Complete</complete><lineage><procstep><procdesc>This map was produced by MnGeo for the Office of Administrative Hearings (OAH) in 2013 under Project Code 45983069. The following  GIS data layers were used to create this map:

Counties: County layer used on Minnesota's Network for Enterprise Communications (MNET) maps produced by MnGeo for MN.IT Services/State of Minnesota. The original source of this county layer is unclear.

City, Township, and Unorganized Territory (MnCTU):   date: 6/19/2012.  Shapefile mnctu_06192102.shp was used as the base for cities, townships, and unorganized territories on the map. The MnCTU database was originally created by MnGeo and is now being updated by MnDOT. For metadata for this layer, see ftp://ftp.gisdata.mn.gov/pub/gdrs/data/pub/us_mn_state_dot/bdry_mn_city_township_unorg/metadata/metadata.html

County Seats: mn_cseat.shp, labels moved where necessary.

Other Cities: OtherCity.shp file was derived from original MCD90 (Minor Civil Divisions 1990 - Census File), with additions and deletions over time.  Only a subset of cities was used on the map. 

Roads: Trunk Highways file downloaded from MnDOT Basemap website April/May 2012.  MnGeo filename: State_Hwy_2010\StateTH\TH091610.  Mapped road types include Interstate, U.S. Trunk Highway, and State Trunk Highway - extracted based on road type codes in the dataset. Minor edits were made to the file for mapping purposes. 

Lake Superior: (Superior4.shp) File was originally produced for a different project and edited to edgematch water to land. 

Additional background data, obtained from the RNC_FGDB 2008 database (base data compiled by MnGeo to support mapping/emergency response during the Republican National Convention in 2008), includes rivers, lakes, state, metro, and international boundaries. 

Rivers:  Major_MN_Rivers - derived from shapefile "mnrivers" which represented major river centerline traces from the River Kilometer Index database (1984).

Lakes: Lake_DLG_D - from USGS 1:100,000-scale Digital Line Graph hydrography features, extracted features coded as "lake" from DLG into MN "dlglakes" file and added MN Lake ID (2002).  For mapping for this project, extracted Major Lakes (lakes with size greater than 5000 acres) and Lakes (lakes with size greater than 500 acres). 

Map was composed in ArcMap Layout View.  The ArcGIS "Export to PDF" was used, with the resolution of 36" x 48" and the "Export layers" function activated. </procdesc></procstep></lineage><posacc><horizpa><horizpar>Map is composed from different GIS layers which were captured at different positional accuracies. </horizpar></horizpa><vertacc><vertaccr>Not applicable</vertaccr></vertacc></posacc><logic>For base GIS layer MnCTU: In the original dataset, MnDOT's more up-to-date dataset for city, township and unorganized territory boundaries was merged with MnGeo's updated boundary data. The resulting gaps and overlaps were manually fixed to produce a seamless statewide dataset. </logic><attracc><attraccr>For base GIS layer MnCTU: MnGeo staff compared the attributes created for the mnctu09 feature class  with the Minnesota CTU database (derived from the U.S. Geological Survey's Geographic Names Information System or GNIS). The checks were done using Esri's ArcSDE and ArcMap software. In September, 2010, CTU GNIS_IDs were updated to include recently assigned USGS GNIS IDs for two Unorganized Territories. Fictitious GNIS_IDs were assigned to nine Unorganized Territories which did not have USGS-assigned GNIS ID's, to create common fields enabling table joins and edits to attribute tables from previous datasets.</attraccr></attracc></dataqual><spref><horizsys><planar><gridsys><gridsysn>Universal Transverse Mercator</gridsysn><utm><utmzone>15E</utmzone></utm></gridsys><planci><plandu>meters</plandu></planci></planar><geodetic><horizdn>NAD83</horizdn><ellips>GRS80</ellips></geodetic></horizsys></spref></metadata>