<metadata>
  <idinfo>
    <citation>
      <citeinfo>
        <title>Liquid Waste Receiving Disposal Sites</title>
        <origin>Metropolitan Council</origin>
        <pubinfo>
          <publish>Metropolitan Council</publish>
        </pubinfo>
        <pubdate>periodically revised</pubdate>
        <onlink>https://gisdata.mn.gov/dataset/us-mn-state-metc-util-liquid-waste-rec-disp-sites</onlink>
      </citeinfo>
    </citation>
    <descript>
      <abstract>This layer contains data showing the locations of where the Metropolitan Council Environmental Services (MCES) accepts the discharge of hauled wastewater.  The Industrial Waste &amp; Pollution Prevention Section (IWPP) regulates hauled liquid waste discharged to the Metropolitan Disposal System.  This waste includes wastewater from septic tanks, holding tanks, commercial establishments, industrial souces and leachate.  Industrial and leachate loads are only accepted at the Metro Liquid Waste Receiving site at the Metropolitan Wastewater Treatment Plant in St. Paul.  Only companies permitted through IWPP's LWH Permit program are allowed to use the sites.  In addition to the LWH disposal sites,  the Vactor site is also included in this dataset.  The Vactor site is used for the disposal of sewer cleaning sludge and can only be used by communities located within the 7 county area.</abstract>
      <purpose>To provide a map showing the locations of Liquid Waste Receiving Disposal Sites.</purpose>
      <supplinf>Twin Cities 7 County Metropolitan Area.</supplinf>
    </descript>
    <timeperd>
      <timeinfo>
        <sngdate>
          <caldate>20101027</caldate>
        </sngdate>
      </timeinfo>
      <current>Data set is up-to-date as of the Time Period of Content date.  This data set changed significantly in 2008, see notes in Abstract.</current>
    </timeperd>
    <status>
      <progress>Complete</progress>
      <update>As needed</update>
    </status>
    <spdom>
      <bounding>
        <westbc>-92.732</westbc>
        <eastbc>-91.532</eastbc>
        <northbc>45.415</northbc>
        <southbc>44.471</southbc>
      </bounding>
    </spdom>
    <keywords>
      <place>
        <placekey>Twin Cities, Anoka County, Carver County, Dakota County, Hennepin County, Ramsey County, Scott County, Washington County</placekey>
      </place>
      <theme>
        <themekey>liquid waste receiving, disposal sites, dump sites, septage, leachate, vactor</themekey>
        <themekt>None</themekt>
      </theme>
    </keywords>
    <accconst>None</accconst>
    <useconst>None</useconst>
    <browse>
      <browsen>ftp://ftp.gisdata.mn.gov/pub/gdrs/data/pub/us_mn_state_metc/util_liquid_waste_rec_disp_sites/metadata/preview.jpg</browsen>
      <browsed>Sample map showing the MCES Liquid Waste Receiving Disposal Sites layer.</browsed>
    </browse>
    <crossref>
      <citeinfo>
        <title>MCES Industrial Discharge Permits, Temporary and Planning Meters, Sewer Interceptor System (Limited Attributes)</title>
      </citeinfo>
    </crossref>
    <native>ArcGIS 9x</native>
    <ptcontac>
      <cntinfo>
        <cntperp>
          <cntorg>Metropolitan Council</cntorg>
          <cntper>Bob Golden</cntper>
        </cntperp>
        <cntpos>Industrial Waste &amp; Pollution Prevention Section, MCES</cntpos>
        <cntaddr>
          <addrtype>mailing and physical</addrtype>
          <address>390 Robert Street North</address>
          <city>St. Paul</city>
          <state>Minnesota</state>
          <postal>55101-1805</postal>
        </cntaddr>
        <cntvoice>651-602-4705</cntvoice>
        <cntemail>bob.golden@metc.state.mn.us</cntemail>
      </cntinfo>
    </ptcontac>
  </idinfo>
  <dataqual>
    <attracc>
      <attraccr>No formal assessment of the attribute accuracy has been made.</attraccr>
    </attracc>
    <logic>The dataset is topologically 'clean'.</logic>
    <complete>Entire seven county geographic area is covered.</complete>
    <posacc>
      <horizpa>
        <horizpar>The positional accuracy of the data set has not been tested under the National Standards for Spatial Data Accuracy. The positional accuracy of the data set is estimated to be 20 ft.

Most of the points were established using a Trimble ProXR GPS, Model TSC1PN, however, a few points were established using aerial photography and the MCES interceptor layer file.</horizpar>
      </horizpa>
    </posacc>
    <lineage>
      <procstep>
        <procdesc>The points were established using a Trimble ProXR GPS, Model TSC1PN.</procdesc>
      </procstep>
      <srcinfo>
        <srcscale/>
      </srcinfo>
    </lineage>
  </dataqual>
  <spdoinfo>
    <indspref>None</indspref>
    <direct>Point</direct>
    <mgmg3obj>point shapes</mgmg3obj>
    <mgmg3til>One layer for entire region.</mgmg3til>
  </spdoinfo>
  <eainfo>
    <overview>
      <eaover>Point Attributes:
 
SITENO:     MCES's designated number for each disposal site
 
NOTES:      Notes on changed anticipated for the site.

STATUS:     Eventually this field will just have two states, active or closed.

ADDRESS:    Address of the location.  In some cases, a building number
            was estimated since the disposal site isn't necessarily 
            connected with a building or parcel.

CITY:       City where site resides.

ZIP:        Postal zip code based on parcel information or adjacent 
            parcel information.

SITE_NAME:  MCES's designated name for each site

SITE:       MCES's designated two digit code for each disposal site</eaover>
      <eadetcit>None</eadetcit>
    </overview>
  </eainfo>
  <distinfo>
    <resdesc>LiquidWasteReceivingSites</resdesc>
    <distliab>NOTICE  The Geographic Information System (GIS) Data to which this notice is attached are made available pursuant to the Minnesota Government Data Practices Act (Minnesota Statutes Chapter 13).  THE GIS DATA ARE PROVIDED TO YOU AS IS AND WITHOUT ANY WARRANTY AS TO THEIR PERFORMANCE, MERCHANTABILITY, OR FITNESS FOR ANY PARTICULAR PURPOSE.  The GIS Data were developed by the Metropolitan Council for its own internal business purposes.  The Metropolitan Council does not represent or warrant that the GIS Data or the data documentation are error-free, complete, current, or accurate.  You are responsible for any consequences resulting from your use of the GIS Data or your reliance on the GIS Data.  You should consult the data documentation for this particular GIS Data to determine the limitations of the GIS Data and the precision with which the GIS Data may depict distance, direction, location, or other geographic features.  If you transmit or provide the GIS Data (or any portion of it) to another user, it is recommended that the GIS Data include a copy of this disclaimer and this metadata.</distliab>
    <stdorder>
      <digform>
        <digtinfo>
          <formname>ArcView Shape file</formname>
          <formvern>ArcGIS 9x</formvern>
          <transize>Less than 1 MB for zip file.</transize>
        </digtinfo>
      </digform>
      <ordering>See Online Linkage Below</ordering>
    </stdorder>
    <distrib>
      <cntinfo>
        <cntperp>
          <cntorg>Metropolitan Council</cntorg>
          <cntper>Jon Hoekenga</cntper>
        </cntperp>
        <cntpos>GIS System Administrator</cntpos>
        <cntaddr>
          <addrtype>mailing and physical</addrtype>
          <address>390 Robert Street North</address>
          <city>St. Paul</city>
          <state>Minnesota</state>
          <postal>55101-1805</postal>
        </cntaddr>
        <cntvoice>651-602-1561</cntvoice>
        <cntemail>jonathan.hoekenga@metc.state.mn.us</cntemail>
      </cntinfo>
    </distrib>
  </distinfo>
  <metainfo>
    <metd>20101027</metd>
    <metstdn>Minnesota Geographic Metadata Guidelines</metstdn>
    <metstdv>1.2</metstdv>
    <metextns>
      <onlink>http://www.gis.state.mn.us/stds/metadata.htm</onlink>
    </metextns>
    <metc>
      <cntinfo>
        <cntperp>
          <cntorg>Metropolitan Council Environmental Services</cntorg>
          <cntper>Bob Golden</cntper>
        </cntperp>
        <cntpos>Principal Engineer</cntpos>
        <cntaddr>
          <addrtype>mailing and physical</addrtype>
          <address>390 Robert Street North</address>
          <city>St. Paul</city>
          <state>Minnesota</state>
          <postal>55101-1805</postal>
        </cntaddr>
        <cntvoice>651-602-4705</cntvoice>
        <cntemail>bob.golden@metc.state.mn.us</cntemail>
      </cntinfo>
    </metc>
  </metainfo>
  <Esri>
    <ModDate>20110725</ModDate>
    <ModTime>11360000</ModTime>
  </Esri>
  <mdDateSt Sync="TRUE">20110725</mdDateSt>
  <spref>
    <horizsys>
      <planar>
        <gridsys>
          <gridsysn>Universal Transverse Mercator</gridsysn>
          <utm>
            <utmzone>15</utmzone>
          </utm>
        </gridsys>
        <planci>
          <plandu>meters</plandu>
        </planci>
      </planar>
      <geodetic>
        <horizdn>NAD83</horizdn>
        <ellips>GRS80</ellips>
      </geodetic>
    </horizsys>
  </spref>
</metadata>
