<?xml version="1.0"?><!--  <!DOCTYPE metadata SYSTEM "metadata.dtd">  --><metadata><idinfo><citation><citeinfo><origin>Minnesota Geospatial Information Office (MnGeo)</origin><pubdate>201506</pubdate><title>Telephone Exchange Service Area Boundaries, Minnesota, March 2016</title><mgmg1cid></mgmg1cid><pubinfo><publish>Minnesota Geospatial Information Office (MnGeo)</publish></pubinfo><onlink>https://gisdata.mn.gov/dataset/util-telephone-exchange</onlink></citeinfo></citation><descript><abstract>This data set provides a statewide view of telephone exchange service area boundaries. 

In addition, LATAs (local access and transport areas) and wire centers are included. At the time of the Bell System breakup, Bell operating companies were restricted to operations within specific areas called LATAs. Wire centers or 'wire center serving area', refers to the area to which local service is provided by one or more switches located at a single point. The wire center serving area is often the same area as the exchange, but a wire center can be equal to a portion of an exchange or to several exchanges combined.

The data was compiled in cooperation with the Minnesota Department of Commerce and the Minnesota incumbent local exchange carriers.</abstract><purpose>The data are intended to provide a statewide overview of telephone exchanges and are the official telephone exchange boundary maps in Minnesota. Please contact the Department of Commerce at (651) 539-1500 with questions on any boundary lines.</purpose><supplinf>Minnesota</supplinf></descript><timeperd><timeinfo><sngdate><caldate>201603</caldate></sngdate></timeinfo><current>Any changes in telephone exchange service area ownership that were filed with the Minnesota Department of Commerce and completely processed by the Department of Commerce by March 2016 were incorporated into the data set.</current></timeperd><status><progress>Complete</progress><update>Annually</update></status><spdom><bounding><westbc>-97.23</westbc><eastbc>-89.53</eastbc><northbc>49.37</northbc><southbc>43.5</southbc></bounding></spdom><keywords><theme><themekt>ISO 19115 Topic Category</themekt><themekey>utilitiesCommunication, telephone exchanges, telecommunications, telecom, area code, LATA zone, wire center</themekey></theme><place><placekey>Minnesota, MN</placekey></place></keywords><accconst>None</accconst><useconst>Redistribution conditions:  In obtaining this data from MnGeo, it is understood that you and/or your organization have the right to use it for any purpose.  If you modify it, you are encouraged to apply responsible best practices by documenting those changes in a metadata record.  If you transmit or provide the data to another user, it is your responsibility to provide appropriate content, limitation, warranty and liability information as you see fit.</useconst><browse><browsed>A screen shot of the online ArcGIS online map.</browsed><browsen>ftp://ftp.gisdata.mn.gov/pub/gdrs/data/pub/us_mn_state_mngeo/util_telephone_exchange/metadata/preview.jpg</browsen></browse><native>ArcGIS v.9.2</native><crossref><citeinfo><title>Other related telecommunications GIS data, maps and statistics are described on MnGeo's webpage, 'Telecommunication Infrastructure Information for Minnesota':  http://www.mngeo.state.mn.us/chouse/telecommunication.html

To view and/or download the FCC's national data set: http://apps.fcc.gov/wcb/sabdata/ </title></citeinfo></crossref><ptcontac><cntinfo><cntperp><cntorg>Minnesota Geospatial Information Office (MnGeo)</cntorg><cntper>Norm Anderson</cntper></cntperp><cntpos>GIS Project Manager</cntpos><cntaddr><addrtype>mailing and physical</addrtype><address>658 Cedar Street, Room 300</address><city>St. Paul</city><state>MN</state><postal>55155</postal></cntaddr><cntvoice>(651) 201-2483</cntvoice><cntfax>(651) 296-6398</cntfax><cntemail>gisinfo.mngeo@state.mn.us</cntemail></cntinfo></ptcontac></idinfo><dataqual><attracc><attraccr>The data revision process was conducted through ArcGIS Online where telephone companies had the opportunity to make edits to the boundaries. Once completed, there was a second revision process by the Minnesota Department of Commerce.

No statistical analysis has been conducted.  MnGeo has worked closely with the Department of Commerce to ensure the accuracy of the attribute data.  </attraccr></attracc><logic>Data are topologically structured and verified within ArcGIS.</logic><complete>All updates to the original digitized exchange, area code and LATA information from the Department of Commerce have maintained the original scale.

Geographic areas not covered by a service area are designated "Unassigned".
</complete><posacc><horizpa><horizpar>Telephone companies review the data. Accuracy can range from +/- 400 feet to +/- 40 feet depending on the area. No statistical analysis has been conducted. 

</horizpar></horizpa></posacc><lineage><srcinfo><srcscale>126720</srcscale></srcinfo><procstep><procdesc>In 1992, the Land Management Information Center (LMIC, now MnGeo) began a telecommunications project with the Minnesota Department of Commerce (the Department of Public Service at that time) as part of LMIC's Datanet online data service. MNDOC had exchange boundaries marked on the Minnesota Department of Transportation highway maps (1:126,720 or 1:63,360 scale). LMIC digitized the exchange, area code and LATA boundaries from these maps using EPPL7 version 2 software. A statewide EPPL7 vector file (.dgt) was created, then converted to ARC/INFO coverage format. The datum was NAD27. The last step in this project was the development of the first statewide telecommunications map. This map depicted exchange, area code and LATA boundaries. Exchanges were labeled and shaded by company. Over time, MNDOC and MnGeo have worked together in order to maintain this data by updating area code boundaries, ownership changes, exchange boundary changes, exchange company changes, and company name changes/corrections.

Process steps for 2013 to 2015 dataset:
The Minnesota Department of Commerce (MNDOC), Minnesota Telephone Alliance (MNTA), Minnesota Geospatial Information Office (MnGeo) and 100% of the telephone companies operating in Minnesota formed an ad hoc alliance in 2012/2013 to prepare these boundaries - encompassing all of Minnesota - for submission to the Federal Communications Commission. That alliance continues for this year's submission. FCC Order DA 13-282. To view document, see: https://apps.fcc.gov/edocs_public/attachmatch/DA-13-282A1.pdf 

To expedite the boundary review process prior to FCC submission, a web-based comment and mark-up application was created using Esri's ArcGIS Online (AGOL) product. In addition to map layers available in AGOL, the following digital base maps were provided to assist the companies:
- 2011 (or more recent) aerial photography served by MnGeo:  https://gisdata.mn.gov/dataset/mn-geospatial-image-service
- 2013 municipal and county boundaries (CTUs):  https://gisdata.mn.gov/dataset/bdry-mn-city-township-unorg
- Public Land Survey (PLS) lines:  https://gisdata.mn.gov/dataset/plan-mndnr-public-land-survey

Process:

1. MNTA coordinates boundary review activities with the companies. 

2. MnGeo conducts webinars to refresh the companies on how to use the AGOL application. It also provides a detailed help document to assist them with their review.

3. Telephone companies canreview the boundaries and suggest corrections using a markup layer. Adjoining companies can agree to the proposed changes or suggest their own boundary.

4. Public Land Survey (PLS) quarter-quarter section data is used as a 'snapping' layer to assist the user in making accurate boundary changes.

5. MNDOC reviews the proposed boundary changes offered by the companies and makes corrections to the digital service territories after agreement on the boundary is reached with the companies. Historical, printed maps of the boundaries housed at MNDOC serve as guides to resolve any differences in opinion.

6. GIS data updates:
a. Once MNDOC makes all the agreed upon corrections to the GIS data, MnGeo checks the topology for gaps and overlaps. All topological errors are corrected using several layers as guides: the markup layer, existing exchange boundaries and quarter-quarter section lines.

b. Companies are given a final opportunity to review the data before the submission to the FCC.

c. Known issues:
- In the June 2013 version of the exchange boundaries, resolving topology errors led to some artifacts, i.e., multiple nodes in intersections and some modest shifting of the lines (typically less than 40 feet).
- There remain some outstanding, proposed boundary changes where an agreement has not been reached between the affected companies. This does not suggest that the boundaries are inaccurate. Rather, due to the timeline for this project, not all of the outstanding issues could be addressed. All such issues are anticipated to be addressed in future submissions and all affected companies are aware of this intent.</procdesc></procstep></lineage></dataqual><spdoinfo><indspref></indspref><direct>Vector</direct><mgmg3obj>Polygon</mgmg3obj><mgmg3til>State</mgmg3til></spdoinfo><spref><vertdef><altsys><altdatum>not applicable</altdatum></altsys><depthsys><depthdn>not applicable</depthdn></depthsys></vertdef><horizsys><planar><gridsys><gridsysn>Universal Transverse Mercator</gridsysn><utm><utmzone>15</utmzone></utm></gridsys><planci><plandu>meters</plandu></planci></planar><geodetic><horizdn>NAD83</horizdn><ellips>GRS80</ellips></geodetic></horizsys></spref><eainfo><detailed><enttyp><enttypl>telephone_exchange_service_areas</enttypl></enttyp><attr><attrlabl>FID</attrlabl><attrdef>A unique ID representing each feature in the shapefile. This field is automatically created with the shapefile.</attrdef><attrdefs>ESRI</attrdefs></attr><attr><attrlabl>Shape</attrlabl><attrdef>Stores the type of geometry associated with the feature. This field is automatically created with the shapefile.</attrdef><attrdefs>ESRI</attrdefs></attr><attr><attrlabl>ID</attrlabl><attrdef>A virtual column created by ArcGIS to guarantee that each record has at least one unique value.</attrdef><attrdefs>ESRI</attrdefs></attr><attr><attrlabl>OCN</attrlabl><attrdef>The four digit NECA(National Exchange Carrier Association) Operating Company Number associated with the polygon.</attrdef><attrdefs>FCC</attrdefs></attr><attr><attrlabl>CO_NAME</attrlabl><attrdef>The company name associated with the polygon. The preferred format for this field is upper case.</attrdef><attrdefs>FCC</attrdefs></attr><attr><attrlabl>EXCHANGE</attrlabl><attrdef>The exchange name associated with the polygon. The preferred format for this field is upper case. If submitting wire center boundaries, or if the polygon represents the study area boundary only, this field may be left blank.</attrdef><attrdefs>FCC</attrdefs></attr><attr><attrlabl>WIRECENTER</attrlabl><attrdef>The eight character CLLI (Common Language Location Identifier) code associated with the polygon. If submitting exchange boundaries, or if the polygon represents the study area boundary only, this field may be left blank.</attrdef><attrdefs>FCC</attrdefs></attr><attr><attrlabl>SAC</attrlabl><attrdef>The six digit Study Area Code assigned to each carrier by NECA (National Exchange Carrier Association, Inc.) or USAC (Universal Service Administrative Company) associated with the polygon.</attrdef><attrdefs>FCC</attrdefs></attr><attr><attrlabl>STATE</attrlabl><attrdef>The two character United States Postal Service state abbreviation for the state corresponding to the Study Area Code associated with the polygon.</attrdef><attrdefs>FCC</attrdefs></attr><attr><attrlabl>FROZEN</attrlabl><attrdef>A single character relating to the status of frozen support for the company associated with the polygon. If a rural carrier purchases an exchange from a non-rural carrier that receives support based on the FCC's High Cost Model (HCM) for non-rural carriers, the loops of the acquired exchange receive the same per-line support as calculated at the time of the transfer under the HCM component.Acceptable values are "Y" (Yes), or "N" (No). If the polygon represents the study area boundary only this field may be left blank.</attrdef><attrdefs>FCC</attrdefs></attr><attr><attrlabl>BOUND_TYPE</attrlabl><attrdef>A two character identifier for the type of boundary represented by the polygon. Acceptable values are "SA" (Study Area), "EX" (Exchange), or "WC" (Wire Center).</attrdef><attrdefs>FCC</attrdefs></attr><attr><attrlabl>LATA</attrlabl><attrdef>Local access and transport area ID code (at the time of the Bell System breakup, Bell operating companies were restricted to operations within specific areas called LATAs)</attrdef><attrdefs>FCC</attrdefs></attr><attr><attrlabl>AREACODE</attrlabl><attrdef>3-digit telephone area code.</attrdef><attrdefs>FCC</attrdefs></attr><attr><attrlabl>METROCALL</attrlabl><attrdef>Area of the Twin Cities metro in which there is flat-rate calling.</attrdef><attrdefs>Minnesota Department of Commerce</attrdefs></attr></detailed></eainfo><distinfo><distliab>MnGeo's data disclaimer is online: http://www.mngeo.state.mn.us/chouse/disclaimer.html</distliab><stdorder><digform><digtinfo><formname>Shapefile</formname><formvern></formvern><transize>The zip file is 2 megabytes.</transize></digtinfo></digform><ordering>This data set (GIS formats only) is distributed on the internet by clicking below after Online Linkage.  

The Telephone Exchange webpage can be accessed here: http://minnesota.maps.arcgis.com/apps/OnePane/basicviewer/index.html?appid=a61fe43236994d43b097d439befb8e70

The Telephone Exchange ArcGIS REST service can be found here: http://geoserver.state.mn.us/arcgis/rest/services/Telex/FCC_20130620v2/MapServer
Note: the date in the REST url is when the service was set up in 2013, not the date of the data. The data delivered by the service is current.</ordering></stdorder><resdesc>Minnesota Telephone Exchange Service Area Boundaries 2016</resdesc><distrib><cntinfo><cntperp><cntorg>Minnesota Geospatial Information Office (MnGeo)</cntorg><cntper>Nancy Rader</cntper></cntperp><cntpos>GIS Data Coordinator</cntpos><cntaddr><addrtype>mailing and physical</addrtype><address>658 Cedar Street, Room 300</address><city>St. Paul</city><state>MN</state><postal>55155</postal></cntaddr><cntvoice>(651) 201-2489</cntvoice><cntemail>gisinfo.mngeo@state.mn.us</cntemail></cntinfo></distrib></distinfo><metainfo><metd>20160328</metd><metstdn>Minnesota Geographic Metadata Guidelines</metstdn><metstdv>1.2</metstdv><metextns><onlink>http://www.mngeo.state.mn.us/committee/standards/mgmg/metadata.htm</onlink></metextns><metc><cntinfo><cntperp><cntorg>Minnesota Geospatial Information Office (MnGeo)</cntorg><cntper>Nancy Rader</cntper></cntperp><cntpos>GIS Data Coordinator</cntpos><cntaddr><addrtype>mailing and physical</addrtype><address>658 Cedar Street, Room 300</address><city>St. Paul</city><state>MN</state><postal>55155</postal></cntaddr><cntvoice>(651) 201-2489</cntvoice><cntemail>gisinfo.mngeo@state.mn.us</cntemail></cntinfo></metc></metainfo><Esri><ModDate>20100819</ModDate><ModTime>08583700</ModTime></Esri><mdDateSt Sync="TRUE">20100819</mdDateSt></metadata>