<metadata>
  <idinfo>
    <citation>
      <citeinfo>
        <pubdate>20140828</pubdate>
        <title catid="39142bd7-29a0-4bc9-baac-fe7c58fd5fca">Hennepin County Wetland Inventory</title>
        <geoform>vector digital data</geoform>
		<pubdate>2014</pubdate>
		<onlink>http://gis-stage.hennepin.us/publicgisdata/NaturalResourcesPacket.zip</onlink>
        <pubinfo>
          <publish>Hennepin County - Department of Environmental Services - Land &amp; Water Unit</publish>
        </pubinfo>
      </citeinfo>
    </citation>
    <descript>
      <abstract>The original Hennepin County Wetland Inventory (HCWI) was developed from the remote sensing of multiple years of orthophotograpy in combination with the analysis of related GIS layers and 10 years of Natural Resources Conservation Service slide reviews to identify and include farmed wetlands. The HCWI does not classify wetlands but merely locates them, whereas the NWI classifies wetlands based on the Cowardin methodology utilizing remotely gathered data and photo signature. For more information concerning detail on procedures followed to develop the HCWI contact Hennepin County Dept. of Environmental Services.National Wetland Inventory Metadata:The National Wetland Inventory (NWI) for east-central Minnesota were updated through multi-agency collaborative effort under leadership from the Minnesota DNR. Operational support for wetland mapping and classification was provided by Ducks Unlimited and support for methods development and field validation were provided by the Remote Sensing and Geospatial Analysis Laboratory at the University of Minnesota. Major funding was provided by the Environmental and Natural Resources Trust Fund.The project area consists of 13 counties in east-central Minnesota including: Anoka, Carver, Chisago, Dakota, Goodhue, Hennepin, Isanti, Ramsey, Rice, Scott, Sherburne, Washington, and Wright Counties. The updated wetland inventory area included complete coverage for all USGS quarter quadrangles that intersect any of these counties (about 7,150 square mile). The NWI classification process for east-central Minnesota consisted of three basic steps: 1) creation of image segments (polygons), 2) RandomForest classification of the segments, and 3) photo-interpretation of the classified image segments. The updated NWI also contains a Simplified Plant Community Classification and a Simplified Hydrogemorphic Classification. Quality assurance of the data included a 100% visual inspection, automated checks for attribute validity and topologic consistency, as well as a formal accuracy assessment based on an independent field verified data set. Further details on the methods employed can be found in the technical procedures document for this project (provide URL). The updated NWI data are primarily based on aerial imagery acquired in 2010 and 2011 as well as other modern ancillary data. This data is intended to replace the original NWI data which was based on imagery acquired in the early 1980s. NWI data support effective wetland management, protection, and restoration. The data provide a baseline for assessing the effectiveness of wetland policies and management actions. These data are used at all levels of government, as well as by private industry and non-profit organizations for wetland regulation and management, land use and conservation planning, environmental impact assessment, and natural resource inventories.</abstract>
      <purpose>This combined wetland inventory was created to assist in the identification and location of existing and potential wetland basins within Hennepin County, Minnesota.  The wetland data presented in this layer is a combination of the existing Hennepin County Wetland Inventory (HCWI), the existing National Wetland Inventory (NWI) and information derived from the Minnesota Land Cover Classification information for Hennepin County.

SPECIAL NOTE:  Those who are required by statue to use the National Wetland Inventory for tax assessment purposes will need to use the INVENTORY field to select only the NWI wetlands for display purposes.


National Wetland Inventory Metadata:

The updated NWI data are based on recent aerial imagery (2010 and 2011) as well as other recent ancillary data. These data are intended to replace the original NWI data which was based on imagery acquired in the early 1980s. NWI data support effective wetland management, protection, and restoration. The data provide a baseline for assessing the effectiveness of wetland policies and management actions. These data are used at all levels of government, as well as by private industry and non-profit organizations for wetland regulation and management, land use and conservation planning, environmental impact assessment, and natural resource inventories.
</purpose>
      <supplinf>Hennepin County</supplinf>
    </descript>
    <status>
      <progress>In work</progress>
      <update>As needed</update>
    </status>
    <spdom>
      <bounding>
        <westbc>-93.882803</westbc>
        <eastbc>-93.124140</eastbc>
        <northbc>45.253181</northbc>
        <southbc>44.746694</southbc>
      </bounding>
    </spdom>
    <keywords>
      <theme>
        <themekt>None</themekt>
        <themekey>Surface Water, Wetlands, Swamp, Marsh, Bog, Fen, Wetland Inventory, Wetlands, Wetland Basins</themekey>
      </theme>
      <theme>
        <themekt>ISO 19115 Topic Categories</themekt>
        <themekey>environment</themekey>
        <themekey>inlandWaters</themekey>
        <themekey>boundaries</themekey>
        <themekey>location</themekey>
      </theme>
      <place>
        <placekt>None</placekt>
        <placekey>Hennepin County</placekey>
        <placekey>Minnesota</placekey>
        <placekey>Twin Cities</placekey>
      </place>
    </keywords>
    <accconst>None</accconst>
    <useconst>Federal, state, and local regulatory agencies with jurisdiction over wetlands may define and describe wetlands in a different manner than that used in this inventory. There is no attempt, in either the design or products of this inventory, to define the limits of proprietary jurisdiction of any federal, state, or local government or to establish the geographical scope of the regulatory programs of government agencies. Persons intending to engage in activities involving modifications within or adjacent to wetland areas should seek the advice of appropriate federal, state, or local agencies concerning specified agency regulatory programs and proprietary jurisdictions that may affect such activities. NWI information is not intended to be used as a precise locator of wetland boundaries, for site specific planning or management, or for regulatory purposes. The NWI maps do not show all wetlands since the maps are derived from aerial photointerpretation with varying limitations due to scale, photo quality, inventory techniques, and other factors. Consequently, the maps tend to show wetlands that are readily photointerpreted given consideration of photo and map scale. In general, the older NWI maps prepared from 1970s-era black and white photography (1:80,000 scale) tend to be very conservative, with many forested and drier-end emergent wetlands (e.g., wet meadows) not mapped. Maps derived from color infrared photography tend to yield more accurate results except when this photography was captured during a dry year, making wetland identification equally difficult. Proper use of NWI maps therefore requires knowledge of the inherent limitations of this mapping. It is suggested that users also consult other information to aid in wetland detection, such as U.S. Department of Agriculture soil survey reports and other wetland maps that may have been produced by state and local governments, and not rely solely on NWI maps. See section on Completeness_Report for more information. Also see an article in the National Wetlands Newsletter (March-April 1997; Vol. 19/2, pp. 5-12) entitled NWI Maps: What They Tell Us (a free copy of this article can be ordered from U.S. Fish and Wildlife Service, ES-NWI, 300 Westgate Center Drive, Hadley, MA 01035). ADDED by HC GIS OFFICE: All data and information ("Products") contained herein are for informational purposes only. Although such Products are believed to be accurate at the time of printing or distribution, Hennepin County does not warrant that such Products are error free. Hennepin County provides these Products on an "as is" basis without warranties of any kind, either express or implied, including, but not limited to, warranties of title or implied warranties of merchantability or fitness for a particular purpose. Hennepin County shall not be liable for any direct, indirect, incidental, special or consequential damages arising out of the use of such Products, or the inability to use such Products or out of any breach of any warranty. The user acknowledges and agrees that the use of such Products is at the sole risk of the user. General questions about this or any other Hennepin County GIS products, including errors, omissions, corrections and/or updates should be directed to the custodial department or division listed in the metadata contact information.</useconst>
    <ptcontac>
      <cntinfo>
        <cntorgp>
          <cntorg>Hennepin County - Department of Environmental Services - Land &amp; Water Unit</cntorg>
        </cntorgp>
        <cntaddr>
          <addrtype>mailing and physical</addrtype>
          <address>701 4th Avenue South #700</address>
          <city>Minneapolis</city>
          <state>MN</state>
          <postal>55415-1842</postal>
          <country>US</country>
        </cntaddr>
        <cntvoice>(612) 348-3777</cntvoice>
        <cntfax>(612) 348-8532</cntfax>
        <cntemail>DESMail@co.hennepin.mn.us</cntemail>
        <hours>08:00-16:30</hours>
        <cntinst>For more information ask for Land &amp; Water Unit</cntinst>
      </cntinfo>
    </ptcontac>
    <datacred>Hennepin County, Minnesota Department of Natural Resources, MN Legislative-Citizen Commission on Minnesota Resources (LCCMR), US Fish &amp; Wildlife Service, Board of Water and Soil Resources</datacred>
    <native>Microsoft Windows 7 Version 6.1 (Build 7601) Service Pack 1; Esri ArcGIS 10.2.2.3552</native>
  </idinfo>
  <dataqual>
    <complete>This data set represents the extent of wetlands and deepwater habitats that can be determined with the use of remotely sensed data and within the timeframe for which the layer was produced. The accuracy of image interpretation depends on the quality of the imagery, the experience of the image analysts, the amount and quality of the collateral data, and the amount of ground truth verification work conducted.</complete>
    <posacc>
      <horizpa>
        <horizpar>Source layer wetl_nwi2py3:  The base imagery used to develop the NWI data has a horizontal RMSE of 1.53 meters. Wetland boundaries typically exist along a gradient of hydrology, soils, and vegetation and determining precise locations can be difficult even in the field.</horizpar>
      </horizpa>
    </posacc>
  </dataqual>
  <spdoinfo>
    <direct>Vector</direct>
    <ptvctinf>
      <sdtsterm>
        <sdtstype>GT-polygon composed of chains</sdtstype>
        <ptvctcnt>110469</ptvctcnt>
      </sdtsterm>
    </ptvctinf>
  </spdoinfo>
  <spref>
    <horizsys>
      <planar>
        <mapproj>
          <mapprojn>NAD 1983 UTM Zone 15N</mapprojn>
          <transmer>
            <sfctrmer>0.9996</sfctrmer>
            <longcm>-93.0</longcm>
            <latprjo>0.0</latprjo>
            <feast>500000.0</feast>
            <fnorth>0.0</fnorth>
          </transmer>
        </mapproj>
        <planci>
          <plance>coordinate pair</plance>
          <coordrep>
            <absres>0.000000002220024164500956</absres>
            <ordres>0.000000002220024164500956</ordres>
          </coordrep>
          <plandu>meter</plandu>
        </planci>
      </planar>
      <geodetic>
        <horizdn>D North American 1983</horizdn>
        <ellips>GRS 1980</ellips>
        <semiaxis>6378137.0</semiaxis>
        <denflat>298.257222101</denflat>
      </geodetic>
    </horizsys>
  </spref>
  <eainfo>
    <detailed>
      <enttyp>
        <enttypl>HC_WETLAND_INVENTORY</enttypl>
      </enttyp>
      <attr>
        <attrlabl>FID</attrlabl>
        <attrdef>Internal feature number.</attrdef>
        <attrdefs>Esri</attrdefs>
        <attrdomv>
          <udom>Sequential unique whole numbers that are automatically generated.</udom>
        </attrdomv>
      </attr>
      <attr>
        <attrlabl>Shape</attrlabl>
        <attrdef>Feature geometry.</attrdef>
        <attrdefs>ESRI</attrdefs>
        <attrdomv>
          <udom>Coordinates defining the features.</udom>
        </attrdomv>
      </attr>
      <attr>
        <attrlabl>WETLAND_ID</attrlabl>
        <attrdef>Wetland Identification Number -  This is a wetland identification alphanumeric code used by the Hennepin County Wetland Inventory.

Preceding "D" indicates a completely or partially drained wetland. 

Preceding "E" indicates an existing wetland with no apparent drainage. (This indicator is a best-guess from remote sensing techniques.)

Preceding "M" indicates a mitigation wetland or stormwater pond.

NOTE:  Not all wetland basins in this data set will have a WETLAND_ID number.
</attrdef>
      </attr>
      <attr>
        <attrlabl>SITE</attrlabl>
        <attrdef>Wetland basin site code.  Used by Hennepin County Wetland Inventory process.

Preceding "D" indicates a completely or partially drained wetland. 

Preceding "E" indicates an existing wetland with no apparent drainage. (This indicator is a best-guess from remote sensing techniques.)

Preceding "M" indicates a mitigation wetland or stormwater pond.

NOTE:  Not all wetland basins in this data set will have a SITE code.</attrdef>
      </attr>
      <attr>
        <attrlabl>TYPE</attrlabl>
        <attrdef>A wetland type code used by the Hennepin County Wetland Inventory.

AWET - Altered wetland
MWET - Potential mitigation site
NWET - Wetlands that have been impacted since the original inventory was completed (2010/2011 Wetland Inventory Update)
RWET - Potentially restorable basin and/or restorable wetland


NOTE:  Not all wetland basins in this data set will have a TYPE code.</attrdef>
      </attr>
      <attr>
        <attrlabl>ACRES</attrlabl>
        <attrdef>Area of the polygon in acres.</attrdef>
        <attrdefs>Calculated in an UTM zone 15 projection using ESRI's geometry calculator.</attrdefs>
      </attr>
      <attr>
        <attrlabl>PERIMETER</attrlabl>
        <attrdef>The perimeter of the polygon features in feet.</attrdef>
        <attrdefs>Calculated in an UTM zone 15 projection using ESRI's geometry calculator.</attrdefs>
      </attr>
      <attr>
        <attrlabl>Hectares</attrlabl>
        <attrdef>Area of the polygon in hectacres.</attrdef>
        <attrdefs>Calculated in an UTM zone 15 projection using ESRI's geometry calculator.</attrdefs>
      </attr>
      <attr>
        <attrlabl>Legend</attrlabl>
        <attrdef>Narrative wetland description used for basic mapping purposes.

Impacted Wetland : Wetland basin has been impacted by human activity.
Lake : Wetland basin that is a lake by definition.
Potential Wetland - HCWI : Wetland basin that may or may not be an actual wetland. Identified by HC Wetland Inventory process.
Probable Wetland - HCWI : Wetland basin that has been determined to likely be an actual wetland. Identified by HC Wetland Inventory process.
Probable Wetland - NWI : Wetland basin that has been determined to likely be an actual wetland. Identified by National Wetland Inventory process.
</attrdef>
      </attr>
      <attr>
        <attrlabl>ATTRIBUTE</attrlabl>
        <attrdef>Alphanumeric code identifying the wetland classification of the polygon.</attrdef>
        <attrdefs>http://www.fws.gov/wetlands/Data/wetlandcodes.html</attrdefs>
      </attr>
      <attr>
        <attrlabl>HGM_CODE</attrlabl>
        <attrdef>Hydrogeomorphic classification code.</attrdef>
        <attrdefs>ftp://ftp.dnr.state.mn.us/pub/eco/nwi/MappingGuidance/NWI_ecmn_Technical_Documentation_051713.pdf</attrdefs>
      </attr>
      <attr>
        <attrlabl>WETLAND_TY</attrlabl>
        <attrdef>General description of  the wetland classification.</attrdef>
        <attrdefs>http://www.fws.gov/wetlands/Data/MapperTips.html</attrdefs>
      </attr>
      <attr>
        <attrlabl>SPCC</attrlabl>
        <attrdef>Simplified Plant Community Classification.

Classifications:  Seasonally Flooded Basin, Wet Meadow, Shallow Marsh, Deep Marsh, Shallow Open Water Community, Peatland, Shrub Wetland, Hardwood Wetland, Coniferous Swamp, Non-Vegetated Aquatic Community</attrdef>
        <attrdefs>ftp://ftp.dnr.state.mn.us/pub/eco/nwi/MappingGuidance/NWI_ecmn_Technical_Documentation_051713.pdf</attrdefs>
      </attr>
      <attr>
        <attrlabl>Landscape</attrlabl>
        <attrdef>HGM Landscape Attribute.

Codes: 
Lentic = Associated with a lake
Lotic River = Associated with a wide river
Lotic Stream = Associated with a narrow stream
Terrene = Not associated with a lake, river, or stream</attrdef>
        <attrdefs>ftp://ftp.dnr.state.mn.us/pub/eco/nwi/MappingGuidance/NWI_ecmn_Technical_Documentation_051713.pdf</attrdefs>
      </attr>
      <attr>
        <attrlabl>Landform</attrlabl>
        <attrdef>HGM Landform Attribute.

Codes:
Slope = Occurs on land with slope &gt; 2%
Island = Completely surrounded by open water
Fringe = Adjacent to, and frequently inundated by open water
Floodplain = Periodically inundated by high water from adjacent open water feature
Basin = Occurs in a distinct topographic depression
Flat = Occurs on nearly level land</attrdef>
        <attrdefs>ftp://ftp.dnr.state.mn.us/pub/eco/nwi/MappingGuidance/NWI_ecmn_Technical_Documentation_051713.pdf</attrdefs>
      </attr>
      <attr>
        <attrlabl>WaterFlow</attrlabl>
        <attrdef>HGM Water flow path attribute.

Codes:
Inflow = Water flows in from an identifiable surface channel
Outflow = Water flows out from an indentifiable surface channel
Throughflow = water flows both in and out through identifiable surface channels
Bidirectional-Nontidal = Water flows back and forth from an adjacent open water feature depending upon water levels
Isolated = Wetland has no identifiable surface connections</attrdef>
        <attrdefs>ftp://ftp.dnr.state.mn.us/pub/eco/nwi/MappingGuidance/NWI_ecmn_Technical_Documentation_051713.pdf</attrdefs>
      </attr>
      <attr>
        <attrlabl>HGM_NAME</attrlabl>
        <attrdef>Full HGM name.</attrdef>
        <attrdefs>ftp://ftp.dnr.state.mn.us/pub/eco/nwi/MappingGuidance/NWI_ecmn_Technical_Documentation_051713.pdf</attrdefs>
      </attr>
      <attr>
        <attrlabl>Cow_Class1</attrlabl>
        <attrdef>Cowardin Wetland Classification system class code.

Codes:
AB = Aquatic Bed
EM = Emergent
FO = Forested
RB = Rock Bottom
RF = Reef
RS = Rocky Shore
SB = Streambed
SS = Scrub-Shrub
UB = Unconsolidated Bottom
US = Unconsolidated Shore</attrdef>
      </attr>
      <attr>
        <attrlabl>Circ39_Cla</attrlabl>
        <attrdef>Wetland type under the old Circular39 wetland classification system.</attrdef>
      </attr>
      <attr>
        <attrlabl>LL_Class</attrlabl>
        <attrdef>Combination of Landscape and Landform field codes.</attrdef>
      </attr>
      <attr>
        <attrlabl>INVENTORY</attrlabl>
        <attrdef>This field denotes which wetland inventory project the wetland basin was identified by.    [ HCWI = Hennepin County Wetland Inventory, NWI = National Wetland Inventory ]</attrdef>
      </attr>
      <attr>
        <attrlabl>Shape_Leng</attrlabl>
      </attr>
      <attr>
        <attrlabl>Shape_Area</attrlabl>
        <attrdef>Area of feature in internal units squared.</attrdef>
        <attrdefs>Esri</attrdefs>
        <attrdomv>
          <udom>Positive real numbers that are automatically generated.</udom>
        </attrdomv>
      </attr>
    </detailed>
  </eainfo>
  <distinfo>
    <distrib>
      <cntinfo>
        <cntorgp>
          <cntorg>Hennepin County - Department of Environmental Services - Land &amp; Water Unit</cntorg>
        </cntorgp>
        <cntaddr>
          <addrtype>unknown</addrtype>
          <address>701 4th Street South #700</address>
          <city>Minneapolis</city>
          <state>MN</state>
          <postal>55415-1942</postal>
          <country>US</country>
        </cntaddr>
        <cntvoice>(612) 348-3777</cntvoice>
        <cntfax>(612) 348-8532</cntfax>
        <cntemail>DESMail@co.hennepin.mn.us</cntemail>
        <hours>08:00-16:30</hours>
      </cntinfo>
    </distrib>
    <distliab>See access and use constraints information.</distliab>
  </distinfo>
  <metainfo>
    <metd>20141110</metd>
    <metc>
      <cntinfo>
        <cntorgp>
          <cntorg>Hennepin County - Department of Environmental Services - Land &amp; Water Unit</cntorg>
        </cntorgp>
        <cntaddr>
          <addrtype>mailing and physical</addrtype>
          <address>701 4th Street South #700</address>
          <city>Minneapolis</city>
          <state>MN</state>
          <postal>55415-1842</postal>
          <country>US</country>
        </cntaddr>
        <cntvoice>(612) 348-3777</cntvoice>
        <cntfax>(612) 348-8532</cntfax>
        <cntemail>DESMail@co.hennepin.mn.us</cntemail>
        <hours>08:00-16:40</hours>
      </cntinfo>
    </metc>
    <metstdn>FGDC Content Standard for Digital Geospatial Metadata</metstdn>
    <metstdv>FGDC-STD-001-1998</metstdv>
    <mettc>local time</mettc>
    <metuc>Federal, state, and local regulatory agencies with jurisdiction over wetlands may define and describe wetlands in a different manner than that used in this inventory. There is no attempt, in either the design or products of this inventory, to define the limits of proprietary jurisdiction of any federal, state, or local government or to establish the geographical scope of the regulatory programs of government agencies. Persons intending to engage in activities involving modifications within or adjacent to wetland areas should seek the advice of appropriate federal, state, or local agencies concerning specified agency regulatory programs and proprietary jurisdictions that may affect such activities. NWI information is not intended to be used as a precise locator of wetland boundaries, for site specific planning or management, or for regulatory purposes. The NWI maps do not show all wetlands since the maps are derived from aerial photointerpretation with varying limitations due to scale, photo quality, inventory techniques, and other factors. Consequently, the maps tend to show wetlands that are readily photointerpreted given consideration of photo and map scale. In general, the older NWI maps prepared from 1970s-era black and white photography (1:80,000 scale) tend to be very conservative, with many forested and drier-end emergent wetlands (e.g., wet meadows) not mapped. Maps derived from color infrared photography tend to yield more accurate results except when this photography was captured during a dry year, making wetland identification equally difficult. Proper use of NWI maps therefore requires knowledge of the inherent limitations of this mapping. It is suggested that users also consult other information to aid in wetland detection, such as U.S. Department of Agriculture soil survey reports and other wetland maps that may have been produced by state and local governments, and not rely solely on NWI maps. See section on Completeness_Report for more information. Also see an article in the National Wetlands Newsletter (March-April 1997; Vol. 19/2, pp. 5-12) entitled NWI Maps: What They Tell Us (a free copy of this article can be ordered from U.S. Fish and Wildlife Service, ES-NWI, 300 Westgate Center Drive, Hadley, MA 01035). ADDED by HC GIS OFFICE: All data and information ("Products") contained herein are for informational purposes only. Although such Products are believed to be accurate at the time of printing or distribution, Hennepin County does not warrant that such Products are error free. Hennepin County provides these Products on an "as is" basis without warranties of any kind, either express or implied, including, but not limited to, warranties of title or implied warranties of merchantability or fitness for a particular purpose. Hennepin County shall not be liable for any direct, indirect, incidental, special or consequential damages arising out of the use of such Products, or the inability to use such Products or out of any breach of any warranty. The user acknowledges and agrees that the use of such Products is at the sole risk of the user. General questions about this or any other Hennepin County GIS products, including errors, omissions, corrections and/or updates should be directed to the custodial department or division listed in the metadata contact information.</metuc>
  </metainfo>
</metadata>