<metadata>
  <idinfo>
    <citation>
      <citeinfo>
        <title catid="d542ba16-aa30-4d60-a691-da8ea22438a4">SAFETY_FIRE_STATIONS</title>
        <geoform>vector digital data</geoform>
		<pubdate>2014</pubdate>
		<onlink>http://gis-stage.hennepin.us/publicgisdata/SAFETY_FIRE_STATIONS.zip</onlink>
      </citeinfo>
    </citation>
    <spdom>
      <bounding>
        <westbc>-93.752174</westbc>
        <eastbc>-93.216955</eastbc>
        <northbc>45.243760</northbc>
        <southbc>44.809598</southbc>
      </bounding>
    </spdom>
    <accconst>None</accconst>
    <useconst>None</useconst>
    <native>Microsoft Windows 7 Version 6.1 (Build 7601) Service Pack 1; Esri ArcGIS 10.2.2.3552</native>
  </idinfo>
  <spdoinfo>
    <direct>Vector</direct>
    <ptvctinf>
      <sdtsterm>
        <sdtstype>Entity point</sdtstype>
        <ptvctcnt>82</ptvctcnt>
      </sdtsterm>
    </ptvctinf>
  </spdoinfo>
  <spref>
    <horizsys>
      <planar>
        <mapproj>
          <mapprojn>NAD 1983 UTM Zone 15N</mapprojn>
          <transmer>
            <sfctrmer>0.9996</sfctrmer>
            <longcm>-93.0</longcm>
            <latprjo>0.0</latprjo>
            <feast>500000.0</feast>
            <fnorth>0.0</fnorth>
          </transmer>
        </mapproj>
        <planci>
          <plance>coordinate pair</plance>
          <coordrep>
            <absres>0.000000002220024164500956</absres>
            <ordres>0.000000002220024164500956</ordres>
          </coordrep>
          <plandu>meter</plandu>
        </planci>
      </planar>
      <geodetic>
        <horizdn>D North American 1983</horizdn>
        <ellips>GRS 1980</ellips>
        <semiaxis>6378137.0</semiaxis>
        <denflat>298.257222101</denflat>
      </geodetic>
    </horizsys>
  </spref>
  <eainfo>
    <detailed>
      <enttyp>
        <enttypl>SAFETY_FIRE_STATIONS</enttypl>
        <enttypd>Any location where fire fighters are stationed or based out of, or where equipment that such personnel use in carrying out their jobs is stored for ready use. Fire Departments not having a permanent location are included, in which case their location has been depicted at the city/town hall or at the center of their service area if a city/town hall does not exist. This dataset includes those locations primarily engaged in forest or grasslands fire fighting, including fire lookout towers if the towers are in current use for fire protection purposes. This dataset includes both private and governmental entities. Fire fighting training academies are also included.</enttypd>
        <enttypds>TGS</enttypds>
      </enttyp>
      <attr>
        <attrlabl>TOTAL_VEHI</attrlabl>
        <attrdef>
Total number of vehicles associated with the DEPARTMENT.

The values that this field is populated with came from individual states and have not been validated or checked by TGS.
</attrdef>
        <attrdefs>TGS</attrdefs>
        <attrdomv>
          <udom>Number</udom>
        </attrdomv>
      </attr>
      <attr>
        <attrlabl>NBR_STA</attrlabl>
        <attrdef>
The total number of stations associated with the DEPARTMENT.

The values that this field is populated with came from individual states and have not been validated or checked by TGS
</attrdef>
        <attrdefs>TGS</attrdefs>
        <attrdomv>
          <udom>Number</udom>
        </attrdomv>
      </attr>
      <attr>
        <attrlabl>OWNER</attrlabl>
        <attrdef>
The type of ownership for the entity. 

The values that this field is populated with came from individual states and have not been validated or checked by TGS.
</attrdef>
        <attrdefs>TGS</attrdefs>
        <attrdomv>
          <udom>Text</udom>
        </attrdomv>
      </attr>
      <attr>
        <attrlabl>TYPE</attrlabl>
        <attrdef>
Type of employees.

The values that this field is populated with came from individual states and have not been validated or checked by TGS.
</attrdef>
        <attrdefs>TGS</attrdefs>
        <attrdomv>
          <udom>Text</udom>
        </attrdomv>
      </attr>
      <attr>
        <attrlabl>EMS</attrlabl>
        <attrdef>Indicates if the entity also has EMS capabilities.</attrdef>
        <attrdefs>TGS</attrdefs>
        <attrdomv>
          <edom>
            <edomv>Y</edomv>
            <edomvd>Indicates the entity has EMS capabilities.</edomvd>
            <edomvds>TGS</edomvds>
          </edom>
          <udom>Sequential unique whole numbers that are automatically generated.</udom>
        </attrdomv>
        <attrdomv>
          <edom>
            <edomv>N</edomv>
            <edomvd>Indicates the entity does not have EMS capabilities.</edomvd>
            <edomvds>TGS</edomvds>
          </edom>
          <udom>Sequential unique whole numbers that are automatically generated.</udom>
        </attrdomv>
        <attrdomv>
          <edom>
            <edomv>&lt;BLANK&gt;</edomv>
            <edomvd>Unable to determine if entity has EMS capabilities.</edomvd>
            <edomvds>TGS</edomvds>
          </edom>
          <udom>Sequential unique whole numbers that are automatically generated.</udom>
        </attrdomv>
      </attr>
      <attr>
        <attrlabl>Shape</attrlabl>
        <attrdef>Feature geometry.</attrdef>
        <attrdefs>ESRI</attrdefs>
        <attrdomv>
          <udom>Coordinates defining the features.</udom>
        </attrdomv>
      </attr>
      <attr>
        <attrlabl>SHAPE</attrlabl>
        <attrdef>Feature geometry.</attrdef>
        <attrdefs>ESRI</attrdefs>
        <attrdomv>
          <udom>Coordinates defining the features.</udom>
        </attrdomv>
      </attr>
      <attr>
        <attrlabl>ID</attrlabl>
        <attrdef>Unique identifier for feature.</attrdef>
        <attrdefs>TGS</attrdefs>
        <attrdomv>
          <udom>Text</udom>
        </attrdomv>
      </attr>
      <attr>
        <attrlabl>NAME</attrlabl>
        <attrdef>Name of entity.</attrdef>
        <attrdefs>TGS</attrdefs>
        <attrdomv>
          <udom>Text</udom>
        </attrdomv>
      </attr>
      <attr>
        <attrlabl>TELEPHONE</attrlabl>
        <attrdef>Ten (10) digit telephone number for entity formatted as nnn-nnn-nnnn.</attrdef>
        <attrdefs>TGS</attrdefs>
        <attrdomv>
          <udom>Phone numbers formatted as nnn-nnn-nnnn. Only numeric digits are used. The area code and exchange must form a valid combination. A list of valid area code and exchange combinations can be obtained from &lt;http://www.nanpa.com&gt;.</udom>
        </attrdomv>
      </attr>
      <attr>
        <attrlabl>ADDRESS</attrlabl>
        <attrdef>Physical street address for entity. "PO Box", "General Delivery", "Rural Route", and "Highway Contract" addresses are not considered physical addresses and should not appear in this field. Some areas do not have regular city style addressing, so entities in those areas may not have a street number. In such cases, the name of the road on which they are located is listed in this field. Some rural areas may not have named roads. In these rare cases, this field will be blank.</attrdef>
        <attrdefs>TGS</attrdefs>
        <attrdomv>
          <udom>Text</udom>
        </attrdomv>
      </attr>
      <attr>
        <attrlabl>CITY</attrlabl>
        <attrdef>
The name of the city associated with the entity's physical address. For physical addresses that the U.S. Postal Service (USPS) delivers to, this should be a "city" acceptable to the USPS as defined in their Address Information System (AIS). Sometimes the USPS does not deliver mail to a physical address but recognizes the location (i.e., they list the location as "undeliverable"). The cities associated with these locations are acceptable. In some cases, the USPS does not recognize individual physical addresses in a city, rather, they list the city as having "General Delivery". In these cases, the city and associated zip code are acceptable (the entity's [ADDRESS] field will contain a street address, not "general delivery"). The entity may not actually be located within the city limits of the "city" specified in its [CITY] field. Instead, it may actually be located within the city limits of another city. In some cases, the "city" that appears in this field may not even be a city in an administrative sense, but it is still an acceptable "city" to the USPS. An example of this is "Notre Dame, IN". There is no city in Indiana called "Notre Dame", but this is considered an acceptable city by the USPS for any delivery going to the University of Notre Dame which is actually located in the city of South Bend. "Notre Dame", like most USPS cities, is an easily recognized place, and it gives the user of the data a good general idea of where the entity is located (if the entity is located in a small municipality, the USPS "city" may be more recognizable than the name of the municipality), and it would be part of the address one would use to send a shipment to the entity's location. Using the USPS acceptable "city" also allows someone to do a logical consistency check between the zip code and the city by using the USPS AIS.

Sometimes an entity may report a city that is not accepted by the USPS, and although TGS has tried to replace those cities with an acceptable alternative, some of them may remain in this dataset.
</attrdef>
        <attrdefs>TGS</attrdefs>
        <attrdomv>
          <udom>Text</udom>
        </attrdomv>
      </attr>
      <attr>
        <attrlabl>STATE</attrlabl>
        <attrdef>Two (2) character abbreviation for state associated with the entity's physical address. In almost all cases, this is the same as the state where the entity has been depicted geospatially. However, there are cases, particularly where an entity is part of a larger facility that cuts across state lines, where the entity's location may be depicted in a state other than the one indicated in this field. Also, the state in which an entity appears to be located may change depending on the scale of the state boundary theme being used.</attrdef>
        <attrdefs>TGS</attrdefs>
        <attrdomv>
          <codesetd>
            <codesetn>Official USPS Abbreviations - State Abbreviations</codesetn>
            <codesets>United States Postal Service http://www.usps.com/ncsc/lookups/usps_abbreviations.html</codesets>
          </codesetd>
        </attrdomv>
      </attr>
      <attr>
        <attrlabl>ZIP</attrlabl>
        <attrdef>Five (5) digit USPS zip code for entity's physical location.</attrdef>
        <attrdefs>TGS</attrdefs>
        <attrdomv>
          <codesetd>
            <codesetn>USPS Address Information System - Domain is further restricted by only allowing physical (non PO Box) zip codes.</codesetn>
            <codesets>United States Postal Service</codesets>
          </codesetd>
        </attrdomv>
      </attr>
      <attr>
        <attrlabl>ZIPP4</attrlabl>
        <attrdef>Four (4) digit USPS zip code extension.  These values are automatically assigned using the entity's physical address and USPS address information system (AIS) data.</attrdef>
        <attrdefs>TGS</attrdefs>
        <attrdomv>
          <codesetd>
            <codesetn>USPS Address Information System (AIS) - ZIP9</codesetn>
            <codesets>United States Postal Service</codesets>
          </codesetd>
        </attrdomv>
      </attr>
      <attr>
        <attrlabl>DIRECTIONS</attrlabl>
        <attrdef>Directions to entity location, or description of the entity's location.</attrdef>
        <attrdefs>TGS</attrdefs>
        <attrdomv>
          <udom>Text</udom>
        </attrdomv>
      </attr>
      <attr>
        <attrlabl>CONTDATE</attrlabl>
        <attrdef>Date entity was contacted by TGS.</attrdef>
        <attrdefs>TGS</attrdefs>
        <attrdomv>
          <udom>Date</udom>
        </attrdomv>
      </attr>
      <attr>
        <attrlabl>GEODATE</attrlabl>
        <attrdef>Date entity was geocoded by TGS.</attrdef>
        <attrdefs>TGS</attrdefs>
        <attrdomv>
          <udom>Date</udom>
        </attrdomv>
      </attr>
      <attr>
        <attrlabl>NAICSCODE</attrlabl>
        <attrdef>NAICS (North American Industry Classification System) Code for entity. NAICS Codes (and NAICS Descriptions) have been assigned based upon the entity's primary function, regardless of if that is the function that qualified it to be included in this dataset.</attrdef>
        <attrdefs>TGS</attrdefs>
        <attrdomv>
          <codesetd>
            <codesetn>North American Industry Classification System (NAICS 2007)</codesetn>
            <codesets>US Census Bureau - http://www.census.gov/epcd/www/naics.html</codesets>
          </codesetd>
        </attrdomv>
      </attr>
      <attr>
        <attrlabl>NAICSDESCR</attrlabl>
        <attrdef>
NAICS (North American Industry Classification System) Description for entity. The "Index Entries" that appear on the NAICS webpage (http://www.census.gov/epcd/www/naics.html) are being used to populate this field, as opposed to the "NAICS Title". While there is a one to one correspondence between NAICS Codes and "NAICS Titles", there is a one to many relationship between NAICS Codes and the "Index Entries". By using the "Index Entries", we have placed the entities that make up this layer into more specific categories; however, the user of this data should be aware that this was not the intended purpose of these "Index Entries". The "Index Entries" were intended as a way to search the NAICS database and as a way of enumerating ways in which establishments falling under the given NAICS Code may be named. Thus, there are often two or more "Index Entries" that are synonyms, for example: "Prisons" and "Penitentiaries". In cases like this, we have standardized on one "Index Entry".

NAICS Descriptions (and NAICS Codes) have been assigned based upon the entity's primary function, regardless of if that is the function that qualified it to be included in this dataset.
</attrdef>
        <attrdefs>TGS</attrdefs>
        <attrdomv>
          <edom>
            <edomv>AIR AMBULANCE SERVICES</edomv>
            <edomvd>AIR AMBULANCE SERVICES - [NAICS Code 621910]: Entities that are primarily engaged in providing transportation of patients by air that have medical care capabilities are classified under this description.</edomvd>
            <edomvds>TGS</edomvds>
          </edom>
        </attrdomv>
        <attrdomv>
          <edom>
            <edomv>AMBULANCE AND FIRE SERVICE COMBINED</edomv>
            <edomvd>AMBULANCE AND FIRE SERVICE COMBINED - [NAICS Code 922160]: Entities providing ambulance services with fire protection service are classified under this description.</edomvd>
            <edomvds>TGS</edomvds>
          </edom>
        </attrdomv>
        <attrdomv>
          <edom>
            <edomv>AMBULANCE SERVICES, AIR OR GROUND</edomv>
            <edomvd>AMBULANCE SERVICES, AIR OR GROUND - [NAICS Code 621910]: Entities that are primarily engaged in providing transportation of patients by ground or air that have medical care capabilities are classified under this description.</edomvd>
            <edomvds>TGS</edomvds>
          </edom>
        </attrdomv>
        <attrdomv>
          <edom>
            <edomv>FIRE AND RESCUE SERVICE</edomv>
            <edomvd>FIRE AND RESCUE SERVICE - [NAICS Code 922160]: Entities that are involved in fire fighting and rescue service are classified under this description, unless they are privately owned or primarily involved in forest fire fighting.</edomvd>
            <edomvds>TGS</edomvds>
          </edom>
        </attrdomv>
        <attrdomv>
          <edom>
            <edomv>FIRE DEPARTMENTS (E.G., GOVERNMENT, VOLUNTEER (EXCEPT PRIVATE))</edomv>
            <edomvd>FIRE DEPARTMENTS (E.G., GOVERNMENT, VOLUNTEER (EXCEPT PRIVATE)) - [NAICS Code 922160]: Entities that are involved in fire fighting are classified under this description, unless they are privately owned, are primarily involved in forest fire fighting, or also operate a rescue service.</edomvd>
            <edomvds>TGS</edomvds>
          </edom>
        </attrdomv>
        <attrdomv>
          <edom>
            <edomv>FIREFIGHTING, FOREST</edomv>
            <edomvd>FIREFIGHTING, FOREST - [NAICS Code 115310]: Entities that are primarily involved in forest fire fighting are classified under this description.</edomvd>
            <edomvds>TGS</edomvds>
          </edom>
        </attrdomv>
        <attrdomv>
          <edom>
            <edomv>FIRE FIGHTER TRAINING SCHOOLS</edomv>
            <edomvd>FIRE FIGHTER TRAINING SCHOOLS - [NAICS Code 611519]: Entities that are primarily involved in training fire fighters are classified under this description.</edomvd>
            <edomvds>TGS</edomvds>
          </edom>
        </attrdomv>
        <attrdomv>
          <edom>
            <edomv>FIRE FIGHTING SERVICES AS A COMMERCIAL ACTIVITY</edomv>
            <edomvd>FIRE FIGHTING SERVICES AS A COMMERCIAL ACTIVITY - [NAICS Code 561990]: Entities providing fire protection for a commercial facility are classified under this description.</edomvd>
            <edomvds>TGS</edomvds>
          </edom>
        </attrdomv>
        <attrdomv>
          <edom>
            <edomv>FIRE MARSHALS' OFFICES</edomv>
            <edomvd>FIRE MARSHALS' OFFICES - [NAICS Code 922160]: Entities that are fire marshals' offices are classified under this description.</edomvd>
            <edomvds>TGS</edomvds>
          </edom>
        </attrdomv>
        <attrdomv>
          <edom>
            <edomv>POLICE AND FIRE DEPARTMENTS, COMBINED</edomv>
            <edomvd>POLICE AND FIRE DEPARTMENTS, COMBINED - [NAICS Code 922120]: Entities providing combined police and fire protection service are classified under this description.</edomvd>
            <edomvds>TGS</edomvds>
          </edom>
        </attrdomv>
        <attrdomv>
          <edom>
            <edomv>PRIVATE VOLUNTEER FIRE FIGHTING</edomv>
            <edomvd>PRIVATE VOLUNTEER FIRE FIGHTING - [NAICS Code 561990]: Entities providing fire fighting services that are privately owned and whose fire fighters are volunteers are classified under this description.</edomvd>
            <edomvds>TGS</edomvds>
          </edom>
        </attrdomv>
      </attr>
      <attr>
        <attrlabl>GEOLINKID</attrlabl>
        <attrdef>Link ID for the street segment to which the entity was geocoded. Refer to the [ST_VENDOR] and [ST_VERSION] fields for the street vendor and version that was used to geocode the entity.</attrdef>
        <attrdefs>TGS</attrdefs>
        <attrdomv>
          <udom>Text</udom>
        </attrdomv>
      </attr>
      <attr>
        <attrlabl>PHONELOC</attrlabl>
        <attrdef>Indicates whether the phone number in the [TELEPHONE] field rings to the actual location of the entity.</attrdef>
        <attrdefs>TGS</attrdefs>
        <attrdomv>
          <edom>
            <edomv>YES</edomv>
            <edomvd>Phone number rings to the actual entity location.</edomvd>
            <edomvds>TGS</edomvds>
          </edom>
        </attrdomv>
        <attrdomv>
          <edom>
            <edomv>NO</edomv>
            <edomvd>Phone number does not ring to the actual entity location. It may ring to an administrative office or central location.</edomvd>
            <edomvds>TGS</edomvds>
          </edom>
        </attrdomv>
        <attrdomv>
          <edom>
            <edomv>&lt;BLANK&gt;</edomv>
            <edomvd>Unknown - It is not known if the entity's phone number rings to the entity's location.</edomvd>
            <edomvds>TGS</edomvds>
          </edom>
        </attrdomv>
      </attr>
      <attr>
        <attrlabl>STATE_ID</attrlabl>
        <attrdef>State Fire Station Data ID. For states that contributed data, this field is populated with the unique ID used by the state to track Fire Stations.</attrdef>
        <attrdefs>TGS</attrdefs>
        <attrdomv>
          <udom>Text</udom>
        </attrdomv>
      </attr>
      <attr>
        <attrlabl>FDID</attrlabl>
        <attrdef>A unique five-character identifier assigned by the state to identify a particular fire department within the state. The first two characters designate the county and the last three designate the department within the county. This identifier is only unique within each state, not nationwide.</attrdef>
        <attrdefs>TGS</attrdefs>
        <attrdomv>
          <udom>Text</udom>
        </attrdomv>
      </attr>
      <attr>
        <attrlabl>FRST_MBRS</attrlabl>
        <attrdef>
Total number of fire fighter members associated with the DEPARTMENT.

The values that this field is populated with came from individual states and have not been validated or checked by TGS
</attrdef>
        <attrdefs>TGS</attrdefs>
        <attrdomv>
          <udom>Number</udom>
        </attrdomv>
      </attr>
      <attr>
        <attrlabl>EMS_MBRS</attrlabl>
        <attrdef>
Total number of EMS members associated with the DEPARTMENT.

The values that this field is populated with came from individual states and have not been validated or checked by TGS
</attrdef>
        <attrdefs>TGS</attrdefs>
        <attrdomv>
          <udom>Number</udom>
        </attrdomv>
      </attr>
      <attr>
        <attrlabl>TOTALPERS</attrlabl>
        <attrdef>
Total number of members associated with the DEPARTMENT.

The values that this field is populated with came from individual states and have not been validated or checked by TGS.
</attrdef>
        <attrdefs>TGS</attrdefs>
        <attrdomv>
          <udom>Number</udom>
        </attrdomv>
      </attr>
      <attr>
        <attrlabl>NUMTRKS</attrlabl>
        <attrdef>
Total number of fire trucks associated with the DEPARTMENT.

The values that this field is populated with came from individual states and have not been validated or checked by TGS.
</attrdef>
        <attrdefs>TGS</attrdefs>
        <attrdomv>
          <udom>Number</udom>
        </attrdomv>
      </attr>
      <attr>
        <attrlabl>NUMABUL</attrlabl>
        <attrdef>
Total number of ambulances associated with the DEPARTMENT.

The values that this field is populated with came from individual states and have not been validated or checked by TGS
</attrdef>
        <attrdefs>TGS</attrdefs>
        <attrdomv>
          <udom>Number</udom>
        </attrdomv>
      </attr>
    </detailed>
    <overview>
      <eaover />
      <eadetcit />
    </overview>
  </eainfo>
  <distinfo>
    <distliab>See access and use constraints information.</distliab>
    <stdorder>
      <digform>
        <digtinfo>
          <formname>SDE Feature Class</formname>
          <transize>0.001</transize>
        </digtinfo>
        <digtopt>
          <onlinopt>
            <computer>
              <networka>
                <networkr>file://Service=sde:sqlserver:echo; Database=HENNEPIN; User=GIS; Version=sde.DEFAULT</networkr>
              </networka>
            </computer>
          </onlinopt>
        </digtopt>
      </digform>
    </stdorder>
  </distinfo>
  <metainfo>
    <metd>20141110</metd>
    <metstdn>FGDC Content Standard for Digital Geospatial Metadata</metstdn>
    <metstdv>FGDC-STD-001-1998</metstdv>
    <mettc>local time</mettc>
  </metainfo>
</metadata>