<?xml version="1.0"?><metadata><idinfo><citation><citeinfo><title>Transit Centers</title><origin>Metropolitan Council - Metro Transit</origin><pubinfo><publish>Metropolitan Council</publish></pubinfo><pubdate>20120924</pubdate><onlink>https://gisdata.mn.gov/dataset/us-mn-state-metc-trans-transit-centers</onlink></citeinfo></citation><descript><abstract>The Metropolitan Council Transporation Policy plan defines a transit center as:  A transit stop or station at the meeting point of several routes or lines or of different modes of transportation. It is located on or off the street and is designed to handle the movement of transit units (vehicles or trains) and the boarding, alighting, and transferring of passengers between routes or lines (in which case it is also known as a transfer center) or different modes (also known as a modal interchange center, intermodal transfer facility or an hub).

The TransitCenters dataset includes all ACTIVE and INACTIVE locations identified by Metropolitan Council's Transportation Policy Plan, mapped on the Regional System Map, identified in a memo, NTD reporting or included in facilities managment.  Field attributes include sources where these facilities were identified as Transit Centers.  Some locations have additional facilities such as shelters, park and rides and rail stations.  In many cases these are places where: 

1. Two or more routes connect to transfer passengers 
2. Buses connect off street, or in clearly designated on-street spaces 
3. There are multiple marked 'gates' for different routes and directions 
4. The location serves a major activity center, such as a shopping center. 
5. There is a standing facility or, in some cases, a collection of bus shelters </abstract><purpose>To identify all transit centers identified by various materials.</purpose><supplinf>Twin Cities 7 County Metropolitan Area.  This includes the counties of Anoka, Carver, Dakota, Hennepin, Ramsey, Scott and Washington in Minnesota.</supplinf></descript><timeperd><timeinfo><sngdate><caldate>20120924</caldate></sngdate></timeinfo><current>The TransitCenters dataset includes all ACTIVE and INACTIVE locations identified by Metropolitan Council's Transportation Policy Plan, mapped on the Regional System Map, identified in a memo, NTD reporting and in asset management.</current></timeperd><status><progress>Complete</progress><update>As needed</update></status><spdom><bounding><westbc>-94.012</westbc><eastbc>-92.732</eastbc><northbc>45.415</northbc><southbc>44.471</southbc></bounding></spdom><keywords><place><placekey>Twin Cities, Anoka County, Carver County, Dakota County, Hennepin County, Ramsey County, Scott County, Washington County</placekey></place><theme><themekey>transit centers, bus shelter, shelters, transit centers, transit system, buses, Metro Transit, transportation, transfer, bus stops</themekey><themekt>None</themekt></theme></keywords><accconst>None</accconst><useconst>None</useconst><browse><browsen>ftp://ftp.gisdata.mn.gov/pub/gdrs/data/pub/us_mn_state_metc/trans_transit_centers/metadata/preview.jpg</browsen><browsed>Sample map showing the Transit Centers layer.</browsed></browse><crossref><citeinfo><title>Transit Shelters, Park and Ride Lots, Transit Routes, Transitway Stations</title></citeinfo></crossref><native>ArcGIS version 9x</native><ptcontac><cntinfo><cntperp><cntorg>Metropolitan Council - Metro Transit</cntorg><cntper>Julie Quinn</cntper></cntperp><cntpos>Associate Planner, Engineering and Facilities</cntpos><cntaddr><addrtype>mailing and physical</addrtype><address>560 6th Ave N</address><city>Minneapolis</city><state>MN</state><postal>55411</postal></cntaddr><cntvoice>612.349.7333</cntvoice><cntemail>julie.quinn@metc.state.mn.us</cntemail></cntinfo></ptcontac></idinfo><dataqual><attracc><attraccr>Attributes are compiled from several sources and are considered accurate.  See the Entity and Attribute Overview for more details.</attraccr></attracc><logic>The dataset is topologically 'clean'.</logic><complete>Entire 7 county area is covered.</complete><posacc><horizpa><horizpar>Heads-up digitizing referencing aerial photos were used to help locate the transit center.</horizpar></horizpa></posacc><lineage><procstep><procdesc>Locations and attributes were compiled from sources within Metro Transit.</procdesc></procstep><srcinfo><srcscale></srcscale></srcinfo></lineage></dataqual><spdoinfo><indspref>None</indspref><direct>Point</direct><mgmg3obj>point shapes</mgmg3obj><mgmg3til>One layer for entire seven county region.</mgmg3til></spdoinfo><eainfo><overview><eaover>Point Attributes:
 
CenterID:  The transit center unique identification number.

NAME:       The name of the transit center or transit station.

TPP:  Identified as a Transit Center in the 2010 Transportation Policy Plan.

SysMapRedT:  Mapped on the Regional System Map symbolized with a Red 'T'.

SysMapBlkBx:  Mapped on the Regional System Map symbolized as a transit transfer center but no red 'T'.

TCode: A unique identification number used for facility maintenance.

WParkRide:  The transit center includes a park &amp; ride lot.

Address:  The Transit Center address if known.

City:  The city the Transit Center is located in.

Zip:  The Transit Center's zip code.

State:  The state the Transit Center is located in.

NTD:  The facility was listed as a Transit Center in the NTD reporting program.

Memo2006:  Facilities identified as a transit center in a 2006 memo.

MT_URL:  Metro Transit Web address for this feature.</eaover><eadetcit>None</eadetcit></overview></eainfo><distinfo><resdesc>TransitCenters</resdesc><distliab>NOTICE:  The Geographic Information System (GIS) Data to which this notice is attached are made available pursuant to the Minnesota Government Data Practices Act (Minnesota Statutes Chapter 13).  THE GIS DATA ARE PROVIDED TO YOU AS IS AND WITHOUT ANY WARRANTY AS TO THEIR PERFORMANCE, MERCHANTABILITY, OR FITNESS FOR ANY PARTICULAR PURPOSE.  The GIS Data were developed by the Metropolitan Council for its own internal business purposes.  The Metropolitan Council does not represent or warrant that the GIS Data or the data documentation are error-free, complete, current, or accurate.  You are responsible for any consequences resulting from your use of the GIS Data or your reliance on the GIS Data.  You should consult the data documentation for this particular GIS Data to determine the limitations of the GIS Data and the precision with which the GIS Data may depict distance, direction, location, or other geographic features.  If you transmit or provide the GIS Data (or any portion of it) to another user, it is recommended that the GIS Data include a copy of this disclaimer and this metadata.</distliab><stdorder><digform><digtinfo><formname>ArcView Shape files</formname><formvern>ArcGIS 9x</formvern><transize>Less than 1 MB for zip file.</transize></digtinfo></digform><ordering>See Online Linkage Below</ordering></stdorder><distrib><cntinfo><cntperp><cntorg>Metropolitan Council</cntorg><cntper>Jon Hoekenga</cntper></cntperp><cntpos>GIS Specialist</cntpos><cntaddr><addrtype>mailing and physical</addrtype><address>390 Robert Street North</address><city>St. Paul</city><state>MN</state><postal>55101-1805</postal></cntaddr><cntvoice>651.602.1561</cntvoice><cntemail>jonathan.hoekenga@metc.state.mn.us</cntemail></cntinfo></distrib></distinfo><metainfo><metd>20130530</metd><metstdn>Minnesota Geographic Metadata Guidelines</metstdn><metstdv>1.2</metstdv><metextns><onlink>http://www.gis.state.mn.us/stds/metadata.htm</onlink></metextns><metc><cntinfo><cntperp><cntorg>Metropolitan Council</cntorg><cntper>Jon Hoekenga</cntper></cntperp><cntpos>GIS Specialist</cntpos><cntaddr><addrtype>mailing and physical</addrtype><address>390 Robert Street North</address><city>St. Paul</city><state>MN</state><postal>55101-1805</postal></cntaddr><cntvoice>651.602.1561</cntvoice><cntemail>jonathan.hoekenga@metc.state.mn.us</cntemail></cntinfo></metc></metainfo><Esri><ModDate>20110721</ModDate><ModTime>15502100</ModTime></Esri><mdDateSt Sync="TRUE">20110721</mdDateSt><spref><horizsys><planar><gridsys><gridsysn>Universal Transverse Mercator</gridsysn><utm><utmzone>15</utmzone></utm></gridsys><planci><plandu>meters</plandu></planci></planar><geodetic><horizdn>NAD83</horizdn><ellips>GRS80</ellips></geodetic></horizsys></spref></metadata>