<metadata>
  <eainfo>
    <overview>
      <eaover>Class Value - Classification of cell based on the number of class (5).

Valid values:
   0 - Less than 3 low-wage jobs per acre
   1 - 3 to 9.9 low-wage jobs per acre
   2 - 10 to 19.9 low-wage jobs per acre
   3 - 20 to 39.9 low-wage jobs per acre
   4 - 40 or more low-wage jobs per acre

Pixel Value - Weighted total of low-wage employment for the cell. Valid values range from 0 to 133.8</eaover>
    </overview>
  </eainfo>
  <idinfo>
    <citation>
      <citeinfo>
        <origin>Metropolitan Council</origin>
        <title>Low Wage Job Density (Less than $40,000)</title>
        <pubinfo>
          <publish>Metropolitan Council</publish>
        </pubinfo>
        <pubdate>20130927</pubdate>
        <onlink>https://gisdata.mn.gov/dataset/us-mn-state-metc-society-job-low-wage-density</onlink>
      </citeinfo>
    </citation>
    <descript>
      <abstract>The U.S. Census's 2010 LEHD Origin-Destination Employment Statistcs (LODES) Dataset was used to map low-wage job and worker density in throughout the Twin Cities Metropolitan Area, Minnesota. The LODES data is part of the U.S. Census's Longitudinal Employer-Household Dynamics program which records the number of jobs by workplace location and the number of workers by household location at the census block level. Jobs and workers are classifies in three earning categories at the U.S. Census 2010 Block level: earnings of $1,250 per month or less, earnings $1,251 per month to $3,333 per month, and earnings greater than $3,333 per month. Earnings of $3,333 per month or less ($40,000 or less, annually) are consider low-wage jobs and workers. The census block level data was converted to a smoothly tapered surface of calculated census block value. The resulting data surface provides a general representation of overall employment density of low-wage jobs in the Twin Cities Metropolitan Area, Minnesota.</abstract>
      <purpose>Representing employment density as a smooth surface can users visualize areas of low-wage job concentration that might be difficult to interpret from discrete block-level data. Representing low-wage jobs seperate from all jobs can help planners better implement services that can benefit low-wage workers.</purpose>
      <supplinf>Twin Cities 7 county metropolitan area.  This includes the counties of Anoka, Carver, Dakota, Hennepin, Ramsey, Scott and Washington.</supplinf>
    </descript>
    <status>
      <progress>Complete</progress>
      <update>Unknown</update>
    </status>
    <spdom>
      <bounding>
        <westbc>-94.012</westbc>
        <eastbc>-92.732</eastbc>
        <northbc>45.415</northbc>
        <southbc>44.471</southbc>
      </bounding>
    </spdom>
    <keywords>
      <place>
        <placekey>Twin Cities, Anoka County, Carver County, Dakota County, Hennepin County, Ramsey County, Scott County, Wasjington County, Minnesota</placekey>
      </place>
      <theme>
        <themekey>employment, jobs, low-wage jobs, LEHD, LED, LODES</themekey>
      </theme>
    </keywords>
    <accconst>None</accconst>
    <useconst>None</useconst>
    <timeperd>
      <timeinfo>
        <sngdate>
          <caldate>20130927</caldate>
        </sngdate>
      </timeinfo>
      <current>Workplace Area Characteristics from the U.S. Census's 2010 LEHD Origin-Destination Employment Statistcs (LODES) Dataset</current>
    </timeperd>
    <browse>
      <browsen>ftp://ftp.gisdata.mn.gov/pub/gdrs/data/pub/us_mn_state_metc/society_job_low_wage_density/metadata/preview.jpg</browsen>
    </browse>
    <ptcontac>
      <cntinfo>
        <cntperp>
          <cntorg>Metropolitan Council</cntorg>
          <cntper>Paul E. Hanson</cntper>
        </cntperp>
        <cntpos>GIS Specialist</cntpos>
        <cntaddr>
          <addrtype>mailing and physical</addrtype>
          <address>390 Robert Street North</address>
          <city>St. Paul</city>
          <state>MN</state>
          <postal>55101-1805</postal>
        </cntaddr>
        <cntvoice>651.602.1642</cntvoice>
        <cntemail>paul.hanson@metc.state.mn.us</cntemail>
      </cntinfo>
    </ptcontac>
  </idinfo>
  <distinfo>
    <distliab>NOTICE:  The Geographic Information System (GIS) Data to which this notice is attached are made available pursuant to the Minnesota Government Data Practices Act (Minnesota Statutes Chapter 13).  THE GIS DATA ARE PROVIDED TO YOU AS IS AND WITHOUT ANY WARRANTY AS TO THEIR PERFORMANCE, MERCHANTABILITY, OR FITNESS FOR ANY PARTICULAR PURPOSE.  The GIS Data were developed by the Metropolitan Council for its own internal business purposes.  The Metropolitan Council does not represent or warrant that the GIS Data or the data documentation are error-free, complete, current, or accurate.  You are responsible for any consequences resulting from your use of the GIS Data or your reliance on the GIS Data.  You should consult the data documentation for this particular GIS Data to determine the limitations of the GIS Data and the precision with which the GIS Data may depict distance, direction, location, or other geographic features.  If you transmit or provide the GIS Data (or any portion of it) to another user, it is recommended that the GIS Data include a copy of this disclaimer and this metadata.</distliab>
    <stdorder>
      <ordering>See Online Linkage Below</ordering>
    </stdorder>
    <distrib>
      <cntinfo>
        <cntperp>
          <cntorg>Metropolitan Council</cntorg>
          <cntper>Paul E. Hanson</cntper>
        </cntperp>
        <cntpos>GIS Specialist</cntpos>
        <cntaddr>
          <addrtype>mailing and physical</addrtype>
          <address>390 Robert Street North</address>
          <city>St. Paul</city>
          <state>MN</state>
          <postal>55101-1805</postal>
        </cntaddr>
        <cntvoice>651.602.1642</cntvoice>
        <cntemail>paul.hanson@metc.state.mn.us</cntemail>
      </cntinfo>
    </distrib>
  </distinfo>
  <metainfo>
    <metd>20130927</metd>
    <metstdn>Minnesota Geographic Metadata Guidelines</metstdn>
    <metstdv>1.2</metstdv>
    <metextns>
      <onlink>http://www.mngeo.state.mn.us/committee/standards/mgmg/metadata.htm</onlink>
    </metextns>
    <metc>
      <cntinfo>
        <cntperp>
          <cntorg>Metropolitan Council</cntorg>
          <cntper>Paul E. Hanson</cntper>
        </cntperp>
        <cntpos>GIS Specialist</cntpos>
        <cntaddr>
          <addrtype>mailing and physical</addrtype>
          <address>390 Robert Street North</address>
          <city>St. Paul</city>
          <state>MN</state>
          <postal>55101-1805</postal>
        </cntaddr>
        <cntvoice>651.602.1642</cntvoice>
        <cntemail>paul.hanson@metc.state.mn.us</cntemail>
      </cntinfo>
    </metc>
  </metainfo>
  <dataqual>
    <lineage>
      <procstep>
        <procdesc>The LEHD Origin-Destination Employment Statistcs (LODES) Workplace Area Characteristic data was used to map low-wage job density throughout the Twin Cities Metropolitan Area, Minnesota. The LODES data is part of the U.S. Census's Longitudinal Employer-Household Dynamics program. Earnings of $3,333 per month or less ($40,000 or less, annually) are consider low-wage jobs. Totals of low-wage jobs were assigned to census block centroids and were converted to a smoothly tapered surface using Kernal Density in the Spatial Statistic Tools in ArcGIS. The data was converted to 1 acre grid cells (output cell size of 63.6 meters) with a 1 mile search radius.
</procdesc>
      </procstep>
    </lineage>
  </dataqual>
  <spref>
    <horizsys>
      <planar>
        <gridsys>
          <gridsysn>Universal Transverse Mercator</gridsysn>
          <utm>
            <utmzone>15</utmzone>
          </utm>
        </gridsys>
        <planci>
          <plandu>meters</plandu>
          <coordrep>
            <absres>63.6</absres>
            <ordres>63.6</ordres>
          </coordrep>
        </planci>
      </planar>
      <geodetic>
        <horizdn>NAD83</horizdn>
        <ellips>GRS80</ellips>
      </geodetic>
    </horizsys>
  </spref>
</metadata>
