<!--  <!DOCTYPE metadata SYSTEM "metadata.dtd">  -->
<metadata>
  <idinfo>
    <citation>
      <citeinfo>
        <origin>Minnesota Geological Survey (MGS)</origin>
        <pubdate>1995</pubdate>
        <title>Geologic Atlas of Rice County, Minnesota  (Part A)</title>
        <mgmg1cid/>
        <pubinfo>
          <publish>Minnesota Geological Survey</publish>
        </pubinfo>
        <onlink>http://conservancy.umn.edu/handle/11299/58514</onlink>
      </citeinfo>
    </citation>
    <descript>
      <abstract>A County Geologic Atlas is a systematic study of a county's geologic and ground water resources. Geologic studies (Part A) include both near-surface deposits and bedrock. Ground water studies (Part B) include flow systems, aquifer capacity, and ground water chemistry. In some areas sand and gravel deposits, sinkholes, or other features are studied. Interpretation of sensitivity to pollution is also part of an atlas. The information is organized, analyzed, and displayed using geographic information technology.</abstract>
      <purpose>County Geologic Atlas and Regional Hydrogeologic Assessment information is used in planning and environmental protection efforts at all levels of government. Wellhead protection and well-sealing programs are examples of local programs that need geologic and ground water information. The information is also used by businesses and the general public.</purpose>
      <supplinf>Rice County, Minnesota</supplinf>
    </descript>
    <timeperd>
      <timeinfo>
        <sngdate>
          <caldate>1995</caldate>
        </sngdate>
      </timeinfo>
      <current>Geologic maps were compiled based on information available during the compilation period 1993-1995.</current>
    </timeperd>
    <status>
      <progress>Complete</progress>
      <update>None Planned</update>
    </status>
    <spdom>
      <bounding>
        <westbc>-93.53</westbc>
        <eastbc>-93.03</eastbc>
        <northbc>44.55</northbc>
        <southbc>44.19</southbc>
      </bounding>
    </spdom>
    <keywords>
      <theme>
        <themekt>ISO 19115 Topic Category</themekt>
        <themekey>geoscientificInformaiton, Bedrock Geology, Surficial Geology, Quaternary Stratigraphy, Bedrock Topography, Bedrock Outcrops, Drift Thickness, Wells, Borings, Hydrogeology, Aggregate Resources, Quarry Locations, Quarries</themekey>
      </theme>
      <place>
        <placekey>Minnesota, MN, Rice County</placekey>
      </place>
    </keywords>
    <accconst>None</accconst>
    <useconst>Credit should be given to the Minnesota Geological Survey for any use of the given digital data in any publication.</useconst>
    <browse>
      <browsen>None available</browsen>
    </browse>
    <native>PC Arc/INFO and Arc/INFO 7.0.2</native>
    <crossref>
      <citeinfo>
        <title>1. Part A Paper Report:  Geologic atlas of Rice County, Minnesota.  (Part A) H.C. Hobbs, Minnesota Geological Survey, project manager. 1995. 6 pls. Scale 1:100,000. Plates: 1, Data-base map; 2, Bedrock geology; 3, Surficial geology; 4, Quaternary stratigraphy; 5, Depth to bedrock and bedrock topography; 6, Geologic resources. $14.00. Report available from MGS Map Sales Office.

2. Part B Paper Report:  Geologic atlas of Rice County, Minnesota (Part B). J. Falteisek, Minnesota Dept. of Natural Resources, Division of Waters, project supervisor. 1997. Color. Scale 1:100,000. 3 pls., 1 pl supplement. . $11.00. Report available from MGS Map Sales Office. Digital data is available.  For a listing of the status of the Department of Natural Resources (DNR) Ground Water Mapping Program, go to: http://www.dnr.state.mn.us/waters/groundwater_section/mapping/index.html

For a listing of all geologic maps go to the Minnesota Geological Survey website at: http://www.mngs.umn.edu/mgsdocs.html

For a complete listing of MGS State Map Series Maps, Reports, and GIS Data, see http://conservancy.umn.edu/handle/11299/708

For other County Atlas and Regional Hydrogeologic Assessment data see: http://www.mngs.umn.edu/county_atlas/countyatlas.htm 
</title>
      </citeinfo>
    </crossref>
    <ptcontac>
      <cntinfo>
        <cntperp>
          <cntorg>Minnesota Geological Survey</cntorg>
          <cntper>General Information</cntper>
        </cntperp>
        <cntpos>Administrative Staff</cntpos>
        <cntaddr>
          <addrtype>Mailing and Physical</addrtype>
          <address>2609 Territorial Road</address>
          <city>St. Paul</city>
          <state>MN</state>
          <postal>55114</postal>
        </cntaddr>
        <cntvoice>612-626-2969</cntvoice>
        <cntemail>mgs@umn.edu</cntemail>
      </cntinfo>
    </ptcontac>
  </idinfo>
  <dataqual>
    <lineage>
      <srcinfo>
        <srcscale>100000</srcscale>
      </srcinfo>
      <procstep>
        <procdesc>Investigations begin with a review of existing information, such as earlier geologic maps, soil maps, and hydrologic reports. Drillers send water well logs to the Minnesota Geological Survey, where they are reviewed, interpreted, and entered into the County Well Index (CWI), an interactive data base of water-well information. Building on the previous data, field studies are conducted to improve the understanding of local geologic and hydrologic conditions. Linework is created based upon the field studies and base data, and digitized. Background GIS data layers such as roads, surface hydrography, township grids, etc., are obtained from various sources, as noted in the Entity/Attribute section.

There is no metadata available for these individual data layers created by MGS for this project.  In general, the linework was compiled at 1:100,000, digitized via PC Arc/Info on a digitizing table and registered to USGS 1:24,000 quad corners, UTM NAD27.  The files were imported into unix based Arc/Info, linework was splined to smooth where necessary,  built or cleaned and coded to MGS standard attributes.  This work was done between 1993-1995.  All digital files were projected to UTM NAD83 projection for public use and posted on the ftp site April 2002.</procdesc>
      </procstep>
    </lineage>
    <logic>Not available</logic>
    <complete>Not available</complete>
    <posacc>
      <horizpa>
        <horizpar>Not available</horizpar>
      </horizpa>
    </posacc>
    <attracc>
      <attraccr>Not available</attraccr>
    </attracc>
  </dataqual>
  <spdoinfo>
    <indspref/>
    <direct>Vector</direct>
    <mgmg3obj>Point, Vector, Polygon</mgmg3obj>
    <mgmg3til>County</mgmg3til>
  </spdoinfo>
  <eainfo>
    <overview>
      <eaover>The following are a list of the digital files used
in compiling the Rice County Geologic Atlas (Part A), 1993-1995.

Data Base plate:
WWPT = point cover of county well index well locations
SGPT = point cover of Quaternary stratigraphy; includes soil boring, hand sample, etc. locations
OCLN = outcrop lines where bedrock extext is too thin for polygons

Bedrock Geology:
BGLN  = line cover of linear structural features 
BGNT  = net cover of bedrock geology
KPG  = poly cover of Cretaceous geology

Surficial Geology:
SGNT    = net cover of surficial geology
SGPGE    = poly cover of eolian deposit areas
GMLN     = line cover of geomorphic features

Drift thickness:
DTNT = net cover of drift thickness isopachs (feet)
BTLN = line cover of bedrock topographic contours (feet)

Resources:
RSNT = net cover of potential aggregate resources
RSPT = point cover of gravel pit, quarry, etc. locations

GEOGRAPHIC BASE:
coan    = annotation cover for lake, city, etc. names (MGS)
cnty = county border polygon (MGS)
hyln    = line cover of streams (TIGER)
lkpg    = poly cover of lakes (TIGER)
mcd = line cover of municiple districts (TIGER)
pls     = line cover of public land survey, T-R-S (TIGER)
rdln1   = line cover of major highways, roads(TIGER), w highway point number(MGS)
rdln2   = line cover of minor roads, roads(TIGER), w highway point number(MGS)</eaover>
      <eadetcit>Metadata is not available for this dataset. </eadetcit>
    </overview>
  </eainfo>
  <distinfo>
    <resdesc>c09 (http://conservancy.umn.edu/handle/11299/58514)</resdesc>
    <stdorder>
      <digform>
        <digtinfo>
          <formname>Arc/Info Export (.e00) files</formname>
          <formvern>7.0.2</formvern>
          <transize>4.6 MB as zipfile.</transize>
        </digtinfo>
      </digform>
      <ordering>Data download is from the U of M Libraries Digital Conservancy. All GIS data and metadata for the Rice County Geologic Atlas is provided in the zip file C9 Part A Extras.zip. (Supplementary Files). GIS distribution format for most data in this dataset is Esri .e00 (arc interchange format). The direct Digital Conservancy link to PDF map products and GIS data projects (Supplementary Files) for this data set is: http://conservancy.umn.edu/handle/11299/58514

If you would prefer to have the digital data on DVD, or paper copies of the geologic plates, contact the MGS Map Sales office at 612-626-2969 and specify publication County Atlas Series C-09, part A, or County Geologic Atlas of Rice County.</ordering>
    </stdorder>
    <distrib>
      <cntinfo>
        <cntperp>
          <cntorg>Minnesota Geological Survey</cntorg>
          <cntper>Timothy E. Wahl</cntper>
        </cntperp>
        <cntpos>Geologic Information Systems</cntpos>
        <cntaddr>
          <addrtype>mailing and physical</addrtype>
          <address>2609 Territorial Road</address>
          <city>St. Paul</city>
          <state>MN</state>
          <postal>55114</postal>
        </cntaddr>
        <cntvoice>612-626-0992</cntvoice>
        <cntemail>tewahl@umn.edu</cntemail>
      </cntinfo>
    </distrib>
  </distinfo>
  <metainfo>
    <metd>20150416</metd>
    <metstdn>Minnesota Geographic Metadata Guidelines</metstdn>
    <metstdv>1.2</metstdv>
    <metextns>
      <onlink>http://www.mngeo.state.mn.us/committee/standards/mgmg/metadata.htm</onlink>
    </metextns>
    <metc>
      <cntinfo>
        <cntperp>
          <cntorg>Minnesota Geospatial Information Office (MnGeo)</cntorg>
          <cntper>Nancy Rader</cntper>
        </cntperp>
        <cntpos>GIS Data Coordinator</cntpos>
        <cntaddr>
          <addrtype>mailing and physical</addrtype>
          <address>658 Cedar Street</address>
          <city>St. Paul</city>
          <state>MN</state>
          <postal>55155</postal>
        </cntaddr>
        <cntvoice>651-201-2489</cntvoice>
        <cntemail>gisinfo.mngeo@state.mn.us</cntemail>
      </cntinfo>
    </metc>
  </metainfo>
  <spref>
    <horizsys>
      <planar>
        <gridsys>
          <gridsysn>Universal Transverse Mercator</gridsysn>
          <utm>
            <utmzone>15E</utmzone>
          </utm>
        </gridsys>
        <planci>
          <plandu>meters</plandu>
        </planci>
      </planar>
      <geodetic>
        <horizdn>NAD83</horizdn>
        <ellips>GRS80</ellips>
      </geodetic>
    </horizsys>
  </spref>
</metadata>
