<?xml version="1.0"?><metadata><idinfo><citation><citeinfo><origin>Metropolitan Council</origin><pubdate>unpublished material</pubdate><title>Counties and Minor Civil Divisions (Cities and Townships), 1990</title><mgmg1cid>N/A</mgmg1cid><pubinfo><publish>Metropolitan Council</publish></pubinfo><onlink>https://gisdata.mn.gov/dataset/us-mn-state-metc-bdry-counties-mcd1990</onlink></citeinfo></citation><descript><abstract>This is a polygon layer of county and minor civil divisions (cities and townships)  in the 7-county Twin Cities metropolitan area as of 1990.

NOTES:
- Lines are of limited positional accuracy
- COMCDLUT (or comcdlut.dbf) is an available table with additional county/mcd attributes.  However, it is geared toward more recent data.
- Some MCDs are split between two counties.  Only those parts of MCDs within the 7-county area are included.</abstract><purpose>This dataset was developed for metro wide display and analysis of counties and MCDs.</purpose><supplinf>Twin Cities 7 County Metropolitan Area.  This includes the counties of Anoka, Carver, Dakota, Hennepin, Ramsey, Scott and Washington in Minnesota.</supplinf></descript><timeperd><timeinfo><sngdate><caldate>1990</caldate></sngdate></timeinfo><current>Boundary lines and attributes are as of 1990.</current></timeperd><status><progress>Complete</progress><update>None Planned</update></status><spdom><bounding><westbc>-94.012</westbc><eastbc>-92.732</eastbc><northbc>45.415</northbc><southbc>44.471</southbc></bounding></spdom><keywords><theme><themekt>None</themekt><themekey>counties, cities, political boundaries, townships, MCD, minor civil divisions, municipal, municipal boundaries, county boundaries, city boundaries, FIPS, FIPS place codes, jurisdictional boundary</themekey></theme><place><placekey>Twin Cities, Anoka County, Carver County, Dakota County, Hennepin County, Ramsey County, Scott County, Washington County</placekey></place></keywords><accconst>None</accconst><useconst>None</useconst><browse><browsen>ftp://ftp.gisdata.mn.gov/pub/gdrs/data/pub/us_mn_state_metc/bdry_counties_mcd1990/metadata/preview.jpg</browsen></browse><native>ArcInfo Version 8x, UNIX platform</native><crossref><citeinfo><title>County_mcd layer combined by the Metropolitan Council from more recent county and MnDOT data.

The BaseMap '97 dataset distributed by the  Minnesota Dept. of Transportation includes county and city boundaries, but not township boundaries.</title></citeinfo></crossref><ptcontac><cntinfo><cntperp><cntorg>Metropolitan Council</cntorg><cntper>Jon Hoekenga</cntper></cntperp><cntpos>GIS System Administrator</cntpos><cntaddr><addrtype> mailing and physical address </addrtype><address>390 Robert Street North</address><city>St. Paul</city><state>Minnesota</state><postal>55101-1805</postal></cntaddr><cntvoice>651-602-1642</cntvoice><cntemail>jonathan.hoekenga@metc.state.mn.us</cntemail></cntinfo></ptcontac></idinfo><dataqual><attracc><attraccr>There are no known inaccuracies in the attribute data.  No tests have been conducted for attribute accuracy.</attraccr></attracc><logic>The dataset is topologically 'clean'.</logic><complete>Entire seven county geographic area is covered.</complete><posacc><horizpa><horizpar>The positional accuracy of the dataset has not been tested under the National Standards for Spatial Data Accuracy.  The estimated positional accuracy is UNKNOWN.</horizpar></horizpa></posacc><lineage><srcinfo><srcscale></srcscale></srcinfo><procstep><procdesc>This dataset was compiled from 1990 post-census TIGER line files, the Metropolitan Council's Geographic Base File (GBF) DIME dataset as well as 1990 MN/DOT roads data.  No documentation exists describing how the boundaries were derived from these datasets.</procdesc></procstep></lineage></dataqual><spdoinfo><indspref>The county/MCD lookup table is referenced by city name, FIPS place codes (5 digit), FIPS county codes (state standard = 3 digits), in addition to a number of other codes.</indspref><direct>Vector</direct><mgmg3obj>arcs, nodes, polygons, label points</mgmg3obj><mgmg3til>One layer for entire seven county region.</mgmg3til></spdoinfo><eainfo><overview><eaover>Polygon Attributes:
 
CO:             3 digit FIPS and state standard county code; 
                e.g. 163, 003
 
MCD:            5 digit FIPS place code for the minor civil division
 
MCD_NAME:       MCD name; e.g. Burns Twp, Blaine
 
MCD_ABBREV:     MCD 6 character abbreviation; e.g. ANDOVE,  ANOKAX
 
COMCD_DESCRIP:  MCD description; e.g. Burns Township, Blaine (Anoka Co. part)
 
COMCD:          8 digit code redefined from CO and MCD
 
COMCD_OLD:      Old Metropolitan Council 6 digit county-MCD code
 
MCD_TYPE:       MCD type.   C = city, T = Twp, U = unorg.
 
ABC_SORT:       3 digit integer that will sort alphabetically e.g. St. is 
                sorted as Saint
 
FIVE_COLOR:     Numbers 1 to 5 for shading MCDs so adjacent MCDs have different 
                colors
 
COMCD_POP_1990: 1990 population for county-MCDs based on the 1990 census 
                (including subsequent corrections of the data by the Census 
                Bureau)</eaover><eadetcit>None</eadetcit></overview></eainfo><distinfo><resdesc>Census1990MnDOTCountyMCD</resdesc><distliab>NOTICE:  The Geographic Information System (GIS) Data to which this notice is attached are made available pursuant to the Minnesota Government Data Practices Act (Minnesota Statutes Chapter 13).  THE GIS DATA ARE PROVIDED TO YOU AS IS AND WITHOUT ANY WARRANTY AS TO THEIR PERFORMANCE, MERCHANTABILITY, OR FITNESS FOR ANY PARTICULAR PURPOSE.  The GIS Data were developed by the Metropolitan Council for its own internal business purposes.  The Metropolitan Council does not represent or warrant that the GIS Data or the data documentation are error-free, complete, current, or accurate.  You are responsible for any consequences resulting from your use of the GIS Data or your reliance on the GIS Data.  You should consult the data documentation for this particular GIS Data to determine the limitations of the GIS Data and the precision with which the GIS Data may depict distance, direction, location, or other geographic features.  If you transmit or provide the GIS Data (or any portion of it) to another user, it is recommended that the GIS Data include a copy of this disclaimer and this metadata.</distliab><stdorder><digform><digtinfo><formname>ArcView Shape files</formname><formvern>ArcView: 3x</formvern><transize>1.1 meg. for ZIP file.</transize></digtinfo></digform><ordering>See Online Linkage Below</ordering></stdorder><distrib><cntinfo><cntperp><cntorg>Metropolitan Council</cntorg><cntper>Jon Hoekenga</cntper></cntperp><cntpos>GIS System Administrator</cntpos><cntaddr><addrtype>mailing and physical</addrtype><address>Mears Park Centre, 390 Robert Street North</address><city>St. Paul</city><state>Minnesota</state><postal>55101-1805</postal></cntaddr><cntvoice>651-602-1561</cntvoice><cntemail>jonathan.hoekenga@metc.state.mn.us</cntemail></cntinfo></distrib></distinfo><metainfo><metd>20010306</metd><metstdn>Minnesota Geographic Metadata Guidelines</metstdn><metstdv>1.2</metstdv><metextns><onlink>http://www.gis.state.mn.us/stds/metadata.htm</onlink></metextns><metc><cntinfo><cntperp><cntorg>Metropolitan Council</cntorg><cntper>Jon Hoekenga</cntper></cntperp><cntpos>GIS System Administrator</cntpos><cntaddr><addrtype>mailing and physical</addrtype><address>390 Robert Street North</address><city>St. Paul</city><state>Minnesota</state><postal>55101-1805</postal></cntaddr><cntvoice>651-602-1561</cntvoice><cntemail>jonathan.hoekenga@metc.state.mn.us</cntemail></cntinfo></metc></metainfo><Esri><ModDate>20060210</ModDate><ModTime>13593000</ModTime></Esri><mdDateSt Sync="TRUE">20060210</mdDateSt><spref><horizsys><planar><gridsys><gridsysn>Universal Transverse Mercator</gridsysn><utm><utmzone>15</utmzone></utm></gridsys><planci><plandu>meters</plandu></planci></planar><geodetic><horizdn>NAD83</horizdn><ellips>GRS80</ellips></geodetic></horizsys></spref></metadata>