<?xml version="1.0"?><metadata><idinfo><citation><citeinfo><title>Metropolitan Parks and Open Space Commission Districts (MPOSC)</title><origin>Metropolitan Council</origin><pubinfo><publish>Metropolitan Council</publish></pubinfo><pubdate>2013</pubdate><onlink>https://gisdata.mn.gov/dataset/us-mn-state-metc-bdry-metprks-opsspcdst</onlink></citeinfo></citation><descript><abstract>This layer defines the district boundaries for the Metropolitan Parks and Open Space Commission (MPOSC)

NOTES:
-  The boundaries for the MPOSC district are based on current Metropolitan Council Districts, which were enacted in 2013.</abstract><purpose>This layer was developed as a general reference for MPOSC Districts</purpose><supplinf>Twin Cities 7 County Metropolitan Area.  This includes the counties of Anoka, Carver, Dakota, Hennepin, Ramsey, Scott and Washington in Minnesota.</supplinf></descript><timeperd><timeinfo><sngdate><caldate>20160101</caldate></sngdate></timeinfo><current>The boundaries for the MPOSC district are based on current Metropolitan Council Districts, which were enacted in 2013.  The communities included in each district are current as of the time period of current Metropolitan Council Disistricts. 

The city and township boundaries used to create this dataset were derived from the metro wide Counties and Cities &amp; Townships, Twin Cities Metropolitan Area dataset.  That dataset is updated on a quarterly basis. This dataset is then recreated quarterly from those boundaries, the date reflected in the Time Period of Content.</current></timeperd><status><progress>Complete</progress><update>As needed</update></status><spdom><bounding><westbc>-94.012</westbc><eastbc>-92.732</eastbc><northbc>45.415</northbc><southbc>44.471</southbc></bounding></spdom><keywords><place><placekey>Twin Cities, Anoka County, Carver County, Dakota County, Hennepin County, Ramsey County, Scott County, Washington County</placekey></place><theme><themekey>Metropolitan Parks and Open Space Commission, Metropolitan Council, administrative boundaries</themekey><themekt>None</themekt></theme></keywords><accconst>None</accconst><useconst>None</useconst><crossref><citeinfo><title>Metropolitan Council Districts, Counties and Cities &amp; Townships, Twin Cities Metropolitan Area</title></citeinfo></crossref><native>ArcGIS 9x</native><ptcontac><cntinfo><cntperp><cntorg>Metropolitan Council</cntorg><cntper>Craig Skone</cntper></cntperp><cntpos>GIS Specialist</cntpos><cntaddr><addrtype>mailing and physical</addrtype><address>390 Robert Street North</address><city>St. Paul</city><state>MN</state><postal>55101-1805</postal></cntaddr><cntvoice>651.602.1328</cntvoice><cntemail>craig.skone@metc.state.mn.us</cntemail></cntinfo></ptcontac></idinfo><dataqual><attracc><attraccr>Attributes are accurate as of the Currentness Reference date.</attraccr></attracc><logic>The dataset is topologically 'clean'.</logic><complete>Entire seven county geographic area is covered.</complete><posacc><horizpa><horizpar>The positional accuracy of the dataset has not been tested under the National Standards for Spatial Data Accuracy. 

NOTE:  The 'SOURCE' field in the line attributes will provide an indication of the positional accuracy of the line.  See Entity and Attribute Overview in Section 5 for more information.</horizpar></horizpa></posacc><lineage><procstep><procdesc>Line work for the mposc_districts layer is derived through a combination of Metropolitan Council district boundaries based on the assignment of commission members found here:  http://www.metrocouncil.org/Council-Meetings/Committees/Metropolitan-Parks-and-Open-Space-Commission.aspx</procdesc></procstep><srcinfo><srcscale></srcscale></srcinfo></lineage></dataqual><spdoinfo><indspref>None</indspref><direct>Vector</direct><mgmg3obj>polygon shapes</mgmg3obj><mgmg3til>One layer for entire seven county region.</mgmg3til></spdoinfo><eainfo><overview><eaover>Polygon Attributes:
 
MPOSC:      Metropolitan Parks and Open Space Commission District (A-H)</eaover><eadetcit>None</eadetcit></overview></eainfo><distinfo><resdesc>MetPOSCDistricts</resdesc><distliab>NOTICE  The Geographic Information System (GIS) Data to which this notice is attached are made available pursuant to the Minnesota Government Data Practices Act (Minnesota Statutes Chapter 13).  THE GIS DATA ARE PROVIDED TO YOU AS IS AND WITHOUT ANY WARRANTY AS TO THEIR PERFORMANCE, MERCHANTABILITY, OR FITNESS FOR ANY PARTICULAR PURPOSE.  The GIS Data were developed by the Metropolitan Council for its own internal business purposes.  The Metropolitan Council does not represent or warrant that the GIS Data or the data documentation are error-free, complete, current, or accurate.  You are responsible for any consequences resulting from your use of the GIS Data or your reliance on the GIS Data.  You should consult the data documentation for this particular GIS Data to determine the limitations of the GIS Data and the precision with which the GIS Data may depict distance, direction, location, or other geographic features.  If you transmit or provide the GIS Data (or any portion of it) to another user, it is recommended that the GIS Data include a copy of this disclaimer and this metadata.</distliab><stdorder><digform><digtinfo><formname>ArcView Shape file</formname><formvern>ArcGIS 9x</formvern><transize>1 MB for zip file.</transize></digtinfo></digform><ordering>See Online Linkage Below</ordering></stdorder><distrib><cntinfo><cntperp><cntorg>Metropolitan Council</cntorg><cntper>Tanya Mayer</cntper></cntperp><cntpos>GIS Specialist</cntpos><cntaddr><addrtype>mailing and physical</addrtype><address>390 Robert Street North</address><city>St. Paul</city><state>MN</state><postal>55101-1805</postal></cntaddr><cntvoice>651.602.1604</cntvoice><cntemail>tanya.mayer@metc.state.mn.us</cntemail></cntinfo></distrib></distinfo><metainfo><metd>20160225</metd><metstdn>Minnesota Geographic Metadata Guidelines</metstdn><metstdv>1.2</metstdv><metextns><onlink>http://www.gis.state.mn.us/stds/metadata.htm</onlink></metextns><metc><cntinfo><cntperp><cntorg>Metropolitan Council</cntorg><cntper>Tanya Mayer</cntper></cntperp><cntpos>GIS Specialist</cntpos><cntaddr><addrtype>mailing and physical</addrtype><address>390 Robert Street North</address><city>St. Paul</city><state>MN</state><postal>55101-1805</postal></cntaddr><cntvoice>651.602.1604</cntvoice><cntemail>tanya.mayer@metc.state.mn.us</cntemail></cntinfo></metc></metainfo><Esri><ModDate>20110729</ModDate><ModTime>14365300</ModTime></Esri><mdDateSt Sync="TRUE">20110729</mdDateSt><spref><horizsys><planar><gridsys><gridsysn>Universal Transverse Mercator</gridsysn><utm><utmzone>15</utmzone></utm></gridsys><planci><plandu>meters</plandu></planci></planar><geodetic><horizdn>NAD83</horizdn><ellips>GRS80</ellips></geodetic></horizsys></spref></metadata>