<?xml version="1.0"?><!--  <!DOCTYPE metadata SYSTEM "metadata.dtd">  --><metadata><idinfo><citation><citeinfo><origin>Minnesota Geological Survey (MGS)</origin><pubdate>2007</pubdate><title>Geologic Atlas of Todd County, Minnesota (Part A)</title><mgmg1cid></mgmg1cid><pubinfo><publish>Minnesota Geological Survey</publish></pubinfo><onlink>http://conservancy.umn.edu/handle/11299/58719</onlink></citeinfo></citation><descript><abstract>A County Geologic Atlas is a systematic study of a county's geologic and ground water resources. Geologic studies include both near-surface deposits and bedrock. Ground water studies include flow systems, aquifer capacity, and ground water chemistry. In some areas sand and gravel deposits, sinkholes, or other features are studied. Interpretation of sensitivity to pollution is also part of an atlas. The information is organized, analyzed, and displayed using geographic information technology.

Most Geologic Atlas and Regional Hydrogeologic Assessment projects are done in two parts. The Minnesota Geological Survey covers basic geology and creates databases of information such as wells and soil borings in part A. The Minnesota Department of Natural Resources handles hydrogeology and ground water sensitivity layers in Part B. Completion of a project's two parts is staggered: Part A is completed about two years before Part B, compiling information used to create part B. Parts A and B are published and distributed as two separate products.</abstract><purpose>County Geologic Atlas and Regional Hydrogeologic Assessment information is used in planning and environmental protection efforts at all levels of government. Wellhead protection and well-sealing programs are examples of local programs that need geologic and ground water information. The information is also used by businesses and the general public.</purpose><supplinf>Todd County, Minnesota</supplinf></descript><timeperd><timeinfo><sngdate><caldate>2007</caldate></sngdate></timeinfo><current>Geologic maps were created based on information available to MGS during the period 2005-2007.</current></timeperd><status><progress>Complete</progress><update>None Planned</update></status><spdom><bounding><westbc>-95.14</westbc><eastbc>-94.65</eastbc><northbc>46.38</northbc><southbc>45.76</southbc></bounding></spdom><keywords><theme><themekt>ISO 19115 Topic Category</themekt><themekey>geoscientificInformation, Bedrock Geology, Surficial Geology, Bedrock Topography, Depth to Bedrock, Quaternary Stratigraphy, Wells, Mineral Resources</themekey></theme><place><placekey>Minnesota, MN, Todd County</placekey></place></keywords><accconst>None</accconst><useconst>Credit should be given to the Minnesota Geological Survey for any use of the given digital data in any publication.  </useconst><browse><browsen>None available</browsen></browse><native>ArcGIS 9.2</native><crossref><citeinfo><title>C-18, Part A. Geologic Atlas of Todd County, Minnesota. Dale R. Setterholm, Project Manager. March 2007. Color. 6 plates. Scales 1:100,000 and 1:200,000. Paper map and report available from MGS Map Sales Office (2609 Territorial Road, St. Paul, Minnesota, 55114, 612-626-2969.)

For a listing of all geologic maps go to the Minnesota Geological Survey website at: http://www.mngs.umn.edu/mgsdocs.html

For a complete listing of MGS State Map Series Maps, Reports, and GIS Data, see http://conservancy.umn.edu/handle/11299/708

For other County Atlas and Regional Hydrogeologic Assessment data see: http://www.mngs.umn.edu/county_atlas/countyatlas.htm 

For a listing of the status of the Department of Natural Resources (DNR) Ground Water Mapping Program, go to: http://www.dnr.state.mn.us/waters/groundwater_section/mapping/index.html
</title></citeinfo></crossref><ptcontac><cntinfo><cntperp><cntorg>Minnesota Geological Survey</cntorg><cntper>Richard S. Lively</cntper></cntperp><cntpos>Geologic Information Systems</cntpos><cntaddr><addrtype>Mailing and Physical</addrtype><address>2609 Territorial Road</address><city>St. Paul</city><state>MN</state><postal>55114</postal></cntaddr><cntvoice>612-626-3103</cntvoice><cntemail>lively@umn.edu</cntemail></cntinfo></ptcontac></idinfo><dataqual><attracc><attraccr>See individual layer metadata files.</attraccr></attracc><logic>See individual layer metadata files.</logic><complete>See individual layer metadata files.</complete><posacc><horizpa><horizpar>See individual layer metadata files.</horizpar></horizpa></posacc><lineage><srcinfo><srcscale>100000</srcscale></srcinfo><procstep><procdesc>Investigations begin with a review of existing information, such as earlier geologic maps, soil maps, and hydrologic reports. Drillers send water well logs to the Minnesota Geological Survey, where they are reviewed, interpreted, and entered into the County Well Index (CWI), an interactive data base of water-well information. Building on the previous data, field studies are conducted to improve the understanding of local geologic and hydrologic conditions. Linework is created based upon the field studies and base data, and digitized. Background GIS data layers such as roads, surface hydrography, township grids, etc., are obtained from various sources, as noted in the Entity/Attribute section. See also individual metadata reports at ftp://mgssun6.mngs.umn.edu/pub5/c-18/</procdesc></procstep></lineage></dataqual><spdoinfo><indspref></indspref><direct>Vector</direct><mgmg3obj>Point, Vector, Polygon</mgmg3obj><mgmg3til>Todd County</mgmg3til></spdoinfo><eainfo><overview><eaover>The following are a list of the GIS files used in compiling the Todd County Geologic Atlas:

Database:
WWPT    = point shapefile of county well index well locations
wwpt_bdrk = point shapefile of cwi wells that reached bedrock
wwpt_extrnl = point shapefile of cwi wells located outside of Todd Co., used in cross-sections.
WW_SWL	= database containing static water level data
WWSTRAT	= database containing water well stratigraphic data
seismic_locs = point shapefile showing seismic survey location for depth to bedrock sounding
qdpt  = point shapefile of Giddings probe hole, samples and MnDot borehole locations
dh_exp_point = point shapefile of exploration drill hole locations
dh_mgs_point = point shapefile of MGS scientific drill hole locations
xsec_ln_pub = line shapefiles of locations of cross sections shown in Plate 4 of the Atlas
xsecln_2k = line shapefile of location of the 33 cross sections used to compile the subsurface geology.  Lines are 2 km apart.
papg_polygon = polygon shapefile of Todd County outline
db_link = shapefile used for hyperlinks to text and figures

Bedrock Geology:
bg_link = shapefile used for hyperlinks to text and figures
papg_polygon = polygon shapefile of Todd County outline
dh_exp_point = point shapefile of exploration drill hole locations
dh_mgs_point = point shapefile of MGS scientific drill hole locations
wwpt_bdrk = point shapefile of cwi wells that reached bedrock
outcrops = polygon shapefile of outcrop locations
bgstln_arc = line shapefile of faults, dikes and other structural features if present
bgpg_arc = line shapefile of unit contacts and faults where they form a contact
bgpg_polygon = polygon shapefile of bedrock geology
toddbgpg polygon.lyr  = layer (legend) file for displaying bedrock geology
bgstrln arc.lyr  = layer (legend) file for displaying structural features
toddbgpg arc.lyr = layer (legend) file for displaying contacts and structural features

Surficial Geology:
bg_link = shapefile used for hyperlinks to text and figures
papg_polygon = polygon shapefile of Todd County outline
xsec_ln_pub = line shapefiles of locations of cross sections shown in Plate 4 of the Atlas
xsecln_2k = line shapefile of location of the 33 cross sections used to compile the subsurface geology.  Lines are 2 km apart.
gmline = line shapefile of geomorphic features associated with glacial ice movement
gmpt_point = point shapefile of geomorphic ice contact features (kames)
sgpg_cat_polygon = polygon shapefile that contains categories to provide additional ways to map the surface geology of Todd County
sgpg_polygon = polygon shapefile showing surficial geology units
ortho_e1-1m153.sid = mrsid file, FSA orthophoto of Todd County
surface_ned = ESRI grid showing the surface topography of Todd County, derived from the USGS NED grid
surf_ned_lks = not included on plate but provided here, the NED topography grid with bathymetry of sixteen lakes added to the topography
demhs = ESRI NED grid with a hillshade applied to accentuate the 3d relief
sgpg polygon.lyr  = layer (legend) file for displaying surficial geology
gmline_pub.lyr  = layer (legend) file for displaying linear geomorphic features

Quaternary stratigraphy:
strat_link = shapefile used for hyperlinks to text and figures
papg_polygon = polygon shapefile of Todd County outline
corepts_02 to 31 = point shapefiles indicating locations of wells with core or cuttings along each 
cross-section lines used on Plate 4 (also labeled A-G)
wwpts_02 to 31 = point shapefiles indicating locations of water wells along each cross-section line used on Plate 4 (also labeled A-G)
corepolys_02 to 31 = polygon shapefiles of stratigraphic logs for core and cuttings locations
wwpolys_02 to 31 = polygon shapefiles of stratigraphic logs for water well locations
xsec_elevln = lines shapefile of elevations against which the stratigraphy is plotted
xsec_polygons = polygon shapefiles of cross sections for Plate 4. Labeled A-02 to G-31.
corepolys.lyr = layer (legend) file for displaying the stratigraphy
wwpolys.lyr = layer (legend) file for displaying the stratigraphy of water wells
xsec_polygons.lyr = layer (legend) file for displaying the cross-section polygons
Additional shapefiles of Quaternary giddings stratigraphy and stratigraphic information for the other cross-section lines is found in the folder nonWW_pts_xs:
qd_pts = point shapefile of all giddings Quaternary locations
qdpt_strat = point shapefile of giddings drillholes with associated stratigraphy
rotos_cutngs = point shapefile of rotosonic and cuttings drillholes
rotos_ctungs_strat = point shapefile of rotosonic, cuttings drillholes with associated stratigraphy
wwpt and wwptstrat were used for all of the cross-section construction

Bedrock Topography and Depth to Bedrock (Drift Thickness):
dt_link = shapefile used for hyperlinks to text and figures
papg_polygon = polygon shapefile of Todd County outline
btln_arc = line shapefile showing lines of equal elevation of the bedrock 
surface (bedrock topography)
in folder grids: btgd = ESRI grid showing elevation the the bedrock surface
dt_contln = line shapefile showing lines of equal thickness of the glacial drift (depth to bedrock)
in folder grids:  dtgd = ESRI grid showing the depth to bedrock (thickness of glacial drift)

depth to bedrock (feet).lyr = layer (legend) file used to display depth to bedrock
Elevation of bedrock surface (fsal).lyr = layer (legend) file used to display bedrock topography

Sand thickness and depth to tops of sand units (3d model):
snd_link = shapefile used for hyperlinks to text and figures
papg_polygon = polygon shapefile of Todd County outline
xsecln_2k = line shapefile of location of the 33 cross sections used to compile the subsurface geology.  Lines are 2 km apart.
surf_snd_thck = line shapefile indicating thickness of surface sands in Todd County.
in folder grids: surfsnds_top = ESRI grid showing areal distribution of surface sands
c1_thck_cont = line shapefile indicating thickness of sand associated with till ct
in folder grids: c1_depth_top = ESRI grid showing areal distribution of c1 sand and depth to top
h1_thck_cont = line shapefile indicating thickness of sand associated with till ht
in folder grids: h1_depth_top = ESRI grid showing areal distribution of h1 sand and depth to top
b2_thck_cont = line shapefile indicating thickness of sand associated with till bt
in folder grids: b2_depth_top = ESRI grid showing areal distribution of b2 sand and depth to top
b1_thck_cont = line shapefile indicating thickness of deeper sand associated with till bt
in folder grids: b1_depth_top = ESRI grid showing areal distribution of deeper b1 sand and depth to top
x3_thck_cont = line shapefile indicating thickness of sand associated with x till
in folder grids: x3_depth_top = ESRI grid showing areal distribution of x3 sand and depth to top
x2_thck_cont = line shapefile indicating thickness of deeper sand associated with x till
in folder grids: x2_depth_top = ESRI grid showing areal distribution of x2 sand and depth to top
x1_thck_cont = line shapefile indicating thickness of deeper sand associated with x till
in folder grids: x1_depth_top = ESRI grid showing areal distribution of x1 sand and depth to top
unk_thic_cont = line shapefile showing thickness of glacial material where data is lacking (unknown stratigraphy)
zerothck_unkpoly = polygon shapefile showing areas where data exists from surface to bedrock
in folder grids\till_surfaces: ups_depth_top = ESRI grid showing depth to top of unknown stratigraphy

Grids of additional sand surfaces that were too small or thin to include on the Plate 5 are included
in the folder grids\snd_surfaces, along with the base of the unit, thickness and depth to top.

Grids of all of the till surfaces which were not included on Plate 5 are provided
in the folder grids\till_surfaces, with the base of the unit, thickness and depth to top.

depth to top of unknown.lyr = layer (legend) file used to display areas where there is no unknown stratigraphy
thickness snds.lyr = layer (legend) file used to display sand thickness
surf_top.lyr = layer (legend) file used to display depth to top of sands

Mineral endowment:
min_end_link = shapefile used for hyperlinks to text and figures
papg_polygon = polygon shapefile of Todd County outline
rspt_point = point shapefile of Quaternary sample data points, including gravel pits
rspg_polygon = polygon shapefile of Quaternary sand and gravel resources
bgst_rs_arc = line shapefile of bedrock structural features on the resource plate
bgpgrs_polygon = polygon shapefile of bedrock geology with potential as a resource
in folder grids: mgd1d = first derivative of magnetic anomaly map used with bedrock geology mapping

rspg polygons.lyr = layer (legend) file used to display Quaternary resources
rspt point.lyr = layer (legend) file used to display gravel pits and other features
bgpgrs_polygon.lyr = layer (legend) file used to display bedrock polygons
bgrs_stln.lyr = layer (legend) file used to display bedrock structural features</eaover><eadetcit>See individual layer metadata files.</eadetcit></overview></eainfo><distinfo><resdesc>C18 ( http://conservancy.umn.edu/handle/11299/58719)</resdesc><stdorder><digform><digtinfo><formname>Arc/Info Export (.e00), shapefile, mxd</formname><formvern></formvern><transize>export (e00).zip 50 MB;  c18.zip 529 MB</transize></digtinfo></digform><ordering>Data download is from the U of M Libraries Digital Conservancy. All GIS data and metadata for the Todd County Geologic Atlas is provided in the zip file C18_CD.zip. (Supplementary Files).

If you would prefer to have the digital data on DVD, contact MGS Map Sales office at (612) 626-2969.

The direct Digital Conservancy link to PDF map products and GIS data projects (Supplementary Files) for this data set is: http://conservancy.umn.edu/handle/11299/58719

If you would like paper copies of the geologic plates; contact the MGS Map Sales office at 612-626-2969 and specify publication County Atlas Series C-18, part A, or County Geologic Atlas of Todd County.</ordering></stdorder><distrib><cntinfo><cntperp><cntorg>Minnesota Geological Survey</cntorg><cntper>Timothy E. Wahl</cntper></cntperp><cntpos>Geologic Information Systems</cntpos><cntaddr><addrtype>mailing and physical</addrtype><address>2609 Territorial Road</address><city>St. Paul</city><state>MN</state><postal>55114</postal></cntaddr><cntvoice>612-626-0992</cntvoice><cntemail>tewahl@umn.edu</cntemail></cntinfo></distrib></distinfo><metainfo><metd>20150415</metd><metstdn>Minnesota Geographic Metadata Guidelines</metstdn><metstdv>1.2</metstdv><metextns><onlink>http://www.mngeo.state.mn.us/committee/standards/mgmg/metadata.htm</onlink></metextns><metc><cntinfo><cntperp><cntorg>Minnesota Geospatial Information Office (MnGeo)</cntorg><cntper>Nancy Rader</cntper></cntperp><cntpos>GIS Data Coordinator</cntpos><cntaddr><addrtype>mailing and physical</addrtype><address>658 Cedar Street</address><city>St. Paul</city><state>MN</state><postal>55155</postal></cntaddr><cntvoice>651-201-2489</cntvoice><cntemail>gisinfo.mngeo@state.mn.us</cntemail></cntinfo></metc></metainfo><spref><horizsys><planar><gridsys><gridsysn>Universal Transverse Mercator</gridsysn><utm><utmzone>15E</utmzone></utm></gridsys><planci><plandu>meters</plandu></planci></planar><geodetic><horizdn>NAD83</horizdn><ellips>GRS80</ellips></geodetic></horizsys></spref></metadata>