<metadata>
  <eainfo>
    <overview>
      <eaover>Attributes for Tabular Data: 

Loc_name: Address geocoded by metro street geolocator or parcel geolocator.

CO_CODE: 3 digit FIPS and state standard county ID code 
003 = Anoka County 
019 = Carver County 
037 = Dakota County 
053 = Hennepin County 
123 = Ramsey County 
139 = Scott County 
163 = Washington County 

CTU_CODE: 5 digit FIPS55 'Place' code for CTU. As of 2006 these 
codes have been officially retired by the federal government. They are 
replaced by the GNIS codes below. The Census Bureau will continue to 
create FIPS55 Place codes for new cities and townships through the 2010 
Census. After that, no new FIPS55 codes will be created. Note that for 
townships that wholly incorporate into cities, the same FIPS55 code for 
the former township will usually be used for the new city. Conversely, 
GNIS creates a new ID for the new city. 

CTU_ID: The Geographic Names Information System (GNIS)official federal 
unique identifier for each city, township or unorganized territory. 

COCTU_ID: 11 digit identifier for the combination of county and CTU 
(concatination of CO_CODE and CTU_ID_CEN). This is the official U.S. 
Census Bureau format. 

CTU_NAME: Name of the city, township or unorganized territory, e.g. 
Benton Twp., Blaine. 

YEAR: The year the data represents. 

DATASOURCE: Source of the data 
CNTY = County 
CTU = City/township/unorganized territory 
METC = Metropolitan Council 

PARK_STATUS: The current status of the park. 
OPEN = The park is currently open and in use. 
CLSG = The park is currently open and in use but is 
in the process of closing 
CLSD = The park is closed. 

PARK_NAME: The name of the manufactured housing park. 

SPACES: Number of spaces or 'pads' in the park. 

MANUFACTURED_HOMES: Number of manufactured homes in the park. 

OCCUPIED_HOMES: Number of occupied manufactured homes in the park. 

POPULATION_LOW_EST: Lowest estimate of population in the occupied 
manufactured homes in the park. 

POPULATION_HIGH_EST: Highest estimate of population in the occupied 
manufactured homes in the park. 

ADDRESS: The street address of the park. 

ZIP_CODE: A system of 5-digit codes that identifies the individual Post 
Office or metropolitan area delivery station associated with an address. 

COMMUNITY_DESIGNATION: A designation of each city and township based on the overall state of development and regional issues faced by that community. 
Senior: Number of age restricted units.








</eaover>
    </overview>
  </eainfo>
  <idinfo>
    <citation>
      <citeinfo>
        <origin>Metropolitan Council</origin>
        <title>Manufactured Home Parks</title>
        <pubinfo>
          <publish>Metropolitan Council</publish>
        </pubinfo>
        <pubdate>20150804</pubdate>
        <onlink>https://gisdata.mn.gov/dataset/us-mn-state-metc-society-manufactuerd-home-parks</onlink>
      </citeinfo>
    </citation>
    <descript>
      <abstract>This dataset contains information on manufactured housing located in manufactured housing parks in the seven-county Twin Cities metropolitan area.</abstract>
      <purpose>This dataset was created to track the number of manufactured home pads (spaces), manufactured homes, occupied manufactured homes and population in occupied manufactured homes in manufactured home parks in the 7-county Metropolitan Area.</purpose>
      <supplinf>Twin Cities 7 county metropolitan area. This includes the counties of Anoka, Carver, Dakota, Hennepin, Ramsey, Scott and Washington.</supplinf>
    </descript>
    <crossref>
      <citeinfo>
        <title>Residential building permits in Cities Metropolitan Area 
</title>
      </citeinfo>
    </crossref>
    <timeperd>
      <current>This dataset reflects permit information collected annually from 1985 through 2014.</current>
      <timeinfo>
        <sngdate>
          <caldate>20150804</caldate>
        </sngdate>
      </timeinfo>
    </timeperd>
    <status>
      <progress>Complete</progress>
      <update>Annually</update>
    </status>
    <spdom>
      <bounding>
        <westbc>-94.012</westbc>
        <eastbc>-92.732</eastbc>
        <northbc>45.415</northbc>
        <southbc>44.471</southbc>
      </bounding>
    </spdom>
    <keywords>
      <theme>
        <themekey>Residential building permits, building permits, permits</themekey>
      </theme>
    </keywords>
    <accconst>None</accconst>
    <useconst>None</useconst>
    <ptcontac>
      <cntinfo>
        <cntperp>
          <cntorg>Metropolitan Council</cntorg>
          <cntper>Joel Nyhus</cntper>
        </cntperp>
        <cntpos>Reseacher</cntpos>
        <cntaddr>
          <addrtype>mailing and physical</addrtype>
          <address>390 Robert Street North</address>
          <city>St. Paul</city>
          <state>MN</state>
          <postal>55101-1805</postal>
        </cntaddr>
        <cntvoice>651.602.1634</cntvoice>
        <cntemail>joel.nyhus@metc.state.mn.us</cntemail>
      </cntinfo>
    </ptcontac>
  </idinfo>
  <dataqual>
    <complete>Entire 7 county area is covered.</complete>
    <lineage>
      <procstep>
        <procdesc>The data were obtained through an annual survey sent to owners or managers of manufactured home parks in the Twin Cities 7-county Metropolitan Area. For those parks not responding, data on spaces and number of homes was obtained, where available, from county assessor data. If no data was available for a given year the previous year's data was used. 

The data on returned surveys were verified by Metropolitan Council staff through various means including contact with park managers or owners. 

Data may be periodically updated to reflect corrections. 

Survey data for two manufactured housing parks (Minnetonka Highlands Mobile Home Park, located in Minnetrista and Mound; and Jackson Heights Mobile Home Park, located in Jackson Township and Louisville Township) could not be allocated to individual communities for some years. Data for these years show as 0. 

Historical data may be available for the following places: 

Burns Township (became the city of Nowthen, July 2008) 
Chaska Township (merged with the city of Chaska, January 2005) 
Columbus Township (became the city of Columbus, September 2006) 
Elko (merged with the city of New Market to become Elko New Market, January 2007) 
Forest Lake Township (merged with the city of Forest Lake, March 2000) 
Grant Township (became the city of Grant, January 1997) 
Hassan Township (merged with the city of Rogers, January 1, 2012) 
New Market (merged with the city of Elko to become Elko New Market, January 2007) 
New Scandia Township (became the city of Scandia, January 2007) 
Norwood (merged with the city of Young America to become Norwood Young America, January 1997) 
Oak Grove Township (became the city of Oak Grove, December 1993) 
Young America (merged with the city of Norwood to become Norwood Young America, January 1997)

For this shapefile, only attached housing units are included. 

A small number of communities each year may not provide data. These are typically places with no residential construction occurring. 

The data on returned surveys were verified by Metropolitan Council staff through various means including: contact with community staff, community websites, and comparison to data in the Council's Service Availability Charge (SAC) reports where possible. 

For this data, projects are counted at the time local units of government issue building permits. 






</procdesc>
      </procstep>
    </lineage>
  </dataqual>
  <distinfo>
    <resdesc>Manufactured Home Parks</resdesc>
    <distliab>NOTICE:  The Geographic Information System (GIS) Data to which this notice is attached are made available pursuant to the Minnesota Government Data Practices Act (Minnesota Statutes Chapter 13).  THE GIS DATA ARE PROVIDED TO YOU AS IS AND WITHOUT ANY WARRANTY AS TO THEIR PERFORMANCE, MERCHANTABILITY, OR FITNESS FOR ANY PARTICULAR PURPOSE.  The GIS Data were developed by the Metropolitan Council for its own internal business purposes.  The Metropolitan Council does not represent or warrant that the GIS Data or the data documentation are error-free, complete, current, or accurate.  You are responsible for any consequences resulting from your use of the GIS Data or your reliance on the GIS Data.  You should consult the data documentation for this particular GIS Data to determine the limitations of the GIS Data and the precision with which the GIS Data may depict distance, direction, location, or other geographic features.  If you transmit or provide the GIS Data (or any portion of it) to another user, it is recommended that the GIS Data include a copy of this disclaimer and this metadata.</distliab>
    <stdorder>
      <ordering>See Online Linkage Below</ordering>
    </stdorder>
    <distrib>
      <cntinfo>
        <cntperp>
          <cntorg>Metropolitan Council</cntorg>
          <cntper>Joel Nyhus</cntper>
        </cntperp>
        <cntpos>Reseacher</cntpos>
        <cntaddr>
          <addrtype>mailing and physical</addrtype>
          <address>390 Robert Street North</address>
          <city>St. Paul</city>
          <state>MN</state>
          <postal>55101-1805</postal>
        </cntaddr>
        <cntvoice>651.602.1634</cntvoice>
        <cntemail>joel.nyhus@metc.state.mn.us</cntemail>
      </cntinfo>
    </distrib>
  </distinfo>
  <metainfo>
    <metd>20150804</metd>
    <metstdn>Minnesota Geographic Metadata Guidelines</metstdn>
    <metstdv>1.2</metstdv>
    <metextns>
      <onlink>http://www.mngeo.state.mn.us/committee/standards/mgmg/metadata.htm</onlink>
    </metextns>
    <metc>
      <cntinfo>
        <cntperp>
          <cntorg>Metropolitan Council</cntorg>
          <cntper>Joel Nyhus</cntper>
        </cntperp>
        <cntpos>Reseacher</cntpos>
        <cntaddr>
          <addrtype>mailing and physical</addrtype>
          <address>390 Robert Street North</address>
          <city>St. Paul</city>
          <state>MN</state>
          <postal>55101-1805</postal>
        </cntaddr>
        <cntvoice>651.602.1634</cntvoice>
        <cntemail>joel.nyhus@metc.state.mn.us</cntemail>
      </cntinfo>
    </metc>
  </metainfo>
  <spref>
    <horizsys>
      <planar>
        <gridsys>
          <gridsysn>Universal Transverse Mercator</gridsysn>
          <utm>
            <utmzone>15</utmzone>
          </utm>
        </gridsys>
        <planci>
          <plandu>meters</plandu>
        </planci>
      </planar>
      <geodetic>
        <horizdn>NAD83</horizdn>
        <ellips>GRS80</ellips>
      </geodetic>
    </horizsys>
  </spref>
</metadata>
