<metadata>
  <idinfo>
    <citation>
      <citeinfo>
        <origin>Metropolitan Council</origin>
        <pubdate>unpublished material</pubdate>
        <title>Metropolitan Urban Service Areas (MUSA) - Historical (1995 - 1998)</title>
        <mgmg1cid>N/A</mgmg1cid>
        <pubinfo>
          <publish>Metropolitan Council</publish>
        </pubinfo>
        <onlink>https://gisdata.mn.gov/dataset/us-mn-state-metc-plan-musa-historical1995-1998</onlink>
      </citeinfo>
    </citation>
    <descript>
      <abstract>This layer contains boundaries of the Metropolitan Urban Service Area (MUSA) in the Twin Cities metropolitan area of Minnesota for each year from 1995 through 1998.  Plans are to also add Local Urban Service Area (LUSA) boundaries to this dataset.

A MUSA boundary line is the outer edge of the urban area.  It is a line agreed to jointly by the Council and local governments through local comprehensive plan reviews.  It delimits the outer reaches of regional services for the specified time period.  

A LUSA boundary line is the outer edge of the urban service are in rural growth centers.  Rural growth centers are incorporated areas that currently provide central sewer service and that have planned long-term expansions of their urban service area.  These small cities are expected to plan for a balance of housing and jobs to promote self-sufficiency.  This service area boundary, like the MUSA, is agreed to jointly by the Council and local governments through local comprehensive plan reviews.  It delimits the outer reaches of regional services for the specified time period.  

Many of the lines that define the MUSA boundary are municipal boundaries.  In this layer, these lines have been derived from the County and Minor Civil Divisions layer compiled by the Metropolitan Council.  Other lines in this layer have been derived from municipal comprehensive plan maps at a variety of scales and accuracy levels.

NOTES:  
-  The lines in this layer are not expected to be as positionally accurate as parcel datasets available from most counties in the Twin Cities area.
-  Significant errors have been noticed in the original 1995 dataset.  These include missing polygons and lines that differ significantly from the parcel boundaries that actually define the MUSA.  These errors will be fixed as they are encountered.  See Horizontal Positional Accuracy for more information.
-  Additionally, areas included in the MUSA in any particular year can, at times, be difficult to determine from maps submitted to the Council prior to 1998, and do not necessarily match maps from previous years.
-  Some communities have 'undesignated' or 'floating' MUSAs.  That is, they may have a large or undefined area within which a specific amount of land may be added to the MUSA within a given period of time.  Thus, the acreage of additional MUSA has been approved by the council, but the location of that acreage will be determined in the future.  These 'undesignated' or 'floating' MUSAs are not represented in this layer until specific locations are identified.</abstract>
      <purpose>This layer was developed to define the location of the MUSA boundary as accurately as possible.   It is used for general planning at the regional and community level.</purpose>
      <supplinf>Twin Cities 7 County Metropolitan Area.  This includes the counties of Anoka, Carver, Dakota, Hennepin, Ramsey, Scott and Washington in Minnesota.</supplinf>
    </descript>
    <timeperd>
      <timeinfo>
        <sngdate>
          <caldate>19981231</caldate>
        </sngdate>
      </timeinfo>
      <current>MUSA boundary is up-to-data as of December 31, 1998.  LUSA boundary information is not included at this time.</current>
    </timeperd>
    <status>
      <progress>In work</progress>
      <update>Annually</update>
    </status>
    <spdom>
      <bounding>
        <westbc>-94.012</westbc>
        <eastbc>-92.732</eastbc>
        <northbc>45.415</northbc>
        <southbc>44.471</southbc>
      </bounding>
    </spdom>
    <keywords>
      <theme>
        <themekt>None</themekt>
        <themekey>MUSA, Metropolitan Urban Service Area, LUSA, Local Urban Service Area, growth management, urban service boundary, sewer service, planning and development, administrative boundaries</themekey>
      </theme>
      <place>
        <placekey>Twin Cities, Anoka County, Carver County, Dakota County, Hennepin County, Ramsey County, Scott County, Washington County</placekey>
      </place>
    </keywords>
    <accconst>None</accconst>
    <useconst>None</useconst>
    <browse>
      <browsen>ftp://ftp.gisdata.mn.gov/pub/gdrs/data/pub/us_mn_state_metc/plan_musa_historical1995_1998/metadata/preview.jpg</browsen>
      <browsed>Sample map showing the Metropolitan Urban Service Areas - Historical (1995 - 1998) layer.</browsed>
    </browse>
    <native>ArcInfo Version 7x, UNIX platform</native>
    <crossref>
      <citeinfo>
        <title>Growth Management Policy Areas, 1996</title>
      </citeinfo>
    </crossref>
    <ptcontac>
      <cntinfo>
        <cntperp>
          <cntorg>Metropolitan Council</cntorg>
          <cntper>Paul E. Hanson</cntper>
        </cntperp>
        <cntpos>GIS Specialist</cntpos>
        <cntaddr>
          <addrtype>mailing and physical</addrtype>
          <address>390 Robert Street North</address>
          <city>St. Paul</city>
          <state>MN</state>
          <postal>55101-1805</postal>
        </cntaddr>
        <cntvoice>651.602.1642</cntvoice>
        <cntemail>paul.hanson@metc.state.mn.us</cntemail>
      </cntinfo>
    </ptcontac>
  </idinfo>
  <dataqual>
    <logic>The dataset is topologically 'clean'.</logic>
    <complete>Entire seven county geographic area is covered for MUSA boundary, but  LUSA boundary data has yet to be incorporated into the dataset.

-  Some communities have 'undesignated' or 'floating' MUSAs.  That is, they may have a large or undefined area within which a specific amount of land may be added to the MUSA within a given period of time.  Thus, the ACREAGE of additional MUSA has been approved by the council, but the location of that acreage will be determined in the future.  These 'undesignated' or 'floating' MUSAs are not represented in this layer until specific locations are identified.

-  Also, many communities have developed STAGED MUSAs.  These typically show MUSA up until 2000, from 2000 to 2005 and from 2005 to 2010.  At this time we are only including MUSA areas that are developable as of the year of the MUSA layer.  Thus, the 1998 MUSA would not include anything staged for 2000 - 2005.  We plan in the future to include these staged areas in a more complex MUSA dataset.</complete>
    <posacc>
      <horizpa>
        <horizpar>The positional accuracy of the dataset has not been tested under the National Standards for Spatial Data Accuracy.  The positional accuracy of the dataset is UNKNOWN.  See Lineage for more information.

Significant errors have been noticed in the original 1995 dataset.  These include missing polygons and lines that differ significantly from parcel boundaries that actually define portions of the MUSA.  These errors will be fixed as they are encountered.  The 'SOURCE' field in the line attributes will provide an indication of the accuracy of the line.  See Entity and Attribute Overview in Section 5 for more information.</horizpar>
      </horizpa>
    </posacc>
    <lineage>
      <srcinfo>
        <srcscale/>
      </srcinfo>
      <procstep>
        <procdesc>This layer is derived from a working source layer at Metropolitan Council named CMM.  CMM stands for County, MCD and MUSA.  The CMM layer was developed because many county, MCD and MUSA lines are identical.  Developing each of these layers separately would lead to the creation of slivers and mismatching arcs - an undesirable condition.

The CMM layer is not specifically documented in an MGMG compliant metadata format, nor is it distributed as a single layer.  Instead, the derivative layers from CMM are documented and distributed.  These layers include COMCD, COUNTY, MCD and USA.  The first three of these are documented in the COMCD layer metadata.  The later (USA) is documented here in it's own metadata record.

Line work for the USA layer is derived from a variety of sources.  A SOURCE code is included in the line attributes of the layer.  Where the source code does not include the string 'MUSA', the line work is most thoroughly described/documented in the metadata for the COMCD layer.  Where the SOURCE code does contains the string 'MUSA', the line work is derived from paper local comprehensive plan maps at a variety of scales and accuracy levels.  No good estimate of the positional accuracy of these lines exists.  However, lines with a SOURCE code of 'MUSA-1995' have been found to be significantly in error in many location.  These errors are corrected as they are encountered.  SOURCE codes of 'MUSA-PARC' indicate lines that were digitized with a county parcel base as a reference.

Occasionally comprehensive plan maps for the same city but for different years do not agree upon what was or was not within the MUSA in a given year.   Also, things like parks, lakes and wetlands may appear in the MUSA at times and outside of the MUSA at other times in city comprehensive plan maps.  This inconsistency is likely a result of the fact that these areas are often considered undevelopable and thus, less attention is paid to their inclusion in the MUSA.</procdesc>
      </procstep>
    </lineage>
  </dataqual>
  <spdoinfo>
    <indspref>None</indspref>
    <direct>Vector</direct>
    <mgmg3obj>arcs, nodes, polygons, label points</mgmg3obj>
    <mgmg3til>One layer for entire seven county region.</mgmg3til>
  </spdoinfo>
  <spref>
    <vertdef>
      <altsys>
        <altdatum>not applicable</altdatum>
      </altsys>
      <depthsys>
        <depthdn>not applicable</depthdn>
      </depthsys>
    </vertdef>
    <horizsys>
      <planar>
        <gridsys>
          <gridsysn>Universal Transverse Mercator</gridsysn>
          <utm>
            <utmzone>15</utmzone>
          </utm>
        </gridsys>
        <planci>
          <plandu>meters</plandu>
        </planci>
      </planar>
      <geodetic>
        <horizdn>NAD83</horizdn>
        <ellips>GRS80</ellips>
      </geodetic>
    </horizsys>
  </spref>
  <eainfo>
    <overview>
      <eaover>Polygon Attributes:
 
USA_1995:  In USA as of end of 1995
 
USA_1996:  In USA as of end of 1996
 
USA_1997:  In USA as of end of 1997
 
USA_1998:  In USA as of end of 1998
 
USAS:      A filed which combines the values of the previous fields.
 
The value for these attributes may be:
     M  =  metropolitan urban service area
     L  =  local urban service area
     N  =  not in an urban service area.
 
 
Line Attributes:
 
CO_BND:        County boundary (Y/N)
 
MCD_BND:       MCD boundary (Y/N)
 
USA_1995_BND:  USA boundary as of end of 1995
 
USA_1996_BND:  USA boundary as of end of 1996
 
USA_1997_BND:  USA boundary as of end of 1997
 
USA_1998_BND:  USA boundary as of end of 1998
 
The value for these attributes may be:
     M  =  metropolitan urban service area boundary
     L  =  local urban service area boundary
     N  =  not an urban service area boundary
 
SOURCE:        The source of the line data.  Values are:

     MUSA-1995:  These lines were transferred from municipal 
          comprehensive plan maps at a variety of scales on to 
          Mn/DOT Street Series mylars.  The lines on the mylars 
          were then digitized using the 1992 Mn/DOT roads layer as 
          a reference base.  No further documentation exists as to the 
          method of digitizing.  Significant errors have been found in 
          these lines.  Observed errors include lines that differ 
          significantly from the parcel boundaries that they are 
          supposed to represent and lines that do not follow the 
          correct alignment of the MUSA, leaving out or including 
          incorrect (sometimes very large) pieces of land.
     MUSA-PARC:  Indicates line work that was digitized using a 
          county parcel layer as a base.  These lines correctly follow 
          the parcel boundaries where they can be defined from the 
          maps provided by communities for comprehensive plans 
          and amendments.  These lines are all expected to lie within 
          10 meters of the digital county parcel boundary lines, with a 
          majority of them lying within 2 meters.  Some of maps 
          provided by the communities, however, do not contain 
          parcel boundaries, or are at such a scale that following 
          parcel boundaries becomes difficult.  
     MUSA-CMPLN:  Indicates line work that was digitized without the 
          help of county parcel boundaries, but with other large-scale 
          reference layers, including digital orthophotography with a 
          resolution of 0.6 meters.  The positional accuracy of most of 
          these lines is estimated to be 10 to 25 meters.  A small 
          number of lines will be significantly less accurate.  These 
          occur where maps supplied by communities and/or base 
          reference data used by the Metropolitan Council 
          (orthophotos) do not have sufficient detail to properly 
          locate the boundary line.  
     DAKO-MCD:  Dakota County MCD boundary data as of 
          October 1998: estimated +or- 0.2 feet on lines that follow 
          the PLS or well described parcels.  90% of lines are 
          estimated to be within 0.5 feet of true location.  Some 
          problem areas exist.  For example, many questions exist as 
          to where the boundary of Mendota is supposed to be.
     SCOT-MCD:  Scott County MCD boundary data as of November 
          1998:  Township boundaries that follow PLS lines are 
          estimated at between 0.4 ft. and 1 ft. of true location.  City 
          boundaries that follow PLS lines are also expected to be 
          near this range of accuracy.  Other boundaries are thought to 
          be within 20 or 40 ft. 
     WASH-MCD:  Washington County MCD boundary data as of 
          September 1998.  Positional accuracy estimated at about 3 ft.
     DOT96-MCD:  MnDOT's 1996 Municipal boundary layer from 
          'BaseMap '97' CD.  Positional accuracy estimate is 40 ft.
     DOT96-CO:  MnDOT's 1996 County boundary layer from 
          'BaseMap '97' CD.  Positional accuracy estimate is 40 ft.
     METC-MCD:  Metropolitan Council's 1990 MCD boundary layer.
          Positional accuracy is unknown, but is estimated to be 
          approximately 40 ft.
     CITY-CMPLN:  Lines are derived from paper City 
          Comprehensive Plan Amendments digitized using 
          Metropolitan Council digital orthophotos for reference.  
          This source is used only for recent annexations where 
          MCD boundary data is not available from the county.  
          Lines are estimated to have about a 40 ft. positional 
          accuracy.
     FUDGE-##:  In some cases, lines from two different data 
          sets never actually touched.  In these cases, 'fudge' lines 
          were added to connect the lines to insure that the layer was
          topologically clean.</eaover>
      <eadetcit>None</eadetcit>
    </overview>
  </eainfo>
  <distinfo>
    <resdesc>MUSAs1995to1998</resdesc>
    <distliab>NOTICE:  The Geographic Information System (GIS) Data to which this notice is attached are made available pursuant to the Minnesota Government Data Practices Act (Minnesota Statutes Chapter 13).  THE GIS DATA ARE PROVIDED TO YOU AS IS AND WITHOUT ANY WARRANTY AS TO THEIR PERFORMANCE, MERCHANTABILITY, OR FITNESS FOR ANY PARTICULAR PURPOSE.  The GIS Data were developed by the Metropolitan Council for its own internal business purposes.  The Metropolitan Council does not represent or warrant that the GIS Data or the data documentation are error-free, complete, current, or accurate.  You are responsible for any consequences resulting from your use of the GIS Data or your reliance on the GIS Data.  You should consult the data documentation for this particular GIS Data to determine the limitations of the GIS Data and the precision with which the GIS Data may depict distance, direction, location, or other geographic features.  If you transmit or provide the GIS Data (or any portion of it) to another user, it is recommended that the GIS Data include a copy of this disclaimer and this metadata.</distliab>
    <stdorder>
      <digform>
        <digtinfo>
          <formname>Arc Export files and ArcView Shape files</formname>
          <formvern>ArcInfo: 7x,  ArcView: 3x</formvern>
          <transize>1 Mb. for zip file.</transize>
        </digtinfo>
      </digform>
      <ordering>See Online Linkage Below</ordering>
    </stdorder>
    <distrib>
      <cntinfo>
        <cntperp>
          <cntorg>Metropolitan Council</cntorg>
          <cntper>Jon Hoekenga</cntper>
        </cntperp>
        <cntpos>GIS System Administrator</cntpos>
        <cntaddr>
          <addrtype>mailing and physical</addrtype>
          <address>390 Robert Street North</address>
          <city>St. Paul</city>
          <state>Minnesota</state>
          <postal>55101-1805</postal>
        </cntaddr>
        <cntvoice>651-602-1561</cntvoice>
        <cntemail>jonathan.hoekenga@metc.state.mn.us</cntemail>
      </cntinfo>
    </distrib>
  </distinfo>
  <metainfo>
    <metd>20010803</metd>
    <metstdn>Minnesota Geographic Metadata Guidelines</metstdn>
    <metstdv>1.2</metstdv>
    <metextns>
      <onlink>http://www.gis.state.mn.us/stds/metadata.htm</onlink>
    </metextns>
    <metc>
      <cntinfo>
        <cntperp>
          <cntorg>Metropolitan Council</cntorg>
          <cntper>Paul E. Hanson</cntper>
        </cntperp>
        <cntpos>GIS Specialist</cntpos>
        <cntaddr>
          <addrtype>mailing and physical</addrtype>
          <address>390 Robert Street North</address>
          <city>St. Paul</city>
          <state>MN</state>
          <postal>55101-1805</postal>
        </cntaddr>
        <cntvoice>651.602.1642</cntvoice>
        <cntemail>paul.hanson@metc.state.mn.us</cntemail>
      </cntinfo>
    </metc>
  </metainfo>
  <Esri>
    <ModDate>20080716</ModDate>
    <ModTime>16034100</ModTime>
  </Esri>
  <mdDateSt Sync="TRUE">20080716</mdDateSt>
</metadata>
